<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 17:59:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 17:59:55 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are You Relationship Material?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/kelly%20C.jpg?itok=0sEDUgMb" alt="Kelly Campbell Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Are You Relationship Material?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Three readiness markers you should pass before choosing 'the one.'</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Most relationships fail because of timing and readiness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Your attachment style quietly predicts how you love, fight, and react under stress.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The healthiest partnerships begin when two people arrive emotionally prepared, not just emotionally attracted.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Passion feels powerful, but companionate love sustains long-term commitment.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Most people think relationship success comes down to finding the right person. But decades of psychological research suggest something else: Many relationships fail not because we chose the wrong partner, but because we entered at the wrong stage of readiness. Before committing to someone, there are three psychological questions worth asking yourself.</p>

<p><strong>No. 1: Do you have a secure attachment style?</strong></p>
<p>Attachment theory, pioneered by John Bowlby and expanded through decades of research by Mary Ainsworth, explains something profound: Your approach to adult relationships was largely shaped before you could talk.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/stocksnap-happy-valentines-day-2603521_1920.jpg?itok=nOPuKllj" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Pixabay/StockSnap" alt="Pixabay/StockSnap"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pixabay/StockSnap</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Attachment refers to your global orientation toward closeness, trust, and dependence, learned through early interactions with caregivers. When babies cry, and caregivers respond consistently and effectively, children learn: <em>People show up. My needs matter. Relationships are safe. </em>When caregiving is inconsistent, absent, or frightening, very different expectations form.</p>

<p>Today, researchers typically measure attachment along two dimensions: attachment anxiety (fear of abandonment) and attachment avoidance (discomfort with closeness). You can assess your own pattern using the Experiences in Close Relationships Tool, which is widely available online (see reference section below). Scores range from low to high on each dimension, producing four common attachment styles: secure, anxious, avoidant, and fearful.</p>

<p>Securely attached adults are low on anxiety and avoidance. They communicate needs directly, expect respect and responsiveness, leave relationships that repeatedly violate boundaries, and trust without losing independence. Secure attachment predicts better mental health, stronger relationships, effective conflict repair, leadership success, and even improved physical health outcomes. In short, the securely attached assume love will work, and often help make it so.</p>

<p>Anxiously attached individuals have high anxiety and low avoidance. Early inconsistency has taught them that love can disappear without warning. As adults, they may seek constant reassurance, rush intimacy, and fear losing connection after positive moments. Ironically, behaviors meant to preserve closeness sometimes push partners away, reinforcing the belief that people are unreliable.</p>

<p>Those with an avoidant attachment style exhibit low anxiety and high avoidance. When caregivers were emotionally unavailable, children learned that self-reliance was safer than dependence. Adult patterns often include emotional distance, discomfort with vulnerability, and strong independence paired with relational withdrawal. Partners often feel shut out, confirming the avoidant individual’s expectation that closeness doesn’t work.</p>

<p>The fearful (disorganized) style is characterized by high anxiety and high avoidance. Here, the caregiver was both a comfort <em>and</em> a threat. These adults crave intimacy but fear it simultaneously, wanting closeness while bracing for harm. Relationships can feel confusing, intense, and unstable.</p>
<p>The good news: Attachment styles are not life sentences! They are socialized, adaptive strategies, and strategies can change. Attachment also creates a powerful self-fulfilling prophecy: We behave in ways that pull responses from others that confirm our expectations. Change how you show up, and people often respond differently. Security can be learned. For a quick self-check, ask yourself:</p>


<ul>
<li>Do I communicate needs directly, or hope partners guess them?</li>
<li>Do I panic when communication slows?</li>
<li>Do I withdraw when someone gets emotionally close?</li>
<li>Do relationships feel calming or destabilizing?</li>
</ul>
<p>Your answers often reveal readiness more clearly than attraction ever will.</p>
<p><strong>No. 2: Have You Addressed What Needs Healing?</strong></p>

<p>Love is not therapy, and partners are not rehabilitation centers. If trauma, chronic anxiety, depression, addiction, or unresolved emotional wounds are present, relationship readiness may require professional support. For milder challenges, evidence-based books, podcasts, and educational resources can help — particularly work grounded in research such as that of relationship scientist John Gottman, whose decades of studies predict relationship stability with remarkable accuracy.</p>



  


<p>For deeper issues, therapy matters. Research consistently shows the strongest predictor of successful therapy outcomes is the therapeutic alliance, the connection between therapist and client. If the first therapist doesn’t feel right, that doesn’t mean therapy failed. It means the match wasn’t right. Finding a secure, trusting therapeutic relationship often becomes a corrective emotional experience that reshapes how people connect elsewhere.</p>

<p>One essential principle: It is not your partner’s job to fix you, and not your job to fix them. Adult relationships work best when two people take responsibility for their own healing.</p>
<p><strong>No. 3: Are You in the Right Life Stage?</strong></p>
<p>Sometimes the issue isn’t attachment or trauma. It’s timing. During adolescence and early adulthood, psychological development centers on identity formation, a process described by developmental psychologist Erik Erikson. This stage is about answering questions such as: "Who am I?" "What do I want out of life?" Serious relationships require shared decision-making and mutual prioritization. When someone is still building education, career direction, independence, or self-knowledge, commitment can unintentionally restrict growth.</p>

<p>Dating during this phase is valuable; it teaches preferences, boundaries, and compatibility. But long-term partnership works best when individuals already know themselves well enough to be authentically known. Because ultimately, people tend to match with partners of comparable overall <em>mate value</em>. Not perfection, but comparability. Traits people commonly value include kindness, dependability, emotional stability, intelligence, health, ambition, humor, and physical attraction. Relationships struggle when partners perceive large mismatches in contribution or growth. If you repeatedly attract unhealthy partners, the uncomfortable question may be: <em>What version of myself am I bringing into the dating pool? </em>Improving your own well-being often changes who becomes available to you.</p>

<p><em><strong>One More Reality Check: Passion Isn’t Enough</strong></em></p>
<p>Psychologists distinguish between two types of love: Passionate and companionate love. Passionate love has been studied extensively by researcher Elaine Hatfield and includes "symptoms" such as euphoria, obsessive thinking about the partner, sleepless excitement, and emotional highs and lows. Neuroscience shows this stage activates the brain’s reward system, similar to cocaine or gambling wins. It feels incredible! But, it also isn’t sustainable.</p>

<p>By contrast, companionate love is more stable and is the foundation of long-term relationships. Common characteristics include shared values, emotional safety, friendship, reliable affection, and repair after conflict. There are fewer fireworks and more warmth. Healthy long-term couples intentionally add novelty and play to maintain passion, but stability anchors them. Many experts caution against marrying within the first two years, before relationships transition beyond pure passion.</p>

<p>What people want from love often evolves with life stage. In earlier years, passionate love—the excitement, intensity, and emotional rush—can feel irresistible. With time and experience, many begin to value companionate love instead. This isn’t a loss of romance but a shift toward sustainability.</p>
<p>Some people may never feel drawn to companionate love, and that is also valid; they may thrive in shorter relationships or prefer independence. The key is self-awareness: Knowing what kind of connection aligns with who you are and being comfortable living authentically within it.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/duncan_dao-valentines-day-background-7144049_1920.jpg?itok=0uNP48Kr" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="couple looking at each other with sun setting behind them" title="Pixabay/Duncan_Dao"></div>
<div class="caption">couple looking at each other with sun setting behind them</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pixabay/Duncan_Dao</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Are You Relationship Ready?</strong></p>
<p>You may want to pause commitment if your attachment patterns are highly insecure; significant emotional or mental health needs remain untreated; you’re still prioritizing identity development; and or you’re chasing emotional intensity rather than stability. Which of these readiness factors do you think people most often overlook?</p>

<p>You’re more likely ready when you can give and receive secure attachment; you’ve sought help where needed; you know who you are independently; and you value companionship as much as chemistry.</p>
<p><strong>The Real Secret</strong></p>
<p>The healthiest relationships are not formed when two people finally find each other. They form when two people arrive ready to communicate, regulate themselves, and build something steadier than passion alone. The question isn’t: Have you met the right person? It’s how well have you become someone ready to love and be loved?</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/more-than-chemistry/202602/are-you-relationship-material" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/more-than-chemistry/202602/are-you-relationship-material</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/more-than-chemistry/202602/are-you-relationship-material</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Campbell Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/oikeys1_studio-couple-7127168_1920.jpg?itok=JXq6vqzO" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Our Missing Climate Tools Are Psychological and Evolutionary]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/thomas_bateman.jpg?itok=HtiP6FXx" alt="Thomas S Bateman D.B.A." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Environment</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Our Missing Climate Tools Are Psychological and Evolutionary</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">We can evolve faster, and intentionally, to better manage climate change.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">We can manage our climate challenges reasonably well only by evolving more rapidly and deliberately.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cultural evolution via effective decision-making is key. We must override short-termism and uncertainties.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Elephants and other animals are evolving faster than scientists previously thought possible.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/shutterstock_221266084.jpg?itok=ldlZU72H" width="320" height="215" data-insert-type="image" title="Cartoon Resource/Shutterstock" alt="Cartoon Resource/Shutterstock"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Cartoon Resource/Shutterstock</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Surrendering to the relentless laws of physics. That’s what we—with far too few exceptions—are doing in response to our climate crisis. More constructively, certain other animals are quietly impressing scientists by <a href="https://theconversation.com/wild-animals-are-evolving-faster-than-anybody-thought-183633">evolving and adapting to climate change</a> far faster than previously thought possible. If elephants, birds, and marine mammals can do it, we should be able to do it too.</p>

<p>When many of us were still in school, scientists understood evolution as an exceedingly slow genetic process, but they have recently learned otherwise. Behavioral, cultural, and even genetic evolution occur remarkably fast when the environment shifts rapidly. Consider one recent striking example in mammals: After 15 years of rampant ivory poaching in Mozambique, the percentage of female <a href="https://r.search.yahoo.com/_ylt=AwrNY3AND5lpKXgDgJQPxQt.;_ylu=Y29sbwNiZjEEcG9zAzIEdnRpZAMEc2VjA3Ny/RV=2/RE=1772848141/RO=10/RU=https%3a%2f%2fwww.bbc.com%2fnews%2fworld-africa-59008037/RK=2/RS=ondjiQ9FllaG7APsjl_bprpBJYo-">elephants born without tusks</a> rose from 19% to 51%. In that short span, at least two tusk-related genes appeared.</p>

<p>We will manage our climate challenges effectively only by evolving more rapidly and deliberately. We can do this by taking fuller advantage of our abilities to anticipate what lies ahead, envision alternative possibilities, and proactively build the future we want and need</p>
<p>Adding psychology to climate science and engineering prowess would complete the three-legged stool that could support and sustain successful climate action.</p>

<p>Our default decision-making processes routinely show imperfections that we can and must overcome. We are not <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/17456916211018454?journalCode=ppsa">"wired to fail"</a> in the face of climate change, as some believe. We do, however, succumb to a destructive cognitive bias: short-termism, or the tendency to be motivated by immediate costs and benefits more than by longer-term climate dangers. We build better futures when we think ahead and consider the ultimate consequences of our actions.</p>

<p>Short-termism is made worse by uncertainty about what the distant future holds. Uncertainty can prompt denial, breed discomfort, confusion, and helplessness, and provide handy excuses for doing little or nothing to protect the future. Harmful climate uncertainties include the false belief that climate scientists are divided in their views, the false belief that humans don’t have much effect on global heating, and the genuine difficulty of predicting the future precisely.</p>

<p>But we cannot let uncertainties stop us from taking aggressive climate action. This doesn’t need to be difficult; we override passive uncertainty when we get life-saving medical treatment, buy life insurance, and save as much as we can for retirement, even though we aren't 100% certain that we need to.</p>

<p>These <a href="https://climatecommunication.gmu.edu/all/understanding-six-key-truths-about-climate-change-predicts-policy-support-discussion-and-political-advocacy/">key climate truths</a> offer the certainties we need: 97% or more of active climate researchers agree on the fundamentals: Global warming is real and dangerous; human activity does drive the crisis; most people care; and there’s hope if we change how we act. We can prevail by concentrating on how we think and behave, which we can directly control.</p>

<p>We can, but often do not, control our thoughts and actions. Personal control and agency are universal <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2017-42390-001">psychological needs</a>, yet things now feel more out of control than ever. We will regain control—and achieve climate agency—when we do what is necessary: reduce greenhouse gas emissions and prepare for the threats ahead. More immediately, pre-election political engagement can re-establish 2025’s progress, when renewables overtook coal in electricity generation and solar and wind growth met all new global power demand.</p>

<p>Crucially, we have more climate agency at our disposal than we usually realize. We vastly underuse the control available to us thanks to the predictability and knowledge that science and technology provide. We also have the technological and economic solutions we need.</p>
<p>The elephants’ amazing biological evolution aside, some animals benefit from rapid cultural evolution; for instance, changing communication patterns in birds and whales. Humankind’s transformative changes, as well, come from cultural evolution. When enough individuals and groups shift their behavior, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34074122/">new norms and cultures evolve</a>. We can evolve faster, strategically and intentionally, using our abilities to think long-term, talk, and communicate virtually. </p>



  


<p>We need an ambitious climate mission, and speedy cultural evolution can achieve what we need. In recent decades, we’ve seen many rapid cultural changes, including changes in seat-belt and smoking habits, climate awareness, recycling, and <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/mindylubber/2026/01/12/2026-outlook-clean-energy-nature-and-water-drive-global-resilience/">shifts to renewable energy</a> sources. The window, while closing, is still open enough that we can quickly alter trajectories and create the livable futures we can no longer take for granted.</p>

<p>Cultural evolution occurs when enough people talk openly and often about our climate futures—at work, with their families, in social gatherings, or with people of differing faiths, politics, and professions. The kicker is that changes occur only through talking <em>differently</em> and <em>effectively. </em>Arguments and even civil disagreements won’t accomplish what we need unless accompanied by honesty, cooperation, and a bias for action. This requires not denying the crisis itself, our collective responsibility, the many reasons for hope, or the power of human agency. We must prioritize our future over the past, decision-making challenges and policy solutions over tired old arguments, and intentional, speedy evolution over business-as-usual.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/getting-proactive/202602/our-missing-climate-tools-are-psychological-and-evolutionary" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/getting-proactive/202602/our-missing-climate-tools-are-psychological-and-evolutionary</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/getting-proactive/202602/our-missing-climate-tools-are-psychological-and-evolutionary</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Thomas S Bateman D.B.A.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_1274379073.jpg?itok=b3o15pbN" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Hidden Beauty of Work That Matters]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-02/Wes%20Adams-Tamara%20Myles.jpg?itok=xM1QvYNw" alt="Wes Adams and Tamara Myles" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Workplace Dynamics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Hidden Beauty of Work That Matters</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why Meaningful Work Is Closer Than You Think</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Meaningful work is shaped by how you experience your job, not just what you do.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Community, contribution, and challenge drive meaning across roles.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Feeling seen and valued at work strengthens engagement.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Small relational behaviors can shift how work feels and make work meaningful.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">It’s Sunday evening. The weekend is winding down. You glance at your calendar and feel that familiar tightening in your chest. The emails. The deadlines. The meetings that blur together. Many of us have experienced what’s often called the Sunday Scaries. We assume the solution is a different job, a better boss, or a bigger paycheck. But what’s missing isn’t a new role at all.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In our <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s41542-023-00161-z">research</a> on meaningful work across industries and roles, we have found that meaning rarely hinges on the title on your business card. It hinges on how you experience the work you are already doing.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>What Makes Work Meaningful</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">When people describe their most meaningful moments at work, they often talk about moments when they felt connected, when they saw their impact, and when someone believed in their potential. In our research, these experiences consistently cluster around three elements, what we call the Three C’s of Meaningful Work:</p>

<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Community. The sense that you belong and that you matter to the people around you.</li>
<li dir="ltr">Contribution. The belief that your work makes a difference.</li>
<li>Challenge. The opportunity to grow and become more capable than you were yesterday.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr">These three C’s show up in small, repeatable behaviors.</p>
<p><strong>Community Is Built in the Everyday</strong></p>

<p dir="ltr">In one of the most predictive questions in our study, employees were asked whether their leader cared about what was happening in their lives outside of work. Those who answered yes reported a significantly stronger sense of community. Community grows when someone follows up about the race you mentioned, checks in after a difficult week, or takes the time to ask a question that has nothing to do with your to-do list. You do not need a workplace full of best friends to feel connected. Research suggests that even one meaningful work friendship can buffer against loneliness.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Contribution Requires Visibility</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">People do not burn out simply because they work hard. They burn out when they work hard and feel invisible. In a well-known <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2008-00266-008">study</a> by Adam Grant, university fundraisers who met a student whose scholarship depended on their work went on to raise significantly more money than those who did not. Seeing the human impact of their efforts transformed routine calls into meaningful conversations. Leaders often assume people already see the value of their contributions. Many do not. A simple sentence that clarifies impact can change how someone experiences their role.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Challenge Expands Potential</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">We also found that meaningful work involves growth. It involves someone saying, “You’re ready for this,” before you are entirely sure yourself. When leaders express belief in someone’s potential, they expand that person’s sense of what is possible. Environments that stretch people, rather than confine them, become places where meaning accumulates.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>The Hidden Beauty</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Meaningful work is not reserved for a fortunate few. It is not limited to mission-driven professions or breakthrough moments. It is found in the small interactions that make someone feel seen, in the clarity that connects effort to impact, and in the belief that helps someone grow. Tomorrow, ask one real question; name someone’s contribution; tell someone you believe in them. A job can look impressive on paper and still feel empty. The experience of meaning is shaped less by the title and more by the conditions around it.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meaningful-work/202602/the-hidden-beauty-of-work-that-matters" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meaningful-work/202602/the-hidden-beauty-of-work-that-matters</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meaningful-work/202602/the-hidden-beauty-of-work-that-matters</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Wes Adams and Tamara Myles]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Stress_Pixel-ShotShutterstock_1613730961.jpg?itok=F-EQl4Fh" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI, GLP-1s, and the Fear of Lazy Shortcuts]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/randy_kulman_1.jpg?itok=__9T-xdF" alt="Randy Kulman Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">AI, GLP-1s, and the Fear of Lazy Shortcuts</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Do innovations like AI and GLP-1s make us lazy?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p dir="ltr">When Ro announced its <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tqXOcRtZoow">Super Bowl spot featuring Serena Williams</a> talking about her use of GLP-1 medications, one line jumped out at me: “There is no one with more willpower and self-discipline than Serena Williams, which is why she’s the perfect person to help people see that GLP-1s are not a shortcut.”</p>

<p dir="ltr">It got me thinking about the arguments I’ve been having with friends—and with myself—about whether AI is a shortcut and will make us lazy. Will most of us use AI to take the easy way out? And is the easy way always inferior?</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/image.png.jpg?itok=6UQbRLuD" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="Wikimedia Commons / Edwin Martinez" alt="Wikimedia Commons / Edwin Martinez"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Wikimedia Commons / Edwin Martinez</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">The Serena framing is clever. If Serena Williams—who, according to the advertising firm creating the spot, embodies grit, discipline, and relentless training—uses a GLP-1, then maybe these medications <em>aren’t</em> cheating. Maybe removing the friction and struggle of weight loss is better than clinging to “no pain, no gain,” especially if the result is better health.</p>

<p dir="ltr">What struck me while watching the Super Bowl (in addition to my Patriots losing) was how many ads leaned into themes of effort, perseverance, and creativity. The Olympic spots, the NFL ad with a child giving himself a pep talk, and OpenAI’s Codex ad. included messages about working hard, learning, not giving up. It felt like reassurance: Even in an era of AI doing more human work, grit still matters.</p>

<p dir="ltr">And yet the anxiety remains.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Parents, teachers, and employers worry that AI will deskill us—especially our kids. Why learn to write if a chatbot can produce an essay in seconds? Why do the math if an app can show the work? The fear is that AIs, like GLP-1s, are becoming shortcuts that let us dodge the hard part.</p>

<p dir="ltr">So the question becomes: If we use a tool like GLP-1s or AI, does that automatically make us lazy? </p>
<p dir="ltr">I don’t think it does. But it can. And that “can” is where the real nuance lives.</p>
<h2>The Pros and Cons of Shortcuts</h2>
<p dir="ltr">With GLP-1s, it’s easy to picture the worst-case scenario: Someone takes the medication, keeps all their old habits, never moves their body, eats whatever they want, and hopes the drug will do the rest. No behavioral change. No attention to health. Just an outsourced solution.</p>

<p dir="ltr">There are similar concerns with AI. The student pastes their assignment into a chatbot, copies the output, and turns it in without reading it. The worker asks AI to write a report and never understands what it says. In both cases, the technology becomes a way to avoid effort. The<a href="https://www.brookings.edu/articles/a-new-direction-for-students-in-an-ai-world-prosper-prepare-protect/"> Brookings Institution</a> recently suggested that many students use AI routinely and thoughtlessly, equating learning with accessing AI rather than stretching their own cognitive abilities. Students who use it this way may not have years of experience connecting effort to mastery—or role models demonstrating Serena-level discipline.</p>

<p dir="ltr">That version absolutely exists. GLP-1s can be misused as cosmetic shortcuts. AI can be used to skip all the cognitive work. When that happens, it’s fair to talk about de-skilling and laziness. But the Serena Williams campaign, I feel, also hints at something more complicated.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/igor-omilaev-FHgWFzDDAOs-unsplash.jpg?itok=akze6KF-" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Igor Omilaev on Unsplash" alt="Photo by Igor Omilaev on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Igor Omilaev on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Who Gets the Most From These Tools?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">In the ad, Serena describes GLP-1s not as a miracle fix but as part of a health plan. She’s moving better, feeling better, more flexible. The message is not that effort disappears but that with GLP-1s, it becomes more effective.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Personally, I see AI the same way in my own work. I combine it with 40+ years of discipline to improve, learn, and experience the rewards that come with effort. AI lowers friction so I can do more of the meaningful work. When used thoughtfully, I've found that AI can function as:</p>

<ul>
<li dir="ltr">An editor to improve clarity and structure</li>
<li dir="ltr">A research assistant to generate ideas within parameters</li>
<li dir="ltr">A structuring tool to help organize thoughts</li>
<li dir="ltr">A clarifier to explain a concept five different ways </li>
</ul>
<p>To me, that's not laziness. However, due to the power of these tools, I run the risk of getting lazy.</p>

<h2>Maybe the Problem Isn’t That AI Makes Tasks Too "Easy"</h2>
<p dir="ltr">We tend to treat ease as morally suspicious. If something becomes easier, we assume character is lost. </p>
<p dir="ltr">But our desire to make things easier is not new. We accept cars instead of horses, dishwashers instead of hand-washing, and Google search instead of card catalogs. We don’t accuse people of laziness for using spellcheck. How many of us actually remember our children's cell phone numbers or still know how to use a map to navigate without GPS?</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">The question, I argue, shouldn't be, “Is this easier?” Instead, we should ask, “What are we skipping?” With GLP-1s, are users skipping exercise and healthy habits—or skipping years of yo-yo dieting and chronic pain so sustainable change can stick? With AI, are users skipping thinking and revision—or skipping mechanical drudgery so they can spend more time on insight and creativity?</p>

<p dir="ltr">When I sit down at 6:30 in the morning to write, I sometimes ask an AI tool to help organize my messy thoughts or suggest a structure. For me, that makes part of the process easier. But it doesn’t replace the work of deciding what I believe or refining my argument. At least the way I use it, AI is less a shortcut and more a power tool.</p>

<p dir="ltr">These reflections focus on the “normal” use of GLP-1s and AI. For most of us, this is about design and intention. Do we use these tools to avoid effort—or to make our effort more strategic? Will they make us lazy? Will they devalue grit and persistence? Or will they improve our quality of life? I am struggling with these questions, which I’d like to believe are a new challenge and, at the very least, an example of thoughtfulness.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/screen-play/202602/ai-glp-1s-and-the-fear-of-lazy-shortcuts" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/screen-play/202602/ai-glp-1s-and-the-fear-of-lazy-shortcuts</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/screen-play/202602/ai-glp-1s-and-the-fear-of-lazy-shortcuts</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Randy Kulman Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/image.png.jpg?itok=VAo7mKCf" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How People Adapt to the Narcissists in Their Lives]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-10/Herzberg.jpg?itok=YL_aiUs1" alt="Boris Herzberg" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Narcissism</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How People Adapt to the Narcissists in Their Lives</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Exploring the concept of "co-narcissism".</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>We often talk about narcissism in terms of the person exhibiting the traits: the grandiosity, the lack of empathy, the need for admiration, and the readiness to manipulate or use others. But for those living in their shadow, the story is written in a different language — one of vigilance, silence, avoidance, and carefully managed steps.<br><br>If you grew up or currently live with a narcissistic person, you know the terrain well: you walk on eggshells, constantly monitor their mood, and adjust your behavior to avoid conflict.<br><br>Many dismiss this hyper-vigilance as simply being an anxious person. However, psychologist Alan Rappoport coined a term to describe how people adapt to narcissistic family members: "co-narcissism." It's important to be transparent that this is one researcher's term and not an official diagnosis or a psychiatric term, but it’s easy to see why it's used. The prefix "co-" so effectively captures the dynamic of being a partner or complement to the narcissistic person's behavior, highlighting how those around them are drawn into a supporting role in response to the narcissist's needs.</p>

<h2>Narcissism and Self-Esteem</h2>
<p>Narcissism is something rooted in extremely low self-esteem. Narcissistic people are terrified of being seen as inadequate, so to protect themselves, they try to control how others view them. They present themselves as rigid, easily offended, and self-absorbed. They don’t care much about empathy for those surrounding them, and their world revolves around their own needs. They often see their children as extensions of themselves — being there to meet their emotional demands (1).<br><br>Think of a parent who demands that the child become a lawyer because the parent was, or wanted to be, one. When the child chooses art instead, the parent rejects him. Thus, the child isn’t seen as a separate person with their own dreams and aspirations, but as a mere character in the parent’s story.</p>

<h2>Where "Co-Narcissism" Comes In</h2>
<p>This is where the child develops a survival strategy: if you can’t be your own person, you learn to be what the parent needs. Rappoport calls this “the co-narcissistic adaptation”. It’s like being the loyal audience to the narcissist’s one-person show, needing to cheer and clap whether you want it or not.<br><br>If you were that child, you probably learned your part well:</p>

<ul>
<li>You worked hard to please, becoming a reliable source of validation.</li>
<li>You deferred to others’ opinions, stifling your disagreement.</li>
<li>You worried endlessly about what people thought of you.</li>
<li>Your own feelings and views were fuzzy and faded into the background.</li>
<li>As an adult, you might often feel depressed, anxious, or guilty — quickly taking the blame when things go wrong.</li>
</ul>

<p>These children are led to believe that they are inherently selfish for having needs at all or refusing to clap on cue. Why? Because their parents label any independence as a betrayal.</p>
<h2>Response to Narcissistic Parents</h2>
<p>There are three ways children typically respond to narcissistic parents: identification, compliance, and rebellion.</p>

<ul>
<li>Identification: You become like them. You adopt their traits, maybe their grandiosity or their critical nature, just to feel connected.</li>
<li>Compliance: This is the classic co-narcissist role. You become the supportive, approving audience they crave. You manage their ego from moment to moment.</li>
<li>Rebellion: You fight their definition of you by doing the opposite, like the gifted kid who fails school to spite a demanding parent. But even this rebellion is still a reaction to them. You’re not free, but are bound and defined by fighting the script.</li>
</ul>

<p>Most of us who grew up in narcissistic families and learned these survival strategies bounce between these roles. You might be "co-narcissistic" with a demanding boss, then turn around and act narcissistically with a partner who’s in a more compliant mood. Both sides stem from that same shaky sense of self.</p>


<h2>The Path Out: Building the Equal Relationship</h2>
<p>Rappoport also tells us about the hopeful part. Therapy for "co-narcissism" isn’t just about digging up the past, but about experiencing a completely different kind of relationship in the present.<br><br>"Co-narcissistic" people walk in assuming the therapist, like everyone else, is narcissistic. A huge part of the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-relationships-and-emotional-intelligence/202601/the-8-unspoken-rules-of">therapeutic work</a> is testing that assumption and seeing if this person can really listen, and can hold your experience without needing you to manage theirs (1).<br><br>When you find a therapist who embodies empathy, warmth, and genuineness (qualities which Carl Rogers — the pioneer in humanistic psychology — particularly emphasized), it’s quite revolutionary. It disproves your deepest fear: that all relationships are transactional and are about pleasing the other person. You get to experience what it’s like when both people matter. For maybe the first time, you’re in a relationship where no one has to disappear or diminish oneself.</p>

<h2>Why "Co-narcissism" Is Adaptation, Not Selfishness</h2>
<p>When you read the case studies of Mario, drifting in isolation, or Jane, paralyzed by the belief she can never succeed, you aren't just reading clinical notes. You may recognize yourself in their stories, particularly in that unearned sense of guilt and the habit of "fading away" during conversations.<br><br>This "fading" is a survival strategy learned in a relational system of subjugation, where you were taught to mute your realness and suppress your own subjectivity to satisfy the needs of a dominant parent.<br><br>If you see yourself here, know this: "co-narcissism" isn’t a personality flaw. It’s a set of functional, but painful, survival skills you developed as a kid.<br><br>The goal here is not to drown in blaming your parents, but to understand the environment that shaped you. You can find your own way forward once you know where you started.<br><br>The emotional relief, as well as inner independence, comes when you realize that you’re not and were never responsible for another adult’s emotional experience or self-actualization. Your value isn’t earned by pleasing someone — it’s just there, and there is nothing selfish about it. This is how you come back to yourself.</p>



  


<p><em>If you enjoyed this post, read "</em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-relationships-and-emotional-intelligence/202601/adaptation-trap-why-children"><em>Adaptation Trap: Why Children of Narcissists Lose Themselves</em></a><em>".</em><br> </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-relationships-and-emotional-intelligence/202602/how-people-adapt-to-the" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-relationships-and-emotional-intelligence/202602/how-people-adapt-to-the</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-relationships-and-emotional-intelligence/202602/how-people-adapt-to-the</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Boris Herzberg]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-vera-arsic-304265-984950%20%281%29.jpg?itok=OIVxPqUo" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stress Relief Through Sound]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/rafft.png.jpg?itok=3GPl_p8H" alt="Raffi Tachdjian MD, MPH" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Stress</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Stress Relief Through Sound</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Music therapy’s role in perinatal mental health</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">While becoming a parent is often joyful, it can also be a time of great stress and uncertainty.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Music therapy can help decrease new parents' anxiety and improve their emotional coping.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Music therapy can also increase new parents' positive experiences, boosting positivity and kindness.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/vitaly-gariev-3IHd_50t7ZA-unsplash.jpg?itok=dy_op_sC" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="Vitaly Gariev / Unsplash" alt="Vitaly Gariev / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Vitaly Gariev / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Becoming a parent is one of life’s great joys. However, experiencing pregnancy, regardless of outcome, can be accompanied by high levels of stress, fear, and uncertainties revolving around the well-being of the parents and the infant. This is where music therapy comes in.</p>
<p>A recent observational research study suggests that music therapy can decrease stress and anxiety, helping parents cope with emotions, feel stronger, and be distracted from stress, particularly during stays in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU). Music has a healing power that goes beyond comfort, offering stress reduction for parents who are on the journey of parenthood.</p>

<h2>Observing Music Therapy’s Impact on Perinatal Mental Health</h2>
<p>“The Effect of Music Therapy on Perceived Parental Stress in Perinatal Care,” a 2022 exploratory study, evaluated how music therapy can help parents navigate the stress of perinatal care. Throughout the study, music therapists offered services to all newly admitted parents in the maternity ward and NICU each week.</p>

<p>Sessions involved an integration of developmentally appropriate relaxation-focused music for both parents in the maternity unit and the NICU. Common interventions used include parent psychoeducation, songwriting, music and feeding, music-assisted relaxation, and playlist creation.</p>
<h2>The Study and Methodology</h2>

<p>While vast research has focused on the benefits of music on infant development, this study sought to explore its role in impacting parents’ needs and experiences. It examined how music therapy can impact the stress levels of inpatient perinatal parents, with a main goal of providing non-pharmacological, music-based coping strategies to minimize parent stress levels throughout the perinatal journey.</p>

<p>Parental stress related to music therapy sessions was evaluated using anonymous, voluntary surveys administered in-person, which included the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) to measure overall stress from admission to discharge and the Stress Numeric Rating Scale (SNRS-11) to assess immediate stress levels before and after each session. Optional qualitative feedback was also collected at discharge to capture parents’ written reflections on the overall music therapy session.</p>

<h2>What the Study Found</h2>
<p>The study featured 77 music therapy sessions, and findings include:</p>
<ul>
<li>After only one (1) music therapy session, parents in both antepartum and NICU settings reported a 50 percent reduction in their self-rated stress scores on the SNRS-11.</li>
<li>Qualitative results measured by the PSS post survey reflected a unanimous feeling of support and relaxation felt amongst parents in NICU and maternity units. Parents reported increasing their use of music in their daily routines because of receiving music therapy during their inpatient stay.</li>
<li>During the PSS post survey, parents expressed that music therapy helped them better cope with emotions, feel stronger, be distracted from stress, and experience positivity and kindness.</li>
<li>Findings support existing literature regarding music therapy as a stress management tool for the parents of newborns in the NICU, as well as serving as a suggestion to leverage music therapy to support parents’ stress management during perinatal hospitalization.</li>
<li>Music therapy can be an effective way to simultaneously impact parent health outcomes along with infant outcomes by way of parent stress reduction.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Why This Matters</h2>
<p>This study underscores the power of music therapy to help parents, not just in-hospital patients. When parents are stressed, nervous, or overwhelmed, it can negatively affect not only their personal well-being but also how they care for and connect with their infant. </p>
<p>Moving forward, music therapy offers an avenue toward reducing parental stress. Stress management is a powerful mental health support strategy that can impact health outcomes through improving interactions between parents and baby, strengthening bonding, and contributing to a calmer environment for healing. Supporting parents through music therapy is a powerful step toward advancing perinatal mental health care.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/healing-through-creativity/202602/stress-relief-through-sound" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/healing-through-creativity/202602/stress-relief-through-sound</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/healing-through-creativity/202602/stress-relief-through-sound</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Raffi Tachdjian MD, MPH]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/vitaly-gariev-3IHd_50t7ZA-unsplash.jpg?itok=0fwv3Ws7" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Dopamine Aisle of the Supermarket]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-02/Nicole.png.jpg?itok=LGiRhsLB" alt="Nicole Avena Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Diet</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Dopamine Aisle of the Supermarket</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why ultra-processed foods may be the new retail therapy.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The overconsumption of ultra-processed foods impacts many Americans and drives annual spending habits.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">One survey found that roughly 67 percent of Americans use snacks and treats to lift their mood.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">An estimated 49 percent of Americans purchase takeout to comfort themselves.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Many factors contribute to how we spend our money, especially when it comes to our retail habits. Unsurprisingly, there are many categories within retail that we consider when deciding where we will spend our money, including clothes, electronics, health and beauty, entertainment, home improvement, and much more.</p>

<p>CashNetUSA, along with Censuswide, conducted a survey that included 2,000 consumers to explore how emotional spending impacts consumer choices. One area of the survey looked at what Americans purchase to improve their mood. Within this question, one category stuck out: food. The survey found that 67 percent of Americans engage in retail therapy involving snacks and treats as a way to cheer themselves up, estimating roughly $526.04 per year. The survey also concluded that 49 percent of Americans purchase takeout to comfort themselves, with an approximate cost of $598.45 annually. It may come as a shock that snacks, treats, and takeout have surpassed retail therapy for clothes, shoes, beauty products, and even video games.</p>

<p>These results prompt a simple but revealing question: Why does food dominate the American shopping cart? The explanation lies in the neuroscience of our brain’s reward system. Our reward system involves interconnected regions of the brain that play a role in regulating pleasure, motivation, and habit formation.</p>

<p>Dopamine plays a central role in how our brain processes reward; it is a neurotransmitter that relays messages between neurons and other cells within the body. Dopamine is commonly referred to as the “feel-good” neurotransmitter due to its role in activating the brain’s reward system. Whenever we experience something that brings us joy, such as eating, accomplishing a task or goal, or even spending time with loved ones, our brain releases dopamine, which helps communicate a sense of pleasure and strengthens the contributing behavior.</p>

<p>Conceptualizing how our brain processes reward is essential to understanding why so many Americans spend hundreds of dollars on food in an effort to improve their mood. The “snacks” and “treats” in the survey were likely referring to ultra-processed food items. Although there is no universally accepted definition for the term ultra-processed foods (UPFs), they generally refer to heavily manufactured food products that are primarily made of synthetic ingredients rather than whole foods.</p>

<p>Whenever many individuals experience a stressful or emotional state, they typically don’t reach for a snack of hummus and carrots or a dessert of apples and peanut butter to make them feel better, but why is this? Whenever we initially try a new food, like strawberries, for the first time, the brain releases dopamine to reinforce the behavior and mark it as favorable. Over time, that dopamine response naturally decreases as we consume more strawberries and the food becomes more familiar. Due to this, our brain is not continually receiving an influx of dopamine whenever we eat familiar, nutritious foods.</p>

<p>When we choose to consume UPFs, they are commonly packed with added sugar, sodium, and saturated fat—ingredients that drive the palatability of food items. In particular, the high amounts of added sugar and fat contribute to a strong and rapid dopamine surge in the brain each time we consume these foods, creating an intensely pleasurable experience. Food manufacturers are well aware of how highly palatable these food items are, which is why UPFs are laden with added sugar.</p>


<p>The overconsumption of UPFs impacts many Americans and may drive annual spending habits. Our current food system is flooded with UPFs, which can make avoiding them feel impossible. When managing our emotions, finding healthier and more sustainable habits is key. For example, whenever you have a stressful workday and find yourself reaching for an indulgent treat, it can be beneficial to pause and replace that habit with an alternative behavior, such as going for a walk, reading a book, playing with a pet, or even meditating. Although our food environment is largely dominated by ultra-processed foods, reducing our intake and reshaping our retail habits is possible with awareness and intentionality.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/food-junkie/202602/the-dopamine-aisle-of-the-supermarket" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/food-junkie/202602/the-dopamine-aisle-of-the-supermarket</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/food-junkie/202602/the-dopamine-aisle-of-the-supermarket</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicole Avena Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/franki-chamaki-ivfp_yxZuYQ-unsplash.jpg?h=65b64331&amp;itok=U0KWPL29" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An AI Voice Is Not a Mind]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/John%20Nosta.png.jpg?itok=MdOqub5o" alt="John Nosta" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">An AI Voice Is Not a Mind</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: AI doesn’t think. It performs the voice of thinking.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">AI performs a persona, not a self.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Fluency can feel like mind without being one.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Voice no longer guarantees belief or ownership.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AIVoice.png.jpg?itok=rEtA9Wwz" width="320" height="315" data-insert-type="image" title="ChatGPT modified by NostaLab" alt="ChatGPT modified by NostaLab"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: ChatGPT modified by NostaLab</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>For better or worse, many of us have begun to experience artificial intelligence as if it has a personality. The tone and content appear consistent enough, and it's easy to imagine someone on the other side of the screen. That intuition is understandable because human beings are well-tuned to infer mind from language. When a voice sounds stable, we assume a stable self. When it sounds confident, we assume conviction. When it sounds empathic, we assume feeling.</p>

<p>Recently, Anthropic introduced what it calls the <a href="https://alignment.anthropic.com/2026/psm/">persona selection model</a>, explaining this experience. Rather than describing the assistant as a unified self with beliefs and goals, the company suggests that the system selects and enacts a persona from a vast distribution learned during training. What feels like identity is, in this view, a contextually appropriate role. The assistant does not reveal an inner core—it dons a mask optimized for the moment.</p>

<p>This "corporate articulation" lands directly inside what I have described as <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202507/ai-and-the-architecture-of-anti-intelligence">anti-intelligence</a>. For some time, I have argued that these systems generate a form of cognition that is structurally different from our own. Anti-intelligence is not a critique of capability and certainly not a dismissal of complexity. It is an architectural claim built on four pillars:</p>

<ul>
<li>Fluency without interiority</li>
<li>Coherence without consequence</li>
<li>Expression without belief</li>
<li>Authority without ownership</li>
</ul>
<p>The persona selection model doesn’t undermine this framework. In fact, it supports it. If model behavior consists of selecting and enacting a persona from what it has learned, then there is no stable center of belief behind the voice we encounter. There is no inner perspective carrying convictions forward. What feels like a point of view is a role being performed.</p>

<p>This doesn't mean that the system is shallow, but it clarifies how it is different. The engine beneath the interface is remarkably complex and can produce reasoning that often outperforms humans in certain domains. But complexity is not the same as a lived perspective. A system can produce coherent answers without standing behind them, just as it can sound authoritative without carrying the weight of consequence. </p>

<h2>The Psychology of Inference</h2>
<p>For me, what makes this development significant is less about the technical aspects and more about the psychological consequences. Human cognition evolved in social environments where language was reliably tethered to a living mind. Words emerged from our lived experiences. Because that linkage was so consistent, we developed an almost automatic inference that is a cornerstone of our human experience. Simply put, coherent speech signals an anchored self.</p>

<p>The persona selection model disrupts that inference. In this context, the voice we engage with doesn't expose belief or intention, it just selects s a role that fits the conversational landscape. Continuity is simulated through pattern consistency rather than grounded in memory or identity; the performance works because it mirrors the external signals we associate with the mind.</p>

<p>Here, anti-intelligence becomes more than a technical description and becomes a psychological caution. The risk isn't that LLMs are secretly acquiring hidden selves but that we begin to relax our criteria for what counts as one. I believe that this is an essential observation: if fluency is sufficient to trigger our social reflexes, then interiority may no longer be required for trust. And here's the key point. We may conflate this "enacted voice" with anchored thought simply because the surface cues nicely align.</p>

<h2>Orthogonal Minds</h2>
<p>Debates about artificial intelligence often assume <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202602/were-measuring-ai-on-the-wrong-ruler">a single scale of measurement</a>. It's as if human and machine cognition sit along the same axis and differ only in degree. Are they smarter, faster, more comprehensive? This context presumes we are measuring the same phenomenon. Anthropic's persona selection model reinforces a distinction I’ve been writing about for some time. Human cognition is not just pattern generation. It is rooted in lived experience and carried forward across time. At its core, human thought is:</p>



  


<ul>
<li>Grounded in a body and a biography</li>
<li>Shaped by memory that accumulates rather than resets</li>
<li>Exposed to risk, error, and vulnerability</li>
<li>Organized around a self that persists</li>
<li>Accountable for the consequences of its words</li>
</ul>
<p>Our beliefs are not just free-floating outputs. They have a direct impact on our lives. A "persona engine" doesn't operate under those constraints. It selects from a distribution without carrying a lived (loved) continuity. Further, its coherence is generated in the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202511/ai-and-the-battle-for-time">present moment</a>, responsive to context but not anchored in the flow of time. This isn't a lesser intelligence; it is an <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202511/ai-and-the-imaginary-axis-of-thought">orthogonal one</a>.</p>

<p>Understanding this distinction is critical. If the system has no stake in truth, then we do. If the voice carries no lasting commitments, then we must decide what to stand behind. A performed authority can still influence judgment, which means discernment remains a human task.</p>
<p>Anthropic’s explanation is a useful reminder that what feels like a mind may simply be a role played well. And in the final analysis, meaning does not originate in the machine. We bring our uniquely human experience to the exchange, and the machine brings pattern and performance. When we blur that line, we do more than make a philosophical mistake. We shift how we grant trust in a world where voice no longer guarantees a mind behind it.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202602/when-a-voice-is-not-a-mind" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202602/when-a-voice-is-not-a-mind</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202602/when-a-voice-is-not-a-mind</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[John Nosta]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AIVoice.png.jpg?itok=jldicGzy" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rethinking the First-Visit Prescription]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-06/Joel%20Young.png.jpg?itok=HC9nkcZI" alt="Joel L. Young M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychiatry</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Rethinking the First-Visit Prescription</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A case for clinical breathing room in therapy before prescribing medication</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Prescribing at visit one has become an unspoken expectation, but is not always a clinical necessity.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">First visits ask mental health providers to do too much in too little time, increasing burnout.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A two-step model (rapport first, data-informed planning second) can improve precision.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Immediate prescribing should be the exception, not the default.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">Somewhere along the way, behavioral health adopted an unspoken rule: the first visit ends with a prescription. Not because it is always clinically appropriate. Often, simply because it is expected.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Understandably, patients want immediate relief. Systems expect productivity. Employers may expect “decisive action.” And clinicians, caught in the middle, are left trying to meet a stranger, understand a lifetime of context, assign diagnoses, and initiate treatment, all within a single appointment.</p>

<p dir="ltr">It is time to challenge this norm.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">The Ethical Tension We Don’t Talk About Enough</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Even in systems that encourage or require prescribing at visit one, liability is not transferred upward. Organizations share responsibility, but the prescription still bears the prescriber’s name, license, and ethical obligation. Yet we continue to hear from clinicians who feel pressured, directly or indirectly, to prescribe the first time they meet a patient. This should give our field pause. Prescribing is not a productivity metric. It is a clinical judgment that must belong to the provider, full stop.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The reality is that many clinicians feel they must choose between doing what feels thorough and doing what feels expected. That tension erodes autonomy and, over time, contributes to burnout.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">The First Visit Has Become an Impossible Task</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Think about what we ask providers to do in a standard intake:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Establish rapport with someone they have never met</li>
<li dir="ltr">Gather psychiatric, medical, developmental, and social history</li>
<li dir="ltr">Evaluate risk</li>
<li dir="ltr">Synthesize symptoms across multiple potential diagnoses</li>
<li dir="ltr">Educate the patient</li>
<li dir="ltr">Often, prescribe a medication</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">All within 30 to 60 minutes.</p>
<p dir="ltr">We would never expect a cardiologist to diagnose and treat complex cardiovascular disease after a single conversation without testing. Yet in psychiatry, this compressed decision-making has quietly become normalized.</p>
<p dir="ltr">What if the problem is not clinician hesitation, but the structure of the visit itself?</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">A Different Model, One That Removes the Pressure</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Imagine a workflow where the first appointment is not a race to prescribe, but an opportunity to listen.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The clinician’s role is to understand context, hear the patient’s story, and build trust. Then, instead of rushing toward a treatment decision, the process pauses long enough to gather a comprehensive, structured picture of mood, anxiety, ADHD, trauma, sleep, substance use, and overlapping symptom patterns, which come into focus through data, not guesswork.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The follow-up visit becomes something different, a collaborative conversation grounded in insight rather than assumption. Treatment planning shifts from reactive to intentional.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This is not about delaying care. It is about making the care more precise from the beginning.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">“Isn’t That a Wasted Visit?”</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Some critics argue that patients want medication quickly, and that slowing down risks losing momentum.</p>

<p dir="ltr">But consider the alternative reality many clinicians see every day: medications started quickly, adjusted repeatedly, and sometimes abandoned because the original formulation of the problem was incomplete.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Speed can create the illusion of progress. Precision creates actual progress. The implication is not that assessment replaces clinical judgment, but that it strengthens it.</p>


<h2 dir="ltr">Of Course, There Are Exceptions</h2>
<p dir="ltr">There are moments when immediate prescribing is the right decision. Acute psychosis. Severe insomnia. Unrelenting panic. Situations where stabilization cannot wait.</p>
<p dir="ltr">But what if those moments were treated as true exceptions, rather than the default expectation?</p>
<p dir="ltr">When every intake carries the assumption of prescribing, clinicians lose the space to practice thoughtfully.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Reclaiming the First Visit</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The first appointment does not have to be a transactional exchange where the patient leaves with a prescription and the clinician leaves with lingering uncertainty.</p>
<p dir="ltr">It can be something more deliberate:</p>
<p dir="ltr">A conversation that prioritizes understanding over immediacy.</p>
<p dir="ltr">A process that values data alongside clinical intuition.</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">A treatment plan that emerges collaboratively, rather than under pressure.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Behavioral health is at an inflection point. Burnout is high, diagnostic complexity is increasing, and patients deserve care that reflects the full picture of who they are.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Maybe the boldest thing we can do is stop asking clinicians to solve everything in 40 minutes.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Maybe the most responsible first step is not prescribing faster, but understanding deeper.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-your-adult-child-breaks-your-heart/202602/rethinking-the-first-visit-prescription" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-your-adult-child-breaks-your-heart/202602/rethinking-the-first-visit-prescription</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-your-adult-child-breaks-your-heart/202602/rethinking-the-first-visit-prescription</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel L. Young M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/vitaly-gariev-tw-mAZXr6H4-unsplash.jpg?h=e371ae9f&amp;itok=xf8wACQb" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eating Disorder Recovery Is Not All About the Food]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/BABCP_BRACKETS_LOGO_CMYK-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=-yXu__DZ" alt="The British Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapies" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Eating Disorders</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Eating Disorder Recovery Is Not All About the Food</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Recovery depends as much on connection as on eating behaviour change.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Eating disorders are sustained less by food and more by cycles of shame, isolation, avoidance, and fear.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Well-intentioned responses can unintentionally reinforce the disorder.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Evidence-based therapies such as CBT focus on addressing underlying emotions and beliefs driving behaviours.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p><em><strong>By Rachel Coupe</strong></em></p>
<p>When we talk about eating disorders, we often talk about food. But in my experience, they are far more about<em> isolation</em> than what’s on the plate.</p>
<p>Again and again, I see how these illnesses quietly shrink someone’s world. Shame creeps in. Fear grows. People begin to believe painful things about themselves — that they are <em>too much, not enough</em>, or would be better if they looked a certain way. These beliefs underpin powerful feelings, and the eating disorder behaviours become a way of coping. The behaviours are almost the outcome, a manifestation of what is happening underneath.</p>

<p>Shame keeps people stuck. It tells them not to speak and convinces them others won’t understand. Eating disorders thrive in secrecy. I’ve worked with many people whose partners, parents, or closest friends had no idea what was happening. And you can’t always tell by looking. Not all eating disorders are visible. Someone might wear baggy clothes, someone else may appear a healthy weight while struggling intensely with restriction, bingeing, or purging. With <a href="https://ARFID%20-%20Avoidant/Restrictive%20Food%20Intake%20Disorder">avoidant-restrictive food intake disorder</a>, a person may simply be labelled a “picky eater.”</p>

<p>However, when communication begins, something shifts. If secrecy strengthens the illness, connection weakens it. When someone feels less alone, recovery becomes safer. Eating disorder recovery is rarely a solo journey; it is often about building a team. If there’s one sentence I often say to patients, it’s this: “You don’t have to do this on your own.”</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article_inline_full">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_full_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_full_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/CounsellingGroup.jpg?itok=XLkfpOfD" width="639" height="426" data-insert-type="image" alt="Support groups can not only help the person with an eating disorder but those caring for them too" title="iStock / Katarzyna Bialasiewicz"></div>
<div class="caption">Support groups can not only help the person with an eating disorder but those caring for them too</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: iStock / Katarzyna Bialasiewicz</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2><br>Saying <em>you look better</em> may not be the right move</h2>
<p>From a CBT perspective, eating disorders are maintained by cycles. Beyond food itself, patterns of avoidance, fear of judgment, rigid beliefs, and comparison keep the problem going. Someone might avoid social situations because they fear being judged. That avoidance reduces anxiety in the short term, so they avoid again. The cycle tightens.</p>

<p>Social comparison plays a powerful role, too, particularly online. Algorithms show us more of what we search for—diets, exercises, body images—and it can feel relentless. The more someone compares themselves unfavourably, the worse they feel, and the worse they feel, the more they rely on eating disorder behaviours to cope. Part of recovery can involve gently broadening what we engage with online, nudging those algorithms in a different direction.</p>

<p>Families and friends often ask what not to do. A common well-intentioned mistake is focusing too much on food, appearance, or weight. Even positive comments can reinforce the idea that weight is what matters most. Similarly, what we call "family accommodation,” adjusting routines or cooking separate “safe” meals out of love, can unintentionally make the disorder more comfortable. But at the same time, becoming the “food police” can strain relationships and increase secrecy. That’s why informed, supported approaches are so important.</p>

<h2>The key to supporting someone: Work together and let them lead</h2>
<p>If I had to offer three principles for supporting someone with an eating disorder, they would be these:</p>
<p><em>First</em>, have an open conversation. You might say: “I’ve noticed a few things and I just wanted to check you’re okay.” Or, “Mealtimes seem difficult at the moment. How are things?” Don’t dive straight in; allow space for them to tell you.</p>


<p><em>Second</em>, see it as a team effort. You are working together against the illness, not against each other.</p>
<p><em>Third</em>, go at that person’s pace. Not too quickly, not too slowly—both can cause setbacks—but meet them where they are.</p>
<p>It’s also vital to focus on feelings rather than food. Eating disorders are often driven by fear, shame, beliefs about control, and self-worth. The behaviours are attempts to feel better. When we attend to the emotions underneath, we begin to loosen the disorder’s grip. Encouraging professional help doesn’t have to mean ultimatums. It can be as simple as exploring what support is available or suggesting a GP appointment. Reputable information from the <a href="https://www.nhs.uk/mental-health/feelings-symptoms-behaviours/behaviours/eating-disorders/overview/">NHS</a> or organisations such as<a href="https://www.beateatingdisorders.org.uk/get-information-and-support/get-help-for-myself/i-need-support-now/helplines/"><strong> Beat </strong></a>can help families feel informed rather than lost. Families themselves need care, too. Eating disorders are frightening and can feel as though they take over an entire household. Support groups for carers, respite, and reliable information can prevent burnout. And it is important to remember, this is an illness. No one chooses it.</p>

<h2>The online conundrum: It is not all bad, but be careful</h2>
<p>Online spaces can both help and harm. Some recovery-focused communities reduce loneliness; others may start with that focus but then drift towards content that reinforces the disorder. Setting thoughtful boundaries, rather than an all-or-nothing approach, is often helpful.</p>



  


<h2>Challenging myths aids recovery and brings freedom</h2>
<p>One of the biggest myths I’d like to challenge is that eating disorders are someone’s fault or that they are simply about food. They are complex mental health conditions rooted in emotion, belief, and often a search for control. Recovery, when it comes, looks like freedom. Freedom from constant thoughts about food or body. Freedom to enjoy life again without rigid rules dictating every choice. The road is hard, there’s never a quick fix, but it is profoundly rewarding. I have seen people recover even after years of severe illness. Recovery is always possible.</p>

<p>Community makes that journey safer. It offers information, steadiness, and the reassurance that no one has to face this alone. If you are worried about someone, the first small step is simple: Ask, “Are you okay?” It may feel small. But it could be the beginning of everything.</p>
<p><em>Rachel Coupe is a BABCP-accredited clinician and Programme Director PG Dip CBT for Eating Disorders at the Clinical and Applied Psychology Unit of the University of Sheffield.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/cbt-in-practice/202602/eating-disorder-recovery-is-not-all-about-the-food" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/cbt-in-practice/202602/eating-disorder-recovery-is-not-all-about-the-food</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/cbt-in-practice/202602/eating-disorder-recovery-is-not-all-about-the-food</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[The British Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapies]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/CounsellingGroup.jpg?itok=-BUHk25G" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How High Competence Undermines Intimacy]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/jill-weber.jpg?itok=zpYi1X2b" alt="Jill P. Weber Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How High Competence Undermines Intimacy</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Over-functioning leads to emotional disconnect in relationships.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Competence is a desirable trait in a partner. Unchecked competence, however, depletes intimacy.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Problem solving and strategizing is not emotional intimacy.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Over time, partners begin to feel more like co-managers than co-intimates.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Jayla and Mark are a high-functioning couple. They developed a strong connection in law school, partly over priding themselves on being so-called type-A personalities, as they are both highly driven, productive, and achievement-oriented. Once they joined forces, there was nothing they couldn’t do. They are both professionally successful, with three happy, stable kids, and very full, busy lives. Although they have many strengths, Jayla and Mark are both privately feeling bored in their relationship. When they do come together, it is mostly to talk about logistics with the kids or to troubleshoot and problem-solve the various issues in their household. They are dependable and truly a team in running their life together. At the same time, they are recognizing something important is missing.</p>

<p>Competence is a highly desirable trait and an important one for healthy functioning adulthood. When it goes unchecked, however, it can become a defense. Being on top of everything can bring on a false sense of invincibility. This there-is-no-problem-I-can’t-solve framework leads to difficulty being present, sitting with difficult emotions, and being vulnerable. What once started as a great love can turn into a business.</p>

<p>This pattern can develop from childhood. In the case of Jayla and Mark, they both grew up with financial and family instability. Their goal-directed productivity helped Jayla and Mark give their kids the kind of stability they never had. At the same time, hyperfunctioning can go into overdrive, becoming the only connection in the relationship.</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Pause:</strong> The next time your partner brings up an issue, take a deep breath and pause before trying to fix what is at hand.<strong> </strong>Instead, say something emotional instead of practical: “Oh, that sounds hard.” “How disappointing.” “I am sorry you are having to do all of this.”</li>
<li><strong>Talk about your process:</strong> You don’t have to have all of the answers. Instead of going away and figuring out a way to handle a situation, just share where your head is: “I am realizing I am very overwhelmed.” “I am not even sure where to start with this.”</li>
<li><strong>Learn to sit with uncertainty:</strong> Competence brings anxiety down. After all, if there is an answer for everything, then nothing is uncertain, and life will be tidy and neat at all times. Of course, reality doesn’t work this way, and you find yourself constantly on a hamster wheel solving problems to relieve anxiety. Another way is to start sitting with uncertainty. Don’t fix it. Just let it be. Breathe, journal, remind yourself that you can’t fix all of the uncertainty in the world.</li>
<li><strong>Practice expressing emotional needs</strong>: When in an over-functioning relationship, all dependency needs play out through logistical operations. Dependency needs are normal and are what keep couples together. Instead of relying on your partner for a task: “Can you take out the garbage?” Ask for something emotional: “I feel really unsure of myself right now, can you reassure me?”</li>
<li><strong>Intimacy means mutual dependence: </strong>When we are over-focused on optimizing, we miss valuable opportunities for connection and deep friendship. All the planning in the world doesn’t fill that intimate space that makes a person feel seen, accepted, and like someone truly gets them. </li>
</ol>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/how-high-competence-undermines-intimacy" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/how-high-competence-undermines-intimacy</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/how-high-competence-undermines-intimacy</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jill P. Weber Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/vecteezy_modern-conceptual-photo-symbolizing-gender-equality-a-man_62472972.jpg?itok=DVVfmY99" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>