<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2026 04:49:26 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2026 04:49:26 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Questions Young Adults Are Asking About Love]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-06/Rebekka%20Grun%20%281%29.png.jpg?itok=rox3yIrq" alt="Rebekka Grun Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Mating</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Questions Young Adults Are Asking About Love</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why "seeing where it goes" is costing you more than you think.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Modern dating offers freedom but little structure.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Situationships may feel safe short-term but can reduce long-term relationship and opportunity options.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People assort by values, education, and sometimes politics; initial sorting matters more than convergence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Compatibility lowers friction; plan your love life directionally rather than “seeing where it goes.”</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/akihiro-miyamoto-nNfXGwH9rgo-unsplash.jpg?itok=g9VJKnJ6" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="By Akihiro Miyamoto on Unsplash" alt="By Akihiro Miyamoto on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: By Akihiro Miyamoto on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Modern dating happens in a world that no longer has clear guardrails. There is no Austenian social choreography of paying calls, and we have long left Vienna ballroom etiquette behind us. On the face of it, there is a myriad of options, and everything seems possible.</p>
<p>The complication is that not everything is good for everyone. Lack of commitment can hurt. Delayed decisions mean reduced options. It takes planning and decision-making — intentionality, not drifting — to thrive in this context.</p>

<p>I recently spoke with students at Georgetown University about this. After the formal discussion ended, many stayed behind. They didn’t want another lecture. They wanted answers.</p>
<p>The questions clustered around four recurring tensions young adults are navigating with impressive seriousness.</p>
<h2>The 4 Recurring Tensions</h2>

<p><strong>1. Situationships and the Cost of Not Deciding</strong></p>
<p>Sometimes young people’s relationships reflect the insecurity of the broader world. They find themselves in “situationships” — romantic or sexual relationships that are not clearly established or recognized as such. These can show up, for example, as “friends with benefits” (FWB).</p>

<p>Allow me to state the obvious: Non-decision is a decision. If you don’t decide, every whim of your environment may decide for you. Because of our <a href="https://www.worldscientific.com/doi/abs/10.1142/9789814417358_0006">human status quo bias</a>, we can get locked into a situationship and hesitate to break the ambiguity.</p>
<p>Ambiguity feels safe in the short run but can be expensive in the long run, as you may miss better opportunities. And <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/buy/2010-25811-011">empirically</a>, it is generally wiser to align your body language — including sexual intimacy — with your level of commitment. When behavior signals more than intention, attachment tends to follow.</p>

<p><strong>2. Do Partners Converge or Polarize?</strong></p>
<p>Historically, we observe strong assortative matching among long-term partners: people pair with those similar in looks, values, education, and even sense of humor. We also observe increasing political sorting, particularly in more polarized societies and periods. The more political leaning is understood as an identity marker, the less acceptable it becomes to date across the aisle.</p>

<p>That is unfortunate, because romantic love can be a force for social integration.</p>
<p>Over time, couples tend to converge in daily habits. <a href="https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev.soc.24.1.395">Political convergence, however, appears more modest than initial sorting</a>. Interestingly, the more politically engaged spouse often exerts greater influence within the relationship (rich literature on this tension from <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/perspectives-on-politics/article/partisan-families-the-social-logic-of-bounded-partisanship-in-germany-and-britain-by-zuckerman-alan-s-dasovic-josip-and-fitzgerald-jennifer-new-york-cambridge-university-press-2007-224p-7500-cloth-2499-paper-democracy-intermediation-and-voting-on-four-continents-edited-by-gunther-richard-montero-jose-ramon-and-puhle-hansjurgen-new-york-oxford-university-press-2007-448p-14300-cloth-3500-paper/DD960C683AA312704B0BB43A51568145">Zuckerman et al</a>.).</p>

<p><strong>3. The “Singles Tax” and Opportunity Costs</strong></p>
<p>Is there a “singles tax”? In other words, is it costly to remain single? This is classic Loveonomics.</p>
<p>Overall, the answer is yes. Couples benefit from economies of scale: shared housing, shared fixed household tasks, shared risk. If one partner is temporarily sick or underproductive, the other can compensate — a form of informal insurance. In some countries, tax codes explicitly favor married couples over singles.</p>


<p>Singlehood is not a failure. But from a strictly economic perspective, partnership often generates efficiencies.</p>
<p><strong>4. Is Assortative Matching Wise?</strong></p>
<p>Should we actively seek assortative matching — for example, by dating within our religious or educational community?</p>
<p>Empirically, strong assortative matching along education, income, religion, and core values predicts greater relationship stability. Values shape how we plan our lives and invest our time. If partners see eye to eye on these fundamentals, there is strength in unity rather than recurring conflict.</p>

<p>Values are also tied to vulnerability. It matters to feel safe expressing them. That said, when differences are embraced, supported, and even cherished, they can become a source of bonding and growth. Bottom line: Compatibility reduces friction. Complementarity creates growth.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/edited.jpg?itok=xNLLhaEk" width="320" height="269" data-insert-type="image" alt="After a recent talk at Georgetown University, students stayed to debate the economics of modern love." title=" Christina Prinssen, Georgetown University"></div>
<div class="caption">After a recent talk at Georgetown University, students stayed to debate the economics of modern love.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Christina Prinssen, Georgetown University</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Bottom Line: Plan, Don’t Drift</h2>
<p>The world is uncertain, and modern dating lacks external guardrails. That means you must make your own decisions. Intentionality is powerful; “seeing where it goes” is not. <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/books/generation-unbound/">Research</a> on decision-making and life outcomes supports this.</p>
<p>How exactly to practice intentionality in love may be the topic of another post. In the end, love is not only about maximizing utility. It is about choosing a direction — and committing to it.</p>



  


<p>The most striking thing about the Georgetown conversation was the rigor and intelligent curiosity students brought to the topic. They are not disconnected, polarizing, or drifting apart. They are thinking carefully.</p>
<p>With young people like this, there is reason for optimism. They will seek, learn, and do better than previous generations.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/maximizing-relationships-and-happiness-in-life/202603/the-questions-young-adults-are-asking" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/maximizing-relationships-and-happiness-in-life/202603/the-questions-young-adults-are-asking</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/maximizing-relationships-and-happiness-in-life/202603/the-questions-young-adults-are-asking</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rebekka Grun von Jolk Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/akihiro-miyamoto-nNfXGwH9rgo-unsplash.jpg?itok=noLKl8u0" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Wisdom From "The Princess Bride"]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/Headshot_Sedley_-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=Osjd4m3Z" alt="Ben Sedley" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Wisdom</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Wisdom From "The Princess Bride"</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">"You keep using that word. I do not think it means what you think it means."</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Acceptance is about making space for thoughts and feelings, even the painful ones.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Suffering comes from trying not have the thoughts and feelings you're having.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Try an exercise to observe painful feelings with care and curiosity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Late last year, we lost one of the world’s greatest film makers when Rob Reiner was murdered alongside his wife. He was a gifted comedic actor, a screenwriter, the director of two of my all-time favourite films, and most importantly, a mensch.</p>
<p>A quote from one of Reiner's films that I regularly use is from the Man in Black in <em>The Princess Bride</em>. He says, <em>‘Life is Pain, highness. Anyone who says differently is selling something.’</em></p>

<p>We were raised to believe that life should be better than this – more fun, more successful, more comfortable, more cool stuff, less sadness, less worry, less bad stuff. We’re given this message repeatedly: Be good and good things come to you; work hard and you’ll get what you deserve. Every ad promises happiness, every social media influencer promises success. Parents, teachers, religions, and politicians all promise us that we should be able to get more if we work for it and deserve it.</p>

<p>We are left feeling bad for having feelings that we can’t avoid.</p>
<p>Pain comes to all of us at different times, in different forms, and different sizes. Often it feels awful or unfair. Pain doesn’t only befall those who deserve it or have done bad things or haven’t looked after themselves.</p>
<p>There are sensible things we can do to reduce pain. Painkillers help…except when they don’t. Thinking positively helps…except when it doesn’t. Exercise and nutrition are great but no guarantee of a healthy, happy life.</p>

<p>Sometimes, our attempts to avoid pain lead to more suffering. We might take medication, drink alcohol, go to therapy, avoid people, say positive affirmations, miss work, or do mindfulness meditation and feel better briefly, only to find that the pain comes back, maybe even a bit stronger or louder.</p>
<p>Instead, we need to find a way to accept the thoughts we don’t like, the feelings that hurt, and the physical symptoms that cause discomfort. But acceptance is not simple.</p>

<p><em>Acceptance</em> is a word that seems to be used everywhere now. Sometimes, it’s used dismissively. People might tell you to just ‘accept it’, meaning ‘suck it up’, ‘ignore it’, or ‘stop talking about it’. Others were taught to associate acceptance with surrendering, giving in, or putting up with injustice. I’m sorry if you’ve had this experience.</p>

<p>Acceptance can also be confused with <em>tolerating</em> a feeling. You might tell yourself you can ‘put up’ with a feeling, as long as it doesn’t get too intense or stick around for too long.</p>
<p>Other times people try to treat acceptance as a clever therapy trick. If you can just ‘accept’ this sadness or anxiety or trauma or chronic pain, then you won’t have to have it anymore. Wouldn’t it be great if this were true? If you could just use acceptance as a tool to avoid accepting what you’re feeling? But acceptance isn’t a trick or a technique. It's about genuinely making space for discomfort. So, why on earth would we want to learn to hold our internal pain? It’s heavy. It hurts. And right now, you have it whether you want it to be there or not (although I’m not making any statement about whether you will always have it).</p>

<p>So, let’s use our curiosity and noticing skills to get to know our pain.</p>
<p>Take in a breath.</p>
<p>As you breathe in, what does it feel like to be breathing in?</p>
<p>As you breathe out, what does it feel like to be breathing out?</p>
<p>Now have a look around inside your body. What feelings, emotions and sensations can you notice? Are there any that feel raw or uncomfortable? Let’s spend some time with those. Don’t try to remove them or change them; rather, notice them with curiosity. Like you’ve never felt these feelings before.</p>

<p>Where do these feelings sit inside your body? How big are they? Do they have a shape? Do they have a particular texture or colour? Are they jagged or smooth? Are they heavy or light?</p>
<p>As you observe these feelings, are you also able to observe your breath? Watch as your breath comes into your body, passes around the feelings wherever they are sitting, and goes out of your body again. Let your breath do whatever it needs to do to care for you and nourish you. Observe this for a few cycles of breath.</p>

<p>Your mind might tell you that there is no room inside you for these feelings. Yet, what is your experience telling you right now? You can breathe around these feelings. There is room inside you for these emotions and sensations, even the feelings that are uncomfortable and you really wish weren’t inside you. Notice your breath is able to pass around these feelings too. Keep coming back to your breath. You’ve got this.</p>



  


<p>Now I invite you to take a warm compassionate hand and place it on the part of the body that is experiencing these feelings. What does it feel like to have the feelings and to have the breath and to have the warmth and compassion? Can you observe them all? Observe this as you breathe in and breathe out. Then slowly, when you’re ready, take three more breaths before bringing your focus back to the world around you.</p>

<p>Now, take some time to notice what it was like to do that. What was it like to observe your discomfort rather than fight it? To see the discomfort for what it is rather than to listen to your mind telling you that it shouldn’t be there or that you won’t cope if it continues?</p>
<p>Did you notice that there is room inside you for the discomfort? For the emotions or judgemental thoughts? Even for those things you really wish that you didn’t have to be holding? You are bigger and stronger that any of these thoughts or emotions or sensations or urges or memories. Knowing that doesn’t stop it hurting, but maybe the awareness that you can hold it frees up some energy that you would have spent fighting it, and allows you to do things that matter to you. </p>

<p><em>Adapted from my book </em>Holding the Heavy Stuff: Making Space for Critical Thoughts and Painful Emotions.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/holding-the-heavy-stuff/202603/wisdom-from-the-princess-bride" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/holding-the-heavy-stuff/202603/wisdom-from-the-princess-bride</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/holding-the-heavy-stuff/202603/wisdom-from-the-princess-bride</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Sedley]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/stuffThatSucks_FINAL%202.png.jpg?itok=CZuIYVm4" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From River to Stream: How Vulnerability Becomes Illness]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/HURFORD-48-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=KEgGRKGY" alt="Irene Hurford MD" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychiatry</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">From River to Stream: How Vulnerability Becomes Illness</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">In psychiatry, genetic vulnerability is not destiny.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The genetics of mental illness are complicated.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Genetic vulnerability does not confer a guarantee of illness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Trauma and adversity can act like a dam — an obstacle to healthy development.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/zhivko-minkov-tQFQh344DN8-unsplash.jpg?itok=jaZyIqyh" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Zhivko Minkov on Unsplash" alt="Photo by Zhivko Minkov on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Zhivko Minkov on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>When I see patients with serious mental health issues, they often speak of their genetic burden: “My father had bipolar disorder”, “my grandmother was schizophrenic”, “my aunt has severe depression”. My patients feel their psychiatric destiny weighing them down, as though there is no hope for recovery or cure in light of their heredity. But the genetics of all psychiatric diagnoses are complex and not easy to understand, even for doctors and scientists. I try to explain it like this:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Psychological development is like a river flowing along its course. </strong>From birth, our psychological maturation runs along healthy developmental lines like a river. Unimpeded, the river flows smoothly, and genetic predispositions towards illness may not be realized. A baby born into a family with emotionally healthy parents in a financially secure position, in a neighborhood without conflict, in a part of the world with geopolitical stability, might grow up psychologically healthy no matter their genetics. Whatever vulnerabilities they have to psychiatric disorders are not exploited by the environment and so lie dormant and unexpressed.</li>
<li><strong>When the river is dammed, pressure builds up behind it. </strong>Along our own rivers of development, sometimes life erects a dam of abuse, neglect, war, disease, poverty, cruelty, or conflict. As the pressure builds behind the dam, water finds new paths, and flows from areas of higher resistance to areas of lower resistance. Our own development will similarly follow paths of least resistance.</li>
<li><strong>Our genetics are the areas of lower resistance. </strong>This is where genetic vulnerability might come in. The vulnerabilities behave metaphorically like dry streambeds that absorb the river’s runoff – areas where our genetic heritage acts as an area of lower resistance. One person’s genetic makeup might lead the river to flow towards an eating disorder; for someone else it may flow into substance abuse. It could flow into a psychotic disorder, or OCD. If her psychological development is left undisturbed, a child might grow up healthy and well-adjusted. But once the river is dammed, she will find herself experiencing the symptoms consistent with her area of lowest resistance.</li>
<li><strong>Genetics are not the only inheritance from our family.</strong> Sometimes the “genetic vulnerability” is something more complicated; perhaps some genetic contribution but also learned patterns of behavior. A child watching her depressed mother or alcoholic father might develop these same coping mechanisms, or coping mechanisms in direct response to those of her parents. Is that genetics, or behavioral learning? And then there is the added complexity of epigenetics — changes to gene activity without permanent changes to the DNA. Epigenetics describes how trauma, adversity, stress, and so on can influence which genes in our DNA are activated or not, thus changing us biologically through influences from our environment. Both behavioral learning and epigenetics illustrate how complex interactions between our genes and environment shape which streams emerge after the open river is dammed.</li>
<li><strong>Adaptations to life.</strong> Nature is constantly adapting to new constraints. We, as part of nature, do the same. While a dam along our river might lead us towards illness determined at least in part by our genetics, it can also lead to healthy modifications. A newer concept in psychology is post-traumatic growth – that while some find themselves damaged by trauma, others experience psychological growth as a consequence. This idea is closely related to resilience. If for some, the dam forces them down paths of genetically predisposed illness, for others, the dam offers an opportunity to change direction and create a more adaptive course.</li>
<li><strong>Treating the dam, not the streams.</strong> What does this mean for treatment? I think of psychiatric medications as widening the banks of the river, so that some water gets around the obstruction. But I believe that therapy and other activities that lead to meaning-making have the ability to actually dismantle the dam. As we make new meaning of our life, we begin to remove the sticks and branches slowly, allowing the dam to eventually weaken and wash away. Then the water flows back through the river, and can continue along the original, or perhaps an improved, course.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>To find a therapist, </strong><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><strong>visit the Psychology Today Therapy Directory</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/reality-in-dialogue/202603/from-river-to-stream-how-vulnerability-becomes-illness" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/reality-in-dialogue/202603/from-river-to-stream-how-vulnerability-becomes-illness</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/reality-in-dialogue/202603/from-river-to-stream-how-vulnerability-becomes-illness</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Irene Hurford MD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/zhivko-minkov-tQFQh344DN8-unsplash.jpg?itok=bl_Pfrb6" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Greetings From My Bomb Shelter]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/alanasiegle_0.png.jpg?itok=x9-CMqie" alt="Alana Siegel Psy.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Trauma</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Greetings From My Bomb Shelter</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: How I have used my trauma training to navigate a war.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In uncertain times, focus on what you can control.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Schedules, rituals, and self-care are paramount in navigating stress.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>I am now 36 hours into my third war in two and a half years, and once again I am leaning heavily into my practice as a trauma psychologist to navigate this intense reality. I have experienced October 7 and its aftermath, the 12-day Israel-Iranian war, and now this newest round of warfare between Israel, the United States, and Iran. Between waking up and eating my breakfast this morning there were already six rounds of sirens, which meant that I could not leave my bomb shelter for an hour. This is a continuation of yesterday, which also had nonstop rounds of sirens punctuated by the loud booms of Iron Dome interceptions, as well as <a href="https://www.timesofisrael.com/woman-killed-dozens-injured-as-iranian-missile-strikes-tel-aviv-residential-block/">a ballistic missile that landed not far from my home</a>. The boom upon landing was enormous, resulting in 20 casualties and one death. There is a lot in my life that lacks control. <em>I focus on what it is in my life that I can control,</em> and lean into where I can make a tangible change.</p>

<p>As soon as I could leave the shelter in my apartment this morning, I leaned into following my schedule. First, I prepared a tasty breakfast for myself. It is important that I eat something nourishing. Although I know that stress eating feels good in the moment – and I love my chocolate – maintaining a healthy diet is important even in stressful times. After eating I cleaned my home, washed dishes, and did laundry; a tidy home gives me a sense of calm and control. Next, I took a shower and readied for my day: I used soaps, shampoos, lotions and perfume that make me feel good. Feeling clean and also using delightful scents bring me happiness, re-centers me, and are also acts of self-care. Although I looked longingly for a moment at my cozy pajamas, I rather opted to do my hair, makeup, and dress as I do on a daily basis – whether or not I will leave my home today. It is important to segment my time into night and day, and how I dress myself helps me make such a distinction. Grateful for a short reprieve from sirens, I cleaned and organized my shelter. I made my temporary bed and opened my metal window cover to let in fresh air into the room. To make the room cozier, I brought in some additional food, fluffed my pillows, and folded extra blankets.</p>

<p>My chores complete, I sat down to work. Even in the midst of an intensive security situation, work gives structure, focus, and purpose to my day – and I am grateful to have the intellectual stimulation. I also use this time to respond to calls and texts from family and friends. I am grateful for the social support, as it makes me feel less isolated and gives me a place to process my experiences. I have many feelings as I navigate these times – fear, anxiety, sadness, hopefulness – and sharing them with loved ones gives me a place to unpack and reflect on what is happening. I also know that if I feel the need, I can reach out to my therapist, as therapy can be a place to further process what is happening. I am here for my own patients as well – and we can schedule Zoom calls as needed.</p>

<p>The same strategies can be followed with children: Although the typical daily school schedule is suspended, meals can be served at their typical intervals, they can get dressed for the day ahead, and bedtime and wake time can remain the same. Try focusing on fun activities and how to make them laugh. Also aim to explain the situation in age-appropriate terms to help them understand all of these confusing events. Focus on modeling calm, as the sounds of the sirens can scare them; know that they are looking to their adults to serve as a guide of how to react to the piercing noise.</p>

<p>I am feeling anxious and tired. The frequent sirens are draining and the missile hit last night frightened and saddened me. So to address this, I did some meditation breathing on a count of four: I breathed in through my nose on a count of four; held for four; and released on a count of four. I like to sit on my couch and repeat this exercise until I feel noticeably calmer. I try to reframe my negative thoughts as much as possible, as a positive mindset helps me feel less fearful. Throughout the day I like to treat myself to little moments of pleasure, whether warm tea with honey, a cozy sweater, or reading a book that I enjoy. If I can do so, I will take a short walk outside but remain close to a shelter should there be a siren. I do take time also to scroll through social media and read the news; this can be a tricky balance between reading enough that I feel informed but limiting my intake so I that do not feel unduly frightened or overwhelmed. This afternoon I scheduled in fun activities that enhanced my sense of calm. I watched a movie that is a comedy, and laughter helped lighten my mood. I then did some exercise that elevated my heart rate.</p>

<p>I will wind down my day with dinner, my usual bedtime rituals, and a change into pajamas. I will go to sleep at my typical time. I also silence my phone before bedtime so that I can prioritize my sleep. I am going to close the metal window and heavy metal door so that I can sleep as well as possible, because I know that my sleep will play a crucial role in how I will function tomorrow. I focus on the present and keep catastrophic thoughts away, as these anxious thoughts are often not helpful and can only serve to enhance my anxiety. It is out of my control as to how long this conflict will last and with what intensity. I do not know what the next hour or day will necessarily bring. Instead, I focus on my training, schedule, and rituals to navigate a scary present.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/traumatized/202603/greetings-from-my-bomb-shelter" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/traumatized/202603/greetings-from-my-bomb-shelter</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/traumatized/202603/greetings-from-my-bomb-shelter</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Alana Siegel Psy.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/TOI.png.jpg?itok=RT1lQtRo" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>