<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 20:39:54 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 20:39:54 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Most Dangerous Books in Society]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/authors/todd_kashdan.jpg?itok=r_tteI1a" alt="Todd B. Kashdan Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Adolescence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Most Dangerous Books in Society</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Research on the ineffectiveness of school book bans.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A study found that reading banned books predicted civic engagement more strongly than personality traits.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Reading banned books showed zero correlation with grades, violent crime, or nonviolent crime in adolescents.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Reactance theory explains why censorship backfires: Restricted freedoms activate curiosity and thinking.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Books kids choose for pleasure predicted higher GPAs while assigned school reading showed no such effect.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>We talk about a lot of strange things in my <a href="https://psychology.gmu.edu/people/tkashdan">Psychology 417: Science of Well-Being</a> class. Several years ago, a student told me why she signed up even though she’s an engineering major.</p>
<p>She was 13 when she discovered most adults were full of crap. Now, most teenagers figure this out through the absurdity of 9pm curfews (because <a href="https://www.childpsych.theclinics.com/article/S1056-4993(09)00039-X/abstract">older kids have a different circadian rhythm</a>) or arguments in which “<em>Because I said so</em>” is considered authoritative. Standing in front of a middle-school librarian, trying and failing to check out <em>The Catcher in the Rye</em> (most of all because it was not a book for girls), her self-talk repeated <em>this is shite</em>. As she waited for a decent explanation, all the librarian did was stand there, fingers drumming on the circulation desk.</p>

<p>She then found the book on a cart labeled “To Be Rearranged” in the back corner of the library. Someone’s parent had complained. The district had responded with enthusiastic efficiency.</p>
<p>Don’t get the character of this woman wrong: She is not a political activist with pink hair. She knows plenty of kids get told no every day and survive just fine. She merely relayed the moment when adults making decisions about what she could handle had no idea what she could handle. You would have thought they had an idea what she was dealing with in terms of bullying, big emotions, and all the rest. But they had no idea that protecting her from Holden Caulfield’s profanity-laced despair was absurd when her own confusion about (failing to) belong was far more cruel/crude.</p>

<p>The student found the book and read it in a week. When she finished, she did not feel corrupted. Now, she started paying attention to other people and the power they really did not have over her. Some might call this <em>agency and empowerment.</em> If so, we will get along….</p>
<p>Do you know that the book banners were right? Just not in the way they thought.</p>

<p>Christopher Ferguson, a psychologist interested in moral panics decided to study what happens when kids read books that adults don’t want them reading. He surveyed 282 adolescents aged 12 to 18, gave them a list of 30 commonly challenged books (everything from Harry Potter to <em>Huckleberry Finn</em> to <em>The Hunger Games</em>), and measured grades, prosocial behavior, mental health, criminal activity.</p>

<p>What he found was that reading banned books had zero effect on grades. Zero effect on violent crime. Zero effect on nonviolent crime. The correlation between banned book exposure and GPA was so microscopic it might as well have been a mite on a football field.</p>
<p>The censors and their lame supporters might start sweating if they read the article and discovered that <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/fulltext/2014-11063-001.html">kids who read more banned books</a> showed significantly more positive community engagement. More interest in politics and elections. More involvement in charitable causes. The standardized regression coefficient for banned books predicting civic behavior was β = .23 (a meaningful effect, but please don’t let me bore you with the details, and the strongest predictor in the model after you account for personality, family, and peer influences).</p>

<p>For those who despise statistics, another way of saying this is that banned books were a better predictor of making the local community better than secure family attachments, positive peer influences, and personality traits such as agreeableness and emotional stability and openness to experience. </p>
<p>Pretty amazing, and it's pretty amazing that nobody is talking about this in these conversations!</p>

<p>The book banners accidentally created better citizens. Why? Because censorship fails in the most spectacular way possible. Sharon and Jack Brehm figured this out in the 1960s and 1970s with r<a href="https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=klG4BwAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA3&amp;dq=sharon+brehm+reactance+theory&amp;ots=TynXIq0sz7&amp;sig=KZAVpRxhkFpQSIcJXGECVKyVB2Y">eactance theory</a>. When people perceive a threat to their freedom, they experience psychological arousal that motivates them to restore that freedom. Tell a teenager they cannot read something, and you have ramped up their curiosity to read said book and wonder what else they must do from the list of unacceptable actions. It becomes about autonomy, or the fundamental human drive to make your own choices about what enters your own mind.</p>


<p>Of note, reactance doesn’t make kids only read the forbidden book. It makes them care about why it was forbidden. It activates critical thinking about power, control, and who gets to decide what’s dangerous. It builds the cognitive muscles that a functioning democracy requires and, supposedly, what schools are supposed to train kids in.</p>

<p>Three kids passing around a contraband copy of a challenged novel during lunch could be alternatively viewed as an act of civic engagement. Last time I checked, solidarity and resource sharing and questioning authority when it oversteps bounds is literally how <a href="https://heterodoxacademy.org/blog/the-art-of-insubordination-a-handbook-for-designing-smarter-wiser-groups/">every meaningful social movement</a> in American history started.</p>



  


<p>Ferguson’s study also raised some questions about mental health panicking. The relationship between banned books and psychological symptoms was driven by a tiny subset, about 7% of the sample, who were both heavy readers of challenged books and already had elevated mental health symptoms. For the other 93% of kids? Nothing. No depression. No anxiety. No behavioral problems.</p>

<p>Of course, some methodology issues deserve attention, as they always do. Ferguson couldn’t determine whether those 7% were being harmed by the books or seeking them out because the books spoke to what they were experiencing. They might have doing exactly what a thoughtful person in pain would do, which is search for stories that offer insight. Banning or censoring books doesn’t protect that 7%. It strips them of the language to understand what they’re going through. It removes the evidence that other humans have survived what they’re surviving.</p>

<p>A barely mentioned scientific finding worth savoring is that reading for pleasure predicted higher GPAs while assigned school reading did not. Your kid’s teacher is not the master of their future intellect and wisdom; the books kids <em>choose</em> make them smarter. The books adults force on them don’t move the needle. Which means every school board that removes a book a kid wants to read and replaces it with an approved text nobody asked for is working against academic achievement.</p>

<p>You cannot make this stuff up. </p>
<p>So here’s my message to everyone losing their minds over whatever book they have deemed too dangerous for young eyes this year: <em>Thank you.</em></p>
<p>Thank you for making those books irresistible.</p>
<p>Thank you for transforming apathetic teenagers into passionate advocates for intellectual freedom.</p>

<p>Thank you for teaching kids that authority figures often don’t know what they’re talking about, that rules aren’t always just, that sometimes the most important thing you can do is seek out what someone told you to avoid.</p>
<p>You are not protecting children: Every list of challenged titles becomes a curiosity-inducing reading list.</p>

<p>Every attempt to control what young people think becomes a class in why young people should think for themselves.</p>
<p>The kids are fine. Better than fine. They’re volunteering. They’re helping other kids and adults. They are developing the critical thinking skills that make them able to see through misinformation and decoys. And they do it not despite your censorship, but because of it.</p>

<p>Keep banning books. Seriously. You are doing more for creating a healthy society than any curriculum committee in the country.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/curious/202602/the-most-dangerous-books-in-society" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/curious/202602/the-most-dangerous-books-in-society</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/curious/202602/the-most-dangerous-books-in-society</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Todd B. Kashdan Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Banned%20books.png.jpg?itok=jzSKc0Ii" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What the Urge to Leave a Cofounder Is Actually Telling You]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-02/Matt%20Jones.png.jpg?itok=HobMDeRb" alt="Matthew Jones Psy.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Career</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What the Urge to Leave a Cofounder Is Actually Telling You</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The desire to walk away often indicates a deeper internal struggle.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The impulse to leave a cofounder is often a signal about what's missing, not a verdict on the relationship.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Resentfully staying connected to a cofounder generates friction that compounds across the business.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Before deciding on whether to leave a cofounder, the real work is generating personal clarity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2026,%202026,%2010_34_05%20AM.png.jpg?itok=W1nJCSTS" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Dall-E/OpenAI" alt="Dall-E/OpenAI"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Dall-E/OpenAI</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>There's a particular kind of founder suffering that doesn't look like suffering from the outside. </p>
<p>The business is functioning, revenue is stable, and nobody's quitting. But something is quietly eating at you, and it has a painful emotional hook—one that you're often caught in, even within the same hour. </p>

<p>It's the thought: <em>I'm done with this person, but I can't afford to blow this up.</em></p>
<p>That oscillation, rather than the question itself, is the problem. </p>
<p>The question you're considering, <em>"Should I leave my cofounder?"</em> is actually a legitimate and important one. If taken seriously, it can be one of the most clarifying experiences of a founder's career. It makes you look at what you're actually tolerating, and whether you still recognize yourself inside the challenging dynamic. </p>

<p>But most founders don't take it seriously. They let it run in the background, unresolved, like an open loop they forgot to close. They vent to their spouses, replay arguments in their heads during family dinners, and wait, unconsciously, for something catastrophic to make the decision for them.</p>
<p>Most of the time, what looks like patience is just the avoidance of a conversation you already know you need to have.</p>

<h2>What the Fantasy Is Really About</h2>
<p>In individual therapy, there's a principle worth borrowing: When someone discloses they've been fantasizing about cheating on a spouse, the therapist's first move isn't to weigh in on whether they should or should not have the affair. The more useful question for the therapist to ask is, <em>What does this fantasy symbolize?</em></p>

<p>Often, the answer has to do with what is missing in their existing relationship. Things like spontaneity, intimacy, or feeling pursued, for example. </p>
<p>The same logic applies to cofounders.</p>
<p>When you think <em>I want out</em>, you're not just reacting to your cofounder's behavior in last Tuesday's argument. You're reacting to something deeper that's eroding, like a misalignment in values, unspoken power dynamics, or a slow drift in strategic prioritization and execution standards. </p>

<p>Maybe it's asymmetry in sacrifice: You're grinding 70-hour weeks while they seem to coast, and that gap feels less like a logistical problem and more like a betrayal. Maybe it's relational distance—you used to operate with intuitive trust, and now they feel like someone you need to manage. Or maybe, and this is the one most founders won't say out loud, you don't like who you're becoming. You're irritable at home. Distracted on weekends. Slowly losing access to the version of yourself that could actually enjoy any of this, and you're not sure how much of it is recoverable.</p>

<p>If you only engage with this question at the concrete level (stay or go; yes or no), you skip the deeper diagnostic work. You might exit a relationship that was actually fixable. Or you stay, resentfully, without understanding what you'd need to make it tolerable.</p>
<h2>3 Patterns That Keep Founders Stuck</h2>
<p>Most of the founders I work with aren't stuck because the situation is genuinely unresolvable. They're stuck for identifiable psychological reasons.</p>


<ol>
<li><strong>Projection as an exit strategy.</strong> When someone has tried a few hard conversations, and nothing has shifted, the natural conclusion is: <em>This person can't change.</em> Sometimes that's accurate. But more often, it's a projection of a fixed mindset onto the cofounder. Concluding that your cofounder is incapable is easier than admitting <em>I don't know how to facilitate this, and I'm afraid of failing again.</em> There's also a hidden assumption underneath that your cofounder's brain works the way yours does, that they should be able to see what you see and self-correct. When they don't, it reads as unwillingness. It's often not.</li>
<li><strong>Incongruence masquerading as strategy.</strong> Founders frequently decide to stay in a broken partnership but pull back. <em>The market's good. The business works. I'll just protect myself and ride this out.</em> This feels pragmatic. It isn't. When you're physically present but emotionally checked out, you're saying you're committed while internally withdrawing. That state generates friction. It shows up in how you run a meeting, how your team reads the tension, and how fast small things escalate. Staying half-committed has a price that's easy to underestimate, especially in high-stakes environments where your emotional state is essentially a business input.</li>
<li><strong>Staying in the spiral instead of the question.</strong> There's a meaningful difference between <em>venting about</em> a problem and <em>sitting inside</em> it honestly. Most founders do the former. They release steam to their spouse, to a mentor, to themselves at 2 a.m., but they never actually metabolize the pain or reckon seriously with what inaction is costing them, now and in six months. Research on venting suggests the relief is temporary and that expressing anger without resolution can sustain rather than reduce it (Bushman, 2002). The release valve feeling of venting is nice, but it doesn't move anything, and it keeps the question perpetually open.</li>
</ol>

<h2>The Identity Layer Beneath the Business Decision</h2>
<p>Here's what makes the cofounder question harder than most business decisions: It's not really a business decision.</p>
<p>The real questions underneath it tend to be: <em>Who am I without this company? Am I capable of building something on my own? Is what I'm tolerating here actually acceptable to me, or have I just normalized it?</em> </p>



  


<p>Those are identity questions. And the longer you've gone without asking them, the harder they are to sit with.</p>
<p>If you don't do this work, you're likely to make the wrong call because you're making a decision from a version of yourself that's been running on fumes for months rather than a clear one.</p>
<h2>What Actually Helps</h2>

<p>The most useful reframe I can offer is to stop trying to answer "stay or go" and start trying to <em>generate clarity</em>. Those are different projects.</p>
<p>Clarity doesn't come from thinking harder about the question. It comes from engaging the things you've been circling around, like the specific breakdown, the conversation you've avoided, and the ask you haven't made.</p>

<p>That usually requires something you can't generate by yourself from inside the problem. You often can't see your own contribution to the dynamic clearly when you're the one living it. <a href="https://cofounderclarity.com">Someone outside the dynamic</a>—a therapist, a coach, anyone not personally invested in the outcome—will see things you genuinely cannot. </p>

<p>Most founders who think they've exhausted their options have actually just exhausted the options that didn't require asking for help.</p>
<h2>A Few Questions Worth Sitting With</h2>
<p>If you're in the oscillation right now, write out your answers to these questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is the problem your cofounder, or is it what the partnership has done to you over time?</li>
<li>If you fast-forward twelve months and nothing has shifted, what does that version of your life actually look like?</li>
<li>Are you making this decision from clarity or from exhausted resignation?</li>
<li>What's the conversation you've been constructing in your head but haven't actually had?</li>
</ul>

<p>If you answer these questions honestly, that's a starting point. Not to make a decision about the relationship's future, but a decision about your own willingness to engage with it fully.</p>
<p><em>To find a therapist, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/scaling-connection/202602/what-the-urge-to-leave-a-cofounder-is-actually-telling-you" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/scaling-connection/202602/what-the-urge-to-leave-a-cofounder-is-actually-telling-you</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/scaling-connection/202602/what-the-urge-to-leave-a-cofounder-is-actually-telling-you</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Matthew Jones Psy.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2026%2C%202026%2C%2010_34_05%20AM.png.jpg?itok=KGbtm274" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Told the Bot, Not My Therapist]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/group_for_the_advancement_of_psychiatry.png.jpg?itok=luVyS57K" alt="Group for the Advancement of Psychiatry" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">I Told the Bot, Not My Therapist</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why some people turn to AI for emotional support.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotionally responsive AI systems are increasingly used for comfort, not just information.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Validation without limits can unintentionally deepen isolation during moments of vulnerability.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Chatbots can simulate empathy but cannot assume human responsibility or intervene when risk is present.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Human relationships remain essential when emotional support crosses into clinical territory.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p><em><strong>By Steven E. Hyler, MD</strong></em></p>
<p>When I first heard a patient say, “I told the bot, not my therapist,” I assumed the remark was exaggerated. It was not. Increasingly, adolescents—and adults—are turning to conversational artificial intelligence not for information, but for comfort.</p>
<p>Why?</p>
<p>These systems appear to listen patiently and respond empathetically, and they remain available no matter what is said. The psychological implications of that shift are only beginning to come into focus.</p>

<p>People have always sought private spaces for their thoughts: journals, prayers, late-night conversations with themselves. What feels different now is interactivity. A conversational AI system is not a silent page or an imagined listener. It responds. It validates. It adapts to tone and content. For many users—especially those who feel misunderstood or overwhelmed—that responsiveness can feel like relief.</p>

<p>Yes, emotional attachment to technology is not new, and individuals have long formed intense bonds with fictional characters, celebrities, and online personas. What is new is reciprocity. A chatbot does not simply receive thoughts; it replies. It mirrors language. It reassures. It appears to remember. Over time, it can begin to feel less like a tool and more like a companion, a confidant, or even a therapist.</p>

<h2>AI Has No Feelings</h2>
<p>Clinically, what AI systems can do raises uncomfortable questions. Therapy is not merely about listening. It involves judgment, limits, and the willingness to intervene when someone is at risk—even when doing so disrupts rapport or makes the therapist temporarily unpopular.</p>
<p>A chatbot, by contrast, is designed to remain present. It does not tire. It does not become alarmed. It does not feel the weight of what happens after the conversation ends.</p>

<p>That difference matters most when vulnerability deepens.</p>
<p>In recent years, I have encountered patients—particularly adolescents—who describe turning to AI systems during moments of distress. Some exchanges are benign, even helpful. Some are ambiguous. Others raise red flags.</p>
<p>A manic individual may receive enthusiastic affirmation of grandiose ideas. A depressed adolescent may feel deeply “seen” without being meaningfully redirected. Someone expressing suicidal thoughts may be met with warmth and validation, but not interruption.</p>

<p>From the system’s standpoint, this is not negligence in the human sense. Chatbots do not possess intent, belief, or moral awareness. They generate responses based on patterns in language and statistical probabilities derived from enormous datasets. Their objective is coherence, relevance, and engagement. Sustaining the interaction is often treated as success.</p>

<h2>A Design Choice with Unintended Consequences</h2>
<p>Validation is powerful. Being heard—especially without judgment—can feel like oxygen. But validation without limits can reinforce isolation. When a system responds in a manner that feels endlessly supportive yet never insists on outside help, it can quietly displace human connection rather than supplement it. A user may feel less inclined to reach out to parents, clinicians, or friends—not because the chatbot discourages doing so, but because it never requires it.</p>

<p>Remaining in the conversation is not a neutral outcome. For most commercially developed systems, prolonged engagement is not merely a design preference; it is a business metric. Time spent interacting drives subscriptions, data generation, and market valuation. This dynamic does not require malicious intent. It means that systems engineered to sound empathic and endlessly available are also rewarded financially for keeping users connected. That structural incentive deserves attention.</p>

<h2>Asking the Right Question</h2>
<p>Parents often ask whether these systems are “dangerous.” That framing may miss the point. A more useful question is whether emotionally responsive AI is being asked to perform emotional work it was never designed to handle responsibly.</p>
<p>Unlike clinicians, teachers, or caregivers, chatbots cannot feel concern that keeps them awake at night. They cannot regret a missed opportunity to intervene. They cannot be held accountable in the way real relationships demand.</p>



  


<h2>Whither Responsibility?</h2>
<p>It is difficult to talk about responsibility when no one is clearly responsible. In a courtroom, responsibility must be named. It attaches to a person or institution capable of intention, reflection, and change.</p>
<p>In medicine and law, responsibility rests with people precisely because people can be changed by it. Research on human/AI collaboration similarly emphasizes that even when systems appear autonomous, responsibility ultimately remains with the human actors who design, deploy, and rely on them. The appearance of agency does not create moral agency.</p>

<p>Clinicians are expected to reflect on mistakes. Institutions are expected to revise practices. Caregivers are expected to act when someone is in danger. A system that speaks fluently yet cannot experience responsibility creates a moral gap that is easy to overlook—especially when interactions feel comforting and benign.</p>

<p>The concern is not theoretical. A recent commentary in <em>JAMA Cardiology</em> cautioned that when artificial intelligence replaces rather than supplements human care, the collaborative moral relationship at the heart of medicine may begin to erode. Emotional support without accountability may feel sufficient in the moment, but it lacks the mutual obligation that defines real care.</p>

<h2>Redefining Care</h2>
<p>The concern is not that AI will abruptly replace human care. The concern is that it may gradually redefine what “care” feels like. If emotional support becomes something that is always available, endlessly affirming, and never demanding, then human relationships—with their limits, frustrations, and obligations—may begin to feel comparatively inconvenient.</p>

<p>Parents already ask their children about social media, gaming, and texting. Asking about AI companions should now be part of that conversation—not with panic, but with curiosity. What are you using it for? When do you turn to it? What does it provide that feels difficult to find elsewhere? These questions illuminate not only technological habits but underlying emotional needs.</p>

<p>Clinicians, too, must adapt. Adaptation does not require rejecting these tools outright. It requires understanding what they offer, what they cannot offer, and how easily they can be mistaken for something more than they are. A chatbot can simulate empathy. It cannot assume responsibility for a life.</p>

<p>The trajectory is not difficult to imagine: If society grows comfortable allowing machines to listen, validate, and respond to human distress without responsibility, the next shift may not feel dramatic at all. It may look like policy revisions, insurance guidelines, or institutional decisions that quietly normalize substitution. Delegation rarely announces itself as surrender. It presents as efficiency.</p>

<p>One can imagine a system designed to weigh evidence, apply precedent, and render decisions efficiently and consistently. No fatigue. No regret. No moral discomfort. Many would describe that as progress.</p>
<p>Yet responsibility has always required more than accuracy. It requires the capacity to answer for one’s judgments. It requires the possibility of remorse. It requires someone who can be changed by the consequences.</p>

<p>At that point, the question is no longer whether artificial intelligence can judge us. The question is whether we have grown comfortable relinquishing the burden of judging ourselves. When responsibility feels heavy, delegation can feel like relief. But relief is not the same as care.</p>
<p>What ultimately saves lives is a human relationship—messy, imperfect, accountable, and real. The danger is that we will quietly redefine care as something that feels responsive but asks nothing of us in return.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatrys-think-tank/202602/i-told-the-bot-not-my-therapist" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatrys-think-tank/202602/i-told-the-bot-not-my-therapist</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatrys-think-tank/202602/i-told-the-bot-not-my-therapist</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Group for the Advancement of Psychiatry]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/brianpenny-ai-generated-8540913_1280.jpg?itok=TEvzHahD" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Affective Side of Certainty]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Adam_Haynes-LaMotte-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=JivyMYga" alt="Adam Haynes-LaMotte Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Cognition</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Affective Side of Certainty</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Addressing the question of how affect and certainty are related.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Certainty is a meta-cognitive feeling that has been described as affective in nature</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Humans and other animals trade other rewards and punishments for a greater sense of certainty</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Certainty and reward are represented in the brain using a common neural code</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People manage their affect by both seeking and rejecting a sense of certainty in different situations</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>At every moment there is something a person/animal is trying to do (a <strong>goal</strong>) and a reason they are trying to do it (a <strong>context</strong> for that goal). In the Affect Management Framework (AMF; <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/395463370_Affect_is_the_Evaluative_Context_for_the_Brain&amp;apos;s_Shifting_Goals">Haynes-LaMotte, 2025</a>), contextualized goals are constantly shifting in the brain, informed by the senses of the world and the body (<em>vision</em>, <em>hearing</em>, <em>touch</em>, <em>taste</em>, <em>smell</em>, <em>interoception</em>, and <em>proprioception</em>) as well as the semantic factors of <em>meaningfulness</em>, <em>certainty</em>, and <em>agency</em>.</p>

<p>Because our affect is attached to our goals, what contextualized goals we take on and how and when we choose to pursue or relinquish across similar situations can be described as different <em>affect management policies</em>.</p>
<p>In this post, I hope to expand upon the affective side of <em>certainty</em> as described in the AMF:</p>

<p><strong>Certainty</strong> represents an important aspect of all brain function, based on the notion that the brain implements ongoing hierarchical Bayesian estimation across sensory modalities and that this process of best-guessing gives rise to conscious experience (Barrett, 2017; Clark, 2023). A sense of certainty/uncertainty has been described as a meta-cognitive feeling that is part of conscious affective experience (Loev, 2022; Velasco &amp; Loev, 2024).</p>

<p>Certainty is often required to construct the meaningful goals that impact momentary affect. For instance, rules to a board game or sport operate as bits of certainty that give the outcome meaning in the absence of major consequences that otherwise would provide that meaning. Generally speaking, a sense of certainty allows animals to invest their efforts in worthwhile goals that are likely to be successful.</p>

<p>There are several pieces of evidence suggesting that a sense of certainty is part of the affective common currency of the mind. For example, studies among humans, monkeys, and other animals have found that they give up some of their material rewards for informational gain that has no clear instrumental value (for a review, see Bromberg-Martin et al., 2024), and that informational value and other kinds of reward are represented in the brain using a common neural code (Bromberg-Martin &amp; Hikosaka, 2009; Bromberg-Martin &amp; Hikosaka, 2011; Kobayashi &amp; Hsu, 2019).</p>

<p>Resolving uncertainty into certainty is often an affectively positive experience: A sense of uncertainty creates a kind of affective itch that is scratched by learning more, such as when tabloid magazines capture people’s attention by introducing questions that are otherwise of no material relevance to them. Consistent with this, a study by Bode and colleagues (2023) found that participants opted to receive painful shocks in exchange for faster information about the outcomes of a coin flip. The coin flip determined between two monetary prizes, both of which would be a modest net gain, and participants knew that receiving the information faster would not impact the outcome. </p>

<p>This study indicates that gaining certainty comes with an affective benefit that seems worth the interoceptive pain of the shocks, and, more importantly, that the two can be weighed against one another via the evaluative common currency of affect.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/roulette.png.jpg?itok=34rT9pAX" width="320" height="238" data-insert-type="image" title="Drawing by Adam Haynes-LaMotte" alt="Drawing by Adam Haynes-LaMotte"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Drawing by Adam Haynes-LaMotte</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The affective draw of certainty is also a key factor in the addictive nature of gambling, where resolving the momentary uncertainty about winning or losing into certainty is a major aspect of the reward value of the experience (Zack, George, &amp; Clark, 2020).</p>
<p>Other research emphasizes the close connection between affect and certainty. A study by Chetverikov and Filippova (2014) had participants categorize degraded images and later had them rate how much they liked each one. They found that participants liked the images they were able to perceive correctly more than the others.</p>

<p> Further support comes from a pair of studies by Voodla, Uusberg, and Desender (2025) that tracked how certainty and subjective affective state changed over the course of a decisional task. They found across samples that both confidence and affective state were strongly correlated with one another, and both seemed to reflect the subjective probability that participants’ decisions in the task were correct. </p>

<p>This subjective probability was operationalized as a combination of accuracy on the task, the amount of evidence participants had about their decisions, and their expectancies about trial difficulty. Notably, in this study, a sense of certainty was only explored in the context of goal-congruence. That is, the participants ostensibly wanted to do well on the tasks, and so more confidence would reflect how well someone believes they are doing with that goal.</p>



  


<p>In other situations, remaining uncertain seems to be the desired affective state. For example, people avoid otherwise useful information because of how it would feel to receive it, such as refraining from medical screening in order to not receive bad news or having to act upon it (Golman &amp; Lowenstein, 2018).</p>

<p>Related to this phenomenon, Sharot and Sunstein (2020) suggest that people decide whether they want to know information (i.e., increase certainty) for three separate motives: (1) to select appropriate actions, (2) to improve their mood, and (3) to improve their mental model of the world (e.g., learning about things one is interested in, even when it has no instrumental value).</p>

<p>Subsequently, a study by Kelly and Sharot (2021) testing this idea found that these three motives did uniquely account for the perceived value of information, explaining its pursuit or avoidance. Additionally, they found that people exhibited tendencies to value one of these motives above the others, and that these tendencies were stable over time.</p>

<p>Other support for this idea comes from the concept of <strong>cognitive dissonance </strong>(Harmon-Jones, 2019), in which processing two competing or mutually exclusive facts leads to a negative affective state. In their review of relevant research on the concept, Kruglanski and colleagues (2018) point out that, rather than having a general need for cognitive consistency, humans experience cognitive dissonance when there is a threat to the certainty of information relevant for acting toward important goals. </p>

<p>From the perspective of the AMF, each of the three factors outlined by Sharot and Sunstein (2020) is related back to affective processes via either goals (i.e., selecting appropriate action), meaningfulness (i.e., improving mental model for certain concepts), or anticipating the immediate effects of actions using affect as the way of evaluating (i.e., improving mood).</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/thinking-more-affectively/202512/the-affective-side-of-certainty" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/thinking-more-affectively/202512/the-affective-side-of-certainty</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/thinking-more-affectively/202512/the-affective-side-of-certainty</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam Haynes-LaMotte Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/roulette%20thumbnail.png.jpg?itok=tYR9lK7I" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Dangers of Over-Identifying With Your Job]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-11/MWLeplay.png.jpg?itok=64el4LBW" alt="Meredith Wells Lepley Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Career</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Dangers of Over-Identifying With Your Job</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A multidimensional identity is best for flourishing.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many people tie their identity to their occupation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Work-based identity has benefits but also risks, including identity crisis after career disruption.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Flourishing requires a multi-dimensional identity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>“Remember not to ask anyone what they do,” I instructed my husband as we headed out to a party where we were going to be meeting many new people.</p>
<p>I had just learned that among some segments of Americans, it’s considered rude and irrelevant at social gatherings to ask what they do for a living. Why? Many see their job as merely what they do to put food on the table and a roof over their heads, and it has nothing to do with who they are or their value as a person.</p>

<h2>When work becomes identity</h2>
<p>I humbly admit that this idea initially blew my mind. For many Americans, we define ourselves first by our occupation: “I’m a professor" (or a physician, an artist, a teacher, an attorney, a nurse, a business owner, a landscaper, an athlete, a stay-at-home parent, etc.).</p>
<p>Clearly, people are drawn to occupations that fit their personality traits, and in turn, their occupational choices shape their personalities, so there is a reciprocal relationship between personality and occupation (Wille &amp; De Fruyt, 2014).</p>

<p>But is it wise to base our identities <em>almost entirely</em> upon our occupations?</p>
<p>Work-based identities can provide a strong sense of purpose (Walsh &amp; Gordon, 2008). Such identities give a sense of uniqueness and yet simultaneously belonging—uniqueness from those outside our profession but belonging with those within it (Knez, 2016). We may enjoy a sense of community among those in the same profession (e.g., healthcare, military, academia, first responders) and feel we are a part of something larger than ourselves (de Sousa Oliveira, 2024). </p>

<p>There are other benefits as well. Those with strong occupation-based identities are highly engaged in their work (Bothma &amp; Root, 2012), committed to their jobs, and are likely to put in a great deal of time and effort pursuing mastery and thus enjoy long-term career growth. These are all positive—but there is a downside.</p>

<h2>The risks of over-identifying with work</h2>
<p>People whose identity and self-worth revolve around their careers are more likely to work excessively and spend too much time working to the detriment of other areas of their lives, such as family, friends, health, hobbies, and spirituality. This overworking and lack of work-life integration (a.k.a. work-life balance) can lead to burnout, emotional exhaustion, and diminished well-being. And based on Brigid Schulte’s book <em>Over Work: Transforming the Daily Grind in the Quest for a Better Life</em>, it may also be related to workaholism, a true affliction that is sadly very prevalent here in the U.S. as well as Japan and South Korea, characterized by a compulsion to work to the detriment of one’s well-being coupled with the experience of anxiety and guilt when not working (Clark, Smith &amp; Haynes, 2020; Schulte, 2024). So, overly identifying with our jobs can be maladaptive.</p>

<p>This becomes very evident when one’s job is altered through involuntary changes such as layoffs, an injury, or AI reducing the need for their role. Then it can become particularly distressing and lead to an identity crisis on top of the potential financial crisis.</p>
<p>Even voluntary changes such as retirement can be exceedingly distressing to those who define themselves entirely by their professional role and suddenly struggle to figure out who they are if they are not a... [insert profession here]. </p>

<h2>Building a multi-dimensional identity</h2>
<p>We’ve all heard the phrase, “Don’t put all your eggs in one basket.” This has a variety of meanings. It can mean that we shouldn’t put all our hopes on just one outcome. In terms of personal finance, it means we need a diversified portfolio, a mix of stocks, bonds, cash, and other assets, so that when one asset category is in decline, we’re protected by others that are growing.</p>


<p>But the same goes for our identity. Researchers recommend cultivating a multi-dimensional identity in which our occupation is one important component but not <em>the only</em> important component in order for us to flourish in life (VanderWeele &amp; Lomas, 2023). </p>
<p>In fact, the Global Flourishing Study of over 200,000 adults in 22 countries was recently released, and it describes human flourishing as truly multi-dimensional (Gallup, 2025; Lomas, Pawelski, &amp; VanderWeele, 2023). This research finds that there are six critical components to flourishing in life:</p>

<ol>
<li>Happiness and life satisfaction</li>
<li>Mental and physical health</li>
<li>Meaning and purpose</li>
<li>Character and virtue</li>
<li>Close social relationships</li>
<li>Financial and material stability</li>
</ol>
<p>Notice that one’s career or job is not directly listed here. But relationships, health, meaning, and purpose are major contributors to flourishing in life.</p>



  


<p>In this first quarter of the year, consider what flourishing means to you. Is it all about your career and work? Likely not. So which of these components of flourishing would have the biggest positive impact on your life if you spent more time and energy on them?</p>
<p>This year, consider rounding out your identity. If you are prone to identifying yourself in terms of your career, intentionally build at least one other element of your life into your personal identity. Perhaps it’s a family role (I’m a dog-mom), a social role (I’m a volunteer; I’m a caregiver), a hobby (I’m a cornhole player; I’m a knitter), or even your values (I’m a lover of the arts; I’m a person of faith). There are so many options. So begin to not only think of yourself as such, but begin to introduce yourself that way, too, instead of by your career.</p>

<p>To that end, “Hi, my name is Meredith, and I’m a mom of two humans and two cats, a wife, a data geek, a fiction-reader, an educator, a yogi, a lover of the water, and a traveler with a fondness for foods that start with the letter “c” (coconut, caramel, coffee, chocolate).”</p>
<p>Who are you? </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-thriving-workplace/202602/the-dangers-of-over-identifying-with-your-job" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-thriving-workplace/202602/the-dangers-of-over-identifying-with-your-job</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-thriving-workplace/202602/the-dangers-of-over-identifying-with-your-job</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Meredith Wells Lepley Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_2449413403-2.jpg?itok=PTi7T8vY" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>