<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 22:25:19 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 22:25:19 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Success at Work Depends on Your Partner's Personality]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Theresa-Didonato.jpg?itok=SZH-sZHQ" alt="Theresa E. DiDonato Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Success at Work Depends on Your Partner's Personality</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Having a partner with these personality strengths predicts professional wins.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In romantic relationships, the effect of partner's personalities are not isolated to the partner's life.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Aspects of people's daily lives can be predicted by their partner's traits, including their work success.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research shows that partners' conscientiousness predicts job satisfaction, income, and promotion likelihood.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Conscientiousness is tied to household work and relationship satisfaction, which may facilitate work success.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>When we think about professional success, we're quick to link it to our own strengths. Get a raise? It's because of your work ethic! Land a new title? You earned it!</p>
<p>All of this may be true, but there's more to the story. Research suggests that people's professional successes are not purely the outcome of their own work. In the background, their romantic partner's personality may be setting them up for success (Solomon and Jackson, 2014). </p>

<h2>Personality Extends Beyond a Person</h2>
<p>Personality researchers often rely on the Big Five traits to help define and differentiate tendencies within and across people. The five traits include extraversion (outgoing, gregariousness), agreeableness, openness, neuroticism (anxious, low on emotional stability), and conscientiousness. If you know where someone falls on these five dimensions of personality, you probably have a pretty good sense of their emotional and behavioral tendencies.</p>

<p>Personality doesn't end with the person. It bleeds into the life and experiences of people close to them, including their romantic partner. Think about a typical evening at home, when both partners are together. If one partner's neuroticism is spiking, the other partner knows it, feels it, and isn't having their best evening either. And if one partner is showing their agreeableness? The other partner may feel like life is easier and more pleasant.</p>

<p>The immediate impact of a partner's personality on another partner's life makes sense, given that emotions and behaviors are linked to personality dimensions. But what if a partner isn't there? How far does the potential impact of a partner's personality extend?</p>
<h2>Personality at Home and Job Success at Work</h2>

<p>If a romantic partner never sets foot in a person's workplace, could they still shape a person's work experiences? Yes. Partners may be nowhere near each other, but they are affecting each other's work success.</p>
<p>Using five waves of data collected as part of a larger survey from an Australian nationally representative sample, researchers looked at the responses of about 4500 participants and examined whether couples' personality traits predicted key markers of job success (Solomon and Jackson, 2014). This study had a longitudinal design: earlier reports of personality were used to predict later job satisfaction, income, and promotions.</p>

<p>Findings suggested, unsurprisingly, that individuals' own personality traits predicted aspects of their job performance. For instance, individuals' own extraversion predicted their subsequent job satisfaction and their promotions; individuals' own agreeableness was inversely associated with their income, but positively linked with their job satisfaction. People higher in neuroticism tended to receive more promotions than those lower in neuroticism. </p>

<p>Next, and critically, the researchers also examined how a <em>partner's</em> personality predicted individuals' own job success later down the line. They uncovered the importance of partner conscientiousness, which predicted individuals' later professional success. To have a more conscientious partner predicted a greater likelihood of promotion, job satisfaction, and income. This was observed regardless of gender and was more pronounced for single-income families.</p>


<h2>Conscientiousness Partners Create a Context that Breeds Success</h2>
<p>Conscientious people tend to follow rules and work hard; they have good other-awareness and assume responsibility for the well-being of others. On account of this definition, might the link between a partner's conscientiousness and one's own job success be tied to certain behaviors or aspects of interdependence?</p>

<p>Included in Solomon and Jackson's (2014) study was an assessment of how much people outsourced household labor (doing the dishes, home repairs) to their partners. In addition, the researchers had access to information suggesting how much time partners spent together (how much opportunity they had to influence each other) and their relationship satisfaction.</p>



  


<p>What they discovered is that conscientious partners elevated their partners' work performance by taking on more household chores and by subtly influencing their partners to emulate their own conscientiousness. Lastly, conscientious partners set the stage for their partner's success by their tendency toward relationship satisfaction. Fewer problems at home mean more mental resources at work. </p>

<h2>The Benefits of Conscientiousness in Relationships</h2>
<p>Having a highly conscientious partner predicted better professional outcomes regardless of gender, and independent of individuals' own conscientiousness (Solomon and Jackson, 2014). As noted above, partners who spend time together emulate each other: this suggests that one highly conscientious partner could support the other, whose own growing conscientiousness could benefit the other, and so forth and so on. </p>

<p>There is potential for a self-propagating healthy pattern that supports both the home front and individuals' work lives.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meet-catch-and-keep/202602/success-at-work-depends-on-your-partners-personality" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meet-catch-and-keep/202602/success-at-work-depends-on-your-partners-personality</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meet-catch-and-keep/202602/success-at-work-depends-on-your-partners-personality</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Theresa E. DiDonato Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-elly-fairytale-4008734.jpg?itok=CQcyvEJY" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Couples Who Fight Well, Love Well]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-02/Moshe%20Ratson.png.jpg?itok=MBy8qAOB" alt="Moshe Ratson MBA, MFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Couples Who Fight Well, Love Well</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why conflict and repair are the true markers of intimacy.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Conflict is not a sign your relationship is failing, but a sign that it’s alive.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The real danger to love isn’t conflict or fighting, it’s avoidance and indifference.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Most arguments are protests for connection, not attacks on a partner.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">How you fight and repair determines the depth, passion, and resilience of your love.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Conflict.jpg?itok=qntKtH4V" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="AI Gerated Image by M. Ratson" alt="AI Gerated Image by M. Ratson"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI Gerated Image by M. Ratson</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Many couples who come into my office are worried about how much they fight. They say, <em>“We argue all the time.” “We disagree about everything.” “Healthy couples don’t fight like this, right?” “Maybe we’re just incompatible.”</em></p>
<p>But conflict is unavoidable. Couples who never fight are not necessarily secure or happy. Two individuals naturally have different needs, wants, and desires. Often, if they don’t argue, they are avoiding something.</p>

<p>Real intimacy is not about peace and quiet; it is about the ability to embrace differences, withstand tension, and be flexible enough to contain conflict and transform it into something greater. The fantasy that love should be calm, seamless, and perpetually harmonious has quietly damaged modern relationships. We have confused peace with health. We have mistaken the absence of conflict for the presence of connection. We have avoided conflict at the price of growth. </p>

<p>But conflict is not the opposite of love. Indifference is. I would even argue that one of the surest ways to deepen love is through conflict. When two people care deeply, friction is inevitable. Two histories, two nervous systems, two sets of values, and two evolving individuals cannot share space without occasionally colliding. The question is not whether couples will experience conflict. The real question is whether they know how to use it.</p>

<p>Handled poorly, conflict destroys trust. Handled consciously, with positive intention, conflict becomes the engine of personal and relational growth.</p>
<h2><strong>Conflict as a Growth Edge</strong></h2>
<p>Most arguments are not about content. They are about longing. The fight about the dishes is rarely about the dishes. It is about feeling unsupported. The argument about time is rarely about schedules. It is about feeling unchosen. The disagreement about tone is often about feeling disrespected. </p>

<p>Underneath conflict and uncomfortable emotions is usually a protest for connection. A desire to challenge the status quo and bring a greater level of harmony.</p>
<p>When we reframe conflict this way, something powerful happens. Instead of seeing our partner as the adversary, we begin to see the unmet need beneath the intensity. We begin to recognize that tension is often an attempt (however awkward and unsuccessful) to restore closeness and agreement. It is an attempt to fulfill an unmet need within the relationship.</p>

<p>Conflict reveals expectations and values, and clarifies boundaries. It forces differentiation. And differentiation is essential for intimacy and authenticity. Desire and being alive require separateness. If two partners never disrupt each other, never challenge each other, never assert themselves, they may preserve peace, but at the cost of vitality.</p>

<p>In addition, when couples suppress disagreement to maintain peace, resentment grows quietly. They shrink themselves to fit the relationship. They trade authenticity for stability. Over time, the relationship becomes calm but emotionally flat. Healthy conflict interrupts that flattening. It says, <em>“This matters to me.” I desire that change with you.”</em> <em>“Let’s work that out with passion and care.”</em> When handled with maturity, conflict does not threaten connection. It strengthens it.</p>


<h2><strong>The Dialectic of “I” and “We”</strong></h2>
<p>At the heart of most conflict is a deeper polarity: the tension between autonomy and connection. Every relationship lives in this dialectic. It challenges the ideas of closeness, freedom, safety, aliveness, stability, and growth. These desires do not always align neatly. In fact, they collide.</p>

<p>If a relationship demands constant harmony, authenticity suffers. One partner may silence their needs to avoid rocking the boat. On the surface, things look stable. Underneath, frustration accumulates and aliveness fades. If a relationship prioritizes individuality without regard for connection, emotional safety erodes. Each partner protects their autonomy, but intimacy weakens.</p>



  


<p>Mature love lives between these poles with care for all. It allows both partners to say, <em>“This is who I am,”</em> without abandoning, shaming, or overpowering the other. It tolerates tension without rushing to eliminate it. Conflict often erupts when this balance is disrupted. One partner may feel overwhelmed or abandoned. One may need space, and the other demands reassurance. These are not signs of incompatibility. They are signs that the relationship is negotiating the infinite tension between “I” and “We.”</p>

<p>When couples learn to see conflict through this lens, they stop asking, <em>“Who is right?”</em> They start asking, <em>“What are we trying to protect?” </em>They begin exploring new ways to create a greater level of harmony between all parties involved, including their internal parts. Often, one partner is protecting autonomy. The other is protecting connection. Both are legitimate. Both are vulnerable.</p>

<p>The work of mature love is to hold it consciously with compassion, while gently pushing ourselves to grow, change, and expand into a deeper level of love and harmony.</p>
<h2><strong>The Power of Repair</strong></h2>
<p>While conflict is inevitable, repair is essential. Healthy, successful couples are defined by their ability to repair. Repair is more than an apology. It is humility in action. It is the nervous system softening.<br>It is the ego stepping aside for the sake of connection. Repair might sound like: <em>“I am sorry, I got defensive.” “That came out harsher than I intended.” “I see how that hurt you.” “Can we start over with care?”</em></p>

<p>Love is measured by how sincerely we return, and every successful repair builds trust capital. It communicates: <em>“Even when we lose our footing, I am willing to come back to you.”</em></p>
<p>Over time, this creates emotional safety. Partners become less afraid of conflict because they trust that disconnection is temporary. They trust that tension does not mean abandonment. They trust that argument and frustration does not mean the relationship is collapsing. When repair is absent, conflict becomes dangerous. Each argument leaves a residue. Hurt accumulates. Distance grows. When repair is present, conflict becomes metabolized. The relationship expands its capacity to handle intensity. It becomes more elastic.</p>

<p>Paradoxically, couples who repair well, especially after a conflict, often feel more secure. They have experienced rupture and survived it. They have walked to the edge and returned. That experience deepens trust in a way that perpetual harmony never could.</p>
<h2><strong>Conflict as Catalyst for Expansion</strong></h2>
<p>Growth requires friction. This is a universal truth, and it is true in love. Without conflict, couples avoid difficult conversations. They sidestep sensitive topics. They tolerate small disappointments. They bury resentments. Over time, what looks like peace is actually emotional stagnation. Healthy conflict demands development. It clarifies what matters. It exposes patterns. It requires better communication and deeper listening. It invites us to communicate more directly. It challenges assumptions. It stretches emotional capacity.</p>

<p>A couple that learns to navigate conflict consciously becomes more resilient. They are less threatened by disagreement. They are more willing to take relational risks. They can speak truth without assuming catastrophe. This resilience enhances passion and allows us to live intensely while remaining grounded.</p>

<p>Safety and aliveness are not opposites. When partners trust that conflict will not destroy the bond, they feel freer to express themselves fully. Authenticity increases. Suppression decreases. Energy returns to the relationship. Conflict, handled with awareness and positive intentions, refines love. It removes illusion. It strips away pretense. It demands honesty. And in that honesty, intimacy deepens.</p>

<h2><strong>Love Is Elastic</strong></h2>
<p>We can abandon the fantasy that love should be perpetually smooth. Mature love is dynamic and elastic. It stretches. It contracts. It ruptures. It repairs. It can tolerate discomfort. It can withstand disagreement. It can survive misunderstanding.</p>
<p>Conflict, when guided by awareness and followed by repair, becomes an act of devotion. It says, <em>“This relationship matters enough for me to show up honestly.” </em>It says<em>, “Our connection is strong enough to hold my truth.” </em>A relationship that survives conflict with integrity expands. It becomes more honest, more resilient, and more alive.</p>

<p>Handled consciously, conflict is one of its most powerful teachers.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-wisdom-of-anger/202602/the-couples-who-fight-well-love-well" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-wisdom-of-anger/202602/the-couples-who-fight-well-love-well</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-wisdom-of-anger/202602/the-couples-who-fight-well-love-well</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moshe Ratson MBA, MFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Conflict.jpg?itok=xM9Tc8-q" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tinder Calls 'Clear Coding' a 2026 Dating Trend]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/bruce_y_lee.png.jpg?itok=5-I4em7x" alt="Bruce Y. Lee M.D., M.B.A." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Mating</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Tinder Calls 'Clear Coding' a 2026 Dating Trend</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">In dating, clear coding means being frank, open, and who you are.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Clear coding in dating means communicating in a clear, accurate manner without hidden meanings or surprises.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">If everyone is clearer on who they are, it will be easier for everyone to find their respective matches.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Clear coding does necessitate overcoming fears of vulnerability, judgment, and the other person tricking you.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-4065137.jpg?itok=QhtuGWv1" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" alt="The clear coding dating trend doesn't mean that you should start bringing your laptop to dates and use some Python script to get the other person to love you.." title="Photo by Cottonbro Studio from Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">The clear coding dating trend doesn't mean that you should start bringing your laptop to dates and use some Python script to get the other person to love you..</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Cottonbro Studio from Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>You may have heard the whole "clear coding" term floating around the dating world. After all, the dating app <a href="https://www.tinderpressroom.com/2025-12-03-TINDERS-YEAR-IN-SWIPE-TM-2025">Tinder has listed</a> clear coding as one of the dating trends for 2026. But while there may be clear reasons to have an interest in clear coding, a question may be whether you and others are ready to get with the program, so to speak. </p>

<h2>What Is Clear Coding</h2>
<p>Clear coding doesn't mean that you should start bringing your laptop to dates and use some Python script to get the other person to wrap themselves around you. Instead, the term sort of riffs on what a good programmer should be doing when writing computer code. It means communicating in a clear, accurate, readily readable manner without hidden meanings or surprises. You wouldn't, for example, design a computer program to act as if it's not interested in a user when it really is. Similarly, in dating, clear coding is about being frank and open about yourself and your interests and intentions. </p>

<h2>What Are the Benefits of Clear Coding</h2>
<p>The potential benefits of clear coding should be, well, clear. If everyone is clearer on who they are and what they want, then it will be easier for everyone to find their respective matches. A historical problem with dating is that many people aren't really what they appear to be, and how they portray themselves. There can be a lot of game playing. Dating can be like shopping at a supermarket where everything is mislabeled in the wrong aisles and in the wrong packaging, like sausage where the bread is supposed to be.</p>

<p>Plus, different people have different intentions when it comes to dating. Some are looking for their forever-and-ever person. Others just want some kind of companion for now. And some people are just looking for, surprise, surprise, no more than sex. Therefore, it would help to know each other's intentions for a proper match. For example, this could help put all the "just want to have sex" people in the same room with each other. </p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-luis-gomes-166706-546819.jpg?itok=F8MQzix9" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Clear coding in dating is analogous to writing a good piece of computer code, communicating in a clear, accurate, readily readable manner without hidden meanings or surprises." title="Photo by Luis Gomes from Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">Clear coding in dating is analogous to writing a good piece of computer code, communicating in a clear, accurate, readily readable manner without hidden meanings or surprises.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Luis Gomes from Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>What Are the Risks of Clear Coding? </h2>
<p>What's not clear: Even though it's being called a dating trend, how many people will actually end up sticking to the script of clear coding? Yeah, when it comes to honesty and openness in dating, a lot of people are going to fall well below the C+ level—meaning the grade and not the programming language. </p>

<p>That's because being more open and frank in your communications does take some guts and confidence in yourself. You have to overcome fears about being left too exposed, feeling vulnerable, and being judged as too eager, strategic, or even desperate. And to be clear, many people may have a tough time overcoming such fears.</p>

<p>Another fear is that clear coding becomes a one-sided affair during a date. While you're being clear and upfront, the other person may be about as clear as mud mixed with Nutella. In fact, the other person may even fake clear coding to get what they want. Yes, surprise, surprise, people can be dishonest about being honest. They might subscribe to sayings like "fake it until you make it," and "the key to success is sincerity, and if you can fake that, you've got it made." </p>


<h2>Why It Can Help to Give Clear Coding a Try</h2>
<p>All that said, don't let such fears discourage you. Beware of allowing fear to drive your decision-making in anything, with the possible exception of whether to run from a tiger. What if others get judgy on you? What if you get burned here and there by some faker-makers? The potential rewards could far outweigh the risks. </p>

<p>After all, the best way to get what you want is to be clear about what you want. And a good way to find the right match for you is to be clear about who you are. After all, you wouldn't walk into a store wanting a pair of pants and ask for a fruitcake instead, expecting salespeople to realize that "fruitcake" is code for something else, would you?</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-funny-bone-to-pick/202602/tinder-calls-clear-coding-a-2026-dating-trend" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-funny-bone-to-pick/202602/tinder-calls-clear-coding-a-2026-dating-trend</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-funny-bone-to-pick/202602/tinder-calls-clear-coding-a-2026-dating-trend</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Bruce Y. Lee M.D., M.B.A.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-4065137.jpg?itok=-gWAAyRX" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>