<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 19:05:18 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 19:05:18 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Coaching Can Improve Mental Health Symptoms and Resilience]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-02/jwatr.jpg?itok=zAeAusVP" alt="Jessica  Watrous Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Coaching</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Coaching Can Improve Mental Health Symptoms and Resilience</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Coaching sessions can lower distress, boost resilience, and complement therapy.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Tech‑enabled sessions with certified and trained coaches can help reduce depression and anxiety symptoms.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Coaching can be an important preventive modality, especially in systems that match intensity of care.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Coaching can improve transdiagnostic emotional processes that are linked to resilience.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">When we think about getting help for our mental health, therapy is often the first and sometimes only option that comes to mind. Therapy works, and for many people, it is essential. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Historically, research on therapeutic interventions focused on the treatment of diagnosable mental health disorders. However, as our perspectives on mental health have evolved, we’ve seen a broader research focus. Preventive interventions, those that are transdiagnostic, and those that can support individuals with subclinical concerns, are all emerging as important parts of a population health strategy. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Continuing to test these strategies in addition to scaling them for populations is key. Recent evidence suggests that well‑designed coaching with clear guardrails—especially when delivered inside an adaptive, stratified care population health model—can help people feel better quickly, build emotional skills, and even relieve pressure on an overburdened clinical system.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">What the New Study Found</h2>
<p dir="ltr">A peer‑reviewed <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC12628405/">study</a> in Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services Research followed working adults using an employer-sponsored blended digital mental health platform. On average, participants screened below clinical cutoffs for mental health symptoms, completed about 2.5 coaching sessions over three months, and reported reductions in depression (-22.5 percent) and anxiety (-12 percent), with gains in distress tolerance, self‑compassion, mindfulness, and perceived stress. Among members with elevated depressive or anxiety symptoms (although not severe symptoms), 72 percent clinically improved or recovered, while 96 percent of lower‑risk users maintained low symptom levels, consistent with coaching as both a treatment‑adjacent and preventive resource.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Why Coaching Can Work (and When)</h2>
<p dir="ltr">It’s important to call out that the coaching delivered via this platform is part of a broader stratified care model, meaning that individuals with more severe concerns are routed to therapy, crisis support, or psychiatry based on their circumstances. Additionally, all coaches had International Coaching Federation certification, went through a rigorous vetting process, received additional training from the benefits platform, and had the opportunity for ongoing consultation and education. </p>

<p dir="ltr">From a clinical perspective, coaching’s appeal is two‑fold. First, it targets transdiagnostic capacities such as distress tolerance, self‑compassion, and stress management that cut across diagnoses and everyday challenges. Second, it is approachable and scalable for people who may not need or are hesitant to start therapy. Earlier, lower‑intensity support can prevent escalation while preserving therapy for situations in which clinical intervention is warranted.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2 dir="ltr">How the Findings Fit With the Broader Evidence</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The idea that non-therapy options and skills‑based support improve mental health outcomes is not new. A randomized clinical trial with physicians found that individualized professional coaching significantly reduced burnout and improved resilience and quality of life. Other trials and meta‑analyses show that mindfulness programs can increase resilience to stress and improve anxiety, depression, and psychological distress in non-clinical settings. This is in addition to the strong evidence that resources such as social connection and addressing social determinants of health are critical to positive mental health outcomes. This is further evidence that mental healthcare is not one-size-fits-all, especially when the focus is on an entire population, and that other approaches can help people before reaching that point.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Implications for Therapists and Healthcare Systems</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Coaching can help fill critical gaps in existing healthcare systems, but not all coaching is created equal. There is currently not a single credentialing body for all coaches; however, there are several organizations with rigorous training programs. Clear vetting and quality monitoring processes serve as important guardrails for the use of non-licensed professionals delivering coaching. Building and understanding these guardrails is necessary to ensure that clients and patients are receiving appropriate support, especially given the variability in access and training across the coaching field. </p>


<p dir="ltr">That being said, equipping well-trained and certified coaches with evidence-based skills offers the opportunity to extend the mental health workforce, reserve specialized clinical resources for those with more severe clinical needs, and deliver an approachable and effective option for improving mental health and resilience.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Implications for Employers</h2>
<p dir="ltr">For organizations, the implications of taking care of an entire population or workforce are practical. Offering an adaptive care model with multiple entry points, like self‑guided tools, coaching, group support, and therapy, allows people to dynamically be routed to the best option based on their needs and preferences. Investing early and measuring outcomes beyond uptake—including symptom change—can help normalize a variety of mental healthcare options. Extending the view of effective mental healthcare beyond just symptom reduction to include emotional and transdiagnostic processes that underscore resilience is also important. The research underscores the dual benefits of coaching: It helps moderate-need employees meaningfully reduce symptoms while giving low-risk employees the preventive support needed to stay well. This combination makes coaching a scalable, cost-effective lever for employers looking to strengthen workforce well-being and reduce downstream healthcare spending. Because employees with moderate needs often account for the majority of the workforce, early support through coaching can significantly reduce demand for higher-intensity services, prevent crises, and improve overall productivity and engagement. </p>



  


<p dir="ltr">As part of an adaptive care model in which employees with more severe needs are recommended to clinical care, these results demonstrate that coaching effectively reaches and supports the workforce, including employees who might not need therapy but would benefit from early, preventive support. </p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>To find a therapist, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/quality-of-care/202602/coaching-can-improve-mental-health-symptoms-and-resilience" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/quality-of-care/202602/coaching-can-improve-mental-health-symptoms-and-resilience</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/quality-of-care/202602/coaching-can-improve-mental-health-symptoms-and-resilience</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica  Watrous Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-4100433.jpg?itok=8lmddyZH" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Before Your Organization's Next Connection Program: Diagnose First]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-04/_1_-_Hans_-_HeadshotPro-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=Kbi5-30y" alt="Hans Rocha IJzerman Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Workplace Dynamics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Before Your Organization's Next Connection Program: Diagnose First</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Intervening at the wrong level costs your organization more than doing nothing.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many connection programs fail by targeting the wrong level of the problem, not because of poor execution.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Disconnection at work is structural, relational, or individual—and each requires a different response.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Diagnosis before design is the step that determines whether any intervention will work.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p><em>This post is co-authored by Nathaniel Sabater (Annecy Behavioral Science Lab), Mariangel Maldonado (former head of well-being at Booking.com), and Hans Rocha IJzerman. </em></p>
<p>Every year, organizations roll out empathy training, wellness programs, mentoring schemes, and team rituals. Engagement scores shift in some teams. In others, nothing moves. Leadership concludes that the initiative needed stronger buy-in, better facilitation, or more budget. They try again next quarter with a slightly different version of the same thing.</p>

<p>Here is a harder explanation: The problem was often never the program. It was the problem selection.</p>
<p>Organizations frequently invest in solutions before identifying the actual source of their disconnection. The result is not just wasted resources. It is something more damaging: employees who engage with initiatives that leave their core frustrations untouched and who eventually stop believing that leadership understands what they are actually experiencing. Over time, responsibility tends to shift toward individuals—people are encouraged to adapt to conditions that are better addressed at the system or team level. This is not a failure of intent. It is a challenge of problem selection.</p>

<p>This is why diagnosis must come before design.</p>
<h2>Why Symptoms Are Misleading</h2>
<p>Burnout, disengagement, quiet quitting, and high turnover are symptoms. They tell you something is wrong, but they do not tell you where the problem lives. And location determines everything about how to address it.</p>
<p>Structural disconnection looks different from team-level disconnection, which looks different again from individual disconnection. When a hybrid policy creates unequal access to leadership, that is a structural problem. When a manager's communication style makes people reluctant to ask for help, that is a team problem. When an employee struggles with belonging after a major life transition, that is an individual problem. All three might register identically as disengagement on your annual survey. They require completely different responses.</p>

<p>Applying the wrong intervention is not neutral. It can actively reinforce the conditions causing the problem. Encouraging employees to build personal resilience in response to structural overload, for instance, shifts system-level problems onto individuals who did not create them. As <a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/human-resources/trends/top-priorities-for-hr-leaders">Gartner's research</a> across 426 chief human resources officers (CHROs) in 23 industries highlights, organizations are far more likely to achieve lasting change when it is embedded into the daily rhythms of work—not added on top of an unchanged environment through campaigns. Connection efforts lose traction precisely when they are designed before leaders are clear on what is disrupting connection in the first place.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>A Three-Level Diagnostic Framework</h2>
<p>Drawing on Burke and Litwin's <a href="https://www.studiodojo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/A_causal_model_of_organizational_performance_and_change.pdf">causal model of organizational performance and change</a>, our multi-country<a href="https://absl.io/publications/"> research on social connection</a>, and qualitative <a href="https://absl.io/creating-connected-workplaces-insights-from-people-leaders-at-leading-companies/">interviews with people leaders across industries</a>, we summarized a<a href="https://absl.io/the-root-cause-questions-every-chro-should-ask-in-2026-to-rebuild-connection-and-culture/"> structured approach</a> to help organizations identify where disconnection is actually generated—before designing any intervention.</p>

<p>The framework distinguishes three levels, and the order in which you assess them matters.</p>
<ul>
<li>The first is the <strong>structural and organizational level</strong>. The key question here is: Are the conditions we have designed quietly disconnecting people? This level covers workload distribution, staffing ratios, meeting loads, hybrid and remote policy design, role clarity, decision authority, and how restructuring transitions are managed. Structural factors shape whether meaningful interaction can even occur—the frequency of contact, modes of communication, and whether employees have access to the relationships and support they need to do their work. If this level is broken, no amount of team programming or individual support will compensate for it.</li>
<li>The second is the <strong>interpersonal and team level</strong>. If the structure seems sound, the question becomes: Is the team environment making connection feel unsafe? This covers psychological safety, manager behavior, team norms, collaboration quality, communication reciprocity, and how conflict and support—emotional, informational, and practical—are handled. Team factors shape not whether interaction occurs but how safe and supportive those interactions feel. A team can have every structural condition in place and still be a place where people feel unable to speak honestly or ask for help.</li>
<li>The third is the <strong>individual level</strong>. When both structure and team dynamics are genuinely supportive, the question becomes: Do individual factors explain persistent disconnection? This level covers personality, beliefs, mental health, personal life circumstances such as caregiving responsibilities or health challenges, social skills, coping strategies, and the impact of life transitions. Individual factors shape subjective experience—whether a person feels they belong, are appreciated, and can be authentic. This is the appropriate level to address last, not first.</li>
</ul>

<p>The sequence matters because each level sets the conditions for the next. Structural constraints define the boundaries within which teams operate. Team dynamics shape what individuals experience day to day. Beginning with individual-level solutions—which is where most programs default—when the problem is structural or relational is not just ineffective. It misattributes the source of disconnection and makes it harder to address the real issue later.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>What Diagnosis Makes Possible</h2>
<p>When organizations identify the right level before designing their response, our analysis shows that return on investment can be two to three times higher than when generic approaches are used. Tailored interventions that address root causes consistently outperform mismatched solutions that treat surface patterns while leaving underlying conditions unchanged.</p>

<p>The practical implication for people leaders is clear, if uncomfortable: Slow down before the next initiative launch. If your data points to structural overload, a mindfulness program will not move the dial. If it points to unsafe team dynamics, a belonging campaign will not reach the core issue. If individual circumstances are the driver, system-level redesign is the wrong tool.</p>



  


<p>Diagnosis is not a delay. It is the precondition for doing anything that actually works. </p>
<p>A culture of connection cannot be built through programs alone. It must be engineered into systems, relationships, and the daily architecture of work. That starts with knowing which problem you are actually trying to solve.</p>

<p><em>A version of this post also appears on the Annecy Behavioral Science Lab website.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/body-meet-mind/202602/before-your-organizations-next-connection-program-diagnose-first" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/body-meet-mind/202602/before-your-organizations-next-connection-program-diagnose-first</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/body-meet-mind/202602/before-your-organizations-next-connection-program-diagnose-first</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Hans Rocha IJzerman Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-fauxels-3184298.jpg?itok=zHF7LsSF" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eating Disorders in Athletes Are More Common Than You Think]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/Jennifer%20Rollin%20%283%29.png.jpg?itok=0Emr24Dp" alt="Jennifer Rollin MSW, LCSW-C" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Eating Disorders</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Eating Disorders in Athletes Are More Common Than You Think</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What we know about disordered eating and relative energy deficiency in sports.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Athletes can be vulnerable to developing eating disorders.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">RED-S is an important topic to be speaking about when it comes to athletes.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research suggests that it' important to screen athletes for eating disorders.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When working with athletes it’s important to affirm the aspects of their identity that feel positive.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">Athletes can be vulnerable to developing eating disorders, particularly in sports that emphasize appearance, weight categories, and leanness. Other factors that make athletes more susceptible to developing eating disorders can include underlying genetic and temperamental factors, combined with coaches that reinforce regularly pushing past your body's needs and ‘discipline’ above all else.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In fact, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38326925/">one study</a> suggests that about 1 in 5 athletes screen positive for disordered eating on validated self-report screening tools (Ghazzawi et al., 2024). Sometimes athletes are taught to override hunger and push past exhaustion in the name of ‘performance.’ The culture of ‘not taking any days off’ and ‘pushing yourself past pain’ can activate an eating disorder in individuals with an underlying genetic and temperamental vulnerability.</p>

<p dir="ltr">It’s also important to note that traditional eating disorder screening tools were not necessarily developed with an athletic population in mind, therefore it’s crucial to meet with a specialist who is knowledgeable both about eating disorders and athletics if someone is concerned that they might be struggling. Athletes can struggle with anorexia, bulimia, binge eating disorder, OSFD, ARFID, body image issues, disordered eating and/or compulsive exercise.</p>

<p dir="ltr">It’s important to note that someone’s overall identity as an athlete may be a positive part of their life. As eating disorder therapists it’s crucial to look at how someone can maintain the positive aspects of this identity (if they’d like), while working to reject the aspects of athletic culture that may serve to fuel their eating disorder.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Relative Energy Deficiency in Sports (RED-S)</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">RED-S is an important topic to be speaking about when it comes to athletes. It may occur with or without an eating disorder, however RED-S and eating disorders often overlap. This concept was formally introduced by The International Olympic Committee. RED-S happens when an athlete consistently is using my energy more than they are taking in. It’s important to note that someone can have RED-S at any weight or body size. Additionally, people of all genders can struggle with RED-S. Essentially RED-S is when the body doesn’t have enough fuel left over to run essential systems after training demands are met.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Symptoms of RED-S may include the following:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">Fatigue</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">Irritability and depression</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">Frequent illness</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">Hair loss</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">Weight loss</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">Trouble focusing</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">Trouble with temperature regulation.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr">(Relative energy deficiency in sport [REDs], Boston Children’s Hospital, n.d.)</p>
<p dir="ltr">RED-S can lead to poor health and training outcomes due to one’s body not having enough available energy. If left untreated, RED-S may lead to issues around bone health, psychological health, immunity, cardiovascular health, and reproductive health (Relative energy deficiency in sport [REDs], Boston Children’s Hospital, n.d.). </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>New Research On Ultra Endurance Athletes </strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">New 2025<a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/sports-and-active-living/articles/10.3389/fspor.2025.1708869"> research</a>, a cross-sectional study published in Frontiers in Sport and Active Living, found that higher training volume among ultra endurance athletes was associated with increased risk for disordered eating behaviors.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This research suggested that there is a need for more awareness about eating disorder vulnerability within the athlete and ultra endurance athlete population. The study also highlighted that eating disorder risk in athletes is not limited to those who are medically considered ‘underweight.’ It’s important to note that eating disorders in athletes can occur in individuals of all genders, races, and body sizes.</p>


<p dir="ltr">Ultimately, the research suggests that it’s important to screen athletes and ultra endurance athletes for disordered eating and eating disorders. It also indicates that it’s important to look at training volume and the impact that it has on eating disorder development in those who are genetically vulnerable (Colangelo et al., 2025)</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Clinical Take Aways</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">As clinicians, even if one does not specialize in treating eating disorders, it’s crucial to be screening the athlete population (and all populations!) for eating disorders. </p>
<p dir="ltr">If you are not knowledgeable about eating disorder treatment, it is crucial to refer out. Eating disorders are the second deadliest mental illness and evidence-based treatment is key (National Eating Disorders Association, n.d.).</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Additionally, when working with athletes it’s important to affirm the aspects of their identity of an athlete that feel positive and helpful, while also examining any disordered messaging that they may want to let go of.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/eating-disorders-in-athletes-are-more-common-than-you-think" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/eating-disorders-in-athletes-are-more-common-than-you-think</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/eating-disorders-in-athletes-are-more-common-than-you-think</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jennifer Rollin MSW, LCSW-C]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/athlete.jpeg.jpg?itok=dtSnYJgm" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From Resolution to Reality: Turning Intentions Into Daily Action]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/liz_matheis.jpeg.jpg?itok=6oBAwJbS" alt="Liz Nissim Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Motivation</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">From Resolution to Reality: Turning Intentions Into Daily Action</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Simple strategies for making change last.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Breaking down goals into smaller, manageable steps makes progress a reality.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Real change happens quietly over time through planning ahead and routines.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Over time, the focus moves away from outcomes and toward trust in yourself.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/resolution%20goals.jpg?itok=BIttchs1" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Cottonbro Studio / Pexels" alt="Cottonbro Studio / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Cottonbro Studio / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>When you think about it, we have no difficulty creating a long list of resolutions. We know exactly what we want to change, improve, or leave behind. We can clearly picture the outcome we’re aiming for. The challenge doesn’t lie in desire or even motivation but rather in the space between intention and execution.</p>

<p>The real obstacle is often a lack of direction. We know <em>what</em> we want, but not <em>how</em> to translate that desire into actions that fit into real life. Big goals can feel abstract and overwhelming, especially when they aren’t broken down into steps that can be practiced daily or weekly. Without a clear path forward, resolutions stay stuck as ideas rather than becoming behaviors. Progress doesn’t come from good intentions alone; it comes from consistent, repeatable actions that are small enough to actually do.</p>

<h2>The Power of Habit Stacking</h2>
<p>Once you’ve identified what you want to accomplish, the next step is finding the system that will support it. A system is not about willpower or perfect conditions—it’s about small, repeatable behaviors that fit into your current life. Not an ideal life. Not a future version of yourself with unlimited time and energy. This life. This week. Today.</p>

<p>One of the simplest and most effective systems is habit stacking. Habit stacking works by attaching a new behavior to something you already do consistently. Because the original habit is already established, it acts as a natural reminder and anchor for the new behavior. Instead of relying on motivation, you rely on routine.</p>

<p>For example, you might say:</p>
<ul>
<li>After I brush my teeth, I stretch for two minutes.</li>
<li>After I pour my morning coffee, I journal one sentence.</li>
<li>After I shut down my laptop, I prepare my gym clothes for tomorrow.</li>
</ul>
<p>The key is clarity and simplicity. The action should be so small that it feels almost too easy. These behaviors may seem insignificant on their own, but they create forward movement in a way that is realistic and sustainable. The goal isn’t intensity but, rather, frequency. Repetition is what creates change.</p>

<p>Over time, those small actions compound. A little progress each day adds up to meaningful movement after one week, two weeks, three weeks, and beyond. When the plan is already decided and built into your routine, you don’t waste mental energy deciding <em>if</em> or <em>when</em> you’ll act. Fewer decisions mean less friction, which makes consistency far more likely.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>And if you miss a day, you simply start again tomorrow. Missing one day doesn’t erase your progress. It doesn’t mean you’ve failed. It means you’re human. Shame and self-criticism only slow momentum; self-compassion keeps you moving forward.</p>
<p>Create small, tangible movements toward your goal. One small change over five days or one week. Now, it’s doable. For example:</p>


<ul>
<li>Plan meals on Saturday, food shop on Sunday, and prepare lunches for the week.</li>
<li>Set the alarm for 6 a.m. so that you are able to visit the gym from 7-8 a.m. on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday.</li>
<li>Place clean gym clothes at the end of the bed on Sunday, Tuesday, and Thursday nights to provide the visual cue to get ready each morning, without thought.</li>
<li>Remove foods that are not aligned with your goals, such as potato chips, cookies, and candy.</li>
<li>Prepare small, healthy snack bags and place them in sight or in the fridge.</li>
<li>Place your supplements in a weekly pill box and pack with your lunch.</li>
</ul>

<p>What I just listed are actual, tangible ways to work toward being healthier in the new year, and now, that larger goal doesn’t seem intimidating or overwhelming, but it translates into actual daily tasks that work toward that goal. Now, it’s doable. You’re creating systems and habits that will hopefully become long-lasting rather than a short-term action that can help you turn this into a lifestyle.</p>



  


<h2>Thinking Patterns That Can Defeat Progress</h2>
<p>If turning resolutions into action feels harder than it should, it’s often because of unhelpful thinking patterns that quietly sabotage progress. These patterns don’t always feel obvious, but they can be powerful enough to stop action altogether.</p>
<p>Common blocks include:</p>

<ul>
<li>All-or-nothing thinking: believing the effort only counts if it’s perfect or done at full capacity</li>
<li>Attaching the outcome to your worth: tying your self-worth to results rather than showing up</li>
<li>Fear of inconsistency: avoiding starting because you’re afraid you won’t be able to maintain it</li>
</ul>
<p>These thoughts create unnecessary pressure. They turn small, manageable actions into emotionally loaded tasks. The truth is that progress doesn’t require perfection—it requires participation. Effort matters even when the outcome is small, incomplete, or inconsistent.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Often, the hardest part is simply starting. The first day carries the most resistance. To reduce that overwhelm, make the starting goal intentionally small. Instead of “I will walk for 60 minutes,” try “I will walk for 15 minutes.” Instead of committing to a full routine, commit to showing up.</p>
<p>Consistency becomes possible when the goal feels doable and realistic—something that fits within your current capacity rather than stretching you beyond it.</p>

<h2>The Quiet Transformation</h2>
<p>Turning goals into daily action isn’t dramatic. It’s subtle. It’s quiet. It’s often unglamorous. It’s choosing the same small behaviors again and again without needing a surge of motivation or inspiration.</p>
<p>Over time, something shifts internally. The focus moves away from outcomes and toward trust—trust in yourself and your ability to keep showing up. The internal dialogue slowly becomes:</p>

<ul>
<li>I can do hard things.</li>
<li>I can do this.</li>
<li>I trust myself to follow through.</li>
<li>I can make progress each day.</li>
<li>My progress may be small, but it is real.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is how real change happens—not through massive, one-time efforts, but through steady, repeatable actions that build confidence and self-belief. Quietly, almost unnoticed, intentions turn into habits. And habits turn into a life that reflects the goals you once only wrote down.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/special-matters/202602/from-resolution-to-reality-turning-intentions-into-daily-action" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/special-matters/202602/from-resolution-to-reality-turning-intentions-into-daily-action</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/special-matters/202602/from-resolution-to-reality-turning-intentions-into-daily-action</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Liz Nissim Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/resolution%20goals.jpg?itok=mnAwIES_" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Man Who Introduced Freud to Psychiatry]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/wallace_mendelson_m.d.jpg?itok=8JdRqqnk" alt="Wallace B. Mendelson M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Freudian Psychology</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Man Who Introduced Freud to Psychiatry</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Theodor Meynert and his rebellious student.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Theodor Meynert was a leader in viewing psychiatry research as a form of brain science.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In 1883, Freud joined Meynert's clinic, leaving in 1885 to study under Charcot in Paris.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Freud's ideas about hypnosis and 'male hysteria' offended Meynert, leading to a break healed on his deathbed.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Freud is best known, of course, for the creation of psychoanalysis as a treatment for mental illness, though later he began to emphasize its utility as a method for enhancing self-knowledge. Interestingly, in his early years, his clinical interests were actually in internal medicine; in this post, we will describe the influence of Theodor Meynert, who guided his first major exposure to clinical psychiatry. As we will see, the two later had a falling out, which continued for some years, until it was resolved on Meynert’s deathbed.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-01/Meynert%20brain%201885.PNG.jpg?itok=6359EHus" width="320" height="198" data-insert-type="image" alt="Brain dissection as seen in Meynert's 1885 book 'Psychiatry. A clinical treatise on diseases of the forebrain based upon a study of its structure, functions and nuatrition'. " title="Theodor Meynert/Wikimedia Commons/Public Domain"></div>
<div class="caption">Brain dissection as seen in Meynert's 1885 book 'Psychiatry. A clinical treatise on diseases of the forebrain based upon a study of its structure, functions and nuatrition'.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Theodor Meynert/Wikimedia Commons/Public Domain</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>After graduating from medical school, Freud began to work in a neuropathology laboratory. His research flourished, though he had little income, and by 1882 he was in financial straits. He cast about for a new career; at first he applied to training programs in internal medicine, but was not accepted. He ultimately followed the advice of his former teacher and mentor, Wilhelm von Brücke, and took a position as a physician in Vienna’s General Hospital. After assignments in a number of areas, including surgery and dermatology, in April 1883, he began working in Theodor Meynert’s psychiatric clinic.</p>

<p>Meynert, one of the best-known European psychiatrists of the late 19th century, was a strong believer that the study of psychiatry should be considered a form of brain science, and advocated associating various psychiatric symptoms with deficits in specific anatomical areas of the brain. Freud became involved in the effort to view psychiatry in this manner, resulting years later in the <em>Project for a Scientific Psychology.</em> It has been argued that Meynert also formulated an early view of the ego, which he believed was based on various patterns of neural connectivity; he also touched on ideas which later grew into expression as repression, defense and the pleasure principle (1). Freud later referred to Meynert as the person ‘in whose footsteps I have trodden with such deep veneration’.</p>

<p>By 1885, Freud was given an appointment as a <em>Privatdozent (an unpaid lecturer)</em> in neuropathology; he then looked for financial support from the university, including travel grants. He took the opportunity to study under Jean-Martin Charcot in Paris. Charcot had made advances in many areas, including parkinson’s and multiple sclerosis, but Freud was particularly intrigued with his work on hysteria (in modern terms, conversion disorder and related conditions). He believed that this disorder, which was most often seen in young women, could be treated with hypnosis and that conversely hypnosis could induce the qualities of hysteria in normal volunteers. His demonstrations were very impressive, often bordering on the theatrical, and Freud became very interested.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Upon his return to Vienna in February 1886, Freud tried to convey his enthusiasm to his former mentors. To his surprise, his lectures were met with disdain by Meynert and others. In the words of one of his colleagues, ‘Meynert in the discussion bluntly rejected Freud’s statements and thus he fell into disgrace with the Faculty.’ They were particularly incensed by the therapeutic use of hypnosis, as well as the notion that hysteria could appear in men as well as women. Such was Meynert’s derision that he cancelled Freud’s use of his university facilities, thus leaving Freud with nowhere to lecture. Ultimately, Freud developed a private practice of neurology, inspired in part by the example of his mentor Joseph Breuer, but even this was difficult without referrals from the academic establishment. In what may have been to some degree an economic decision, he let it be known that he would see patients with hysteria. One wonders how he might have felt, given that his interest in hysteria had so greatly affected his professional life. Many physicians were reluctant to treat it, and consequently Freud received many referrals. Ultimately, his practice was highly successful and continued until 1938.</p>

<p>Over the years, the views of Freud and Meynert hardened with respect to each other. Meynert continued to deride Freud, challenging his skill as a doctor, and Freud criticized Meynert’s unshakeable dictum that specific symptoms could always be related to specific anatomical loci in the brain. Freud, instead, believed in the importance of experiences in shaping nervous system function and elaborated on Charcot’s notion of the ‘functional dynamic lesion’.</p>

<p>Meynert became very ill. It is said that Freud came to visit him in 1892, though the date remains uncertain, but by many accounts they appear to have had a reconciliation. Freud described the conversation some years later in <em>The Interpretation of Dreams,</em> in the context of a dream in which he believed his father represented Meynert: "When I visited him during his fatal illness and asked after his condition, he spoke at some length about his state and ended with these words: ‘You know, I was always one of the clearest cases of male hysteria.’ He was thus admitting to my satisfaction and astonishment, what he had for so long obstinately contested” (2).</p>


<p>It is uncertain whether Meynert was trying to gain closure with his former protégé, and of course his own mental acuity at that moment is unclear. He had been grieving from the death of his daughter Christi in February 1892, and of his wife a few years earlier. On the other hand, he was able to give a complex lecture on neuroanatomy to the Academy of Sciences a few days before his death in May 1892. There is also a mythic quality to Freud’s description of this meeting, and it is not certain whether this account published in 1900 may have reflected his own wishes and memories. We may never know exactly what happened.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The reconciliation was also ironic in a way: Freud had long since given up the use of hypnosis in favor of the techniques which grew into psychoanalysis, and Meynert seemed to have now agreed that 'male hysteria', as it was then called and understood, existed. Meynert had made a major contribution in emphasizing that psychiatric research could be seen as a form of brain science, even though he was later criticized for his unwavering focus on specific nuclei rather than the functional networks advocated by his student Carl Wernicke and others. And among his many accomplishments, it was he, as well as Josef Breuer, who first introduced the newly-minted general physician Sigmund Freud to the practice of clinical psychiatry. To some degree, the interaction of the two can be seen as a microcosm of the beginnings of the historically differing paths of those who advocate a biological approach to psychiatric symptomatology, and those who emphasize some forms of psychotherapy. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatry-a-history/202601/the-man-who-introduced-freud-to-psychiatry" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatry-a-history/202601/the-man-who-introduced-freud-to-psychiatry</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatry-a-history/202601/the-man-who-introduced-freud-to-psychiatry</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Wallace B. Mendelson M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-01/Meynert%20brain%201885.PNG.jpg?itok=KRhiNr7K" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Marcus Aurelius Taught How to See Beauty Beyond Praise]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-05/Leon-Garber.jpg?itok=SCVGgFWd" alt="Leon Garber LMHC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Perfectionism</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Marcus Aurelius Taught How to See Beauty Beyond Praise</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Perfectionism's fixation on winning is a deviation from the path of real value.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perfectionism is a preoccupation with control, which makes us falsely believe that we create our own luck.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Accepting the role of luck can help steer us away from fixating on rewards to focus on our stable traits.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Marcus Aurelius argued that beauty doesn't need praise to be beautiful, as that quality is self-evident.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Perfectionism, at bottom, is an outsized sense of self-importance, or control. Taking on all of the responsibility of both success and failure eliminates the possibility of acknowledging the most feared aspect of life to many of us: chance. Therefore, emotionally, perfectionism is akin to gambling addiction. Intellectually, many gamblers can easily tell you they know how significant luck is to betting. Yet, despite that, their reactions betray another, more fundamental, reality.</p>

<p>People with gambling addiction tend to feel like losers and winners, as though they’re the sole or main source of complex outcomes. Some feel as though they’re special because they’re lucky (at least at times, such as when they say they’re ‘due for a win”), so they account for luck but do so in a personal manner—in this way, they’re still the reason they won. Others believe winning and losing stem from intelligence, using fallacious thinking to convince themselves they’re great players, even if it’s because they merely have the courage to persist in the face of defeat (I’m not referring to poker since it requires more skill than your average casino game). While this mindset can be helpful in areas that demand a strong work ethic, it’s detrimental in those also involving a significant amount of luck, such as the entertainment industry.</p>

<p>Perfectionists, however, are rarely content with life’s usual rewards, setting their sights instead on fame and/or universal acclaim, even if only within some specific industry. While pursuing acclaim isn’t inherently harmful, rigidity and myopia are. Like the obsessive gambler, the perfectionist spends their time trying to game the system, to control luck. They somehow lump the concept of luck in with the idea of working hard—the harder you work, the more luck you’ll have. While it’s true that working hard may increase your opportunities, it’s a logical stretch to infer that working hard is synonymous with owning luck. Unlike the cliche, fortune doesn’t always favor the bold; sometimes, it even favors the timid. Luck, for the most part, exists outside of our influence; we can’t even adequately define ‘chance’—we just know it’s there.</p>

<p>Through self-deception, the gambler uses an external reward to prove their superiority to themself. On that day, in that moment, compared to others, they were better. Dividing the world up between winners and losers, the myopic perfectionist not only fails to account for all of the elements of success, including trends and biased preferences (which often have little to do with the perfectionist), they also often fail to note what’s already there; the ugliness of competition blinds you to beauty. In my writing, I repeatedly refer to our minds and how much they influence our conceptions of things. I do so because mental illness, largely stemming from them, with its accompanying inflexibility, precludes us from noticing, or causes us to devalue whatever we do.</p>

<p>In the philosophical classic, <em>Meditations</em>, Marcus Aurelius wrote, “Everything in any way beautiful has its beauty of itself, inherent and self-sufficient: praise is no part of it. At any rate, praise does not make anything better or worse. This applies even to the popular conception of beauty, as in material things or works of art. So does the truly beautiful need anything beyond itself? No more than law, no more than truth, no more than kindness or integrity. Which of these things derives its beauty from praise, or withers under criticism? Does an emerald lose its quality if it is not praised? And what of gold, ivory, purple, a lyre, a dagger, a flower, a bush?” This is antithetical to the gambler’s mindset, constantly searching for the dopamine hits of validation, which thrive, in large part, on both luck and self-deception. The gambler never notices what’s beautiful about them, never allows themself to see beyond their comparisons to everyone else in the room.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Seeing beauty, even in oneself, begins with curiosity. Is there more to the gambler than winning? Are they charismatic, clever, kind, wise, or endearing? Do they need to win to offset some distorted self-concept, or can they learn to see through it, finding a more stable sense of self? Do they devalue parts of themself that others appreciate? Or do they devalue themself because they aren’t perfect? In reality, the gambler obviously only feels good when they’re winning. Yet, the stoic, according to Aurelius, doesn’t need social trappings, the so-called ‘preferred indifferents.’ Fortunately, there is a middle ground for the rest of us, who aren’t as self-assured. We can accept that we need some wins without resorting to something like the constant pursuit of validation through gambling. Indefinite winning, for lack of a better term, can be challenging because of its scope, which includes luck, timing, and (depending on the industry) even popularity. But we can still be winners to some, who take the time to learn about us and our gifts. They see us at our cores, beyond the folly and ugliness of our obsessions.</p>

<p>For instance, most of the world may not love my writing because it doesn’t suit the tastes of some, writing about perfectionism may not be in vogue, writing about it in this particular epoch was a stroke of bad luck, and other factors, especially those related to algorithms. But some consistently read it, which means that it may stand alone as meaningful or even beautiful because someone somewhere out there thinks it is. It being beautiful is now a fact of life, even if all that anyone else can see is ugliness. If my goal was to write something beautiful, then I have succeeded. But it’s my responsibility to find a way to see that through the ugliness of my own mind, to see what's obvious to someone else.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/marcus-aurelius-taught-how-to-see-beauty-beyond-praise" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/marcus-aurelius-taught-how-to-see-beauty-beyond-praise</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/marcus-aurelius-taught-how-to-see-beauty-beyond-praise</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Leon Garber LMHC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/fszalai-ai-generated-8390622_1920.jpg?itok=Ws3YifVD" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Get Out of the Friend Zone]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/bruce_y_lee.png.jpg?itok=5-I4em7x" alt="Bruce Y. Lee M.D., M.B.A." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Mating</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How to Get Out of the Friend Zone</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">To get out of the friend zone, it helps to know what got you there in the first place.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Being Friend Zoned means that the person you are interested in romantically views you as just a friend.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Before you try to get out of the Friend Zone, check whether you are even there by asking frankly, directly.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Realize that dating is about finding the right mutual match rather than one trying to win the other over.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/GettyImages-1363894376.jpg?itok=ioao7h3G" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Are you interested in someone romantically, but that person sees you as only a friend? Then you've probably been Friend Zoned." title="golubovy / Getty"></div>
<div class="caption">Are you interested in someone romantically, but that person sees you as only a friend? Then you've probably been Friend Zoned.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: golubovy / Getty</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>There are some places known to be really hard to get out of, like the Alcatraz Federal Penitentiary, referred to as "The Rock"; the Sahara Desert; the Moon; and, of course, the "Friend Zone." For the first three, there are at least obvious solutions for escaping, like that John Patrick Mason character played by Sean Connery, a hot air balloon, and a spacecraft. However, getting out of the Friend Zone—where the person you are romantically interested in has already deemed you to be only-friend material rather than significant-other material—can seem near impossible. But fear not, adventurer; there are steps you can take to get out of the Friend Zone. There's no guarantee, though, as to which direction out you'll be going. </p>

<h2>Step 1: Determine if You Are Even in the Friend Zone </h2>
<p>First things first, check whether you have actually been Friend Zoned. The other person could think that you're the one doing the Friend Zoning. Or perhaps he or she is still sorting out feelings for you. Therefore, if you want the possibility of a romantic relationship, be frank, ask, and see the response. The answer will be very telling. If it's something like "I wouldn't want to risk our friendship," "I see you more as a friend," "Heck, no," or simply "Ick," then you know the deal.</p>

<h2>Step 2: Determine How You Even Got Into the Friend Zone</h2>
<p>To know your way out of anywhere, it's best to know how you got there in the first place. This can help identify whether it's even worth pursuing a romantic relationship. For example, if you got there because the other person is already in a romantic relationship with someone else, especially a solid one, then do you really want to be that guy or that gal who breaks up a relationship? You know, the home wrecker? Plus, what goes around can come around. If that person essentially cheats on his or her significant other with you, how loyal might he or she end up being with you? </p>

<p>A second no-go situation is when the other person clearly expresses a preference that you cannot provide. For example, if the other person says something like, "I just don't find Asian Americans attractive," and that happens to be your racial background, then you may be fighting against an insurmountable bias. The same may apply if that person wants someone richer, higher society, or bigger breasted than you. It may be too much to contort yourself into something that you are not just for the hopes of being accepted. Instead, look for someone else who will appreciate you for who you are.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>If, on the other hand, you landed in the Friend Zone because you behaved in some way that's not really you, then there is some hope. Common examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Being too amenable and agreeable: </strong>Does he or she assume that your answer to anything will always be "Yes"?</li>
<li><strong>Being too available: </strong>Does he or she view you as some kind of 24-hour customer service hotline?</li>
<li><strong>Putting the other person on a pedestal: </strong>Does he or she feel like some kind of king or queen around you, and see you as the plebeian?</li>
<li><strong>Subverting your interests and needs:</strong> Does he or she even know or care what you want?</li>
<li><strong>Being too passive or afraid:</strong> In that person's eyes, are you a man or a mouse? A female or a piece of mail? </li>
</ul>

<h2>Step 3: Reverse the Behavior That Put You in the Friend Zone</h2>
<p>The next thing to do is to stop it. Just stop it. Stop exhibiting the behavior that got you Friend Zoned because, news flash, it's not working romantically. Do it now.</p>
<h2>Step 4: Change Your Mindset About the Other Person and Dating</h2>
<p>And change your mindset so that you don't view the other person as someone you have to win over or convince to love you. Instead, dating is about finding the right mutual fit for each other. That includes determining whether the other person will treat you as you deserve. Just because he or she has that hot body doesn't mean that the person has the right personality and values for you that will make you stronger, not weaker. When you adopt more of a "Let's see if we actually are a good fit for each other" mindset, you may find yourself automatically shedding the behaviors that led you into the Friend Zone and displaying a whole lot more confidence, which can be more attractive. </p>

<h2>Step 5: Stop Focusing on the Person and Build Up the Rest of Your Life</h2>
<p>At the same time, stop treating the person as the Sun and yourself as some kind of gaseous planet like Uranus revolving around him or her. View your time as valuable and not to be wasted focusing on someone who doesn't value you to the same degree. Instead, shift much more of your time to building your other relationships, work abilities, interests, and hobbies, and thus, more opportunities for yourself. This includes finding other people to date. The stronger you are, the more attractive you will become in general.</p>


<p>Also, consider stepping away from this friendship for at least a while. Being caught in the Friend Zone could cause you to zone out and forget your value and what you want, what you really, really want. Creating some distance could help not only you think more clearly but the other person as well. Who knows? Maybe he or she may stop taking you for granted. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Plus, be honest with yourself. Would you maintain this kind of "friendship" with someone if you were not attracted romantically to him or her? Or are you simply staying friends in the hopes that you will somehow someday get in there, like waiting in line for an amusement park ride? If it's the latter, consider the other way of getting out of the Friend Zone—namely, severing your friendship. </p>



  


<p>Life is too short to be spent waiting in some kind of line when you are not even sure if the ride will ever be open. So, your leaving the line could be a big time and effort saver. It may even prompt the ride to suddenly open. But don't count on it. Going from the Friend Zone to the Romantic Zone may not be possible in this situation. But going from the Friend Zone to the Free Zone is something totally within your control. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-funny-bone-to-pick/202602/how-to-get-out-of-the-friend-zone" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-funny-bone-to-pick/202602/how-to-get-out-of-the-friend-zone</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-funny-bone-to-pick/202602/how-to-get-out-of-the-friend-zone</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Bruce Y. Lee M.D., M.B.A.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/GettyImages-1363894376.jpg?itok=PHNiGFGi" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>