<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 18:45:51 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 18:45:51 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Five Retirement Pathways]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-01/Michael-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=hpxG3FYg" alt="Michael Shelton MS, LPC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Aging</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Five Retirement Pathways</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Our retirement pathway predicts how we will thrive (or not) in our later years.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Up to one-third of retirees struggle with retirement.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People tend to approach their retirement years by one of five pathways.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Each pathway can be evaluated as to its risk for mental health complications and adjustment distress.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-kampus-8422672.jpg?itok=8eMzHaxw" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="Kampus Production/Pexels" alt="Kampus Production/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Kampus Production/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Let’s start with the good news, which is that most retirees describe this stage of life as positive. However, there is bad news too. Taylor (2024) concludes that up to one-third of people who retire find the transition either stressful or notice a decline in their well-being, and an additional 10 to 25 percent experience difficulties adjusting to retirement, including mental health complications.</p>

<p>Even the popular press now acknowledges that retirement can be difficult. In the book <em>Thrive in Retirement</em>, Thurman (2019) cautions, “Retiring can hurt your health, strain relationships, wipe out your finances, and shorten your life expectancy” (p. 151). In <em>Living Your Best Third Act</em>, Schwarzkopf (2023) states, retirement “may easily become a tragedy” (p. 21), consisting of retirees “making the couch, the fridge, and the TV their three best friends” (p. 36).</p>

<p>As psychological and gerontological research accrues, it is increasingly evident that there are five approaches to retirement, and each one can be evaluated for its risk to adjustment and mental health complications, including loss of identity, relationship distress, sadness, loneliness, substance use problems, gambling concerns, and implicit ageism. We now recognize that <em>how we retire</em> can have long-lasting effects, both positive and negative.</p>

<h2>Low-Risk Retirement Types</h2>
<p><em>Type One: The Proactive Retiree</em></p>
<p>This low-risk retirement type is the individual who plans out their retirement in multiple areas (finances, health care, lifestyle) long before the final day of employment. They questioned how they would create a meaningful and satisfying retirement years before entering this new phase of life. They have already considered and explored post-retirement activities, new roles and interests, ways of maintaining identity and purpose, and preparing relationships for change. </p>

<p><em>Type Two: The Voluntarily Employed Retiree</em></p>
<p>These folks tend to really like their job, are passionate about their careers, and obtain much meaning and support from them. They may gradually reduce hours, seek out a similar but possibly less-stressful position, engage in a new career, or entrepreneurially create a niche that resonates with their deep-seated interests. Of critical importance, these reduced-workload jobs provide older workers with the opportunity to adapt gradually to a life without work while simultaneously benefiting from social contact, structured use of time, and connection with current developments.</p>

<p>(Note that if you remain at a job due to financial limitations or insurance needs, this category does not apply to you. You are instead a Type Five.)</p>
<h2>Moderate-Risk Retirement Type</h2>
<p><em>Type Three: The Psychologically Unprepared Retiree</em></p>
<p>This category is comprised of individuals who did some, minimal, or no planning for retirement. If substantial planning occurred, financial matters were typically prioritized. Type Three individuals may or may not be looking forward to retirement, feel hopeful or anxious, or even powerless or empowered about the transition. In almost all cases, what has not occurred is psychological preparation. </p>

<p>After a brief honeymoon period, those in this category begin to experience boredom and meaninglessness. As a sense of being irrelevant insidiously creeps into their lives, they begin to ask the immemorial questions: “Who am I now?” and “What do I do with my time?” For those whose identity was primarily found in their jobs, retirement is particularly challenging.</p>


<p>Fortunately, while those in the moderate-risk category often struggle early in retirement, they eventually rebound after a period of time, months to years, to a life as satisfying as Types One and Two retirees. A note of caution is needed here: Time—one of our most precious commodities as we age—is inevitably passing, and spending years figuring out retirement after the fact detracts from what could otherwise be a joyous, meaningful, and satisfying life. </p>

<h2>High-Risk Retirement Types</h2>
<p>Some studies suggest that those in the two high-risk categories could face a long-term decline in well-being and life satisfaction and don’t necessarily rebound like the moderate-risk type.</p>
<p><em>Type Four: The Involuntary Retiree</em></p>
<p>Over 50 percent of people retire earlier than planned. The “Retiree Life in the Post-Pandemic Economy” report (Transamerica Center for Retirement Studies, 2024) found that ill health was the cause of 28 percent of early retirements. Of course, people involuntarily retire for other reasons, and this same report notes job loss (16 percent), organizational changes (16 percent), or job unhappiness (14 percent) also contribute to the decision.</p>



  


<p>Similarly, the 2025 Confidence Retirement Survey (Employee Benefit Research Institute/Greenwald Research, 2025) found that nearly seven in 10 retirees indicate the reason for retirement was something out of their control. Studies find involuntary retirement can lead to depression, anxiety, increased alcohol use, reduced physical activity, and decreased general well-being.</p>

<p><em>Type Five: The Involuntarily Employed Retiree</em></p>
<p>These are individuals who’ve reached retirement age and can’t retire (no matter how much they want to). Financial insecurities restrict their ability to leave the labor market even when facing serious health issues or adverse working conditions. An Economic Policy Institute study (2023) found that significant shares of older workers aged 50–70 experience difficult working conditions. Augmenting this finding is a recent spate of articles examining the mental health consequence of feeling trapped in one’s job as an older adult (e.g., Amilon, Larsen &amp; Siren, 2025; Guan et al., 2025; Raihan et al., 2024), including anxiety, depression, anger, the exacerbation of pre-existing mental and physical health problems, fatigue, and a sense of powerlessness.</p>

<p>What category do you fit into? Of course, a category by itself is not the final word on its mental health impact(s). It is equally important to factor in your physical and emotional health, social supports, financial resources, and personality characteristics. These can (1) support a satisfying retirement, (2) buffer the challenges in certain categories, or, in the worst case, (3) amplify the risks associated with each. Each person’s experience of retirement is idiosyncratic.</p>

<p>In the end, our retirement type does not definitively predict adjustment and mental health complications, but it can lead us to better prepare for the complications that can and, for many, do occur. The moderate-risk type can begin to prioritize psychological adjustment to retirement, while the two high-risk types should consider implementing supportive interventions sooner rather than later.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-life-of-the-american-male/202602/the-five-retirement-pathways" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-life-of-the-american-male/202602/the-five-retirement-pathways</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-life-of-the-american-male/202602/the-five-retirement-pathways</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Shelton MS, LPC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-kampus-8422672.jpg?itok=giI-tzd9" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[6 Ways to Manage Your Emotional Pain]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/untitled_2_0.jpg?itok=sNYHTgsC" alt="Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Self-Help</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">6 Ways to Manage Your Emotional Pain</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The keys to managing emotional pain are action and problem-solving.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">LIke physcial pain, emotional pain can go up and down for a variety of reasons. Our tolerances can differ.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It's helpful to track your emotional state, have tools to calm yourself, and solve the source of the problem.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Most of all, it is important to pat yourself on your back for making small behavioral changes.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/angst-802639_1280.jpg?itok=kU9TBl4C" width="320" height="459" data-insert-type="image" title="Johnhain/Pixabay" alt="Johnhain/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Johnhain/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>If you’ve ever gone to a doctor for an injury, it’s likely that one of the first questions you’re asked is: “What’s your pain level now on a scale of 1 to 10?” Some people tolerate pain better than others, and emotional pain (anxiety, anger, depression) is no different. Some can endure and are resilient, with high tolerance levels, while others—due to trauma, personality, or physical makeup—have lower ones.</p>

<p>Just as your doctor suggests ways to manage physical pain, there is much you can do to handle emotional pain. Here are six tips to help you:</p>
<h2>1. Track your emotions.</h2>
<p>When the doctor asks you to rate your pain level, take a moment to step back and assess exactly where it is. Create some distance between yourself and the pain instead of being fully immersed in it. The same approach applies when you consider your emotional state. By asking yourself about your emotional pain level, you shift your perspective, enabling you to take action.</p>

<p>And just as doctors warn you to take pain medication early, before it becomes unmanageable and less effective, tracking your emotions helps you take action early, increasing your chances of controlling it. </p>
<h2>2. Know your triggers.</h2>
<p>You’re recently divorced and attending a friend’s wedding this weekend, and naturally, the event will bring up all sorts of memories and emotions. Or your supervisor is unexpectedly harsh about your work on a recent project, leaving you feeling crushed and self-critical, just as you did as a child living with your critical parents.</p>

<p>Knowing what you’re sensitive to ahead of time can help you prepare mentally and behaviorally. You might ask a close friend to sit next to you at the wedding for support, or proactively email your supervisor for feedback on your work, giving you time and space to process it instead of risking being caught off guard.</p>

<h2>3. Have techniques handy to shift from your emotional brain to your rational one.</h2>
<p>When you become emotional, your amygdala (your emotional center) releases chemicals to your prefrontal lobes (your rational brain), and it literally shuts down. The key is to get your rational brain back online as quickly as possible. Here are a few suggestions:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Stop going down the rabbit hole.</strong> When you’re emotional, your mind is like a runaway horse, fixating on worst-case scenarios and what-ifs, leaving you overwhelmed. It’s time to pull on the reins. Regain control by taking a deep breath, then either plan for that worst-case scenario or shift your perspective by recognizing that this is really a first-world problem.</li>
<li><strong>Write down your thoughts. </strong>This is about venting to clear your head, but set a time limit—say, 10 minutes—so you don’t get lost and become even more overwhelmed.</li>
<li><strong>Get exercise. </strong>Vigorous activity, like walking briskly around the block, boosts endorphins, an effective antidote to negative thinking.</li>
<li><strong>Practice self-care. </strong>Here, you do something for yourself that helps you feel pampered or relaxes you. It could be taking a hot bath, listening to your favorite music, meditating, or doing another mindful activity you enjoy. The key is choosing something you can do alone; if your self-care depends on others—like calling a good friend—you might be in trouble if they’re not available.</li>
</ul>

<h2>4. Solve your problems.</h2>
<p>If you’re worried about ongoing problems with your finances or health, these can quickly become background noise that keeps you stressed or on edge. It’s time to put these issues to rest. Find someone to help you budget or offer financial advice; make an appointment with your doctor instead of waking up at 3 a.m., obsessing. Action is the best remedy for worry.</p>


<p>But also address the underlying emotional issues, such as learning new skills to better manage your anxiety or sensitivity to triggers. Read books or consider a short round of therapy. Be honest and clear with the therapist from the beginning about your goals.</p>
<h2>5. Build up your confidence and resilience by challenging yourself.</h2>

<p>As part of their training, Navy SEALs are constantly challenged. The reason is that learning to handle stressful situations enhances not only skills but also self-confidence. You can do the same.</p>
<p>By pushing yourself and going beyond your comfort zone, your anxiety lessens; you realize you are more capable than you thought, or that things are not as overwhelming as they initially appeared. You become more resilient to stressful and potentially emotional situations.</p>



  


<h2>6. Give yourself credit.</h2>
<p>Changing your behavior and stepping outside your comfort zone can be difficult, but even the smallest effort is a step forward. Turn off that critical voice and give yourself plenty of pats on the back. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/6-ways-to-manage-your-emotional-pain" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/6-ways-to-manage-your-emotional-pain</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/6-ways-to-manage-your-emotional-pain</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/ai-generated-8520972_1280.png.jpg?itok=PWaKt6FN" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is the Gut-Autism Link Overblown?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/anderson_scott-profile_0.png.jpg?itok=mPYu-dGy" alt="Scott C. Anderson" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Autism</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Is the Gut-Autism Link Overblown?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Researchers have found a link between the gut and autism, but is it real?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A recent article challenges the validity of gut-autism research.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It can be hard to pin down causality in the gut-brain axis, but it may not even be necessary.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Microbes may not cause autism, but they can affect mood and anxiety.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Studies show that it is possible to lower anxiety levels in autistic kids with diet and supplements.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <blockquote><p>“When you have exhausted all possibilities, remember this: you haven’t.” — Thomas A. Edison</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As a writer and a scientist, I have to say: writing is a lot easier than sciencing. In science, if you recommend a drug that doesn’t work, people may die. In writing, the worst that can happen is that people die of boredom. Fortunately, they usually revive.</p>

<p>For such a nerdy field, science can be surprisingly cutthroat. Witness a recent article that says gut-autism research is so bad they might as well just throw in the towel.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/science%20fight.jpg?itok=3LtU5kRd" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" alt="Science fight!" title="Generated with AI / Midjourney"></div>
<div class="caption">Science fight!</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Generated with AI / Midjourney</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2025.10.006">The article</a> from the journal <em>Neuron</em> argues that the gut-autism axis is a house of cards built on lousy studies with inconsistent data. They assert that the studies are contradictory and that too much emphasis is placed on dubious mouse models.</p>
<p>They may have a point.</p>
<p>It is notoriously challenging to nail down microbial causes of disease—it is hard enough to simply identify a normal microbiome. Moreover, many of these studies were done with mice, and what exactly is an autistic mouse?</p>

<p>One of their strongest critiques is that the studies have causality backward: Instead of microbes causing autism, they posit that people with autism have strange diets that compromise their microbiome.</p>
<p>But this may be a straw man argument. Microbiome studies are particularly prone to this criticism because there is some inherent circularity in the gut-brain axis. Your diet will clearly alter your microbiome, but your microbes can cause cravings that alter your diet. The take-home is that when you change either your diet or your microbes, you can convert a vicious cycle into a virtuous one. <em>It isn’t necessary to pin down causality in order to make an improvement.</em></p>

<p>More importantly, none of this research asserts that microbes <em>cause</em> autism. Rather, they find that changes in the microbiome can ameliorate certain symptoms. That seems uncontroversial and extremely useful. Let’s look at some of the studies.</p>
<h2>The microbial connection</h2>
<p>One study found an interesting connection between autism and microbes in the mouth. According to Kathy Kar-man Shum at the University of Hong Kong, there is a microbial signature of autism in the mouth microbiome. Simply by looking at oral microbes, the researchers can predict if a child will develop autism with 80 percent accuracy. That’s important for early identification and intervention, when therapy is most effective.</p>

<h2>Gut-brain studies</h2>
<p>John Cryan and Ted Dinan of University College Cork in Ireland have published widely on a mouse model of autism and have found specific populations of gut bacteria that are associated with the syndrome. They have also found microbes that ameliorate social symptoms of autism, including <em>Blautia stercoris</em>. (Full disclosure, I wrote a book with Cryan and Dinan called <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Psychobiotic-Revolution-Science-Gut-Brain-Connection/dp/142621846X"><em>The Psychobiotic Revolution</em></a> from <em>National Geographic</em>.) Cryan says, “There seems to be something about the social brain in particular that makes it sensitive to signals from the microbiome.”</p>

<p>It’s not just rodents. There is a gut microbe signature of autism in humans as well. Autistic children have lower levels of <em>Prevotella, Coprococcus,</em> and <em>Veillonella</em>. These microbes can produce GABA and serotonin, two neurotransmitters that may reduce agitation in people with autism.</p>
<h2>Finding causality</h2>
<p>Despite the circular nature of the gut-brain axis, studies by Sarkis Mazmanian and colleagues at Caltech provide some strong evidence for causality. They collected fecal samples from autistic and non-autistic people and transferred them to mice. The mice that received the autistic poop avoided socializing and engaged in repetitive behaviors, while the control mice acted normally. <em>The autistic behavior was transferred by fecal microbes.</em> That is as close to showing causality as biology can come right now.</p>

<p>Autistic kids often adhere to an idiosyncratic diet, whether it is healthy or not. In fact, their abnormal gut microbes may affect their cravings, making it difficult to alter their diet, but probiotics may help. A study by Rosa Krajmalnik-Brown and colleagues at Arizona State University showed that <em>probiotic supplements reduced gastric distress and lowered autism scores by almost 50 percent.</em> That’s a remarkable result and points to future therapies.</p>


<p>These studies are still too small, but that is to be expected from a new field of research. And we need to move beyond mice, but that’s expensive, and in America, research funding is drying up. Still, there is no reason to abandon this research, just as it is producing tangible results that are improving life for thousands of autistic kids and their parents.</p>

<p>There is a lot to be learned about autism, but like many other brain disruptions, there is a surprising link to the gut. Further studies will improve our understanding. Science is hard, but despite the naysayers, now is not the time to throw in the towel.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mood-by-microbe/202602/is-the-gut-autism-link-overblown" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mood-by-microbe/202602/is-the-gut-autism-link-overblown</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mood-by-microbe/202602/is-the-gut-autism-link-overblown</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Scott C. Anderson]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/science%20fight.jpg?itok=HohhgZ40" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>