<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 16:30:27 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 16:30:27 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Could Some Out-of-State Teletherapy Sessions Be Illegal?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-10/Barksy.jpg?itok=zklOIWhD" alt="Allan E. Barsky" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Online Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Could Some Out-of-State Teletherapy Sessions Be Illegal?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Ignorance of patient location is no excuse to out-of-state licensing violations.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Licensing laws restrict mental health practice to the states where the professional is licensed.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">At the start of sessions, telemental health professionals should ask clients where they are currently located.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Not verifying location is not a legitimate defense for out-of-state licensing violations.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When in doubt about what constitutes “practice,” consultation with an appropriate authority is advisable.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>In the case of <em>Illinois Nurses Association v. Rosenblatt et al.</em> (2025), hospital-based nurses were providing health care to clients both prior to and after admissions. Nurses expressed concerns that they could be violating state licensing laws because the hospital had instructed them not to ask patients for their physical locations; thus, the nurses could not determine whether they were serving clients who were in Illinois or out of state. </p>

<p>In its decision, the court noted:</p>
<blockquote><p>“Providing care to out-of-state patients is unlawful in many states, but nurses are reluctant to withhold care given the potentially dire consequences for patients… A nurse that refuses an out-of-state telehealth assignment may be subject to discipline under both Hospital policy and the nurse‘s state licensing agency.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>Relevance to Mental Health Professionals</h2>
<p>The case cited above was a trial court decision in Illinois and applied specifically to the nursing profession. Technically, the decision, therefore, is not a binding decision for courts in other states or for other professions, whose regulatory laws may be somewhat different than the laws for nurses. Still, the rationale for the court’s decision seems relevant to mental health professionals (MHPs). Just as regulatory laws for nurses typically state that nurses may provide nursing services only in states where they are licensed, laws regulating licensed MHPs also restrict practice to where they are licensed.</p>

<p>From a legal perspective, the location where practice takes place is defined primarily by where the client is physically located (Center for Connected Health Policy, n.d.). So, whether MHPs are providing therapy via telephone, videoconference, interactive online applications, or text messaging, they should ask where the client is located. If the client is located in another state where the MHP is not licensed, the MHP could be violating state laws. Ignorance of where the client is located may not be an excuse, at least from a legal perspective. Avoiding inquiry about client location does not shield MHPs from potential violations.</p>

<h2>Ethical-Legal Tensions</h2>
<p>MHPs have ethical duties to ensure clients have access to needed services (<a href="https://www.counseling.org/docs/default-source/default-document-library/ethics/2014-aca-code-of-ethics.pdf?sfvrsn=55ab73d0_1">ACA, 2014</a>; <a href="https://www.apa.org/ethics/code">APA, 2017</a>; <a href="https://www.socialworkers.org/About/Ethics/Code-of-Ethics/Code-of-Ethics-English">NASW, 2021</a>). The principle of fidelity suggests that MHPs should prioritize serving their clients and their well-being (Barsky, 2023). Consider a client in need of services, but who is out-of-state when services need to be provided. One response would be to refer the client to another MHP in the state where the client is currently located. Still, it may be in the client’s best interests to have continuity of care, which could mean that the original MHP should provide services even though the client is not in a state where the MHP is licensed. Just as the nurses in the Illinois case faced a conflict between their patient’s best interests and state laws, so may MHPs.</p>

<p>When such tensions arise, MHPs should strive to address the conflict in a manner that satisfies both. Since there may be no easy answer, consulting with attorneys, ethicists, risk managers, or clinical consultants may be prudent. Potential strategies include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Obtaining licensure in all states where clients are likely to be located (e.g., an MHP in Kansas City, Missouri may want to be licensed in the state of Kansas because it is so close to the MHP’s primary location).</li>
<li>During the informed consent process, letting clients know that the MHP can only provide services in the state or states where licensed to practice.</li>
<li>Exercising due diligence by verifying client location at the beginning of telehealth sessions.</li>
<li>Offering referrals to alternative service providers when clients require services in states where the MHP lacks licensure.</li>
</ul>

<h2>The Question of What Constitutes Practice</h2>
<p>Licensing laws prohibit practice in states where MHPs are not currently licensed (<a href="https://www.cchpca.org/topic/cross-state-licensing-professional-requirements">Center for Connected Health Policy, n.d.</a>). However, there may be questions about “what constitutes practice.” Not all communications with clients outside the state are necessarily considered practice. For instance, administrative communications such as scheduling appointments with out-of-state clients are unlikely to constitute practice. Similarly, brief follow-up calls with clients to see how they are doing may fall outside regulatory definitions. But what if the follow-up call generates new concerns and the client needs or requests assistance during the call? What if an MHP assigns clients online homework between sessions and the client completes and submits it from another state? Does this situation constitute out-of-state practice?</p>


<p>While some situations may be relatively clear, there may be fuzzy lines about whether certain types of tech-assisted interactions between MHPs and clients constitute practice for regulatory purposes. "Provider beware": For MHPs with questions about whether particular types of telephone, videoconference, or text-messaging interactions constitute practice, it may be wise to seek advice from an attorney, professional association, or licensing body. Some states and some professions may have already issued clarifications about <em>what constitutes practice</em> in terms of distance or virtual interactions with clients. Others may still need to do so.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/agens-scientiam/202602/could-some-out-of-state-teletherapy-sessions-be-illegal" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/agens-scientiam/202602/could-some-out-of-state-teletherapy-sessions-be-illegal</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/agens-scientiam/202602/could-some-out-of-state-teletherapy-sessions-be-illegal</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Allan E. Barsky PhD, MSW, JD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/shutterstock_2638922081.jpg?itok=0NyFao_X" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I’m Trying to Lose Weight. What Does Mean for My Kids?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/JosephSkelton.png.jpg?itok=cCzO9BJ_" alt="Joey Skelton M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Child Development</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">I’m Trying to Lose Weight. What Does Mean for My Kids?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How a parent's diet change can influence their children.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>When parents begin a weight‑loss program, change how they eat, or start new health routines, children notice more than we think. They see shifts in schedules, meals, and how adults act or feel around food. These changes can shape how kids think about eating, bodies, and health.</p>
<p>Caregivers often wonder how these efforts will affect their children. How do we pursue our own health goals without stressing our kids? How do we avoid mixed messages about weight and health, or cause our children to worry about their own weight? Can it be harmful for my children to see me trying to lose weight? Most of all, parents hope these changes can benefit their family as well as themselves.</p>

<p>A family‑centered approach—like the one discussed in my book, <em>Your Child Is Not Their Weight</em>—focuses on emotional safety, connection, and lifelong healthy habits, not weight. This helps children grow into confident, resilient eaters with a positive sense of self.</p>
<h2>The Family Environment Matters More Than the Diet</h2>

<p>When parents are advised to change how they eat or move, it might seem simplest to place the whole family on the same plan. But children are not “small adults.” Tools such as calorie counting, smaller portions, or strict food rules can feel confusing or even harmful for kids. <em>Dieting</em>, particularly counting calories or removing entire food groups, can set children up for eating disorders.</p>

<p>What children need most is structure, not restriction. Children, even older teens, do best when they know what to expect, as a predictable routine provides a feeling of comfort and safety. A general, but not overly strict, schedule for meals and snacks lays the foundation for healthy habits. Eating meals together as a family (however you define family) is an additional opportunity to model healthy eating. Making those meals pleasant, without pressuring children to eat more or less of certain foods, is another foundational practice for parents. Collectively, these habits help kids trust their bodies, reduce stress around food, and build healthy long‑term eating patterns.</p>

<h2>Talking to Kids About Your Health Without Talking About Weight</h2>
<p>Kids don’t need explanations about dieting, calories, or weight loss. These topics can feel overwhelming or scary, and can lead to an unhealthy focus on their bodies, disrupting their relationship with food.</p>
<p>Instead, keep conversations simple and focused on health, energy, and care, such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>“My doctor wants me to take good care of my heart.”</li>
<li>“This food helps my body feel strong.”</li>
<li>“I’m taking medicine to help my body stay healthy.”</li>
</ul>
<p>This reinforces that health isn’t the same as thinness, and that taking care of your body is something everyone does. It also supports the idea that food is something that can bring us together, nourish our bodies, and sustain traditions, instead of being about weight, body size, or worse, something to be feared.</p>

<h2>Avoiding Dieting Language That Can Harm Kids</h2>
<p>Even well‑intended comments about eating less or changing body size can create worry or harmful beliefs for children. Talking about weight too often can increase anxiety and weaken trust between parents and kids. Families can avoid labeling foods as <em>good</em> or <em>bad; </em>labeling a favorite snack food, like potato chips, as bad can inadvertently reinforce that tasty food is bad for you, and that “healthy” foods, like Brussels sprouts, won’t taste as good. Keep labels out of it and let food be food in all its complexity.</p>


<p>Another important practice is not commenting on anyone’s body size. That can be loaded and often backfire, having the opposite effect. Commenting on how someone “looks good” after losing weight, for example, could make them think, “did I look bad before I lost weight?” Another problem is <em>why</em> someone lost weight; they may be struggling with an illness or going through a rough time, and so the weight loss wasn’t intentional. It’s best just to show children that people’s bodies are not meant to be commented on.</p>

<p>This can apply to activity and exercise as well. We want children and families to find activities they enjoy doing; being active should not be a chore or a negative experience. Don’t tie activity to food or weight, like talking about calories, dieting, or “burning off” food.</p>
<p>Instead, parents should focus on a more holistic relationship with food and activity. Eating meals together without pressure allows children to notice hunger and fullness cues, to eat until they are full, and to stop eating without having to finish a certain amount of food. Offer balance and variety without pressure, even making room for treats and indulgent foods. People come in all shapes and sizes, and by not commenting on people’s bodies, you are fighting against societal tendencies toward an idealized body size and shape. Overall, kids thrive when they feel supported, not judged, so modeling that behavior is key. </p>



  


<h2>Modeling the Behaviors You Want Kids to Learn</h2>
<p>Children learn by watching the adults around them. When parents practice healthy habits, kids naturally absorb them. “Do as I say, not as I do" absolutely doesn’t work, and can even result in the opposite.</p>
<p>Helpful modeling of habits includes sitting together for meals, preparing balanced meals, moving your body in ways you enjoy, getting enough sleep (and keeping routines that support these habits, like having quiet bedtime routines), maintaining predictable schedules, and speaking kindly about your own body. Parents may also need to explain that some adult tools—such as shakes, tracking apps, or medical treatments—are not for kids, helping prevent imitation that could be unsafe for young people.</p>

<h2>Navigating Bariatric Surgery or Weight‑Loss Medication as a Parent</h2>
<p>If a parent uses weight‑loss medication or has bariatric surgery, kids may notice smaller portions, changes in appetite, or different food choices. Simple, honest explanations help them understand without worry:</p>
<ul>
<li>“I take this medicine to help my body stay healthy.”</li>
<li>“My surgery makes my stomach work differently, so I get full faster.”</li>
</ul>

<p>Avoid describing these tools as ways to become “better” or “smaller.” Emphasizing health, not size, teaches kids that everybody deserves care and respect. It’s up to parents how much to share with children, taking into account age and developmental status.</p>
<h2>Maintaining Emotional Safety for Kids</h2>
<p>Children pay close attention to how parents speak about their bodies. When adults criticize themselves or focus on the scale, kids may learn that only certain bodies are okay. Support emotional safety by using positive or neutral body talk (“My legs are strong; I walked three miles today.”). Avoid comparing yourself with others, particularly celebrities, models, or influencers, who may offer unrealistic body expectations. Praise children for what they <em>can</em> do, not what they can’t. Help them respect and like their own bodies. One way to do that is by celebrating qualities unrelated to appearance, but more inherent behaviors, such as kindness and empathy. A steady message of body respect nurtures strong self‑esteem.</p>

<h2>Family Connection as the Anchor for Change</h2>
<p>Healthy change grows from connection, not control. Warm routines, shared meals, and enjoyable activities help children feel secure. This foundation supports trust, self‑awareness, and a positive relationship with food and movement. We think of habits as “eating more fruits and vegetables” or “getting more exercise,” but we can shift that thinking to include more supportive habits: eating meals together as a family, having open and positive conversations during meals, establishing a predictable daily schedule, modeling patience and kindness, and showing respect for every person’s body.</p>

<p>Every body is unique, capable, and worthy. When children learn this at home, it strengthens their well-being for life.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/no-easy-answers/202601/im-trying-to-lose-weight-what-does-mean-for-my-kids" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/no-easy-answers/202601/im-trying-to-lose-weight-what-does-mean-for-my-kids</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/no-easy-answers/202601/im-trying-to-lose-weight-what-does-mean-for-my-kids</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Joey Skelton M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-01/boys-future-ZurijetaShutterstock_131957264.jpg?itok=tjRl3IJ1" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Too Competitive? How to Stop Comparisons From Taking Over]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/Plumbly080724-7127_LR_-_Copy-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=dODry8Fc" alt="Claire Plumbly ClinPsyD." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Career</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Too Competitive? How to Stop Comparisons From Taking Over</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to stop comparisons without losing your competitive edge.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Competitive urges are natural and essential for survival.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Threats can trigger increased competitive urges.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">We can counterbalance this by tending to our other motivational system: our affiliative/caring system.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Yesterday my daughter came home from school with a test result: 61 out of 70. But she was quiet and I knew something was up.</p>
<p>I assumed she thought she’d not done well, so started to reassure her that this was a good result.</p>
<p>But that wasn't the problem.</p>
<p>She explained that this was the third time in a few weeks where her best friend had scored a few marks higher than her. She couldn't help comparing herself to her friend, which made her determined to try hard to avoid being left behind.</p>

<h2>Why We Compare Ourselves to Others Like This</h2>
<p>This is due to the natural competitive motivations within us; there to help us reach goals essential for surviving and thriving—a secure status in our social group, money, food, a home, or a mate.</p>
<p>Healthy competitiveness can sharpen our skills, push us to try hard, and drive us toward personal growth. But sometimes competitiveness takes over in an <em>unhealthy </em>way, leaving you comparing yourself to <em>everyone</em>, obsessing about results, or distancing yourself (or even feeling hostile toward) friends and colleagues.</p>

<p>The story shared by the renowned shame researcher Brené Brown about her weekly swim is excellent at conveying how instinctive this competitive urge is. In this, she describes the deeply primal reaction she gets when someone comes alongside her in the swimming lane—how this intense urge to finish the length before them takes over (even though she’s not in a race with them).</p>

<p>If you’ve noticed this occurring in yourself, then know that it’s very normal. This was what had happened with my daughter with her math results, causing her to focus outwardly on comparisons rather than her own achievements.</p>
<p>This post explains why competitiveness can feel so compelling but also trigger insecure-striving behaviours and what you can do about this.</p>

<h2>Understanding Our Two Systems of Motivation</h2>
<p>We have two primary motivation systems that developed for our survival:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Our competitive system</strong>: As mentioned already, this is focused on status, achievement, outperforming others, and protecting our place in the hierarchy. It’s activated particularly strongly when we feel threatened or when we perceive that resources, recognition, or opportunities are limited.</li>
<li><strong>Our caring system</strong>: Oriented toward connection, cooperation, and mutual support. This system is grounded in compassion—for both others and for ourselves. When our caring system is active, we feel safe, valued, and less preoccupied with “proving” ourselves.</li>
</ol>

<p>Both are essential. The challenge is that when we feel stressed or threatened (such as by deadlines, performance reviews, or difficult feedback), our competitive system often takes over. This can lead to overwork, strained relationships, and burnout.</p>
<h2>What Does Overactive Competition Look Like?</h2>
<p> Here are some fictitious examples to demonstrate.</p>

<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>When Competitiveness Shows Up as Perfectionism</strong><br>Julie is always diligent at work but lately, she’s been feeling anxious, obsessing over tiny mistakes, and secretly comparing her work to her colleagues’. Instead of celebrating her colleagues’ successes, she worries that others are catching up to her.</p>
<p><em>Competitive Motivation:</em> Julie's fear of falling behind has shifted her focus from collaboration to constant self-evaluation and trying to perfect every detail as a result.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>When Competitiveness Shows Up as Resentment</strong><br>Rob's friend and colleague shares news that he's been promoted to lead an exciting new project that Rob had hoped to work on himself.</p>
<p><em>Competitive Motivation:</em> Rob feels resentment toward his friend, and he starts to withdraw from him to avoid the intense jealousy and to focus on working for a similar promotion.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>When Competitiveness Shows Up as Overworking</strong><br>Michaela agrees to every new task, even when her itinerary is already full. She wants to show she’s indispensable to the team (after all, this was how she was praised when she was a kid)—but this has left her exhausted, overwhelmed, and increasingly frustrated.</p>
<p><em>Competitive Motivation: </em>Michaela's drive to stay ahead is fueled by insecurity, leaving her overworked and unable to prioritise her well-being.</p>
</li>
</ol>


<h2>Why We Become More Competitive When Threatened</h2>
<p>Our competitive system is linked to our body’s threat response system. When we feel vulnerable, whether because of external pressures like a tough work situation or internal doubts about our ability or worth, we often default to competing as a way to protect ourselves. It’s a form of fight response (from the fight-or-flight reaction of the sympathetic nervous system).</p>

<p>Whilst this fight response might be instinctive, the truth is that in many modern-day situations it’s counterproductive. Allowing overactive competition to rule your decisions can lead to:</p>
<ol>
<li>Distancing from those who we perceive to be our competitors. For example, my daughter got an urge to sit next to someone else who didn’t score so well to make herself feel better.</li>
<li>A tendency to see rest as unacceptable (because it isn’t safe). For example, my daughter was tempted to revise excessively for the next test to aim for 100%.</li>
</ol>



  


<p>Additionally, when our threat response is triggered in this way, we tend to push support away and hold others at arm's length. We feel shame and don’t want to let on what’s happening. This was the case for my daughter after school—I was a neutral ally (she wasn’t in competition with me for results) but still it took quite a bit of time of sitting and nursing a cup of tea together until she felt able to tell me what was bothering her.</p>

<p>Social connection and a sense of belonging dampen down this threat response, giving us respite from this insecure-striving part of ourselves. So even though it goes against what our body <em>thinks </em>it needs during a moment of overactive competitiveness, this can be part of the solution.</p>
<h2>Practical Steps for an Overactive Competitive System</h2>

<p>These can help you choose your level of competitiveness. We aren't trying to get rid of this, but to make it manageable.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Pause and Notice Your Response</strong><br>Ask yourself: What triggered my competitive feelings? Am I feeling insecure, overlooked, or underappreciated? Often, simply naming your emotions can help you gain clarity and create distance from them.<br> </li>
<li><strong>Practice Self-Compassion</strong><br>When you’re hard on yourself, it’s easy to become hard on others, too. Try this exercise: Picture yourself as a friend who’s struggling. What would you say to support and encourage them? Now, turn those kind words toward yourself.<br> </li>
<li><strong>Focus on Your Contributions</strong><br>Shift your attention from “What am I achieving compared to others?” to “How am I contributing to the team’s goals?” By celebrating your unique strengths, you can reconnect with a sense of purpose and belonging.<br><br><em>Example</em>: If Julie (from earlier) focused on mentoring a junior team member instead of striving to be “perfect,” she might be reminded of how much she knows and is capable of.</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Engage in Acts of Care</strong><br>Small gestures—like checking in on a colleague or friend, offering help, or even expressing gratitude—can activate your caring system. This not only improves relationships but also boosts your own sense of well-being.</p>
<p><em>Example</em>: If Rob spent time with his friend chatting about his achievement, Rob might begin to connect to the feeling of "sympathetic joy"—our natural capacity to feel joy in response to the happiness of others, which could reduce his threat mode.</p>
</li>
</ol>

<h2>A Compassionate Mindset Is a Resilient Mindset</h2>
<p>Balancing competition and care doesn’t mean you need to abandon your ambitions. You are at your best when you feel connected, supported, and valued. By learning to tune into your caring motivations, you can create a more sustainable, fulfilling work-life balance and avoid the burnout that comes from the constant striving that living in your competitive motivational system brings.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/overwhelm-unlocked/202603/too-competitive-how-to-stop-comparisons-from-taking-over" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/overwhelm-unlocked/202603/too-competitive-how-to-stop-comparisons-from-taking-over</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/overwhelm-unlocked/202603/too-competitive-how-to-stop-comparisons-from-taking-over</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Claire Plumbly ClinPsyD.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/pexels-mikhail-nilov-6592363.jpg?itok=Cy9fdqTH" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why the News Feels So Personal Right Now]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-10/Headshot_1-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=ST9_TWos" alt="Ankita Guchait MBPsS" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Identity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why the News Feels So Personal Right Now</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Trauma, identity, and the psychology of constant news exposure.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Global news affects people differently depending on identity, memory, and trauma history.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Diaspora, nationality, and professional roles shape emotional responses to world events.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Staying informed does not necessarily lead to emotional flooding if news consumption is paced.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Recognizing your nervous system response to headlines helps preserve psychological choice.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/pexels-alex-green-5699854.jpg?itok=YFMU4jUR" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Alex Green / Pexels" alt="Alex Green / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Alex Green / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Three people read the same headline.</p>
<p>One texts their loved ones immediately.<br>One feels a flicker of shame they cannot quite explain.<br>One thinks about the clients they will see tomorrow.</p>
<p>The news is rarely just information. It moves through identity, family memory, and the nervous system.</p>
<p>We often speak about “staying informed” as if information lands the same way for everyone. It does not. In moments of war, humanitarian crisis, or political controversy, people tend to occupy different psychological positions even when reading the same story.</p>

<p>Broadly, I notice three.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/pexels-rdne-6414712.jpg?itok=uNNcsU0k" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="RDNE Stock Project / Pexels" alt="RDNE Stock Project / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: RDNE Stock Project / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>When It’s “Back Home”</h2>
<p>For people with roots in an affected region—immigrants, diaspora communities, refugees, or those with family still there—the news is deeply relational.</p>
<p>You may be physically safe, but your body may not fully register safety.</p>
<p>Media exposure to global crises can increase distress and anxiety by sustaining uncertainty and threat perception signals to the nervous system (Kesner et al., 2025).</p>

<p>A headline can become many things:</p>
<ul>
<li>A memory of leaving.</li>
<li>A fear for family.</li>
<li>The reopening of older grief.</li>
<li>A trigger for hypervigilant monitoring of news updates.</li>
</ul>
<p>For some, crises also activate intergenerational narratives of survival and migration. Trauma can echo across generations, shaping emotional and biological stress responses.</p>

<p>What helps is not emotional detachment but intentional pacing:</p>
<ul>
<li>Structured news consumption rather than endless scrolling.</li>
<li>Naming layered grief—the present crisis alongside older wounds. </li>
<li>Maintaining contact with loved ones in ways that are intentional rather than constant.</li>
<li>Asking a simple but powerful question: What is within my sphere of agency right now?</li>
</ul>

<p>Distance can amplify helplessness. Agency restores psychological coherence.</p>
<h2>When Your Country or Group Identity Is Involved</h2>
<p>There is another, more complex discomfort when the country or community you identify with is perceived as causing harm.</p>
<p>Even if you personally disagree with policies or political leadership, something inside may still feel unsettled.</p>

<p>A subtle internal question may emerge: <em>Is this who we are?</em></p>
<p>Collective guilt and collective shame are well-established psychological experiences linked to group identity and perceived wrongdoing (Schaller, Schumann &amp; Arlt, 2025). When identity is involved, threatening information can trigger defensive responses or excessive self-blame.</p>

<p>Emotional reactions vary:</p>
<ul>
<li>Some move into denial or minimization.</li>
<li>Some experience intense polarization.</li>
<li>Some withdraw from news altogether.</li>
<li>Others carry disproportionate self-blame.</li>
</ul>
<p>These are attempts to regulate psychological discomfort, and not moral failures. Differentiation is often the key: You are not identical to a government. You are not morally pure because you distance yourself. You are not morally irredeemable because you belong to a group associated with harm.</p>

<p>Processing these positions requires tolerating complexity—staying engaged with the world without collapsing into shame or defensive certainty. This may mean consuming information from multiple perspectives, having slower conversations than social media encourages, and allowing space for grief without fusing it with personal identity.</p>

<p>Discomfort that is metabolized can become ethical clarity. Discomfort that is avoided often becomes polarization.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/pexels-shvets-production-7176029.jpg?itok=QPb1qu5l" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="SHVETS Production / Pexels" alt="SHVETS Production / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: SHVETS Production / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>When You Work With People Who Are Directly Impacted</h2>
<p>Another experience often invisible in public discourse is that of helpers. Therapists, teachers, doctors, NGO workers, journalists, and community responders do not encounter global crises only through headlines. The world enters their professional spaces the next day.</p>



  


<p>I remember this from working with Afghan evacuees during contingency hotel placements in London, when conflict was unfolding. Many individuals I screened were navigating displacement, uncertainty, and layered trauma.</p>
<p>Rapport building sometimes began with something very simple: clarifying identity and safety.</p>

<p>Because of time spent in the United States, I was occasionally positioned through political assumptions linked to nationality. Some screening conversations included direct questions shaped by geopolitical narratives. At the same time, my Indian cultural background also required gentle explanation in certain interactions.</p>

<p>Building trust often meant moving away from geopolitical categories and toward shared human experiences. We would look for small relational anchors: Historical and cultural ties between India and Afghanistan; food, cricket, community life, and family-centered social values; and shared experiences of religion and belonging.</p>

<p>These were not political strategies but psychological bridges that allowed safety to emerge before deeper trauma narratives were explored.</p>
<p>Working in such contexts also revealed how thin the boundary can feel between personal and professional identity when global events unfold. Research shows that repeated indirect exposure to trauma in helping professions can contribute to experiences resembling vicarious trauma and secondary traumatic stress (Cooley et al., 2026). Such exposure can contribute to emotional exhaustion, countertransference activation, boundary strain, and identification with suffering that challenges professional containment.</p>

<p>If you carry personal history linked to the affected region, these internal boundaries may feel even more fragile.</p>
<p>Reflective spaces therefore matter:</p>
<ul>
<li>Supervision and peer discussion that explicitly acknowledge current events.</li>
<li>Slowing down clinical or professional responses.</li>
<li>Monitoring rescue impulses that push toward over-responsibility.</li>
<li>Remembering that staying regulated is part of ethical and clinical responsibility.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Living With News Without Being Held by It</h2>
<p>In a hyperconnected world, we are exposed to crisis continuously, and repeated exposure to distressing media content can influence anxiety and stress regulation even among people not directly affected by events (Nguyen et al., 2025).</p>
<p>Before reacting to the next headline, it can help to pause and consider:</p>

<ul>
<li>What position am I occupying right now? </li>
<li>Which part of my identity is activated?</li>
<li>Is my body feeling mobilized, frozen, ashamed, or hyper-alert?</li>
<li>What would regulated engagement look like rather than emotional flooding?</li>
</ul>
<p>The same headline can evoke fear, shame, grief, or responsibility. None of those responses are inherently wrong. They are context-shaped nervous system responses. But understanding why something lands the way it does gives us more psychological choice.</p>

<p>In a world saturated with crisis, this may be one of the most protective skills we can cultivate.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-realities-of-refugee-screening/202603/why-the-news-feels-so-personal-right-now" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-realities-of-refugee-screening/202603/why-the-news-feels-so-personal-right-now</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-realities-of-refugee-screening/202603/why-the-news-feels-so-personal-right-now</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Ankita Guchait MBPsS]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/pexels-alex-green-5699854.jpg?itok=y3Z9rJtz" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What the Acetabulum Can Teach Us About Marriage]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-03/Bonnie%20Comfort.png.jpg?itok=PicpqAum" alt="Bonnie Comfort Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Marriage</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What the Acetabulum Can Teach Us About Marriage</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Our hip joint shows us how to maintain love in spite of the ways we are damaged.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Look for how your history contributes to pain in your relationships. Ask yourself questions and take notes.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Reduce conflict by understanding the emotional logic of your partner and eliminating mean words or threats.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Love your partner but don't sacrifice what you need. Find some joy in other ways.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>My partner, a retired surgeon, described what the acetabulum is in the human body: the cup-shaped socket into which the top of the femur fits. The femur is the thigh bone. The acetabulum (a·suh·ta·byuh·luhm) is on the outer sides of the large pelvis bone about two-thirds of the way down.</p>
<p>Both the acetabulum and femur head are lined with “articular cartilage”—slippery tissue that allows the motion of the bone in the socket to rotate smoothly. When both structures fit perfectly into each other, that cartilage creates a smooth, low-friction surface that helps the bones glide easily across each other during movement.</p>

<p>This is like the beginning of a happy marriage, when two people fit together well enough that their interactions cause only minor or transient pain for some years. When the bones don’t form so well during childhood growing years, they can develop an irregular shape. Then, because they don’t fit together perfectly, the bones rub against each other during movement as they age, eventually causing pain and limiting activity. </p>

<h2>Document Your Own Childhood Wounds</h2>
<p>That is a good description of how a marriage can deteriorate: after the early contentment has diminished, old and damaging childhood experiences surface and begin to impinge on the smoothness of the relationship, causing irritation and conflict between the partners, which can lead to pain, disillusionment, and sometimes divorce. Can we be smart enough to recognize that distress in our childhood eventually behaves like an overgrowth of bone that damages our connection to others and results in pain and distress? This is how <em>you and your history </em>contribute to the pain and conflict in your relationship. To some extent, childhood adversity shapes our identity, our self-esteem, and our fears and expectations of others.</p>

<p>We all grow up in less-than-perfect homes, with less-than-perfect caregivers. That means your psychological articulating cartilage doesn’t work perfectly all the time. To improve that, it’s helpful to know how you were shaped by your childhood. Think about the questions below and write down your notes:</p>

<p>How did you learn to cope with difficult emotions? Who and how much could you trust? How did you learn to resolve conflict? Were you able to compete? Was your self-esteem nurtured or were you too often demeaned and therefore carry a sensitive wound that can easily cause pain?</p>
<h2>Dial Down Your Angry Dialogue</h2>

<p>These formative experiences drive differences between you and other people. Having respectful conversations about those differences and helping your partner understand your past struggles is everything in how your relationships will go, so:</p>
<ol>
<li>Try to understand the emotional logic underneath your partner’s point of view. There’s always a reason that makes sense in their internal world.</li>
<li>Lower the ugliness of the dialogue. Cruel, demeaning, and discounting words or threatening to end the relationship can create permanent damage that’s like growing excess bone that cannot be smoothed away.</li>
</ol>

<p>The acetabulum is ringed by strong fibrocartilage called the labrum. The labrum forms a gasket around the socket, creating a tight seal that helps provide stability to the joint. This is like a firm boundary around your own identity. If you can remain intact as a separate person, know what you need, and accept that not everything you need can be given by your partner, your level of anger and resentment can be toned down.</p>


<h2>Look After Yourself</h2>
<p>There must be a compromise between pleasing others and pleasing yourself, just the way a ball and socket move together smoothly but are always unique and separate. To some extent, it’s up to you to love, understand, and support yourself. Here’s what can help:</p>
<ol>
<li>Ask yourself what gives you joy, what nurtures you, and when you’re happiest. Pursue those experiences. The less you expect anybody else to do that for you, the greater your capacity for contentment, and the smoother your relationships will be.</li>
<li>Going through life withdrawn and alone is a recipe for depression. Make a point of nurturing not only your primary relationship but your important connections with friends and family.</li>
<li>Notice small, beautiful things around you—maybe it’s a 5-year-old learning to roller skate, her helmet, and knee pads Barbie pink, her tongue curled outside the corner of her mouth, her mom, keeping her safe next to her. Maybe it’s a dog running across a field in time to catch a frisbee before it lands, or maybe it’s a perfect, shiny red door to someone’s house. Noticing beauty can lift your mood and inspire you.</li>
<li>Focus on the present. Past regrets and future anxieties can interfere with enjoying current positive experiences.</li>
</ol>

<p>You look after your body through exercise, good nutrition, and good sleep. When it comes to marriage, conflict is inevitable, and just as bones don’t stay strong without being stressed, resilience in a marriage doesn’t develop without tolerating some pain and disappointment in each other and embracing other avenues of meaning and pleasure. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-complexities-of-relationships/202603/what-the-acetabulum-can-teach-us-about-marriage" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-complexities-of-relationships/202603/what-the-acetabulum-can-teach-us-about-marriage</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-complexities-of-relationships/202603/what-the-acetabulum-can-teach-us-about-marriage</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Bonnie Comfort Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/bony%20pelvis%20for%20Bon%20iStock-1328735734_0.jpeg.jpg?itok=aRZo3M35" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>