<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 18:56:31 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 18:56:31 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anatoly: An In-depth Look at His Heavyweight Humor]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/jcsimon_headshot-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=sgKqFmPE" alt="John Charles Simon" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Laughter</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Anatoly: An In-depth Look at His Heavyweight Humor</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Appreciating how one prolific prankster serves up laughter by the pound.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">TikTok and YouTube prankster Anatoly uses his modest stature and incredible strength to humble his victims.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Feigning ignorance or weakness, Anatoly seems incapable of lifting the same weights as others in his videos.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Anatoly's victims often laugh at his pranks out of embarrassment, and we fans may laugh in sympathy.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-victorfreitas-703012_crop.jpg?itok=yjQH9u95" width="320" height="284" data-insert-type="image" title="Victor Freitas / Pexels" alt="Victor Freitas / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Victor Freitas / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Anyone who spends untold hours surfing the Web for humorous content will eventually find the work of one Vladimir Shmondenko, a prankster who goes by the name Anatoly. He’s developed a faithful following, and, as far as I can tell, makes a comfortable living entirely from his TikTok and YouTube videos. For those of us fascinated by laughter and the humor used to solicit it, a careful look at his work can be quite instructive.</p>

<h2>The 4 types of laughter</h2>
<p>As most of my readers already know, the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/laughter-and-humor-101/202105/what-you-say-laughter">mutual vulnerability theory</a>—the explanation for laughter that I rely on in this blog series—recognizes four “types” of laughter. These reflect the four different motivations we might have for reminding others that they and we both possess vulnerabilities. </p>

<p>When someone else’s shortcoming is highlighted in a way that lowers their status, sympathetically affirming that we share similar vulnerabilities can lift their spirits. This “lifting laughter" is common among friends and family, and even with strangers. Similarly, when we ourselves fall short of expectations, “self-lifting laughter” reminds others of their limitations and helps restore our status. This is common after we embarrass ourselves, especially when among those we believe will be understanding. When our status is inflated to the point of discomfort, for example, when we are overly praised or attain some advantage due to luck, we can use “self-lowering laughter” to communicate that we are no better than anyone else. It conveys modesty and humility that can serve to preempt others from thinking of us as arrogant.</p>

<h2>'Lowering laughter' in Anatoly's pranks</h2>
<p>What first attracted me to Anatoly’s content was the presence of what I have come to refer to as “lowering laughter.” This is the sort that helps keep in check others who, for whatever reason, think their status is higher than we believe it to be—the conceited, self-important, egotistical people who need to be reminded that they, too, have vulnerabilities just like we do. </p>

<p>When they exhibit a loss in status, we use lowering laughter to do the job. It’s sometimes referred to as derisively “laughing at” someone, rather than compassionately “laughing with” them. This lowering form is relatively rare in online content when compared to lifting- and self-lifting laughter. </p>
<p>What is nice about Anatoly’s work is that the lowering laughter he typically inspires from his victims is <em>not<strong> </strong></em>like the more intense forms commonly associated with bullies. It is not mean-spirited and degrading, but rather something gentler, aimed at those who are behaving a bit overconfident or pretentious. See my <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/laughter-and-humor-101/202202/how-your-laughter-can-take-others-down-peg">earlier post</a> for a more thorough explanation.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>How Anatoly's pranks work</h2>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-ivan-s-4164761_crop.jpg?itok=-tuobcmV" width="320" height="287" data-insert-type="image" title="Ivan S / Pexels" alt="Ivan S / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Ivan S / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Anatoly’s pranks are typically initiated in one of several ways and follow a general pattern. He always wears clothing that hides his muscular build. He pretends to be a trainer offering unsolicited advice, an over-confident novice, a know-it-all passerby, or (most often) a cleaner at the gym. Then, often by getting his unsuspecting victims to insist <em>he</em> lift the heavy weights they are using, he cleverly turns the tables. How? By lifting roughly three times the amount of weight anyone would expect, simply by looking at him. Let’s analyze a sample of his work.</p>

<p>In the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/ERvE4s-g1tw">first example</a>, Anatoly approaches two gym patrons and asks them if he can do a “warm-up” with them. They understandably assume he’s kidding. They laugh (what I would characterize as a relatively mild lowering laugh), thinking, “There’s no way he can lift the weight they are using; he must be confused.” Next, Anatoly says he wants to lift even more than what they have on the bar. This brings about a more potent lowering laugh meant to counter his inflated ego. Anatoly then hands his mop to the one laughing hardest, a custom prop that weighs 70 lbs (32kg). Suddenly, the look of self-satisfaction and superiority disappears from his victim’s face. A few moments later, we see Anatoly effortlessly lift the massive weight as his targets look on in disbelief. They assumed theirs was a higher status (vis-à-vis weightlifting) based solely on Anatoly’s outward appearance, and now it is their loss of status that we, the audience, respond to with our laughter. What form? Maybe a little lowering, because they judged him, but mostly (I would wager) lifting. After all, they were not bullying him. They were duped. Their embarrassment was brought about by design, and context matters. In many instances, his targets are simply trying to protect Anatoly from hurting himself. That’s a motive with which viewers can sympathize.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-victorfreitas-949129_crop.jpg?itok=Xm8satnh" width="320" height="282" data-insert-type="image" title="Victor Freitas / Pexels" alt="Victor Freitas / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Victor Freitas / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Of course, this outcome is not repeated in all of Anatoly’s videos. Some victims are irritated, others confused, and many respond only with smiles, which can signal <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/laughter-and-humor-101/202209/you-laughed-she-smiled-and-he-did-neither">low-level amusement</a>. But it happens enough to require an explanation.</p>
<p>Below are a few more links to check out. In the first three, Anatoly cleverly gets them to express lowering laughter before later generating self-lifting laughter after their misgivings are revealed. Their faulty assumptions about his abilities expose the same pridefulness they initially attributed to Anatoly, and they acknowledge this by affirming their own vulnerability. This is exactly the kind of self-awareness and humility we as viewers find appealing, and we convey <em>our</em> lifting laughter in support. Then, too, for those of us with a special appreciation for just how brilliantly Anatoly executes his pranks, a little self-lifting laughter of our own may be added to the mix. Enjoy.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Mild lowering laughter, then self-lifting laughs and smiles:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/lm-0w1wzAoA">Example 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/nvL127LJIdg">Example 3</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/sN_GiW_ycB4">Example 4</a> </li>
</ul>
<p>No lowering laughter; mostly surprised self-lifting laughter and a smile:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/HGmrmEpBbxk">Example 5</a> </li>
</ul>
<p><em>© John Charles Simon</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/laughter-and-humor-101/202602/anatoly-an-in-depth-look-at-his-heavyweight-humor" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/laughter-and-humor-101/202602/anatoly-an-in-depth-look-at-his-heavyweight-humor</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/laughter-and-humor-101/202602/anatoly-an-in-depth-look-at-his-heavyweight-humor</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[John Charles Simon]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-tima-miroshnichenko-5327535_full.jpg?itok=HpqGdE80" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You Want a Clinician Who Treats You as Person]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-02/Mitchell%20Liester.png.jpg?itok=AJjY6Q6z" alt="Mitchell B. Liester M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychopharmacology</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">You Want a Clinician Who Treats You as Person</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">You do not want a clinician who treats you as a diagnosis.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Evidence-based medicine treats the "average patient" — but that patient doesn't exist.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Knowing a patient's history, family, stress, and habits predicts outcomes more powerfully than any checklist.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The therapeutic alliance is more important than the medication itself in determining treatment success.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">15-minute appointments force algorithmic care, leaving patients unseen, unheard, and frustrated.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Imagine two people walk into their psychiatrist’s office on the same day. Both are struggling with low mood, poor sleep, and fatigue. Both leave with the same prescription, the same dose, and the same follow-up appointment scheduled in six weeks. One gets better. The other doesn't. Why?</p>
<p>This story is repeated millions of times each year, and raises the question: Should doctors treat diseases, or should they treat people?</p>

<h2>Evidence Based Medicine</h2>
<p>For most of the 20th century, medicine operated on a simple premise: find the best treatment for a given condition, test it on large populations, and apply that knowledge universally. This approach —called evidence-based medicine (EBM)— was formalized in the 1990s, largely by Canadian physician David Sackett.</p>

<p><a href="http://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.312.7023.71">Sackett</a> described the goal of EBM is to replace hunches and habits with data and clinical trials. Clinical guidelines were developed involving protocols that tell doctors which drug to prescribe first, what dose to use, when to escalate treatment, and when to refer a patient to a specialist. Today, these guidelines are often incorporated into electronic health records, where they guide physicians toward the statistically optimal choice for the average patient.</p>

<p>But there’s a problem with this model: the average patient doesn’t exist. The studies that generate these guidelines often underrepresent women, older adults, children, people of color, and anyone with more than one diagnosis. The "average" is a statistical construct. And when you apply a treatment designed for a construct to a human being, the treatment doesn’t always work.</p>

<h2>Treating the Person in the Room</h2>
<p>There’s another tradition in medicine. This tradition is older than algorithms, older than clinical trials, and it doesn’t begin with a diagnosis but rather with a question: Who is this person?</p>
<p>This approach starts with the assumption that effective care involves knowing your patient. Sounds revolutionary, but it’s not. It requires a clinician to invest time in getting to know their patient — not just their symptoms, but their history. Their work. Their family. Their fears. Their habits. Their preferences about medication. Their history with past treatments, and what "getting better" means to them personally.</p>

<p>This is not pseudoscience. It’s clinical science. A patient's occupation, family situation, sleep environment, financial stress, and social support system are important details. They’re some of the most powerful predictors of health outcomes available to any physician. A doctor who knows that her patient is a firefighter working 24-hour shifts, or his patient is a single father of three with no time to fill prescriptions, or her patient grew up in a household where mental illness was treated as a moral failing — that doctor has access to information no algorithm or checklist will identify.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>The Science of Knowing Your Patient</h2>
<p>The therapeutic alliance, which is the quality of the relationship between a clinician and their patient, is one of the most powerful predictors of treatment outcome in psychiatry and psychology. A <a href="https://psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/appi.ps.201700114">2017 meta-analysis</a> examined over 1,000 patients and found that a positive physician-patient relationship was associated with better outcomes even in medication-based treatment — not just psychotherapy. The strength of the relationship mattered as much as the drug itself.</p>


<p>Similarly, a 2006 <a href="https://psychiatryonline.org/doi/10.1176/foc.4.2.269">psychotherapy trial</a> found the quality of the therapeutic alliance predicted outcomes across every treatment condition, whether patients were receiving psychotherapy, medication, or placebo. A clinician who takes time to understand their patient isn’t just being kind. They’re being effective.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1367516/full">2024 meta-analysis</a> found that the emotional bond between a patient and their clinician, a bond which comes from feeling known and understood, is among the most important determinants of what happens in treatment. Patients who feel heard and seen get better more often than patients who feel they have been reduced to a diagnosis or a number.</p>



  


<h2>The Art of Pattern Recognition</h2>
<p>There is something else the algorithms cannot replicate: the trained eye of a seasoned clinician.</p>
<p>When an experienced clinician meets a new patient, they’re drawing on years of encounters, thousands of patients, hundreds of variations, and countless combinations of details. This is called <em>pattern recognition</em>, and research shows it’s a powerful tool that is employed by experienced, successful practitioners.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10366061/pdf/41235_2023_Article_497.pdf">2023 review</a> reported that expert clinicians rely on fast, intuitive pattern recognition that allows them to identify subtle diagnostic signals in ways that are not revealed in protocols or checklists.</p>
<p>Pattern recognition in psychiatry is complex. An experienced clinician might notice a patient's animated speech and pacing that doesn’t match the dark circles under their eyes. Or they recognize that the man sitting across from them has the affect of someone who is depressed, despite his statement that he’s happy. Or they recognize a pattern they've observed before when a man focuses on his marital problems, rather than his problem with alcohol.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>What Gets Lost When the Appointment Lasts Fifteen Minutes</h2>
<p>The modern healthcare system is not designed to support the kind of medicine described above. The average primary care appointment in the United States lasts about fifteen minutes. In psychiatry, "medication management" visits can be as short as ten minutes. There is barely enough time to update a medication list, let alone ask how their job is going.</p>

<p>This is not a failure of individual practitioners. Most clinicians went into healthcare because they wanted to know their patients as human beings and help them. The shortening of appointment times is a structural problem — one that pushes clinicians to use algorithmic medicine.</p>
<p>The result is that patients often feel unseen and unheard. They answer the questions on the intake form, receive a diagnosis that fits those answers, and walk out with a treatment plan that may not work, not because the treatments are bad, but because the doctor didn’t know enough about them to develop an effective, individualized treatment plan.</p>

<p>The solution to our current healthcare crisis is deceptively simple. It involves training clinicians who listen carefully, ask questions that go beyond the symptom checklist, and treat their patients as unique human beings rather than diagnoses or CPT-codes. Which approach would you prefer your doctor use?</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-leading-edge/202602/you-want-a-clinician-who-treats-you-as-person" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-leading-edge/202602/you-want-a-clinician-who-treats-you-as-person</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-leading-edge/202602/you-want-a-clinician-who-treats-you-as-person</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mitchell B. Liester M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Mart%20Production%20%20Pexels.jpg?itok=e1I-keGR" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Harnessing the Power of 'If']]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/mcnaughton-cassill_3.jpg?itok=QIgMFkEq" alt="Mary McNaughton-Cassill Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Self-Talk</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Harnessing the Power of 'If'</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How proactive coping can change your outlook.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Counterfactual regret occurs when a person ruminates about alternative ways things could have happened.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Preventive coping involves anticipating and preparing for threatening future events.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Proactive coping is based on viewing future threats as challenges, which can result in personal growth.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Humans, like animals, make decisions based on prior experiences. But unlike our animal companions, we have a highly developed ability to ruminate about what has already happened and to worry about what might occur in the future. </p>
<p>In his book, <em>Why Zebras Don’t Get Ulcers,</em> psychologist Robert Sapolsky argues that, unlike humans, most animals experience a fight-or-flight response when faced with a stressor but immediately return to their resting state when the danger abates. In contrast, humans spend significant amounts of time replaying what happened, assessing the choices they made, and worrying about future threats and challenges. These ruminations can fall into three categories centered around the conditional word “if.”</p>

<h2>Counterfactual regret</h2>
<p>The first of these is referred to as counterfactual regret, or spending time thinking about alternative ways things could have gone. </p>
<p>When we dwell on the ways we wish things had gone, it can generate regret and sadness. Such “if only” thoughts make it difficult to accept reality and move on. </p>

<p>Not surprisingly, we engage in counterfactual regret most often when we believe our own actions led to an undesired outcome. While we might have been able to respond differently, knowing the best option in the moment is difficult. In the meantime, blaming ourselves or focusing on how we wish things had gone can result in depression, prolonged grief, and post-traumatic stress disorder. </p>

<h2>Preventive coping</h2>
<p>In the second case, we focus on trying to anticipate and prepare for possible threats. Essentially, we formulate “what if ” thoughts to avoid or manage the things that come our way. </p>
<p>To some degree, this type of preventive coping is healthy. We all know that the economy, the climate, and our life circumstances can change rapidly. Saving money for unexpected costs, planning in advance for natural disasters, and investing resources now to obtain an education, a home, or a business can pay off. </p>

<p>Research suggests that preventive coping is characteristic of people who believe in their ability to influence the future through their actions. But, maintaining constant vigilance taxes psychological, financial, and social resources and can significantly diminish our ability to enjoy the present.</p>
<h2>Proactive coping</h2>

<p>The third option, proactive coping, is based on the ability to accumulate the tangible and psychological resources necessary to deal with future challenges and facilitate personal growth.</p>
<p>Proactive copers still plan for adversity, but rather than doing so with an anxious, threat-based approach, they assume that their present efforts to accumulate resources will enable them to cope effectively when adversity occurs. Such resources include tangible goods and money, but also personal skills, social capital, and psychological resilience. Proactive copers trust their ability to solve problems as they arise, to rely on social support when appropriate, and to manage their own emotional response to stressful events. They focus on learning from the choices they have made rather than obsessing about what could have happened. Instead of seeing negative events as threats, they frame them as challenges. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>This “if it happens” mindset is based on the assumption that things won’t always go your way, but that you will rise to the occasion when you need to. Proactive coping requires confidence in your ability to look for flexible solutions to problems, honesty about the things that have and haven’t worked for you, and the belief that life is about growing and exploring, not achieving perfection.</p>


<h2>How coping styles develop</h2>
<p>Of course, our coping choices depend on the circumstances we face, how the people who raised us coped, and our temperament and personality. Likewise, the things we find stressful vary as a function of our personal values, needs, and stressors. Systemic inequities and resource imbalances can make effective coping difficult. </p>

<p>However, dealing with hardship sometimes fosters the very sorts of skills necessary to be a proactive coper. Paradoxically, people who haven’t had to struggle can sometimes become so overwhelmed by adversity that they give up rather than adjusting their expectations or their behaviors.</p>
<h2>Reframing the 'ifs'</h2>



  


<p>If you find yourself second-guessing choices you made in the past or worrying excessively about the future, it might be time to think about reassessing your coping strategies. </p>
<p>When you are prefacing all your thoughts in “if only” terms, it suggests that you are struggling to accept the reality of a situation, which makes it hard to move forward. Accepting the way things are allows us to create a vision of what we want to do in that reality. Constantly envisioning and trying to prevent future threats is exhausting, and there will always be unknown factors that are out of our control. When we dwell only on the way things could or should have gone, we deprive ourselves of the opportunity to enjoy the present. </p>

<p>Focusing on future events as challenges, not threats, takes energy, but it is worth the effort. The first step is to conduct a thought inventory. Tracking how you think about the "ifs" in your life, and when they occur, can help you see how they are influencing your decisions and whether there are alternative ways to approach the problems. Life is full of uncertainty, but managing the "ifs" in proactive ways is a strategy that can benefit us all. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mental-health-matters/202602/harnessing-the-power-of-if" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mental-health-matters/202602/harnessing-the-power-of-if</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mental-health-matters/202602/harnessing-the-power-of-if</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mary McNaughton-Cassill Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-mellamed-442447-1133742.jpg?itok=BHRTjHsX" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is a Few Minutes of Meditation Better Than More?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-02/Diane-Solomon.jpg?itok=KiLhd5fI" alt="Diane Solomon  Ph.D., PMHNP-BC, CNM" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Meditation</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Is a Few Minutes of Meditation Better Than More?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">If you’re a beginner, just a few minutes of meditation is enough.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Standard wisdom around meditation tends to prescribe 20 minutes or more per session.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A recent study shows long-time meditators use longer sessions, but beginners are best served by short bursts.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Consistency is key, but skipped days are okay, and 5 minutes several days a week might be all you need.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/by%20Handmadefont%20from%20Handmadefont.png.jpg?itok=2cJ6XA-C" width="320" height="256" data-insert-type="image" title="Handmadefont/handmadefont" alt="Handmadefont/handmadefont"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Handmadefont/handmadefont</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Over many years, I tried to meditate with a baby in my lap (not recommended), in yoga class, before getting out of bed, after getting into bed, in meditation groups, alone, and even (literally) in the closet. It never worked. I could rarely make it to 20 minutes. But even if my mind wandered like crazy, I thought I had to sit there for that full, magical meditative 20 minutes.</p>

<p>Turns out, that was the wrong approach, according to a new study published by Insight Timer (the most utilized free digital meditation app), which spins what we thought about meditation on its head (pun intended).</p>
<p>Today, it makes sense nothing worked to jumpstart my meditation practice until my kids were older (or at least toilet-trained). Then, I gave Headspace a try—a meditation app that offers ten days of free, ten-minute meditations. Even ten minutes seemed like a lot, but I could make that work. After the free trial, I was too cheap to buy in, but the meditation habit finally stuck. It’s almost ten years later, and I’m still at it.</p>

<p>Insight Timer’s study looked at meditation habits and several novel targets, showing that my experience was common. They looked at dose (how long meditators meditate), habits (meditation routines and times), and types of meditation (interoceptive, based on internal foci like the breath or body; and exteroceptive, based outwardly, like lovingkindness or mantra meditation). Between spring 2021 and summer 2022, they followed more than 10,000 volunteers from 103 countries. (As you might recall, this was a lovely time to meditate as we were often home alone in lockdown.)</p>

<p>A highlight of the study was that it was longitudinal: Instead of looking at meditators (or potential meditators) at one or two timepoints, they measured participants for over a year. And they delved into much more than a binary yes-no of meditation, including what, how, when, and so on.</p>
<p>They found that meditating with a digital app consistently offers improvements in mood, equanimity, and resilience. But we already knew that. Digital meditation apps are known to be effective. This study, however, found much more:</p>

<ul>
<li>Over the first 50-100 meditations sessions, rapid improvements in mood, equanimity, and resilience stood out, and improvements continued increasing through the end of the study.</li>
<li>Consistency was more important than minutes meditated, but “consistency” was measured as four to seven days a week—not every day.</li>
<li>Yes, longer (21-30 minute) sessions offered greatest benefits in improved mood, but 11-20-minute sessions were associated with the greatest benefits in resilience, and mood stabilization effects (a feeling of equanimity) were similar no matter what the length of the meditation session.</li>
<li>A greater variation in types of meditation—interoceptive and exteroceptive—was associated with better mood, equanimity, and resilience.</li>
<li>Morning meditation doubled the likelihood of continuing to meditate (versus evening sessions).</li>
<li>Beginners who started with 5-10-minute or 11-20-minute sessions reaped higher mood scores (up to the 20th session, when longer sessions took over in predicting better mood).</li>
</ul>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/by%20Vlada%20Karpovich%20from%20Pexels.png.jpg?itok=oIWSek6y" width="320" height="400" data-insert-type="image" title="Vlada Karpovich/Pexels" alt="Vlada Karpovich/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Vlada Karpovich/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>So how do we put this together for beginning meditators who want to make it a habit? Meditating a few times a week, consistently, is more important than length of time spent meditating. Five minutes a day (most days) is more likely to keep you meditating and accruing greater mindfulness and mood results. If one day gets away from you, don’t give up; just start again.</p>

<p>As you enjoy meditation and its benefits over time, you’ll likely want to increase session length and/or frequency. It’s self-reinforcing because it feels good.</p>
<p>And finally, mix it up: Balance interoceptive meditations where your mind sometimes takes over (“I’m not breathing right.” “Damn, my mind keeps wandering.” “This sucks, I’ll never make a good meditator!”), with external meditations, like lovingkindness, mantra, or metta sessions. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-narrative-nurse-practitioner/202512/is-a-few-minutes-of-meditation-better-than-more" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-narrative-nurse-practitioner/202512/is-a-few-minutes-of-meditation-better-than-more</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-narrative-nurse-practitioner/202512/is-a-few-minutes-of-meditation-better-than-more</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Diane N Solomon  Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/by%20Miljan%20Z%CC%8Civkovic%CC%81%20from%20Getty%20Images.png.jpg?itok=mdGjkGkP" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Raising Kids in a World That Rewards Anxiety]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/image0_1_-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=9LsLSHnF" alt="Jeffrey Bernstein Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Anxiety</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Raising Kids in a World That Rewards Anxiety</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why overthinking is becoming a developmental minefield for children and teens.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many children today are being trained to overthink.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Kids need to take sensible risks with actions, fail at times, and then prevail.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">There is a model that can help change kids' relationship with anxiety-ridden thoughts.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>My mom always encouraged me during my youth to think about time and place. She would say, "Jeff, make sure you pick the right time and place for what you say and do." Similarly, I have heard parents encourage their kids to "read the room." No doubt, in moderation, this is great advice. Thank you, Mom. </p>

<p>In a high-visibility, judgment-laden age, however, where the stakes of managing our impressions and engaging others "properly" are higher than ever due to social-media-driven scrutiny and aggression, and a more ferocious, nasty court of public opinion, parents tell kids to be even more mindful, self-aware, reflective, and careful. But then these parents scratch their heads, wondering why their kids can't power down their racing thoughts. </p>

<h2>The Truth You Don't Want to Hear</h2>
<p>Many children today aren't just anxious. They are being trained by their parents to overthink. The kid who double-checks everything is "conscientious." The one who worries over outcomes is "motivated." Similarly, the teen who can't relax about the future is "driven." </p>
<p>For example, the words, "What if my friends are just pretending they like me?" were recently uttered by a 5th-grade counseling client of mine. The mom said, "I keep telling him he has nothing to be worried about." Because our brains are wired to be on the lookout for danger, these goal-oriented kids, like this young man, are actually getting stuck in maddening threat-detection loops. Parents who blindly reassure without helping kids face the likely uncertainties of disappointments and setbacks are fueling these worry loops. </p>

<h2>Kids Frozen Stuck by Running Mental Simulations </h2>
<p>In my work with children, teens, and adult children, I noticed a concerning, easy-to-miss pattern that led me to write my recent book, <em>Freeing Your Child From Overthinking. </em>What I saw was is big-time, overthinking-driven anxiety that hides behind high grades, polite behavior, and high empathy. On the outside, these kids look great. But inwardly, their thoughts are riddled with: "What if I mess up?" "What if they think I am weird?" "What if I made the wrong choice?" "What if I can't do it?"</p>

<p>How do I know this? Because my counseling sessions are filled with children and teens stuck in those nasty "What if?" thought loops. And over time, these pressurized thoughts stop acting as tools for achievement and feel like a cage trapping these young people in a relentless pursuit of certainty in a world full of uncertainty. </p>

<h2>Parents, I Implore You to Hear This</h2>
<p>Please stop overly reassuring (and unwittingly fueling their overthinking) your child, teen, or adult child. The more your child uses overthinking to try to feel in control, the less they feel capable in real life. Confidence comes from trial-and-error learning. </p>
<p>Yes, by that I mean making mistakes. If you don't believe me, know that after 35 years as a psychologist and eight books, I still get anxious writing posts like the one you are reading. Uncertainty is scary, but being frozen in our tracks by overthinking is even scarier. Confidence is built through action, risk, and recovery, not through endless loops of mental rehearsal. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Changing Your Child's Relationship With What-Ifs</h2>
<p>We need to shift from helping kids analyze their worries to changing their relationship with their problematic, looping, anxiety-laden thoughts. That's where my PACE model comes in, which is further described in my book. <strong>PACE </strong>stands for:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>P</strong>ause the mental spinning. Gently say to your child, "Let's take a breath for a moment" or "How about you tell me about something funny that happened at school this week?"</li>
<li><strong>A</strong>cknowledge their overthinking. You could say. "That worry sounds really huge," or "I can see this is really upsetting to you." The more you help your child name it, the more they feel they can tame it because they feel less alone in it. </li>
<li><strong>C</strong>ontain by reminding your child that it is okay to have uncertainty. You might say, "It's great that you want to do well on this assignment, but would you agree that this alone will not make or break how the rest of your life turns out?"</li>
<li><strong>E</strong>ngage by encouraging your child, teen, or adult child to take one concrete step forward if they feel frozen in their tracks. You might say, "What can you do right now that feels challenging but not impossible?"</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Takeaway</h2>
<p>Our mentally exhausted, overthinking kids are not becoming confident adults because they are becoming dependent on certainty. The goal is not to get our kids to worry less by reassuring them. It is to promote them taking sensible risks through actions that lead to a life of moving forward, failing at times, prevailing, and navigating further obstacles and setbacks. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/liking-the-child-you-love/202602/raising-kids-in-a-world-that-rewards-anxiety" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/liking-the-child-you-love/202602/raising-kids-in-a-world-that-rewards-anxiety</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/liking-the-child-you-love/202602/raising-kids-in-a-world-that-rewards-anxiety</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeffrey Bernstein Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/anxious%20boy%20head%20in%20hands%20pexels-648298123-29065605.jpg?itok=fmZ1-RI6" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Some Good News for Sandwich-Generation Caregivers]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/georgia_witkin_crop-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=a5fDaPiV" alt="Georgia Witkin Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Caregiving</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Some Good News for Sandwich-Generation Caregivers</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Caring across generations has hidden benefits.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Caregiving can strengthen family bonds and build resilience across generations.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Caregiving others can boost mood, purpose, and emotional well-being.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Children gain empathy and confidence when included in caregiving.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Psych%20Today%20Images%20(3).png.jpg?itok=jzN1HJy4" width="320" height="192" data-insert-type="image" title="Jsme MILA / Pexels" alt="Jsme MILA / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Jsme MILA / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Since the term “sandwich generation” was first introduced in 1981, referring to those who were caring for young children and aging parents at the same time,<sup>1</sup> a lot has changed. In fact, you could say that the sandwich has become a double Whopper. Life expectancy has increased, so it’s often not only our young children and our parents we care for, but also grandparents and even great-grandparents who may be alive and need care. </p>

<p>Because the cost of higher education and daily life has also increased, our grown children and their children—our grandchildren—and our partners’ parents and relatives may also need our financial help and emotional support. Anxiety about holding onto jobs, therefore, has become more likely, and self-care less likely. </p>

<h2>The hidden benefits of caregiving</h2>
<p>But here’s the good news: Despite caretaker fatigue, the financial squeeze, and role-strain guilt, most of my patients tell me that all this caretaking is not having a negative effect on their psychological or physical health. Research findings suggest the same conclusion.<sup>2</sup> In fact, there seem to be many benefits resulting from all this caretaking.</p>

<ul>
<li>We are neuronally wired to help each other, so acts of altruism trigger the release of serotonin, the feel-good hormone.</li>
<li>Cross-generational caretaking can help us feel like we have repaid a debt we never thought we could repay.</li>
<li>Family connections usually become strengthened when siblings help each other care for their parents, and we feel part of a greater group.</li>
<li>Resources are generally gathered and shared, which increases our sense of control and competence.</li>
<li>Helping others along their life journeys helps us predict what may come next for ourselves as well as for those we are helping, and when our ability to predict what comes next increases, stress and anxiety typically decrease.</li>
<li>Caring for other generations can give us a sense of purpose.</li>
<li>Caretaking for the elderly can make us feel young and strong by comparison, though we're frequently tired.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Helping children share a caregiving parent</h2>
<p>The question that keeps coming up, however, is this: How do you give children what they need from you when they are sharing you not only with siblings, but also with older generations? </p>
<p>First, be aware of the dynamics that may confuse children. Although you are their primary caregiver, you may now also be a primary caregiver to your own parents, who may be equally as needy as your child or children. Reassure them that sharing you with grandparents and others who need help is as much a part of family life as sharing you with siblings. And every time they help you with chores, meals, or even caretaking, count it as time together—and help them see it that way, too.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Then emphasize what their grandparent, for example, is adding to their life rather than just taking away time with you. They may be an additional listening ear, someone who can read with them, play games, or watch special movies.</p>
<p>Encourage them to develop their own relationship with the relative who is being cared for. Task them with searching for jokes to share, drawing pictures to be pinned up, or creating a special song.</p>

<p>Show them photos of those who need caretaking now, when they were younger and taking care of you. If there are no major memory problems, have them interview their grandparent or great-grandparent about Mommy or Daddy when they were little.</p>
<p>Let the child know that they are making that older person happy. It will introduce them to altruism and empathy, and both will be reinforced by the good feelings they will have about themselves.</p>


<p>When my grandmother was living with us and being cared for by my mother, my job was to make care packages for her. I would decorate a paper bag and include candy, of course, a stuffed animal I had outgrown, and whatever else I found in the house. I loved the project, my grandmother said she loved the surprises, my mother thanked me, and the experience helped me define myself. To this day, I am in a caretaking profession.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-chronicles-of-infertility/202602/some-good-news-for-sandwich-generation-caregivers" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-chronicles-of-infertility/202602/some-good-news-for-sandwich-generation-caregivers</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-chronicles-of-infertility/202602/some-good-news-for-sandwich-generation-caregivers</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Georgia Witkin Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Psych%20Today%20Images%20%283%29.png.jpg?itok=hE1xlnw7" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2 Ways to Stop Shutting Down During Conflicts]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/photoofmarktravers.png.jpg?itok=4rcV_Py2" alt="Mark Travers Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Neuroscience</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">2 Ways to Stop Shutting Down During Conflicts</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to prevent your nervous system from collapsing under relational stress.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Shutting down during conflict is a stress response, not indifference or weakness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perceiving conflict as danger triggers shutdown.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Regulating one's physiological response to a conflict helps break the shutdown cycle.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/getty-images-8gzxhU80lAI-unsplash.jpg?itok=yWndkb5k" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Getty Images / Unsplash" alt="Getty Images / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Getty Images / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Shutting down during <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202512/why-69-percent-of-couples-conflict-will-never-go-away">conflict</a> is a habit that often gets misunderstood because it’s confused with weakness, indifference, or an avoidance tactic. In reality, however, it is usually a stress response.</p>
<p>Many people who shut down care deeply about the conversation or event that’s causing them to close up. And like the rest of us, they want connection during conflict, too. The difference is that when conflict escalates, their nervous system shifts into protection mode. Speech might become harder, their thoughts might narrow down, and overall, their body shifts to prioritize safety over communication.</p>

<p>Psychology has a clear explanation for this pattern, clarifying that shutdown is not a character flaw. It is a predictable response to emotional overload.</p>
<p>Research on attachment, stress physiology, and emotion regulation shows that people who shut down during conflict are often experiencing two repeating internal patterns. Interrupting these patterns is what allows conflict to feel survivable instead of overwhelming.</p>

<p>Here are the two most important ones to recognize and change.</p>
<h2>1. Stop Interpreting Conflict as Emotional Danger</h2>
<p>The first pattern that drives shutdown is the internal meaning assigned to conflict. For many people, disagreement does not just signal a difference of opinion; it signals an emotional threat.</p>

<p>Individuals who’ve grown up with inconsistent, critical, or emotionally intense caregivers often associate conflict with rejection, loss of connection, or emotional punishment. As a result, their adult selves respond to conflict with the urgency of someone protecting something important for their survival, even when the present situation is relatively safe.</p>

<p>This leads to rapid threat appraisal. Their inner voice might sound something like:</p>
<ul>
<li>“This is going to spiral.”</li>
<li>“I am about to be misunderstood.”</li>
<li>“Nothing I say will help.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Once the brain interprets conflict as dangerous, shutdown becomes protective. Techniques like silence, emotional withdrawal, or dissociation are then employed to reduce stimulation and limit perceived risk.<strong> </strong>Contrary to popular belief, however, the antidote to this tendency is not positive thinking; it’s accurate threat assessment.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p><a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4168764/">Research</a> on cognitive reappraisal shows that changing the meaning you’ve assigned to a stressor can also reduce the physiological arousal it might induce. So, the next time you begin to experience the onset of a shutdown, instead of asking yourself, “How do I make this stop?” the more regulating question is, “What is this conflict actually about right now?”</p>

<p>You can practice separating present reality from past emotional memory by anchoring to concrete facts:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is this person trying to harm me or trying to be understood?</li>
<li>Is this disagreement about safety or about preference?</li>
<li>Has conflict here led to rupture before or resolution?</li>
</ul>
<p>This shifts the brain out of global threat mode and into situational processing. Over time, repeatedly reinterpreting conflict as uncomfortable rather than dangerous teaches the nervous system that engagement is survivable.</p>

<h2>2. Stop Letting Physiological Flooding Dictate Behavior</h2>
<p>The second pattern is assuming that once your body is activated, communication is no longer possible. Physiological flooding involves elevated heart rate, shallow breathing, muscle tension, and narrowed attention.</p>
<p><a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7007326/">Research</a> shows that when partners are physiologically aroused due to emotional overwhelm during conflict, problem-solving and empathy decline sharply. Many people respond to this state by either forcing themselves to stay engaged or shutting down completely, and both states reinforce the problem.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The body learns that conflict leads to overwhelm, which increases the likelihood of shutdown next time. So, interrupting the habit here is not about saying the right thing; it’s more about regulating the body first.</p>
<p>Bottom-up (body-first) strategies calm the nervous system more effectively than reasoning alone during high arousal. Effective strategies include:</p>



  


<ul>
<li>Slowing the breath with longer exhales</li>
<li>Grounding attention in physical sensation</li>
<li>Briefly pausing the conversation with a clear return plan</li>
</ul>
<p>Research by relationship expert John Gottman also shows that taking a structured break of 20 to 30 minutes during flooding <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202409/the-4-strongest-predictors-of-divorce">reduces defensiveness</a> and improves repair attempts. Importantly, this is not avoidance if the pause is intentional and communicated. Saying, “I am getting flooded and need a short break so I can come back present” preserves connection while respecting physiological limits.</p>

<p>This teaches your nervous system that regulation leads back to safety and engagement, not abandonment or escalation.</p>
<h2>Why These Habits Reinforce Each Other</h2>
<p>These two patterns often operate together. When conflict is interpreted as emotionally dangerous, arousal spikes faster. When arousal spikes, shutdown feels inevitable. Over time, the brain links conflict with helplessness. Breaking this cycle requires interrupting both meaning and physiology.</p>

<p>You cannot think your way out of flooding, and you cannot regulate your body if your mind is convinced something terrible is about to happen. Addressing and understanding both is what restores choice.</p>
<p>Interrupting shutdown does not mean becoming confrontational or expressive in ways that feel unnatural. It also does not require processing everything in the moment. It simply means staying relationally available without overwhelming your nervous system.</p>

<p>Some people need time to respond. Others might need structure. Some people might even need written communication. None of these are deficits when used consciously rather than reactively.</p>
<p>The two patterns that keep you stuck in shutdown are interpreting conflict as danger and letting physiological flooding run the show. Interrupting these patterns allows your body to learn to stay present without pushing past your limits. And over time, your nervous system can learn that connection does not require collapse or withdrawal.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p><em>A version of this post also appears on Forbes.com.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/2-ways-to-stop-shutting-down-during-conflicts" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/2-ways-to-stop-shutting-down-during-conflicts</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/2-ways-to-stop-shutting-down-during-conflicts</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Travers Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/getty-images-8gzxhU80lAI-unsplash.jpg?itok=shRSlqL8" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The People Who Never Made It to the Room]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/authors/steven_hayes.jpg?itok=HwFV3hM7" alt="Steven C. Hayes Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Bias</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The People Who Never Made It to the Room</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: On perspective-taking and the doors we forgot to open.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotional acceptance helps people endure the pain of division and discrimination.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perspective-taking reveals the barriers that divide communities.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perspective-taking isn't automatic. It takes practice, humility, and willingness to feel.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-jimbear-949557.jpg?itok=g8S3QdZ-" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Jimbear / Pexels" alt="Jimbear / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Jimbear / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>A few months ago, I got a message from a therapist in Vancouver. She’d been following my work for years. She’d read the books on ACT, done the online courses, and built her entire practice around psychological flexibility and a process-based approach. But she’d never been to a live training with me.</p>
<p>“<em>I just can</em>’<em>t cross the border right now,” she wrote. </em>“<em>It doesn</em>’<em>t feel safe.”</em></p>

<p>I sat with that for a while.</p>
<p>This therapist—dedicated, trained, exactly the kind of clinician I’d want working with my family—had been cut off from a community she belonged to, not by anything she’d done, but by a shift in the weather between two countries.</p>
<p>The border hadn’t moved. She had.</p>
<p>Reading those words hurt. I felt sad. My whole life has been about building community around how to alleviate human suffering and to promote human well-being, and here we are living in a world that increasingly divides us–even communities of helping professionals.</p>

<p>My mind went to an unexpected place.</p>
<h2>Acceptance as a source of strength</h2>
<p>There was a recent study in the journal <em>Emotion</em> (Gatchpazian et al, 2026) that found that the well-being of Black people who have been subjected to racial discrimination is profoundly protected by acceptance.</p>
<p>It’s not the kind of acceptance that the common-sense meaning of the word gives you. It’s the kind of acceptance that is deep inside the mindfulness traditions, or ACT, and psychological flexibility. Acceptance in that context means an active process of being open to feeling what you feel, deeply engaging with it, and learning from it.</p>

<p>Acceptance looked at that way is not some kind of passive resignation or tolerance—as if discrimination is somehow OK and we should accept it—nor is it perseverating on how awful it is and how bad it feels. It means my feelings are valid; they are worth my attention.</p>
<p>Here was the actual item: “When experiencing discrimination, I am successful at accepting my emotions." In open-ended questions, people said it meant things like “I allowed myself to feel what I needed to."</p>

<p>But here is the awesome finding word-for-word. Yes, discrimination hurts health outcomes, but “the association between being exposed to more racial discrimination and experiencing worse health outcomes was significantly (or completely) attenuated for people who relatively successfully engaged in emotional acceptance compared to those who were relatively unsuccessful in emotional acceptance.”</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Wow. You get it?</p>
<p>This epidemic of division hurts. It hurts us all, and that feeling <em>is part of what we need to feel right now.</em></p>
<p>Moments later, my sadness turned into anger—a far more active emotion. And far more difficult for me to be open to, for deep historical and family-of-origin reasons, having seen anger-based domestic violence in my home as a young child.</p>

<p>This time, I allowed even that feeling to show up. And I thought: If she can’t come to the training, the training should come to her. Grrr. “I’m gonna do something” (as my 8-year-old self once said, after seeing more violence at home).</p>
<p>And, yes, I’m now doing an ACT workshop in Regina, Canada. </p>
<p>That same issue and energy are everywhere I look.</p>

<h2>Seeing hidden barriers to access</h2>
<p>I’ve done ACT BootCamps for years—all across the US and even in other parts of the world. They always run Thursday through Sunday. Four days—three of them long. People travel to the site on Wednesday, learn all day and into the evening Thursday, Friday, and Saturday, and then finish with a normal 8-hour day on Sunday, leaving that evening or the next day.</p>

<p>Reasonable. Efficient. And if you’re lucky, you only shut down your practice for two weekdays.</p>
<p>And quietly, unintentionally, it profoundly excludes.</p>
<p>If your Sabbath falls on Friday, Saturday, or Sunday, you’ve always been out. Orthodox Jews. Seventh-day Adventists. Christians who hold Sunday sacred. For years, without meaning to, the scheduling of professional training has sent a message to people of faith: <em>This space wasn</em>’<em>t designed with you in mind.</em></p>



  


<p>I didn’t <em>intend</em> that. Heck, I’ve worked like crazy to do ACT training programs for chaplains and pastoral counselors. I even wrote a book about it (Niewesma, Walser, &amp; Hayes, 2016), and the US military chaplains voted to train ACT (and motivational interviewing and problem-solving therapy).</p>
<p>But intention doesn’t change the effect.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>This year, for the first time, ACT BootCamp® will be running Monday through Thursday.</p>
<p>None of this was hard. I’m not asking for applause. I’m shamefacedly pointing toward my own lack of sensitivity and the need for awareness, perspective-taking, and the openness to <em>doing</em> something that can allow us to build something helpful atop the pain of division that we are now all experiencing. In that effort, psychological flexibility is a profound ally.</p>

<h2>Perspective-taking in action</h2>
<p>One of the core processes in ACT is called flexible perspective-taking—the capacity to hold your own point of view lightly enough to genuinely stand in someone else’s shoes. To ask, with real curiosity: What is the world like from where they’re standing? What do they see that I can’t see from here?</p>

<p>It sounds simple.</p>
<p>It isn’t.</p>
<p>Our minds are very good at assuming the world is basically structured around our own experience of it.</p>
<p>If we can allow perspective-taking a hand old, our own emotions can begin to be a more useful guide.</p>
<p>The research on psychological flexibility shows that the capacity to hold multiple perspectives simultaneously, and to feel what you feel when you do, is a predictor of prosocial behavior, compassion, and the ability to maintain connection under pressure. Like all skills, it requires practice, however. It does not come automatically, even for people who know the theory.</p>

<p>I could climb atop a pedestal and say I saw a need and I responded. The truth is much less flattering. The therapist in Vancouver wrote. I suspect others never did.</p>
<p>That sits uncomfortably with me.</p>
<p>It should.</p>
<p>The world right now is working very hard at building walls. Between countries. Between communities. Between people who used to work in the same rooms and now struggle to find the same ground.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>If we are going to do something about it, it is time for perspective-taking. It is time to hurt, to feel sad, to get angry. Not at <em>them</em>. At our own mindlessness and casual indifference.</p>
<p>If you’re one of the people this matters to — I’ll see you in Regina, or in New York.</p>
<p>For everyone else, I’ll leave you with this: Is there someone in your life, or your practice, or your community, who stopped trying to get through a door you had the power to open?</p>

<p><em>ACT BootCamp, New York — May 4–7, 2026 (Monday–Thursday). Process-Based ACT, Regina, Canada — May 29–30, 2026. </em><a href="https://ibh.com/events"><em>Both are open for registration at ibh.com.</em></a></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/get-out-of-your-mind/202602/the-people-who-never-made-it-to-the-room" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/get-out-of-your-mind/202602/the-people-who-never-made-it-to-the-room</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/get-out-of-your-mind/202602/the-people-who-never-made-it-to-the-room</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven C. Hayes Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-jimbear-949557.jpg?itok=sMqUqnun" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Most People Can’t Handle Their Own Company]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Aigerim%20Alpysbekova.png.jpg?itok=Hg0RHami" alt="Aigerim Alpysbekova MPH" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Authenticity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Most People Can’t Handle Their Own Company</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Choosing to be alone can be the bravest thing you do.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Letting go of relationships that no longer serve you is an exercise in emotional self-regulation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotional authenticity means allowing your internal states to guide behavior, rather than seeking approval.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Loneliness isn’t inherently negative; purposeful solitude can protect mental health and foster clarity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>It is 4 a.m., and I just want to write this.</p>
<p>My daughter told me recently during a heated conversation: “You have no one.” And it is true. No matter how painful it might feel inside, that is my raw reality. I cannot say I am 100 percent happy about it. At times, it feels lonely, but it is better to have a conversation with yourself than with someone who is not equally present emotionally or mentally, or who is just present like background noise. I am not sure what is worse.</p>

<p>When she said, “You have no one,” I thought that it would have hurt two years ago. Back then, I would have felt exposed and perhaps ashamed. But now I cannot even fully name the feeling. It is something between shock and a surrender, like, wow, it is true, but <em>let it be, so what? </em>It feels right. It is my path and my experiment with my own self.</p>

<p>My entire life, I was surrounded by many people, and I kept them the way you keep the TV on, even when you’re not watching it. Psychologically, it’s not just the number of social contacts that matters; the strength and emotional quality of those connections are what support mental health (Marinucci and colleagues, 2021).</p>

<p>One time, I asked my aunt, who is 63 years old, about her group of friends. I always felt they were not really her friends, but more of a favor-for-favor arrangement, or people to pass the time with, no matter how different their perspectives were. And she knew it. Her friends probably knew it too.</p>
<p>I asked her, “Why keep them?”</p>

<p>She said, “At this age, it is better to have social connections, a support system, and you just close your eyes to small annoying details.”</p>
<p>Maybe she is right. Maybe one day I will see it differently. But for now, keeping people around me only for safety or future support does not feel true. I am not afraid of being alone at the end of my life. The idea of living quietly in a sacred place, serving, and ending my days there has always felt peaceful to me and not depressing at all. Hopefully, I’m healthy enough to carry my own water! If that is how my life unfolds, I would accept it. At least I would know I stayed honest with myself.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/rexandros-witch-8259351_1280.jpg?itok=S4tSSbt0" width="320" height="427" data-insert-type="image" title="Pixabay/Alexander Roy " alt="Pixabay/Alexander Roy "></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pixabay/Alexander Roy</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The great lesson in life may be to let go—of anything. Material things, situations, environments, people. My logic: If you see that a particular person no longer reflects you on a deep level, if you no longer feel passion for the relationship (not only romantic ones), if you have outgrown it, if your interests are different, and all that connects you is your past, then perhaps it is the end of the relationship.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content ad--content-loaded" data-google-query-id="CKuY--3q95IDFUeDOgUdXWkt5Q">
    
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"><iframe id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0" name="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0" title="3rd party ad content" width="300" height="250" scrolling="no" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" frameborder="0" aria-label="Advertisement" tabindex="0" allow="private-state-token-redemption;attribution-reporting" data-load-complete="true" data-google-container-id="7"></iframe></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>My way is to let go and move on. Why keep someone and invest effort if the other side is not there, if they do not need or want that depth? Psychologically, letting go is an exercise in emotional self-regulation and boundary-setting, which protects mental health (Berking and Whitley, 2024)<strong>.</strong></p>
<p>How do I know I have outgrown someone, and that I am not just protecting myself from disappointment? I ask myself that often. When I notice that someone maintains relationships because it is “right” for their age, culture, children, or because one day they might need them, I sense that our motivations are different. And that means we are walking separate paths.</p>

<p>I have been holding on to some relationships because they reminded me of my past self, my child self, my high school self, my early adulthood self, without realizing that they were no longer serving either of us. If I am honest with myself, do I really need this connection, or am I holding on out of habit? I did not want to admit that the effort felt pointless, that it was not going to be received in the way I hoped.</p>

<p>I started letting go of relationships that were not meaningful to me. I cut ties with people with whom I did not feel like myself. And I ended up alone. Am I satisfied? At times, yes. It feels like the TV in the background has been shut off, and now it is only my own voice. It is uncomfortable at the beginning, but nourishing for some reason. There are no disappointments, no proving points, no need for validation or acknowledgment, no blame. Just stillness.</p>



  


<p>I used to be scared of judgment, misunderstandings, and society’s disapproval. Now I do not care. Does that sound defensive? Maybe. Even the people with whom I once shared secrets are no longer here. Have I stopped caring, or have I become tired? Maybe tired. Tired of explaining myself. Tired of adjusting where I don’t feel understood. Just tired of performing.</p>

<p>Being real means allowing myself to feel however I feel in the moment. Just honest. And I understand that not everyone will be comfortable with that. Not everyone will like that. Psychologically, this aligns with emotional authenticity, allowing internal states to guide behavior rather than suppressing them for social conformity (Ryan and colleagues, 2000). Is that okay? Can I accept that not everyone is for me? Yes. Because that is what it means to be me. Yes, we are social beings. We need connection, that’s what my mother tells me, and I agree to some extent. But there are species that can thrive in solitude. We cannot have one rule for everyone.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content ad--content-loaded" data-google-query-id="CKmY--3q95IDFUeDOgUdXWkt5Q">
    
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"><iframe id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0" name="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0" title="3rd party ad content" width="300" height="250" scrolling="no" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" frameborder="0" aria-label="Advertisement" tabindex="0" allow="private-state-token-redemption;attribution-reporting" data-load-complete="true" data-google-container-id="5"></iframe></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>It is like medical treatment: We cannot apply the same treatment to every patient. Some have allergies, some have intolerances, and some need adjusted doses. The approach must be individual. Maybe it is a phase. Maybe not. As long as it keeps me true to my real self, I am content.</p>
<p>So yes. I am alone.</p>
<p>But I am free emotionally and mentally. And I am at peace.</p>

<p>I don’t know what the next chapter holds, and I am okay with that uncertainty.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/trauma-growth-and-the-search-for-meaning/202602/why-most-people-cant-handle-their-own-company" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/trauma-growth-and-the-search-for-meaning/202602/why-most-people-cant-handle-their-own-company</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/trauma-growth-and-the-search-for-meaning/202602/why-most-people-cant-handle-their-own-company</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Aigerim Alpysbekova MPH]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/rexandros-witch-8259351_1280.jpg?itok=C2HfzEZJ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>