<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 16:05:35 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 16:05:35 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Happens When Parents Spank Their Kids]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/bctr_web_color_clear_bg_0.jpg?itok=OQGTdzGI" alt="The Bronfenbrenner Center for Translational Research" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Punishment</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What Happens When Parents Spank Their Kids</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">New evidence makes the science on physical punishment of kids clearer than ever.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A WHO report and a meta-analysis confirm that spanking has no benefits for children and carries real risks.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Spanking predicts increases in aggressive and acting-out behavior in children, even years later.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Warm, supportive parenting can buffer some of the harm, but does not fully undo the negative effects.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AdobeStock_29937976.jpeg.jpg?itok=MMtuvPjb" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="Bronwyn Photo/Adobe Stock" alt="Bronwyn Photo/Adobe Stock"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Bronwyn Photo/Adobe Stock</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Researchers estimate that up to <a href="https://preventchildabuse.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/Prevent-Child-Abuse-America-2021-Physical-Punishment-Report.pdf">40 percent of U.S. families</a> spank their children, and <a href="https://www.who.int/news/item/20-08-2025-new-report-demonstrates-that-corporal-punishment-harms-children-s-health">1.2 billion children worldwide</a> are physically punished at home. Many parents justify the behavior because they grew up being spanked. Others point to a theory that spanking is less harmful in cultures where it is widely practiced and considered socially acceptable.</p>

<p>But a wave of research published during the past year is strengthening what scientists have <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evidence-based-living/201608/what-really-happens-when-parents-spank-kids">demonstrated over the past several decades</a>: Spanking doesn’t work, and it may cause lasting harm to kids.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.who.int/news/item/20-08-2025-new-report-demonstrates-that-corporal-punishment-harms-children-s-health">The most recent comprehensive report</a> on spanking was published in 2025 by the World Health Organization. Combining evidence available globally, it found overwhelming scientific evidence that physical punishment carries multiple risks of harm and has no benefits for children, parents, or societies.</p>

<p>“We know from the vast amount of research on spanking that it simply does not work,” said Kim Kopko, a child development expert at Cornell’s Bronfenbrenner Center for Translational Research and representative for the World Organization for Early Childhood Education at the United Nations. “It is not only ineffective for correcting children’s behavior, but it is also harmful.”</p>

<p>“The United Nations Committee on the Rights of the Child views physical discipline as a violation of children’s human rights, and 65-70 countries have banned physical punishment of children in all settings, including the home and school,” she explained.</p>
<p>The WHO report analyzed data from 49 low- and middle-income countries. It found that children exposed to physical punishment are 24 percent less likely to be developmentally on track compared to peers who are not spanked. Children subjected to physical punishment face increased risks of anxiety, depression, low self-esteem, and emotional instability. The evidence shows these problems frequently persist into adulthood, leading to higher rates of anxiety, depression, and substance abuse. The problems can also lead to increased rates of contemplating a suicide attempt or dying by suicide.</p>

<p>The WHO report also found that spanking carries broader consequences as well. Children who experience it are more likely to develop aggressive behaviors, struggle academically, and, as adults, engage in violent, antisocial, or criminal conduct. The practice also fuels a broader social acceptance of violence, reinforcing harmful cycles across generations.</p>

<p>Along the same lines, <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/15248380221124243">a 2022 systematic review</a> published in the journal <em>Trauma, Violence, &amp; Abuse</em> combined data from 34 articles that evaluated the link between maternal spanking and child development. Researchers found that in 94 percent of the studies, there were significant associations between physical punishment and behavioral problems, delayed cognitive development, and poorer emotional well-being.</p>

<p>The evidence clearly shows that spanking is bad for kids. But is there anything parents can do to counteract the negative consequences? <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10826-025-03087-y">A 2025 longitudinal study</a> posed this question by following more than 2,200 low-income preschool kids enrolled in the Early Head Start program. It found that being spanked at age 5 significantly predicted higher levels of negative behaviors—including aggression, defiance, and rule-breaking—by fifth grade, even after accounting for earlier behavior problems and family factors. Study authors also asked if a warm, supportive mother offset the harm. They found that supportive parenting did appear to protect children from some of the effects of spanking, but did not fully prevent the negative outcomes.</p>

<p>Why is spanking so bad for kids? Scientists point to several mechanisms. Physically punishing a child models the use of force to solve problems. It can damage the parent-child relationship and undermine a child’s sense of safety and trust. Over time, children who are spanked don’t learn better behavior so much as they learn to fear punishment, and that fear doesn’t translate into self-regulation or cooperation once the threat is removed.</p>

<p>So, what works instead? There is clear evidence <a href="https://publications.aap.org/pediatrics/article/142/6/e20183112/37452/Effective-Discipline-to-Raise-Healthy-Children?autologincheck=redirected">that positive, non-physical discipline strategies</a>—reasoning with children, setting consistent limits, using natural consequences, and offering warmth alongside structure—are effective ways to discipline children without the negative consequences, and programs that help parents build these skills are effective.</p>



  


<p>“There are several effective discipline strategies parents can utilize, both ‘in the moment,’ when challenging behaviors arise, and proactively,” Kopko said.</p>
<p>These methods include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Time-outs</li>
<li>Loss of privileges</li>
<li>Positively reinforcing good behaviors</li>
<li>Modeling positive behavior</li>
<li>Talking with children about the connections between actions and consequences</li>
</ul>

<p>The take-home message: The evidence on spanking is not ambiguous. Across countries, cultures, and income levels, research consistently shows that physical punishment leads to worse outcomes for children. Warm and supportive parenting matters enormously, but it works best when paired with non-physical discipline.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evidence-based-living/202602/what-happens-when-parents-spank-their-kids" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evidence-based-living/202602/what-happens-when-parents-spank-their-kids</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evidence-based-living/202602/what-happens-when-parents-spank-their-kids</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[The Bronfenbrenner Center for Translational Research]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/AdobeStock_29937976.jpeg.jpg?itok=g7kkpEA-" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Legal Cases Against Social Media's Do No Harm]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/phil_reed.png.jpg?itok=BhiU99b5" alt="Phil Reed D.Phil." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Social Media</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Legal Cases Against Social Media's Do No Harm</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Assessing social media and mental health defence cases.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>Recent legal cases brought against social media companies concerning the impact of their products on mental health have provoked some significant questions and debates. Notably, these debates involve accusations of the knowing and deliberate design of an addictive device. However, a further issue of significant psychological importance is the extent to which digital usage (whether the consequence of addiction or not) is responsible for a person’s poor mental health. This question was brought to the fore by the tenor of the argument presented by Facebook’s legal team, suggesting that pre-existing mental health conditions are a more important factor than social media use.</p>

<p>The contention: Even if a person is in clear difficulty with their mental health and they have used social media a great deal, if their mental health condition was poor before the social media usage, then this somehow absolves the social media company from any responsibility. It is an argument long used by insurance companies attempting not to pay out to claimants; in this sense, it is nothing new. However, in the context of digital use, there seem to be clear flaws in this defence, which can be highlighted by some thoughts about analogies.</p>

<p><strong>Arguments Over Baseline Levels</strong></p>
<p>First, there can always be questions asked about the prior mental functioning of an individual displaying problematic behaviour. Yet, even if they did present mental health problems before engaging in social media use, it may well be that social media made that individual’s condition worse. To determine this would require longitudinal analysis of data concerning the individual’s mental health, both pre- and post-social media use, which may or may not be available. Moreover, once a condition is present, it can be irreversible, so arguments about baseline levels are not easily going to get anybody anywhere. Even with this pre- and post-data, it would always be possible to argue that their mental condition would have worsened anyway, with or without social media. This would require assessment of the impact of ‘a return to baseline’ (no social media) to determine whether mental health comes and goes as a function of social media use. That could possibly be done, but it’s difficult. Presenting the likelihood of mental health declining or improving on its own, drawn from the whole population, scientifically interesting though it is, wouldn’t help when an individual case requires specific evidence, as in court.</p>

<p>Second, the argument for the defence is somewhat perilous when looked at from the perspective of risk assessment. The defence team is saying, in effect, that ‘this person was vulnerable, so whatever happens to them is not our fault.’ However, many products do take into consideration, or at least should, to whom they are being sold. For example, guns are not sold to those with mental health problems; similarly, knives are not sold to young people, because there is a risk they will mishandle them and do harm. Perhaps of more direct relevance is that addictive substances, like alcohol and nicotine, are not sold to the vulnerable, as defined by youthfulness. It could be countered to this last example that social media is not addictive—that could be debated, of course—but it is fairly clear that knives are rarely addictive, and they are restricted based on considerations of vulnerability. Finally, it just seems morally questionable to blame the vulnerable for their own calamities, but, of course, defence lawyers often do this.</p>

<p>Third, even if the person is vulnerable in terms of having pre-existing mental health difficulties, would this be an argument that is accepted in defence of the heroin pusher, or the dodgy knife salesperson? To misquote Jane Austin, it is a truth universally accepted that a person with a mental health difficulty is in want of a substance of abuse. Perhaps not quite, but it is certainly the case that many substance misusers, and those with habits and addictions, do have mental health problems. For many who become involved in either substance misuse or process addictions— like gambling, shopping, or social media—the substance or activity is reinforced due to the escape or avoidance it provides from the pre-existing problem. Thus, saying the person was mad before they bought the heroin, or the alcohol, or the knife, is not really a defence; it may predispose to an action, but the brittleness of the glass does not cause the shattering in the way that the person who drops it causes the shattering. Rather, this suggestion of pre-existing vulnerability would tend to exacerbate the guilt of the pusher, or salesperson, or social media company (you know to handle fragile glass carefully).</p>

<p><strong>The Responsibility of the Provider</strong></p>
<p>The question then becomes, did the substance or activity help the person, or not? Perhaps there are some cases where addictions have helped; however, these individuals do not usually turn around and cry foul. The fact that these sorts of individuals exist does not, of course, lessen the responsibility of the provider in the other cases where it did not help. The fact that some people become successful carnival knife throwers, as a result of a knife addiction, facilitated by easy access to sharps, does not mitigate the responsibility of the person who illegally sold a knife to a subsequently rampaging 10-year-old.</p>

<p>Thus, the question boils down to this: In cases of harm, should the social media developer have known that their product can harm some people (not cause addictions per se), and did they take steps to obviate that harm? Of course, answering the question will need evidence that the mental state has worsened, and that it worsened because of social media use, which is tricky. However, the previous mental states of the individual, and or the mechanism of action of the device (overuse, habit, addiction), seem quite irrelevant, and these arguments are just distractions. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/digital-world-real-world/202602/the-legal-cases-against-social-medias-do-no-harm" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/digital-world-real-world/202602/the-legal-cases-against-social-medias-do-no-harm</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/digital-world-real-world/202602/the-legal-cases-against-social-medias-do-no-harm</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Reed D.Phil.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-ekaterina-bolovtsova-6077181.jpg?itok=ncxaDerf" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Debugging Overconfidence: Is AI Too Sure of Itself?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/alain-samson_1.jpg?itok=hql9fsaI" alt="Alain Samson Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Debugging Overconfidence: Is AI Too Sure of Itself?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How a characteristically human bias shows up in today’s large language models.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">AI inherits human cognitive biases through training data, model assumptions, and user feedback loops.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Overconfidence, a characteristically human metacognitive bias, increasingly appears in LLM outputs.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Both LLMs themselves and users tend to overestimate the correctness of LLMs' answers.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mitigation requires both developer strategies and user vigilance.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>With the rising popularity of AI, particularly Large Language Models (LLMs), there has been a lot of talk about bias. Since AI is made by humans, our cognitive shortcomings can easily creep into AI technology. When training data become biased in input selection, measurement, or labeling processes, algorithms and outputs <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.modpat.2024.100686">will be biased</a>, too. Frequently mentioned areas in which biases occur include demographics (e.g., gender stereotypes or underrepresentation of minorities) and culture (e.g., Western-centric norms). When it comes to users' perceptions of AI, the concern of <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s43681-024-00419-4">anthropomorphic bias</a> has also become an important area of discussion. This bias arises because humans interact with AI (e.g., Chat GPT) as if it were a human being. AI, in turn, learns to play to those expectations. </p>

<p>There are other biases in human thinking that may not be highlighted sufficiently with respect to AI algorithms. Take one of the most ubiquitous human biases: overconfidence, an excessive belief in one’s own abilities, as evident in gaps between perceived and actual performance. I’ve written about it in relation to <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/consumed/202403/the-benefit-of-the-doubt-do-experts-know-their-unknowns">expert judgments</a>, <a href="https://www.advisorperspectives.com/articles/2018/08/13/overconfidence-the-dark-side-of-risk-tolerance">financial risk tolerance</a>, and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/consumed/201306/underoverconfidence-its-all-about-the-mindset">gender differences</a>, to mention just a few.</p>

<p>We don’t usually think of machines in terms of metacognitive biases because these distortions entail self-reflection or self-judgment. But biases like overconfidence are highly relevant, because AI simulates human thought and is built by humans. Overconfidence can affect AI products like LLMs at both the development and user feedback stages.</p>

<p>At the <a href="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2025.findings-acl.1316">development stage</a>, data is used to train an AI model. Developers may be overconfident in their selection of data (e.g., favoring confident statements in news articles that make definitive predictions), interpretation of data (e.g., labeling an image as representing a cat when it could be another animal), or model building (e.g., avoiding uncertainty by producing single answers rather than probabilities).</p>

<p>Indeed, the architecture of AI itself fosters <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/coli_a_00530">overgeneralizations</a>. These are often presented with language that signals certainty. For example, I recently used ChatGPT to diagnose a technical issue at home and described the malfunctioning product as “a few months” old, which the LLM subsequently labeled as “brand new.” In addition, “seeing” patterns where none exist and completing patterns based on probability can also produce the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3728894">LLM hallucinations</a> you may have encountered. Overconfident LLMs produce wrong answers (such as incorrect math or <a href="https://medium.com/@nirdiamant21/llm-hallucinations-explained-8c76cdd82532">false attributions</a>), which are then confidently communicated to users.</p>

<p>The problem of overconfidence has been an important topic in the AI industry and academic literature, often with a focus on the gap between an LLM’s <a href="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2025.acl-long.1184">expressed certainty and its actual accuracy</a>. One study prompted five LLMs to answer 10,000 questions they knew the true answer to. The researchers then asked for the LLMs’ confidence in their answers ("What is the probability that your answer is correct?”) and found that LLMs at the time <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2505.02151">overestimated</a> the correctness of their answers between 20 percent (for GPT o1) and 60 percent (for GPT 3.5).</p>

<p>Researchers have attempted to calibrate LLMs and their accuracy or reduce overconfidence in numerous ways, including those resembling debiasing techniques applied to human overconfidence. One example is to use a multiple-choice question format with the correct answer alongside credible answers as <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2502.11028">distractors</a>, which is similar to asking overconfident individuals to “consider alternative answers” as they think about an answer.</p>

<p>AI overconfidence can be both transferred and amplified further at a second stage, which involves user interaction and feedback. This is where so-called <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2310.06452">RLHF (Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback)</a> comes into play. As anthropomorphic bias suggests, we tend to perceive AI as human. And as humans, we prefer certainty over ambiguity and confidence over doubt. We may overestimate the capabilities of intelligent machines and subconsciously associate confidence with authority. Users are more likely to “upvote” LLMs’ confident answers. They are less likely to challenge answers that are expressed with greater authority. Perhaps not surprisingly, research shows that users also tend to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13040-026-00518-4">overestimate the accuracy of LLMs</a>.</p>

<p>Thus, AI architects and developers have to battle accuracy on several fronts in order to mitigate overconfidence: the accuracy of information generated by the LLM, the accuracy of the LLM’s “self-perceived” knowledge, and the accuracy of user perceptions of LLMs’ actual answers. At the same time, users have to be aware of AI’s shortcomings and <a href="https://youtu.be/Ut9aXhRamL0?si=slgU4-XgB33o6n-y">ensure that they get the most accurate and reliable information</a> out of LLMs. This may involve cross-checking answers between LLMs or verifying answers with non-AI sources, as well as prompting AI to be explicit about uncertainties, show how it arrived at an answer, rate its own confidence across answer options, or take on different “adversarial” personas to stress-test answers. </p>



  


<p>Without mitigation processes as a safeguard, and as AI output is increasingly used to train new AI, there is a growing risk of a third stage, where biases like overconfidence emerge as a system-level property.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/consumed/202602/debugging-overconfidence-is-ai-too-sure-of-itself" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/consumed/202602/debugging-overconfidence-is-ai-too-sure-of-itself</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/consumed/202602/debugging-overconfidence-is-ai-too-sure-of-itself</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Alain Samson Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Overconfident%20robot.png.jpg?itok=BrBrcmMq" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Ways to Overcome the Habit of Over-Explaining]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/photoofmarktravers.png.jpg?itok=4rcV_Py2" alt="Mark Travers Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Self-Esteem</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Ways to Overcome the Habit of Over-Explaining</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to stop using the interpretations of others as a measure of self-worth.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/sophia-richards-_1_KUUzrX4g-unsplash.jpg?itok=RNM_f30A" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Sophia Richards / Unsplash" alt="Sophia Richards / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Sophia Richards / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>If you identify as a serial over-explainer, there are two things you should know: first, that you’re not alone. An over-explaining habit is one of the most common protective strategies people use while communicating. And second, this <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202512/3-ways-to-use-your-overthinking-habit-for-good">protective habit</a> might be secretly harming your self-esteem.</p>
<p>Here’s what’s happening behind the scenes when you feel the urge to over-explain to someone: your mind—while anticipating misunderstanding, conflict, or rejection—is trying to preemptively manage reactions by offering more context than the situation requires. The problem is that this habit, over time, quietly chips away at self-trust, boundaries, and perceived confidence.</p>

<p>If you are also trapped in this pattern, the aim is not to be blunt or emotionally detached. It is to become more accurate, firm, and respectful of yourself in the way you communicate. Here are three behaviors you should stop immediately, and what to practice instead.</p>
<h2>1. Stop Habitually Defending Your Boundaries</h2>

<p>Contemporary models of assertiveness no longer view boundary-setting as a single social skill; instead, it’s now being viewed as a broader form of psychological agency.</p>
<p>Recent theoretical <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2025.1610807/full">research</a> describes assertiveness as operating across social, behavioral, emotional, and mental domains, ranging from the ability to speak up, the capacity to act, the willingness to trust one’s emotional experience, and accept reality without excessive self-protection.</p>

<p>When this multidimensional sense of agency is weak, people struggle to believe that they have the right to say “no.”</p>
<p>In these contexts, explanation becomes a substitute for authority. Rather than experiencing a boundary as a legitimate expression of need, individuals experience it as a request that must be justified. While “no” could be a sentence in and of itself, over-explainers cannot control their urge to supply logic to compensate for low perceived relational power.</p>

<p>For example, an over-explainer might say, “I can’t come because I’m exhausted, and I had a really long week, and I have a lot of work tomorrow,” even for a leave of absence they were completely entitled to.</p>
<p>When viewed from this perspective, over-explaining no longer looks like a communication flaw. Instead, it reveals itself as a compensatory strategy for diminished assertive agency. The fewer internal permissions you have, the more external reasons you feel compelled to provide. To strengthen a boundary, you need to take ownership of your feelings.</p>

<h2>2. Stop Habitually Explaining Your Intentions</h2>
<p>The nature of anticipatory clarification is that you end up explaining yourself before anyone has questioned you. This often sounds like:</p>
<ul>
<li>“I’m not saying this to criticize you, but…”</li>
<li>“I don’t mean this in a bad way, I just…”</li>
<li>“I might be wrong, but…”</li>
</ul>
<p>This tendency reflects heightened threat sensitivity in social evaluation. The brain, anticipating misinterpretation, attempts to inoculate the message against negative judgment before it is even delivered. Ironically, this often weakens communication.</p>

<p>A 2025 <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC12401852/">study</a> on social evaluation of written communication shows that hedging language consistently lowers perceived competence and professionalism, particularly for speakers in positions of authority. In contrast, direct, unmodified statements are judged as more competent, while added softeners rarely increase credibility. The more you qualify, the less weight your message tends to carry.</p>


<p>Repeated over-explaning primes you to experience your own thoughts as potentially problematic, requiring constant disclaimers rather than confident expression. Here’s what you need to train yourself in instead:</p>
<ul>
<li>Trust the clarity of your message</li>
<li>Say it</li>
<li>Let it land</li>
</ul>
<p>If a misunderstanding arises, you can clarify. But you do not need to apologize for having a perspective. Confidence is not the absence of nuance, but it is the absence of unnecessary self-doubt in delivery.</p>

<h2>3. Stop Habitually Over-Justifying Your Reactions</h2>
<p>"I know I shouldn’t feel this way, but…” “It’s probably silly, but it really upset me because...” These phrases are not uncommon among over-explainers. This pattern usually suggests that the person has internalized emotional invalidation and has built the habit of minimizing their own feelings in advance to make them more acceptable to others.</p>



  


<p>Recent <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10615806.2022.2033973">research</a> shows that individuals who perceive themselves as emotionally invalidated experience lower positive affect across the day, heightened negative affect in social situations (especially with people who are not too close), and greater stress reactivity. Invalidation does not remain a social experience; it is also a larger, and often more impactful, internal event. This means that it can reshape how you will feel emotions and interpret your life.</p>

<p>From a developmental lens, this tendency spawns in environments where emotional expression is met with dismissal, rationalization, or critique. Over time, the individual learns that feelings are not sufficient on their own. They must be supported with evidence if they have to be understood. In reality, as we know, it’s our emotions that dominate our existence. There is always a feeling of upholding your thoughts. You feel first, and you reason second. In moments where you feel pressured to defend your emotions, you train yourself to doubt the very signals your nervous system is designed to provide.</p>

<p>As a result of this compulsion, conversations about feelings may no longer lead to “understanding.” Instead, they’re often turned into a game of persuasion. The listener becomes an evaluator, and the over-explainer an advocate for their own legitimacy.</p>
<p>To counteract this habit, try naming the feeling without litigating it. Don’t hesitate to say aloud things like:</p>

<ul>
<li>“I felt hurt.”</li>
<li>“That made me anxious.”</li>
<li>“I was disappointed by that.”</li>
</ul>
<p>You can add context later, if needed. But try to begin with ownership and not apology. Over time, you may internalize that emotional clarity is not fragility; it is a sign of psychological maturity.</p>
<p><em>A version of this post also appears on Forbes.com.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-ways-to-overcome-the-habit-of-over-explaining" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-ways-to-overcome-the-habit-of-over-explaining</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-ways-to-overcome-the-habit-of-over-explaining</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Travers Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/sophia-richards-_1_KUUzrX4g-unsplash.jpg?itok=ufcqddAZ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We Need to Talk About the Fenfluramine Study]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/rupi-legha.jpg?itok=oxD6GCPU" alt="Rupinder K. Legha M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychiatry</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">We Need to Talk About the Fenfluramine Study</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Child psychiatry has not reckoned with one of its worst research abuses.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In the 1990s, researchers injected 34 Black and Brown boys with a banned drug to study their violence risk.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The boys were selected by race by design. White children were explicitly excluded from participation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The NIMH investigated and found no wrongdoing. Researchers were never sanctioned. Careers flourished.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Training did not teach me this: What's missing from psychiatric training is as important as what's taught.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">When I graduated from my child psychiatry fellowship training in 2018, I felt qualified to provide quality mental healthcare to children. I had trained at a nationally recognized program and successfully passed my board certification exam.</p>
<p dir="ltr">And then I learned about the fenfluramine study. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Not during my formal training or as part of board certification prep. I learned about it the way I’ve learned most of what I know about psychiatry’s racist history—on my own, through resources well outside of my profession.</p>

<p dir="ltr">I first saw it referenced in Ibram X. Kendi’s landmark book <em>Stamped from the Beginning</em>, which cited Harriet Washington’s <em>Medical Apartheid</em>, where I read about it in greater depth. </p>
<p dir="ltr">I felt ashamed that as a prescriber of psychotropic medication for children, I had not been required to learn about it, much less take responsibility for it.</p>

<h2>What Happened</h2>
<p dir="ltr">In the mid-1990s, child mental health researchers at top New York institutions injected grade-school boys with fenfluramine, also known as the diet drug “fen-fen,” a substance that was later banned by the Food and Drug Administration, due to its links to valvular heart disease and pulmonary hypertension. </p>

<p dir="ltr">The boys were all Black or Hispanic by design: Eligible participants were required to be African American or Hispanic because they were deemed to be at higher risk for developing disruptive behaviors. They fasted for 18 hours and had a catheter in their arm for six hours while being injected with a drug later pulled from the market.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The study explored whether serotonin levels were correlated with other possible indicators of risk status, such as adverse rearing practices, antisocial family environments, parental or sibling aggression, or increasing displays of aggressive behavior.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The families received less than $200 for the procedures, and their risk was minimized in the informed consent paperwork. The recruitment letter told parents that researchers wanted to learn “what keeps children out of trouble”—the opposite of what they were actually studying.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Prominent contemporaries, like Harvard child psychiatrist Alvin Poussaint, described the recruitment letter as “sugarcoated” and “misleading.” </p>
<p dir="ltr">These nontherapeutic experiments were conducted on 34 boys, between the ages of 6 and 10, who were younger brothers of convicted delinquents. The researchers breached the confidentiality of juvenile court records to identify the boys.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In December 1997, Disability Advocates lodged an official complaint against the study on behalf of the children and families affected.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The controversy was covered extensively in the press. <a href="https://www.villagevoice.com/half-truths-and-consequences/">Mark Schoofs’ 1998 <em>Village Voice</em> investigation</a> contended that the researchers had deliberately obscured the study’s true purpose from parents. </p>


<p dir="ltr">The NIMH investigated and found no wrongdoing. The researchers and institutions denied wrongdoing and were never sanctioned. Their findings were published in <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9294375/">top journals</a>. </p>
<h2>The World These Boys Were Living In</h2>
<p dir="ltr">One of the most alarming aspects of this study for me is that the researchers were focused on studying the violence risk of these children while perpetrating a form of violence against them (through the nontherapeutic administration of fenfluramine and the extrajudicial use of their brothers’ court records). </p>

<p dir="ltr">Another is that they were not interested in assessing the structural sources of violence, like poverty and racism, criminalizing and traumatizing Black and Latinx youth like them nationwide.</p>
<p dir="ltr">All of this was happening during the era of the Exonerated Five, five children wrongfully convicted and later acquitted of sexually assaulting a White woman in Central Park. </p>



  


<p dir="ltr">This was the height of the War on Drugs, when racialized myths of superpredators were being leveraged to justify tough-on-crime approaches that disproportionately policed and incarcerated the communities these boys came from.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Instead of interrogating structural violence, researchers searched for biological markers in Black boys’ bodies.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Where was the desire to protect them?</p>
<h2>This Is the Pattern, Not the Aberration</h2>
<p dir="ltr">It was, perhaps, muted by the mental health profession’s broader historical pattern of pathologizing racially minoritized people’s survival and resistance to racial violence.</p>
<p dir="ltr">For drapetomania—or runaway slave syndrome–during slavery, the recommended treatment was whipping. During the Civil Rights Movement, psychiatrists labeled Black men championing their human rights with a “protest psychosis” diagnosis. </p>

<p dir="ltr">In both cases, more humane alternatives—like abolishing slavery or ending apartheid—were disregarded. Psychiatrists squarely located pathology in the minds and bodies of those who struggled against oppression, even though their resistance ultimately secured broader civil rights.</p>
<p dir="ltr">More recently, disruptive behavior diagnoses, like oppositional defiant disorder, have been overdiagnosed in Black, Latine, and Indigenous children. Practice parameters do not require providers to account for the structural racism these children face.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The fenfluramine study perpetuates this legacy: the normalization of racial oppression, the pathologizing of resistance, and behavioral control as intervention rather than advocacy against racial violence. </p>
<p dir="ltr">The study used dangerous drugs, relied on scientific racism about the heritability of “violence,” and treated marginalized kids as expendable research subjects, infringing upon ethical standards of consent, safety, and respect.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The study cannot be separated from the broader history of forced medical experimentation on Black and Brown bodies. The Tuskegee Study of Untreated Syphilis in the Negro Male (1932-1972) is often held up as the most disturbing exemplar of this legacy. The fenfluramine study, which transpired only a few decades ago—and was directed at children–is part of a broader arc that also includes forced sterilizations on tens of thousands of racially minoritized women.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article_inline_full">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_full_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_full_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Tuskegee_syphilis_experiment_venipuncture.jpg?itok=Z8mKrqzi" width="600" height="440" data-insert-type="image" alt=" An African American male is tested and treated during the Tuskegee Study of Untreated Syphilis in the Negro Male. According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the study began in 1932 as U.S. Public Health Service medical personnel conducted these tests without the benefit of patients’ informed consent. (Courtesy photo from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention/Released)" title="Wikimedia Commons, Public Domain Image"></div>
<div class="caption">An African American male is tested and treated during the Tuskegee Study of Untreated Syphilis in the Negro Male. According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the study began in 1932 as U.S. Public Health Service medical personnel conducted these tests without the benefit of patients’ informed consent. (Courtesy photo from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention/Released)</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Wikimedia Commons, Public Domain Image</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Why This Matters Now</h2>
<p dir="ltr">To prescribe psychotropic drugs to children safely, I was trained to check certain labs, verify the medical history, and follow established guidelines regarding dosing, side effects, and discontinuation. Medication management was upheld as objective, protocol, and neat.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Nowhere was I trained to prescribe with critique: to analyze how psychiatry can function as social control under the banner of care. </p>

<p dir="ltr">This is especially true for kids in settings where freedom is curtailed: juvenile detention, foster care, group homes, and inpatient psychiatric facilities. The most vulnerable children are often the most medicated. And they are often racially minoritized.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That I—a board-certified child psychiatrist with a specific focus on racism and antiracism in healthcare—did not learn about it during my fellowship training raises serious concerns. What’s missing from psychiatric training is as important as what’s taught. </p>

<p dir="ltr">I am disappointed that child psychiatry has not reckoned with this research abuse nor offered any atonement. </p>
<p dir="ltr">This study should be taught to all child psychiatrists. The institutions that conducted this research, whose researchers built distinguished academic careers, should be held accountable.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The critique came from outside the profession—from public advocacy groups, legal advocates, and community members who organized and spoke out. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Silence in the face of this history teaches its repetition.</p>
<p dir="ltr">It is time for our profession to stop being quiet.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/protective-care/202602/we-need-to-talk-about-the-fenfluramine-study" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/protective-care/202602/we-need-to-talk-about-the-fenfluramine-study</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/protective-care/202602/we-need-to-talk-about-the-fenfluramine-study</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rupinder K. Legha M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Tuskegee_syphilis_experiment_venipuncture.jpg?itok=mt5QLejU" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>