<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 22:35:58 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 22:35:58 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Perfectionists Don't Ever Believe You're Trying Your Best]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-05/Leon-Garber.jpg?itok=SCVGgFWd" alt="Leon Garber LMHC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Perfectionism</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Perfectionists Don't Ever Believe You're Trying Your Best</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Pleasing a perfectionist is impossible.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">While most believe people are trying their best, perfectionists tend to believe they can always do better.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Socially-prescribed perfectionists tend to try to meet others' excessive demands to prove they're special.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Addressing one's philosophy of others may help reveal internal emotional struggles.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>There are two general philosophies most of us have about others. On the one hand, many, if not most, believe that others are trying their best, usually if not always. These individuals don’t presume to know the hardships other people are experiencing but believe in their core goodness. So, they don’t need to know specifically what someone is struggling with to give them grace. </p>

<p>On the other hand, some, if not a select few, believe that you should always try your best. The distinction is meaningful. The second perspective implies a directive because accompanying it is the belief that others aren’t always trying their best and, in fact, usually aren’t.</p>
<h2>The demands of perfectionism</h2>

<p>Other-oriented perfectionists, those who hold others to extremely high standards, tend to view people as lazy, hypocritical, and dependent in comparison to themselves, who they view as diligent, rational, and independent. Their disdain is expressed through comments like, “You can always do better,” and “But did you really try your best?” </p>

<p>So, you may be damned if you do and damned if you don’t. If you admit that you didn’t perform as well as you could have, then you’re branded as lazy. And if you defend yourself, maintaining you did, you’ll be criticized for lacking insight, if not outright deception: “But you can always do better.” Fundamentally, the latter comment means you shouldn’t expect praise, ever, as perfection, whatever that is, remains unknown.</p>

<p>Therefore, socially-prescribed perfectionists—those who believe others hold them to extremely high standards and thus always try to meet them—continue to pine for recognition in a dizzying dance. The other-oriented perfectionists use these argumentative tricks to keep you hungry for approval, in the same way they may treat themselves when they aren’t comparing themselves to someone they believe to be inferior. </p>

<p>Differentiating between these two philosophies is important because it gets to the heart of how someone sees you, which starts to feel less personal when you discontinue believing you can become special to them, to stand apart from their apparently observant insights. All of us make this mistake at some point, whether with a demanding parent, partner, or even, as in my case, patient. We wish to be the exceptions because, at bottom, we hold the same perspective, even if feeling guilty for having it.</p>

<h2>How perfectionism shapes relationships</h2>
<p>When a patient says, “Well, you don’t really care about me,” some therapists rush to challenge them, listing every way they’ve tried to help. And, in a magical sort of way, they try to become King Arthur, saving the majestic sword of hope from crystalized cynicism. </p>


<p>A more interesting response may be, “How often do you assume others aren’t trying their best? How often do you think your sense of being more thoughtful and selfless, if not smarter too, alienates them?” Some perfectionists even discover that others, in a self-fulfilling way, don’t try their best since they’ve given up, recognizing the distance between them and gratitude. This is the epitome of a self-fulfilling prophecy.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>For another perfectionist, who’s already bought into the philosophy that they can and should be special, exploitation becomes inevitable. And reorienting oneself to seeing the actual problem, perfectionism, is difficult because of how true their sense of the world feels. But, to mitigate the sorrow of internalized shame, the socially-prescribed perfectionist, who’s on the fence about whether or not the demands are reasonable, is implored to conclude how they ought to see the world. Is it divided between winners and losers? Are most people actually lazy? Would you charge your own friends with the crime of not trying their best if they appeared to be struggling?</p>



  


<h2>Challenging cynicism and rigid standards</h2>
<p>Other-oriented perfectionism is a bottomless pit. The other-oriented perfectionist is implored to challenge their world-view. Is it possible that your cynicism is rooted in shame, projected onto others to feel important? And how would you know if others are or aren’t trying their best? Do you know of their struggles or what is and isn’t possible for them? </p>

<p>Other-oriented perfectionists struggle with differentiating between equality and equity. Yes, they may treat everyone fairly, in that they hold everyone to impossible, ever-growing standards; but, they can’t seem to empathize with their needs and, more importantly, their limitations. I often ask these individuals questions beginning with, “How would you know…” Generally, the lack of humility supports both grandiosity and ignorance. Therefore, the other-oriented perfectionist is asked to seriously consider that they may be oversimplifying the assumptions of their expectations; that it may still be their responsibility to learn what others are and aren’t capable of, while accepting that none of us ever truly know, despite our accumulated wisdom.</p>

<p>These philosophies are estimations due to that fact. Whether most people are stupid, lazy, hardworking, or thoughtful is basically unanswerable. But, I’m not saying we have to leave it up to faith, either. Challenging your cynicism implies the need for constant refinement and specificity; it may even mean having a general perspective, based on prior experience, but allowing yourself to remain open to correction. Both the self-oriented and other-oriented perfectionists would be better served if, rather than fixating on their beliefs, they set them aside to learn others’ experiences. Or at least accept that if others can always be doing better, that means, by extension, you’ll never be satisfied with any of them.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/perfectionists-dont-ever-believe-youre-trying-your-best" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/perfectionists-dont-ever-believe-youre-trying-your-best</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/perfectionists-dont-ever-believe-youre-trying-your-best</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Leon Garber LMHC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/mohamed_hassan-noise-10046486_1920.png.jpg?itok=5xdbyGqV" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Architecture of Identity: How the Brain Builds a Self]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/1761172841497-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=psO-sgMZ" alt="Elizabeth Mateer Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Memory</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Architecture of Identity: How the Brain Builds a Self</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why what we remember becomes who we are.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Identity is shaped by repeated patterns of attention and memory.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotionally salient events are encoded and retrieved more easily.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Repeated recall strengthens neural pathways and stabilizes self-narratives.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Neuroplasticity allows reinforced identity patterns to be reshaped.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/nick-fancher-e8Jy-IhGT58-unsplash%20crop.jpg?itok=_n4TxZ4H" width="320" height="181" data-insert-type="image" title="Nick Fancher / Unsplash" alt="Nick Fancher / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Nick Fancher / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">There is a popular idea that you must “find” yourself. As if you are somewhere outside, waiting to be found. But how can you be lost if you are reading this? </p>
<p dir="ltr">If you’ve ever struggled with lack of direction, wondering what you should do with your life, perhaps achieving a goal and realizing it wasn't what you thought it would be, or had an existential crisis, the idea of “finding yourself” has likely crossed your mind. Probably creating more stress than clarity, as “finding yourself” is about as vague as searching for buried treasure from a hand-drawn map. And yet, it feels necessary to move forward with confidence. </p>

<p dir="ltr">But emerging research in cognitive neuroscience suggests something different: The self is not found, it is built — and the architecture is already present in our cognitive systems and how we apply them. </p>
<h2>Attention Is the Gatekeeper of Identity</h2>
<p dir="ltr">We cannot talk about any cognitive domain without first focusing on attention. Attention is the brain’s filtering mechanism; what passes through that filter is what gets encoded. What gets encoded becomes memory. And memory is the raw material of identity.</p>

<p dir="ltr">So in the architecture of your identity, attention is the doorway. </p>
<h2>What We Repeatedly Remember Becomes What Feels Real</h2>
<p dir="ltr">An often forgotten aspect of memory is that it is not a fixed record but rather, a dynamic archive. Studies suggest that emotionally charged experiences are prioritized during encoding and tend to be retrieved more readily than neutral ones, a phenomenon researchers call emotional memory enhancement (Peris-Yague et al., 2024; Koevoet et al., 2024). The emotional salience of a memory can impact how it is encoded, and can also modify the memory upon retrieval. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Imagine you are back in high school and raise your hand to answer a question. You stumble over your words. A few students laugh quietly. The teacher corrects you and moves on. At that moment, you feel embarrassed. But the class eventually ends, the day continues, and life moves forward.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Years later, when describing yourself, you say, “I’m just not someone who speaks up. I’m not good under pressure.”</p>

<p dir="ltr">What you may not realize is that this conclusion is built from selective retrieval.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The original moment encoded with emotional salience: embarrassment heightens memory consolidation. Because the memory is emotionally charged, it is easier to retrieve. And each time you enter a situation that involves public speaking, your brain retrieves that prior experience as evidence.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">With each retrieval, the neural pathway strengthens. The memory reconsolidates not as “one awkward moment,” but as proof of a trait. This reflects what memory researchers call reconsolidation—the process by which a memory is briefly destabilized upon retrieval and then re-encoded, sometimes with subtle modifications (Ecker, 2024). Each recall is, in a small way, a rewrite.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Over time, the reinforced memory shifts from event to identity:</p>
<p dir="ltr">“I stumbled once” becomes “I’m not articulate.”<br>“A few people laughed” becomes “I’m not confident.”<br>A single episode becomes architecture.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The archive has not changed in content, but its weight within the system has. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Each time we recall a memory, we reinforce it. Neural pathways become more efficient with use. Over time, the themes we retrieve most frequently—failure, resilience, belonging, inadequacy, competence—become the dominant threads in the story of the self.</p>

<p dir="ltr">This is where memory is essential to identity formation. The self is assembled not from everything that has happened to us, but from what the brain has chosen to preserve and retrieve. </p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/getty-images-5Zu4gaFCA5w-unsplash_0.jpg?itok=cl6S_4NW" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Getty Images / Unsplash" alt="Getty Images / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Getty Images / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Neuroplasticity and Cognitive Flexibility</h2>
<p dir="ltr">There is good news: Our brains are neuroplastic, and we can alter those automatic pathways. Neuroplasticity, the brain's capacity to reorganize itself through experience, is now understood to persist well into adulthood, meaning the patterns built over a lifetime are not permanently fixed (Bhatt et al., 2025).</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">Cognitive flexibility—the capacity to shift perspective, update interpretations, and inhibit automatic responses—allows the archive to be recontextualized. Without flexibility, reinforced memory patterns harden into rigid identity conclusions. With flexibility, the same archive can be reorganized.</p>
<h2>Where Neuroscience and Psychology Meet</h2>



  


<p dir="ltr">While neuroscientists study memory and attention, the connection to identity is where cognitive science and psychology meet. These principles are not designed with identity in mind, but the parallels are hard to ignore. </p>
<p dir="ltr">If identity is constructed through reinforced patterns of attention and retrieval, then it is both more stable, and more malleable, than we tend to believe.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><em>Stable</em>, because repetition creates efficiency. The brain favors what is familiar. Retrieval strengthens pathways. Over time, certain narratives about ourselves become neurologically elevated. They feel automatic, obvious, and true. But also <em>malleable</em>, because efficiency is not permanence.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The same systems that reinforce identity also allow it to evolve. When attention shifts, encoding also shifts. When new experiences are revisited deliberately (not just the most emotionally charged ones) the archive reorganizes. Cognitive flexibility allows previously dominant memories to lose their weight, while new patterns gain strength.</p>

<p dir="ltr">This reframes how we think about growth.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Growth is not the discovery of a hidden, authentic self buried beneath layers of confusion. It is the gradual reshaping of retrieval patterns. It is the cultivation of attention toward different experiences. It is the decision to reinforce different evidence. Autobiographical memory researchers have long noted that the stories we repeatedly tell about ourselves shape self-concept over time, and that those stories can be consciously revised (Conway, 2005).</p>

<p dir="ltr">Identity, then, is not a fixed essence but a stabilized pattern—and patterns, while powerful, can change.</p>
<h2>Building Your Identity</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Identity is less essence and more pattern. It emerges from what we attend to, what we encode, and what we repeatedly retrieve. Over time, certain memories become neurologically efficient, certain interpretations become automatic, and certain narratives become dominant. The self begins to feel stable as its patterns are reinforced. What feels like “who I am” is often the result of what has been most consistently activated.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">What feels fixed today may simply be what has been most reinforced. However, what is reinforced can, over time, be reshaped.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Identity is not something we find. It is something we build.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-architecture-of-identity/202602/the-architecture-of-identity-how-the-brain-builds-a-self" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-architecture-of-identity/202602/the-architecture-of-identity-how-the-brain-builds-a-self</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-architecture-of-identity/202602/the-architecture-of-identity-how-the-brain-builds-a-self</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Elizabeth Mateer Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/nick-fancher-e8Jy-IhGT58-unsplash.jpg?itok=BdM47G7V" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reimaging Psychology or Revitalizing the Humanities?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-07/Clemente-Goodman.jpg?itok=N3uk6pAt" alt="Matthew Clemente, Ph.D. and David  Goodman, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychology</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Reimaging Psychology or Revitalizing the Humanities?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How the psychological humanities can help us accomplish both.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The psychological humanities is a burgeoning field seeking to reshape psychological theory and practice.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">As a discipline, it takes seriously the contributions of psychological science.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Yet it holds that science becomes a better version of itself when it dialogues with art and literature.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <blockquote><p dir="ltr">“I wish we would recognize the place of psychology at the intersection of all disciplines that deal with the human mind and the behavior of living things.” —James H. Korn, “Psychology as a Humanity”</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/jorge-mendez-rb_ILYHx_3w-unsplash_0.jpg?itok=ApT2dl57" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Unsplash/Jorge Mendez" alt="Unsplash/Jorge Mendez"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Unsplash/Jorge Mendez</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">We are often asked to define the term “psychological humanities.” As scholars working in a Center that helps set the discourse for the field, it is understandable why. Yet as is the case with any of the disciplines that have emerged from the rich tradition of the liberal arts, the psychological humanities resists simplistic articulation. And as a field that seeks to enhance both our theoretical understanding of the human person and our practical approaches to caring for one another, it is an ever-evolving discipline – one that must be continuously imagined anew.</p>

<p dir="ltr">When we offer something like this in answer to the question <em>What do you mean by “psychological humanities”?</em>, however, we are typically met with sly smiles and quips about academics being good at talking around problems but not addressing them. It is important to us, therefore, to share some reflections on what constitutes the psychological humanities and what possibilities we believe can be opened up by this burgeoning field.</p>

<p dir="ltr">To do so, we will begin with an anecdote, one that gets to the heart of why we view the humanities as an essential companion to psychological science and mental health care more broadly. A few years back, we undertook a grant-funded project that sought to promote interdisciplinary dialogue between philosophers, psychologists, and theologians. The idea was simple: These three disciplines share a fundamental concern – understanding what it means to be human – and yet the methodologies they employ and the languages they use are radically different. What would it look like for scholars from each field to come together and learn from one another?</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/europeana-rM6LeUY1V1Y-unsplash.jpg?itok=dvQWVw9A" width="320" height="206" data-insert-type="image" title="Unsplash/Europeana" alt="Unsplash/Europeana"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Unsplash/Europeana</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">One thing we recognized early on was that it is far easier for scholars and practitioners from diverse intellectual backgrounds to engage with one another when they are discussing something outside of their area of expertise, something they can appreciate and enjoy whether they have a deep theoretical knowledge of it or not.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In anticipation of our first convening, for instance, we asked participants to read Tolstoy’s slim masterpiece <em>The Death of Ivan Ilyich</em> – a work of singular genius that deserves to be read by anyone who wants to understand suffering and know how to better care for those in need. The conversation that arose around that text was simply astonishing. There, in a room full of highly accomplished academics, we had colleagues share stories of their first encounters with death, of the helplessness they’ve felt having to sit by and watch loved ones suffer, of their own fear of mortality and the various ways it shapes their lives. It was a stirring, powerful discussion occasioned by our shared appreciation of a beautiful work of art.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">That art and literature and the great religions and ideas, which have inspired awe and wonder throughout all of human history, can help us to better understand ourselves and one another ought not to surprise us. Indeed, at some level we already know this, which is why we refer to films and song lyrics and lines of poetry when we want to express that which we find most inarticulable. And yet for various reasons – some historical, some political, some merely accidental – we deprive ourselves of access to these rich resources of insight and meaning when it comes time to think deeply and scientifically about the human condition.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/klaudia-piaskowska-g55bG1O5Lf0-unsplash.jpg?itok=zChizZK_" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Unsplash/ Klaudia Piaskowska" alt="Unsplash/ Klaudia Piaskowska"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Unsplash/ Klaudia Piaskowska</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">It is just this problem that the psychological humanities seeks to address. As a discipline that takes seriously the contributions of psychological science, and yet holds vigorously that science becomes a better version of itself when it is put into dialogue with philosophy, theology, history, and literature, the psychological humanities works to broaden the discourse and practice of psychology such that it can entertain questions of meaning and value.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><em>Why do we suffer? How ought we to treat one another? What is the meaning of human life? </em>These are the kinds of questions the psychological humanities was created to entertain.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Incidentally, they are also the questions each of us wrestles with, the ones that most characterize our lives. Isn’t it odd that a discipline designed to help us understand ourselves and alleviate our suffering asks us to bracket such vital questions? Isn’t it odd that therapists, whose job it is to meet patients where they are at and accompany them in their trials, enter the profession ill-equipped to speak to these most human concerns?</p>

<p dir="ltr">If the psychological humanities seeks to reinvent psychology, its method for doing so involves the restoration of the humanities, which have been so lamentably diminished in recent decades. This can only be accomplished if the value of things once understood to be inherently valuable – art, literature, religion, moral discourse, the search for truth – is assessed not in terms of utility but the degree to which it contributes to a good and prosperous life. </p>



  


<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/jeremy-bishop-EwKXn5CapA4-unsplash.jpg?itok=cWvZf1RL" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Unsplash/ Jeremy Bishop " alt="Unsplash/ Jeremy Bishop "></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Unsplash/ Jeremy Bishop</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Coincidentally, those seeking psychotherapeutic care are often motivated by a desire to live better lives. They enter therapy with ailments the alleviation of which they believe will improve their existence. What if, instead of merely teaching coping techniques and providing medication, clinicians were also able to introduce patients to the kinds of experiences and ideas that have provided human beings with consolation, understanding, and meaning for centuries? What if no topic or question was off limits because psychology understood itself to be a convening discipline where every aspect of human experience meets?</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">This may seem like an audacious goal, and for many in the field as it is currently constituted, even an inadvisable one. But it is the work of the psychological humanities all the same, and only time will tell how far this growing movement will take it.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-human-condition/202602/reimaging-psychology-or-revitalizing-the-humanities" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-human-condition/202602/reimaging-psychology-or-revitalizing-the-humanities</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-human-condition/202602/reimaging-psychology-or-revitalizing-the-humanities</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Matthew Clemente, Ph.D. and David  Goodman, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/klaudia-piaskowska-g55bG1O5Lf0-unsplash.jpg?itok=rYjdCVw6" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Trying Too Hard Keeps You Stuck: The Art of Letting Go]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/jordan_scotti.jpg?itok=hwL5YCKO" alt="Jordan Fiorillo Scotti Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Mindfulness</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Trying Too Hard Keeps You Stuck: The Art of Letting Go</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The evidence is clear: Control is a fist. Peace is an open hand.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Letting go doesn't mean condoning or agreeing with something; it's an act of choosing acceptance.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Acceptance and letting go create a mental state that is less stressed and more open to positive emotions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Clinging and rumination make our brains behave as if they are under threat, limiting our choices.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">Ever had a hard time letting go? Maybe you're still simmering over a painful relationship ending. Or ruminating about a career disappointment. You're not alone. Many of us harbor resentments for decades. Just think about the anger we hold toward parents or people who hurt us in childhood. But holding on to events we can't change doesn't serve us. </p>

<p dir="ltr">In my practice, one of the most powerful things I help clients do is learn the art of letting go. They get to discover firsthand what monks and sages have been saying for thousands of years: Letting go is the key to emotional freedom. And now modern psychology <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9598947/#ref-list1">research</a> confirms this wisdom with findings from brain scans and clinical trials.</p>

<h2>What 'Letting Go' Actually Means</h2>
<p dir="ltr">It's important to understand what letting go actually means—otherwise the practice can feel invalidating. Letting go is not suppressing emotions, avoiding difficult thoughts, condoning behavior that hurts us, or forgetting the past. Letting go is releasing the grip that memories have on us, rather than releasing the memories themselves.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In Buddhism, this is known as non-attachment. In clinical practice, we call it experiential acceptance (practiced most directly through Acceptance and Commitment Therapy). Both share the idea that suffering comes not from painful experiences themselves, but from our struggle against them.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This is best illustrated by Daniel Wegner's famous <a href="https://www.apa.org/monitor/2011/10/unwanted-thoughts">"white bear study,"</a> in which participants who were asked to "think aloud" (but <em>not</em> to think about a white bear) mentioned a white bear about once per minute anyway. Countless studies have replicated the basic idea: What we resist, persists.</p>

<h2>The Neuroscience of Release</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Brain scans help explain what happens when we hold on versus let go. When we're mentally gripping, <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1111/j.1745-6924.2008.00088.x#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20response%20styles%20theory%20(Nolen%2DHoeksema%2C%201991,Nolen%2DHoeksema%2C%201991).">research</a> shows hyperactivity in the default mode network, increased amygdala activation (our threat response), and decreased prefrontal cortex activity (our rational brain). Over time, this carves neural grooves that make this mental state easier to fall into and harder to escape.</p>

<p dir="ltr">When we practice letting go, we see decreased default mode network activity, greater activation in emotion regulation regions, and reduced cortisol production. Experientially, the difference feels like unclenching a fist you didn't know you were making. That release creates space for new emotions, new interpretations, and a greater capacity for wellbeing.</p>

<h2>3 Types of Letting Go</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Letting Go of Outcomes. </strong>In Buddhism, this is sometimes referred to as "non-attachment to results"; in psychology, it maps onto "locus of control" research. When we practice this form of letting go, we take ownership of our efforts while relinquishing control over results. The Serenity Prayer captures it precisely: "Grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change, courage to change the things I can, and wisdom to know the difference."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Letting Go of Identity Stories. </strong>Buddhism calls this "anatta (non-self)"; clinically, it appears in "cognitive defusion" and "schema therapy" approaches. The idea here is that rigidly held self-narratives keep us stuck. A simple shift can help us get unstuck: from "I am anxious" (an identity) to "I am experiencing anxiety" (a temporary state). From there, we can rewrite our stories—moving from "I was hurt as a child, so I choose the wrong partners" to "I'm learning more with each relationship about what a good fit looks like for me."</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Letting Go of Control. </strong>Buddhism frames this as "acceptance of impermanence"; psychology calls it "tolerance of uncertainty". The idea is that trying to control what can't be controlled leads to suffering. The research on helicopter parenting is instructive: Hypervigilance didn't protect children — it <a href="https://www.massgeneralbrigham.org/en/about/newsroom/articles/helicopter-parents-children#:~:text=Excessive%20reliance%20on%20others%2C%20particularly,their%20personal%20set%20of%20aspirations">increased their anxiety</a>. Clinically, exposure therapy works on exactly this principle, teaching us to face what we fear in graduated steps until fear of the uncontrollable loosens its grip.</p>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Paradox That Makes It Work</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Clients often worry: "Doesn't letting go mean I stop trying?" No. When we release attachment to outcomes, we do not give up on our intention to grow. And paradoxically, releasing the desperate need for things to be different often makes us more effective at changing them. For example, insomnia treatments work partly by teaching patients to accept wakefulness because we know that forcing sleep makes it impossible. Similarly, people with social anxiety whose need for approval creates awkwardness find that accepting the possibility of rejection allows them to relax into genuine connection.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Practical Steps</h2>
<p dir="ltr">If you're ready to start letting go, consider the following strategies:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Notice the Grip. </strong>When you feel resistance, ask: Where in my body am I holding on? What thoughts keep looping? Try a body scan or write them down. Sometimes just naming what we are fighting helps us stop battling.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Name What You Can't Control. </strong>When you are stressed or worried, make an explicit list of what's outside of your control: other people's feelings, past events, ultimate outcomes, etc. Give yourself permission to let go of worrying about these things. Consider what is within your control that you can address.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Practice Micro-Releases Daily. </strong>Every day offers opportunities to practice letting go. Start small. For example, let plans change or release the need for an immediate reply from others. Know that these small steps build the neural pathways of acceptance.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Distinguish Acceptance from Approval. </strong>Acceptance means acknowledging reality, not endorsing it. You aren't giving up or condoning when you choose to accept and let go. Know that, from that grounded place of acceptance, we can choose our responses more clearly.</p>
</li>
</ul>



  


<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Both ancient contemplatives and modern researchers have arrived at the same truth: The tight fist creates suffering; the open palm creates space. Not space for passivity, but for intentional, effective action. The question isn't whether to let go; it's whether you're ready to stop exhausting yourself holding on to what you cannot change.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/buddhist-psychology-east-meets-west/202602/why-trying-too-hard-keeps-you-stuck-the-art-of" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/buddhist-psychology-east-meets-west/202602/why-trying-too-hard-keeps-you-stuck-the-art-of</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/buddhist-psychology-east-meets-west/202602/why-trying-too-hard-keeps-you-stuck-the-art-of</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jordan Fiorillo Scotti Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-majesticaljasmin-6440273.jpg?itok=f5jYAVqC" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Antisemitism Distinct From Other Prejudices?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-08/Stitt.jpg?itok=400D04yY" alt="Stitt" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Identity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Is Antisemitism Distinct From Other Prejudices?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The complexity of Jewish identity may worsen the animus against Jewish people.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The tenacity of antisemitic hatred may be related to misunderstanding of the complexities of Jewish identity.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Jewishness is defined, sometimes inaccurately, in racial, religious, or cultural terms.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Due to misunderstandings about their identity, Jews have long been vulnerable to persecution and violence.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Since the October 7, 2023, attack on Jewish residents of Israel, there has been both a rise in concern about antisemitism, its sometimes violent outcomes, and an increase in antisemitic sentiment being expressed publicly. </p>
<p>Those who hold strong anti-Jewish views have been emboldened to share those views in public spaces, especially on college campuses, on social media, and in podcast interviews. In some cases, academic leaders who worked to constrain free speech around other social issues (e.g., COVID response, transsexualism, conservatism) suddenly insist that antisemitic students have absolute freedom to express these views, despite the fear and harm it demonstrably causes.</p>

<p>Antisemitism isn’t limited to one side of the political spectrum. It’s found most often on the extreme left or extreme right, but also to some extent, in the moderate middle. </p>
<p>An atmosphere of antisemitism seems to give way to various conspiracy theories about Jews—that they are engineering cultural and political shifts, or are controlling the media and the global economy. This serves to breed much suspicion about Jews as a people group, often without presenting evidence of these alleged malign machinations.</p>

<h2>What is prejudice?</h2>
<p>As stated in a <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/walking-in-wisdom/202401/the-cognitive-development-of-prejudices">previous post</a>, prejudice tends to evolve in the same way. It is a learned behavior starting in childhood, when children cognitively place people, places, and things in categories based on what they are taught by the adults around them. The individual can then develop an irrational, hostile attitude against a particular individual or group based on the stereotyped characteristics they have used to categorize people. This can lead to terrible consequences for both the hater and the hated.</p>

<p>My question here is whether antisemitism differs in any way from hostility and prejudice against other identity groups.</p>
<p>After discussing this with Roger Barnes, an emeritus professor of sociology, we concluded that prejudice against Jews is not significantly different than other prejudices. The only true distinction we could point to is the tremendous, often confusing complexity of how Jewish identity is defined. </p>

<p>Because of this complexity, Jews have historically been blamed and scapegoated more often than most other groups.</p>
<h2>Antisemitism is ancient and pervasive</h2>
<p>Antisemitism is an ancient hostility that has manifested in nearly every major culture that has included even a small Jewish population. The Jews’ biblically-based claims to land, progeny, and the blessing of their God have provoked the hatred of other cultural groups who see themselves as rivals for those assets.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>With the emergence of the Christian church in the first century, the divisions between Jews and Gentiles grew deeper. The first Christians were mostly Jewish, and the Jewish religious authorities pushed back vehemently against what they perceived to be a threat to their power and influence.</p>
<p>With widespread evangelism, the balance in the church shifted toward Gentiles. Now it was the Roman Empire that was threatened by the Christians’ refusal to bow the knee to the emperor, resulting in brutal persecution of both Jewish and Gentile Christians until the 4th century. When the emperor Constantine exalted Christianity as the state religion, Jews were further marginalized and excluded.</p>

<p>Jumping forward to the Reformation, we see that though Martin Luther revolutionized the understanding of the Scriptures, he was also rabidly antisemitic. He advocated for eliminating portions of what he saw as overly Jewish portions of both the Old and New Testaments, and for destroying Jewish synagogues. </p>

<p>This animosity toward Jews persisted into the twentieth century, when Reich-allied German Lutherans began using Mein Kampf in place of the Bible as their guide for faith. Fighting against Jews was justified and even commanded as their service to God. </p>
<p>With so many centuries to establish itself, this anti-Jewish bias has seeped deep into the root structure of many cultures, in Europe, in the Arab world, and in nations sympathetic to Arab causes. </p>

<h2>Is Jewish identity based on race?</h2>
<p>According to the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25653666/">National Institutes of Health</a>, the notion that Jews constitute a distinct biological race is an artifact of the Enlightenment. No genetic marker of Jewishness has been identified:</p>
<blockquote><p>In recent decades, ever-increasing efforts and ingenuity were invested in identifying Biblical Israelite genotypic common denominators by analysing an assortment of phenotypes, like facial patterns, blood types, diseases, DNA-sequences, and more. It becomes overwhelmingly clear that although Jews maintained detectable vertical genetic continuity along generations of socio-religious-cultural relationship … in spite of considerable consanguinity, there is no Jewish genotype to identify.</p>
</blockquote>



  


<p>The Enlightenment of the 18th century brought about the concept of Jewishness as a racial identity, and not simply a religious one. This meant that even the most secularized, assimilated Jews would never erase their “Jewishness,” because it was now defined as a biological reality. This had the effect that individuals already predisposed to bias against Jews because of some other perceived characteristic might now justify their animus on racial differences. This has brought untold confusion and false racial hatred that persists today. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Is Jewish identity based on religion? </h2>
<p>Many Jewish educational websites agree that a Jewish person is someone who either has a Jewish mother or who has converted to the Jewish religion.</p>
<p>Sammy Davis Jr., a Black man, and Connie Chung, an Asian woman, identified as Jewish because they had converted to the Jewish religion. This illustrates that people from many races and ethnicities can identify as Jewish. </p>

<p>These ambiguities and false beliefs about Jewish identity have historically allowed people of ill will to claim contradictory stereotypes of Jewish people. For instance, they might say that Jews are weak and powerless, and later say that they are too powerful. Or that they are too communist or too capitalist. Or that they are needy parasites and also privileged manipulators. Or that they are like repulsive animals (the Nazis compared Jews to rats) and also disproportionately—and unfairly—intellectually gifted and vocationally successful.</p>

<p>Over time, this use of contradictory stereotypes gives great linguistic and sociological flexibility for fomenting antisemitic hatred, using whatever works best to provoke contempt or envy in a specific cultural context. Jews become cultural scapegoats, easy to blame for society’s ills. This is exactly what Adolf Hitler did, convincing millions of Germans that Jews were inferior and should be eliminated.</p>

<p>It is fair to say that antisemitism, compared to other prejudices, has led to a disproportionate number of attempts at the genocide of Jews, the Holocaust being the most dramatic example. </p>
<p>So, though many people perish in tribal and national wars based on race, culture, or religion, the case of the Jews is that they have persecuted because of all three factors, and because of deep misunderstandings about who they are and what they believe. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/walking-in-wisdom/202602/is-antisemitism-distinct-from-other-prejudices" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/walking-in-wisdom/202602/is-antisemitism-distinct-from-other-prejudices</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/walking-in-wisdom/202602/is-antisemitism-distinct-from-other-prejudices</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Ruth E. Stitt M.S., M.Div., LPCS]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/anton-mislawsky-bEt1yhLX7oo-unsplash.jpg?itok=i8mWlHgR" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>