<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 22:42:40 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 22:42:40 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Leaders Struggle With Prioritization, Not Time Management]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-08/Marty-Dubin.jpg?itok=s4Skm2wv" alt="Martin Dubin" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Leadership</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Leaders Struggle With Prioritization, Not Time Management</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Leadership effectiveness isn't about doing more, it's about doing what matters.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Prioritizing your work around what only you can do in your role is the hidden key to effectiveness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Roles in organizations exist because certain duties and decisions belong to only that role.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">There are five duties that only the CEO can do.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Doing too much multi-tasking at work?</p>
<p>Questioning your productivity?</p>
<p>Feeling like you don’t have enough time to do what’s really important?</p>
<p>The problem may not be with your time-management skills, but with knowing what <em>only </em>you can do.</p>
<p>As an executive coach working with Fortune 500 CEOs, there is one question I ask that stumps them. What can <em>only</em> the CEO do?</p>

<p>When you are the CEO, you have infinite degrees of freedom in how you spend your time. No one tells you what meetings you must attend (except Board Meetings), what projects you must work on, or when your day starts or ends. There are more people and projects demanding your time than hours in the week. So how do you decide what to prioritize, what requires your presence, and where your influence will make the biggest impact? </p>

<p>It starts by shifting the question from “How do I fit it all in?” to “What can <em>only </em>I do?”—and then aligning your behavior with the true demands of your role.</p>
<h2>Leadership Prioritization: How Leaders Decide What Deserves Their Time</h2>
<p>Leaders are quite often—and certainly at the C-level— the only ones in their respective positions, but all too often they haven’t thought through the activities that only the person in that role can do. The CEO, for instance, is the person who must set corporate strategy. If you are a CEO and you are not spending significant time on strategy, you are failing in your role. Yet many leaders spend their time doing what they like to do, what they think they are good at, or what the previous person in their role did. Over time, these default behaviors can become a costly prioritization blindspot. </p>

<p>When helping CEOs prioritize, I start by asking for their top five priorities. Then we look at their calendar from the past three months to see where their time actually went. More often than not, fewer than 50 percent of their hours reflect what they say matters most. </p>
<p>Intuitively, we all know why this happens. We are distracted from what we should be doing because, in the moment, something seems urgent, and if we don’t attend to it, a crisis will emerge. Or, we are enticed into doing things we enjoy and are good at; or we are convinced that a particular problem requires our special expertise. I worked with one CEO who loved to sweep in and solve difficult problems so much so that he proudly displayed a fireman’s helmet in his office. Although this was his superpower, it also became a blind spot when it pulled him away from the work <em>only </em>he could do. </p>

<h2>Leadership Roles and Responsibilities: What <em>Only</em> You Can Do</h2>
<p>Roles on a company’s organizational chart exist because <em>only</em> the person in that role is authorized to make certain decisions or do certain activities. If there aren’t special duties assigned to a role, then that role doesn’t need to exist and can be removed from the organizational chart.</p>

<p>Thinking about what <em>only</em> the person in the role can do is a riveting exercise in focus. It eliminates our likes and dislikes, our unique expertise, and our concerns about societal or career expectations. It focuses our attention on what is truly critical to success in our job. </p>
<h2>What <em>Only </em>the CEO Can Do</h2>

<p>I have found that there are 5 things that <em>only</em> the CEO can do. CEOs who filter the demands on their time through these 5 tasks are efficient and effective. And if the CEO isn’t doing these 5 duties, then either they aren’t getting done, or the wrong person is working on them. </p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Hiring and Firing Senior Team Members.</strong> This seems obvious, but I have worked with many organizations where the CEO, upon arrival, accepted the team that was in place, or senior team selection and recruitment was delegated to HR. Senior team members must not only be subject matter experts, but they must also complement the CEO. A self-aware CEO knows their own gifts and their gaps and selects team members accordingly.</li>
<li><strong>Owning the Strategy.</strong> CEOs are accountable for the decisions that are made about how, when, and where corporate resources are allocated and which opportunities to pursue and threats to mitigate.</li>
<li><strong>Ensuring Fidelity to Priorities. </strong>Employees need to know what they should be working on, and the CEO is the ultimate authority to rein in the profusion of priorities.</li>
<li><strong>Championing the Culture.</strong> CEOs know that culture makes or breaks corporate success, and they need to be continually alert to how they use the power of their position in support of cultural initiatives.</li>
<li><strong>Owning Key Relationships.</strong> Board members, significant customers, investors, and suppliers only want to talk to the CEO. These relationships can’t be delegated and must be attended to with care and sophistication.</li>
</ol>

<p>Once the CEO is clear on these 5 duties, they can use the following framework to prioritize their time. </p>
<ul>
<li>What do they own?</li>
<li>What do they own in partnership with another?</li>
<li>What should they delegate?</li>
<li>What should they monitor?</li>
<li>What should they actively ignore?</li>
</ul>
<h2>What Can Only <em>You</em> Do?</h2>
<p>Whatever your role, there are things that <em>only </em>your role can do. Do you know what they are? What is your role in supporting the company’s strategy and priorities? What is your role in representing and championing corporate culture? What key relationships do you own, and which ones could be delegated to others? Are you clear on what decisions only you in your role are authorized to make? Are you making decisions that should be made by those you manage? </p>

<p>Leadership effectiveness is less about doing more and more about doing what truly matters. When you align your time with the things only you can do, you avoid blind spots and lead with intention instead of impulse.</p>
<p><em>For a deeper look at how prioritization blindspots impact executive leadership, read </em><a href="https://www.blindspotting.com/blog/yara-the-ceo-with-a-revolving-door"><em>this case study</em></a>.<br> </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/blindspotting/202602/why-leaders-struggle-with-prioritization-not-time-management" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/blindspotting/202602/why-leaders-struggle-with-prioritization-not-time-management</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/blindspotting/202602/why-leaders-struggle-with-prioritization-not-time-management</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Martin Dubin]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-sora-shimazaki-5669603.jpg?itok=LJRVyl1W" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do Yourself a Favor: Don’t Read the News This Week]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-03/APuutio-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=AyQHx2r8" alt="T. Alexander Puutio Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Attention</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Do Yourself a Favor: Don’t Read the News This Week</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Staying informed can feel like a moral obligation, but it comes with a real cost.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">What you pay attention to can have a powerful effect on your mental health—for better or worse.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Constant consumption of stressful news stories skews risk perception and amplifies anxiety, studies find.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Staying “informed” can leave you subtly misinformed and mentally taxed.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Take one week off the news and reclaim your focus.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Your attempts at keeping informed probably aren't doing you any favors, even if checking the news can feel like a civic obligation. And this is coming from a recovering RSS feed junkie who once prided himself on knowing every headline and stray piece of zeitgeist trivia in the cafeteria, and who still feels the twitch to refresh a newsfeed out of fear of missing something important—or worse, being exposed as the ignoramus he is.</p>

<p>For years, I equated awareness of world affairs with virtue—and something similar may be happening with you as well (I doubt Psychology Today is your only online pitstop today). Which is exactly why we need to talk about the growing stack of empirical studies that speak to the cognitive and emotional costs of staying constantly “informed.”</p>

<h2>The Hidden Cost of Staying Informed </h2>
<p>Author and entrepreneur Rolf Dobelli, who founded the intellectual community WORLD.MINDS, has long argued that modern news functions less as education and more as a gravity well for our attention that offers little in return. His claim is not that we should be ignorant or disengaged, but instead, he argues that the structure of contemporary news consumption systematically distorts our perception of reality.</p>

<p>Neutrality and objectivity are challenging goals for any attention-driven industry, particularly when its incentives are aligned with engagement rather than our psychological health. The cognitive consequences of the news industry are well documented by psychologists as well. </p>
<p>One subtle way news distorts our perception of reality operates through the availability heuristic, our tendency to overestimate the likelihood of events that are vivid and easily recalled (Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1973). When plane crashes dominate headlines or rare crimes are amplified, risk feels omnipresent because the mind confuses salience with prevalence, a distortion that Dobelli has argued is structurally embedded in modern news production (Dobelli, 2010).</p>

<p>In addition to skewing our perception of risk, sustained news consumption can exert measurable effects on psychological well-being. Research conducted during the COVID-19 pandemic found consistent associations between high levels of pandemic-related news exposure and increased anxiety, stress, and depressive symptoms (Bendau et al., 2021; Garfin et al., 2020). A large review indexed in PubMed Central concluded that intensive news consumption during crisis periods correlated with psychological distress across multiple populations (Su et al., 2022).</p>

<p>On the flip side, more recent experimental work suggests that reducing digital input can have measurable benefits. Randomized studies examining screen time reduction and mobile internet blocking have reported improvements in mood, well-being, and sustained attention (Allcott et al., 2020). While these studies do not isolate “news” in pure form, the implication is difficult to ignore. </p>

<p>Constant digital exposure, including news, taxes cognitive and emotional systems in ways that often go unnoticed.</p>
<h2>What to Do Instead: Your Task for This Week</h2>
<p>Here on the East Coast, the snow is coming down hard enough to quiet the streets. Blizzard weeks have a way of compressing the world into something smaller and slower, making ideal grounds for an experiment. Even if you aren't joining me in the shoveling, consider locking hands in taking the next seven days as a slow-burn week where we limit our intake of the immediate yet insubstantial, and focus on something more nourishing instead.</p>


<p>We'll begin by doing our best to avoid the hot buttons and skipping the daily outrage cycle that often begins the moment we unlock our mobile phones. This week, let's simply have faith in the fact that if something truly consequential occurs, the world will find a way to let us know. </p>
<p>And once we have the subtraction part of the equation down, we'll move on to substitution and slap a nicotine patch on our doomscrolling habits. Before the week begins, choose one long read or long-form video that you have postponed. Load it onto every device that usually pulls you toward newsfeeds, and when the reflex to check headlines surfaces, open that tab instead. </p>

<p>Notice the discomfort that accompanies sustained attention and stick with it. For me, that text is Nietzsche’s <em>Thus Spoke Zarathustra</em>, a book I have deferred for years in favor of easier intellectual calories. From a psychological perspective, this is habit replacement instead of a lifestyle overhaul, and we are simply retraining our attentional pathways rather than suppressing them.</p>



  


<p>The aim of this week's exercise is not to detach from reality but to recalibrate your relationship with it. Attention compounds over time, and so does distraction. A week will not transform your life, but it may reveal how much of your cognitive energy has been quietly siphoned away by the Sisyphean task of staying informed.</p>

<p>Snowstorms have a way of simplifying choices. Let this one be an invitation to test whether constant news consumption is nourishing your mind or merely occupying it.</p>
<p>Your neurons, and perhaps your nervous system, may thank you.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/curiosity-code/202602/do-yourself-a-favor-dont-read-the-news-this-week" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/curiosity-code/202602/do-yourself-a-favor-dont-read-the-news-this-week</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/curiosity-code/202602/do-yourself-a-favor-dont-read-the-news-this-week</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[T. Alexander Puutio Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-nhaan-ngo-184413993-11616960.jpg?h=fc26badb&amp;itok=e_2HifvH" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>