<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 23:26:10 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 23:26:10 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Silent Cycle of Bulimia Nervosa]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-09/Melissa%20Gerson.png.jpg?itok=8PUUY5I6" alt="Melissa Gerson LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Bulimia Nervosa</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Silent Cycle of Bulimia Nervosa</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Bulimia hides in silence and shame, but recovery is possible.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Bulimia often remains hidden because it unfolds in secrecy and private rituals.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Shame reinforces the binge-purge cycle and keeps many from seeking help.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The behavior serves a short-term emotional function, so in a way it "works"—but not in the long run.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Bulimia nervosa is frequently overlooked not because it is mild, but because it is often profoundly secretive in how it presents and progresses. The disorder tends to unfold in private, with binge episodes hidden and compensatory behaviors carried out discreetly. Individuals may sustain careers, academic performance, and relationships while structuring much of their internal world around food, restriction, and purging. When visible physical changes are minimal, this concealment becomes even more sustainable, enabling the cycle to continue largely undetected.</p>

<p>Unlike eating disorders that may signal distress through visible weight loss, bulimia often allows a person to appear outwardly stable. That stability can delay recognition. But the more powerful reason bulimia goes undetected is psychological rather than visual: it is sustained by shame.</p>
<h2>The Secrecy and Shame of Bulimia Nervosa</h2>

<p>Shame is not simply a byproduct of the disorder; rather, it is part of its architecture. Binge eating is frequently experienced as a loss of control, followed by intense regret and self-criticism. Purging may temporarily relieve both physical discomfort and emotional distress, but it is typically followed by renewed guilt and resolve. This cycle reinforces silence. Many individuals minimize their symptoms, convincing themselves that because they are functioning, the problem is not severe.</p>

<h2>Emotional Function of the Binge-Purge Cycle</h2>
<p>At the same time, bulimia often serves a functional role. The binge-purge cycle is rarely random. For many individuals, it becomes a highly conditioned strategy for regulating affect. Binge eating may blunt anxiety, numb sadness, discharge anger, or create a temporary escape from shame. Purging can produce a powerful sense of relief, both physiologically and psychologically, reinforcing the behavior through negative reinforcement. Over time, the cycle becomes wired into the nervous system as a predictable way to manage internal distress.</p>

<p>For others, bulimia functions as a method of maintaining control in the face of emotional chaos. Periods of restriction may provide a sense of order and discipline, while binge episodes express the pressure that builds under rigidity. The cycle can also carry elements of self-punishment, particularly in individuals with deeply internalized self-criticism. In this way, bulimia is not only an eating disorder; it becomes an organizing framework for emotional regulation.</p>

<p>Because the behavior “works” in the short term, even as it erodes health and self-trust over time, it becomes deeply entrenched. And because it is accompanied by shame, it remains hidden. Many people live for years in this loop, believing they should be able to stop on their own, or assuming that the absence of visible decline means the problem is manageable.</p>

<h2>Treatment for Bulimia</h2>
<p>Clinically, this combination of function and secrecy makes bulimia particularly persistent. Effective treatment must address both. It is not enough to simply remove behaviors without understanding what they have been regulating. At the same time, insight alone is insufficient if the behavioral cycle remains intact.</p>


<p>Evidence-based treatments for bulimia nervosa focus on disrupting the binge-purge cycle directly while also helping individuals develop alternative strategies for managing distress. Structured approaches such as cognitive behavioral therapy for eating disorders have demonstrated strong outcomes in reducing binge and purge frequency and restoring more stable patterns of eating. Equally important, treatment creates a space in which secrecy is replaced with shared understanding.</p>

<p>Breaking the silence is often the first step in recovery. When individuals are able to describe the full cycle out loud, without minimization or judgment, the disorder begins to lose some of its power. Shame diminishes when experience is met with clarity rather than condemnation. As behaviors are interrupted and emotional regulation skills expand, the reliance on the cycle gradually weakens.</p>



  


<p>Bulimia nervosa may be quiet, but it is not untreatable. Its invisibility should not be mistaken for inevitability. With direct intervention, transparency, and evidence-based care, individuals can exit the cycle that once felt endless. What has been hidden can be brought into the open, and what once functioned as survival can be replaced with healthier forms of stability. </p>

<p><em>To find a therapist, please visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>. </em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-road-to-recovery/202603/the-silent-cycle-of-bulimia-nervosa" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-road-to-recovery/202603/the-silent-cycle-of-bulimia-nervosa</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-road-to-recovery/202603/the-silent-cycle-of-bulimia-nervosa</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Melissa Gerson LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/felirbe-BUkU-VhzW-s-unsplash.jpg?itok=XV5AT8K_" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What "Punch" Taught Us About Earned Secure Attachment]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/_Beatrice%20Ng-Kessler.png.jpg?itok=9uSxtCGv" alt="Beatrice Ng-Kessler MsC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Attachment</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What "Punch" Taught Us About Earned Secure Attachment</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Therapists can become a secure base for clients with insecure attachment.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Earned secure attachment develops through reflection and integration.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Relational safety is the foundation of attachment repair.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Therapy itself provides a corrective attachment experience.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Recently, a young monkey named Punch (an interesting note: a primatologist said Japanese monkeys are hierarchical) went viral online. Rejected by his mother, he was filmed clinging to a soft Ikea toy as if it were an attachment figure. Videos showed him attempting to rejoin his troop, seeking contact, connection, and belonging despite early rejection.</p>

<p>The internet responded with empathy. People saw not just a monkey, but something deeply recognizable: the instinct to attach, even after rupture.</p>
<p>Perhaps this is a moment to discuss<strong> </strong><em>secure attachment.</em></p>
<p>Attachment is not simply about whether one had a secure beginning. It is also about what becomes possible later.</p>

<h2>What Is Earned Secure Attachment?</h2>
<p>Attachment theory distinguishes between secure and insecure patterns formed in early caregiving relationships. But research has identified a category known as <em>earned secure attachment</em>.</p>
<p>Earned security refers to individuals who:</p>
<ul>
<li>May have experienced inconsistency, neglect, emotional unavailability, or trauma in childhood.</li>
<li>Yet develop secure attachment patterns later in life.</li>
<li>Demonstrate reflective capacity about their past.</li>
<li>Can integrate painful experiences without being dominated by them.</li>
</ul>

<p>Research using the Adult Attachment Interview suggests that individuals with earned secure attachment are not defined by ideal childhoods. They are defined by coherence. They can reflect on early experiences with balance and integration. </p>
<p>It is not the absence of adversity that defines security. It is the integration of it.</p>

<h2>What Makes Security “Earned”?</h2>
<p>Several elements tend to be present in "earned security."</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reflective Capacity: </strong>The ability to think about one’s own mind and others’ minds. Not just “what happened,” but “what did it mean?"</li>
<li><strong>Emotional Tolerance: </strong>The capacity to experience primary emotions without immediate avoidance or dysregulation.</li>
<li><strong>Narrative Coherence: </strong>The ability to tell one’s attachment story in a way that is organized, balanced, and not dominated by idealization or resentment.</li>
<li><strong>Corrective Relational Experiences: </strong>Later relationships—partners, mentors, therapists—that offer consistent safety and attunement.</li>
</ul>

<p>Security, in this sense, is less a fixed trait and more a developmental achievement.</p>
<h2>Why Earned Secure Attachment Matters for Therapists</h2>
<p><strong>Relational Safety Is the Primary Concern</strong></p>
<p>Relational safety between therapist and client is always the primary concern.</p>
<p>If your client has an insecure attachment style, you must consistently attune to their attachment needs within the therapy room. The therapist models a “good parent” function—providing reliability, attunement, and a secure base. The therapeutic relationship itself becomes a vehicle for corrective attachment experience. In schema therapy, we call this "limited reparenting."</p>

<p>Clients are not only working on symptoms. They are testing relational predictions:</p>
<p><em>Will I be judged?</em><br><em>Will I be dismissed?</em><br><em>Will I overwhelm you?</em><br><em>Will I be too much?</em></p>
<p>Security in the therapist regulates the dyad.</p>
<p><strong>The Therapist as Attachment Environment</strong></p>
<p>Therapy is not just a conversation. It is a relationship.</p>
<p>Clients bring expectations into the room, which are unconsciously shaped by their attachment style:</p>


<ul>
<li>Fear of rejection or intimacy.</li>
<li>Fear of engulfment.</li>
<li>Assuming hierarchy.</li>
<li>Uncertainty of abandonment.</li>
</ul>
<p>Earned secure therapists tend to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tolerate emotional intensity.</li>
<li>Repair ruptures without collapse.</li>
<li>Invite disagreement without defensiveness.</li>
<li>Maintain healthy boundaries.</li>
</ul>
<p>Insecure dynamics in the therapy room can unintentionally reinforce clients’ fears.</p>

<p><strong>Narrative Work Is Central</strong></p>
<p>Facilitating the client’s narrative process is central to the work.</p>
<p>Therapists can lose their way in the middle of treatment—becoming overly focused on problem-solving, measurable outcomes, or behavioural goals. While these elements are important, healing attachment-related wounds requires more than deliverables.</p>



  


<p>We cannot overlook the corrective emotional experience that emerges through the therapeutic relationship itself, nor the transformative power of helping clients narrate their story in their own terms, rather than through narratives imposed by others.</p>
<p>Storytelling is not incidental to therapy; it is constitutive of it.</p>

<p>The therapeutic journey is interwoven with the client telling, reviewing, and revising their narrative with the therapist over time. Through this process, coherence emerges. And coherence is one marker of earned security.</p>
<p><strong>Encouraging Manageable Risk-Taking</strong></p>
<p>Encouraging interpersonal risk-taking begins within the therapy room.</p>

<p>Therapists often encourage clients to take relational risks in daily life without first recognizing that therapy itself should function as the incubator for such risk-taking.</p>
<p><em>Can the client disagree with you?</em><br><em>Express anger toward you?</em><br><em>Reveal shame in front of you?</em></p>
<p>At times, facilitating this work may involve the therapist’s willingness to be appropriately vulnerable. Such moments can activate the therapist’s own attachment system and personal sensitivities.</p>

<p>For this reason, the therapist’s relational stance should be an ongoing subject of supervision.</p>
<p>For example, a therapist with an avoidant attachment style may feel more comfortable working with similarly avoidant clients, yet experience greater difficulty with clients who present with anxious or disorganized attachment patterns. These dynamics require reflection rather than avoidance.</p>

<p>Earned security in the therapist does not mean perfection. It means awareness, regulation, and integration.</p>
<p><strong>Protection Against Burnout and Reactivity</strong></p>
<p>Without reflective integration of one’s own attachment history, therapists may:</p>
<ul>
<li>Over-identify with clients and burn out.</li>
<li>Avoid certain emotional themes.</li>
<li>Become overly directive or overly passive.</li>
<li>Tendency to please clients or fish for validation.</li>
<li>Struggle with rupture repair.</li>
</ul>

<p>A therapist who has earned security supports:</p>
<ul>
<li>Awareness of countertransference.</li>
<li>Capacity to tolerate being misunderstood.</li>
<li>Stability in the face of client anger, overcompensating behaviours, or withdrawal.</li>
<li>Emotional endurance without emotional numbing.</li>
</ul>
<p>It allows therapists to remain open without becoming overwhelmed.</p>

<h2>Final Reflection</h2>
<p>Punch, the young monkey clinging to a toy after maternal rejection, reminds us that the drive to attach persists even after rupture. </p>
<p>Attachment patterns are powerful, but not fixed.</p>
<p>Earned secure attachment reminds us that security can be built.</p>
<p>For therapists, this is both hopeful and demanding. We are not required to have perfect histories. But we are called to cultivate reflective integration and relational steadiness so that clients can experience something different from what they expect.</p>

<p>Security is not something we declare. It is something the clients feel. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-therapy-meets-cultures/202602/what-punch-taught-us-about-earned-secure-attachment" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-therapy-meets-cultures/202602/what-punch-taught-us-about-earned-secure-attachment</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-therapy-meets-cultures/202602/what-punch-taught-us-about-earned-secure-attachment</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Beatrice Ng-Kessler MSc]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/pexels-dsd-143941-1829979.jpg?itok=k5Q9LBXa" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>