<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 17:22:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 17:22:06 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Listening to Understand Can Help Families of Gray Divorce]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/carol-hughes-and-bruce-fredenburg.jpg?itok=g1BdWcIV" alt="Carol R. Hughes, Ph.D., LMFT, and Bruce R. Fredenburg, M.S., LMFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Divorce</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Listening to Understand Can Help Families of Gray Divorce</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Tools to help parents of gray divorce and their adult children communicate.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Misunderstood feelings can fuel conflict and estrangement after gray divorce.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Understanding does not mean agreement. It means listening without judgment.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Feeling understood brings security, relief, and stronger bonds between parents and adult children.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Listening to understand, not to reply, can reduce conflict in families of gray divorce.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/adult%20daughter%20and%20mother%20tense_Pexels%20Cottonbro.jpg?itok=86ynmsDI" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Cottonbro / Pixels" alt="Cottonbro / Pixels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Cottonbro / Pixels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em><strong>T</strong>he biggest communication problem is we do not listen to understand. We listen to reply. </em>—Mahatma Gandhi</p>
<p>When couples 50 and older end their marriage—what in known as gray divorce—parents and their adult children may have painful feelings about what's happened. When they lack the tools to communicate effectively, misunderstandings abound, and estrangement can result.</p>

<p>Lorraine, 58, and her husband divorced four years ago. Lorraine and her 33-year-old daughter Stephanie began conjoint therapy for help in having difficult conversations and to heal their pain-filled relationship. In preparation for their upcoming session, their assignment was to read a handout that contained the following information:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>People in conflict are often mired in misunderstood feelings.</strong></p>
<p>Feeling misunderstood impedes our ability to understand another person. Neuroscience found that when people feel understood by others, transformative shifts occur.</p>
<p>Feeling understood evokes three predominant emotions that are the antithesis of fear and anxiety: Satisfaction <em>–</em> Security <em>– </em>Tension Relief. Feeling understood helps us relax and mollifies defensiveness.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>Listening to understand is crucial to communicating effectively.</h2>
<p>In <em>Zen Mind, Beginner's Mind</em>, Shunryu Suzuki writes that true listening emerges from what he calls "beginner's mind," which is willing to remain receptive and open without preconceptions and judgment. <em>Looping</em> utilizes the concept of beginner's mind.</p>

<p>Looping is short for "closing the loop of communication." It is a technique that helps develop listening to understand. There is a speaker and a listener. The speaker must speak about only one topic at a time for no more than two to three minutes. Here are the steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>The listener listens carefully to the speaker, does not interrupt, and does not focus on their own thoughts.</li>
<li>The listener repeats as closely and carefully as possible what they heard the speaker say. The listener refrains from expressing their judgments, reactions, and assumptions.</li>
<li>The listener repeats to the speaker the speaker's words as accurately as possible and then asks if what they repeated is accurate and complete.</li>
<li>The speaker confirms that what the listener repeated is accurate and complete, adds what the listener left out, and corrects anything the listener got wrong. </li>
<li>The listener repeats what the speaker said in number 4.</li>
<li>When the speaker says the listener heard them accurately, the loop of communication is closed. The listener cannot speak until they have demonstrated that they have listened accurately.</li>
</ol>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The purpose of looping is not to convince or contradict, not to take exception, nor to explain away. It is to understand. People are much more willing and able to understand one another when they feel understood.</p>
<p><em>“Being heard is so close to being loved that for the average person, they are almost indistinguishable.” </em>—David W. Augsburger</p>

<p>Understanding is not the same as agreement. Looping requires that each person genuinely wants to understand and listen from the heart to how they are experiencing a situation. The inner desire to understand is critical.</p>
<p>Stephanie and Lorraine sat diagonally across from each other on the love seats in my office.</p>


<blockquote><p><strong>Stephanie:</strong> Since our last session, Mom and I decided to practice the steps of looping. It isn't easy, but we made some progress. Do you agree, Mom?</p>
<p><strong>Lorraine:</strong> I agree that it wasn't easy. Instead of listening with a non-judging mind, I kept falling back into thinking that what Stephanie was saying was wrong and that I was right. We need your help to improve.</p>
<p><strong>Stephanie:</strong> Let's practice. Mom, you be the speaker, and I'll be the listener.</p>
<p><strong>Lorraine:</strong> Stephanie, I'm very hurt that you said you did not want me to bring Joe, my significant other, to your rehearsal dinner and wedding.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Lorraine turned to me and said, "I've learned to leave out, 'How could you do that to me?' I now understand that I'm blaming and attacking Stephanie. I've also learned that I need to be brief and speak about only one topic at a time. I tend to talk in ongoing paragraphs."</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Stephanie:</strong> Mom, you're very hurt that I said I did not want you to bring Joe, your significant other, to my rehearsal dinner and wedding. Did I get that right?</p>
<p><strong>Lorraine:</strong> Yes, you did.</p>
<p><strong>Carol</strong>: Stephanie, since you accurately heard what your mother said, now it's your turn to speak.</p>
<p><strong>Stephanie:</strong> I want to lecture Mom about how she should respect my feelings. I have learned that's not listening to understand, so I'm not going to say that. Mom, I want you to honor my feelings that our wedding is about Joshua and me, not about what you want.</p>
<p><strong>Lorraine: </strong>You want me to honor your feelings that your wedding is about Joshua and you, not about what I want. Did I get that right?</p>
<p><strong>Stephanie:</strong> Yes, you did.</p>
<p><strong>Lorraine:</strong> Is there anything else?</p>
<p><strong>Stephanie:</strong> No, you got it right.</p>
<p><strong>Carol:</strong> What was your experience doing that exercise?</p>
<p><strong>Stephanie:</strong> It felt so good that Mom didn't launch into telling me how I should feel. I felt she finally heard me.</p>
<p><strong>Lorraine:</strong> I felt the same way. Stephanie didn't tell me how I should feel. I felt understood. It's amazing how simple it seems, although it's difficult to break my old patterns.</p>
</blockquote>



  


<p>During the session, Stephanie and Lorraine continued practicing looping. Sometimes they had difficulty. They will need more practice and are committed to doing so.</p>
<p><em>When you talk, you are only repeating what you already know. But if you listen, you may learn something new.” </em>—The Dalai Lama</p>
<p><em>Patient names and details changed to preserve confidentiality.</em></p>

<p><strong>To find a therapist, </strong><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><strong>visit the Psychology Today Therapy Directory</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>
<p>Copyright 2026 Carol R. Hughes, Ph.D.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/home-will-never-be-the-same-again/202602/listening-to-understand-can-help-families-of-gray" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/home-will-never-be-the-same-again/202602/listening-to-understand-can-help-families-of-gray</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/home-will-never-be-the-same-again/202602/listening-to-understand-can-help-families-of-gray</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Carol R. Hughes, Ph.D., LMFT, and Bruce R. Fredenburg, M.S., LMFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/0_teaser_pexels-shvets-production-6975383-Adult%20daughter%20frustrated.jpg?itok=fISbbMuy" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Health Benefits of Looking at Beauty]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/GreggLevoy.jpg?itok=tC3V4Ofh" alt="Gregg Levoy" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Beauty</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Health Benefits of Looking at Beauty</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Looking at beauty lifts your mood, boosts your immune system, and lowers stress.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Looking at beauty releases the same feel-good chemicals as being in love, eating chocolate, and exercising.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">There’s no agreed-upon checklist of what constitutes beauty. It's whatever gives you an aesthetic charge.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Appreciating beauty gives your psyche and nervous system a break from exposure to the world’s ugliness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Beauty keeps you interested in life, making you eager to sustain it and remember it’s worth living.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-photo-12268359_0.jpeg.jpg?itok=3IqQtScK" width="320" height="490" data-insert-type="image" title="Sofya Borboris/Pexels" alt="Sofya Borboris/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Sofya Borboris/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Isaac Asimov once came up with a unit of measurement for beauty that he called a milli-helen. If Helen of Troy’s legendary beauty was sufficient to launch a thousand ships, then a milli-helen is the amount of beauty sufficient to launch a single ship.</p>
<p>Asimov was not just a science-fiction writer, but a professor of biochemistry, and beauty, it turns out, is capable of launching not just an armada of ships, but a cascade of the same feel-good chemicals you get from being in love, eating chocolate, exercising, and having orgasms—dopamine, endorphins, serotonin, oxytocin. It also lowers stress, blood pressure, and heart rate. </p>

<p>In other words, aesthetics isn’t superficial. It’s biochemical. And it isn’t a luxury, but a deep human drive.</p>
<p>And this is by design. In evolution’s logic, beauty brings pleasure, and pleasure reinforces useful behavior, whether in the selection of a mate (symmetry of face and luster of hair, for instance, signal good health and strong genes), or the selection of an environment to live in (lush greenery signals water and fertile land; scenic overlooks make it easier to spot predators). Furthermore, beauty keeps you aroused and interested in life, reinforcing behaviors that make you eager to sustain it, to remember that life is pleasurable and worth living.</p>

<p>The psychologist Abraham Maslow’s famous hierarchy of human needs places “aesthetic needs” near the top of the pyramid (below only “self-actualization” and “self-transcendence” needs), and they encompass our motivations to seek out and appreciate beauty, harmony, and order in our environments and experiences.</p>

<p>This applies whether the beauty you’re beholding is art, architecture, nature, music, a well-designed room, a virtuous action, a beautiful face, or a beautiful idea like “love thy neighbor.” It applies whether the beauty is an elegant mathematical formula, a perfect pitch in baseball, or a monster truck rally. There are, after all, beauty contests for hogs.</p>

<p>Clearly, there’s no universally agreed-upon checklist of what constitutes beauty, though researchers have identified some common attributes like simplicity, symmetry, certain juxtapositions of color or musical notes, certain ratios and geometries in the arrangement of physical elements. But beauty is whatever gives <em>you</em> an aesthetic charge.</p>

<p>If there’s anything universal about beauty, it might be that it represents some kind of ideal—of perfection, order, harmony, even joy. Or at least an ideal of <em>perfectibility</em>, something as enticing as it is elusive. In other words, beauty doesn’t just help create life, but inspires its higher flowering.</p>

<p>Given the imperfect nature of the world we live in, though, and the frequently unsightly behavior of those who live in it, the appreciation of beauty is a salve, a coping mechanism, a balancing act, reminding you that the world may be awful, but it’s also beautiful. You have the choice where to direct your gaze, of course, but the ability to hold the paradox that <em>both</em> exist, simultaneously, is a skill that can help you maintain balance when life goes off-kilter.</p>

<p>People who study neuro-aesthetics—a branch of science that examines how the brain responds to beauty—tell us that by engaging with beauty you’re essentially hacking your brain to boost your mood and immune system, stir your creative juices, and give your psyche and nervous system a break from continual exposure to the world’s ugliness and untidiness (which is also subjective). Looking at beauty is the emotional equivalent of the pleasure and relief you get from taking your contacts out at the end of a long day.</p>

<p>One researcher, Rene Proyer at Martin Luther University in Germany, demonstrated this neuro-aesthetic principle with a simple experiment. He created what he calls the “<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/292985900_Nine_beautiful_things_A_self-administered_online_positive_psychology_intervention_on_the_beauty_in_nature_arts_and_behaviors_increases_happiness_and_ameliorates_depressive_symptoms">nine beautiful things</a>” practice and tested it on a group of adults. For a week, he had them write about beautiful things they observed in their day-to-day lives—in human behavior, nature, art, whatever. The result: happiness increased, depression decreased.</p>



  


<p>Not that beauty doesn’t occasionally come with a payload of melancholy, especially the kind of beauty that’s fleeting, that fades before your eyes—sunsets, murmurations, the last notes of a favorite song. These may come freighted with a poignancy that can border on anguish: the sun sets, the light fades, the day ends, the days end.</p>

<p>At beauty’s farther extremes—where you’re stunned into wordlessness by a breathtaking landscape, a ravishing passage of literature, or someone’s physical beauty—it can even lead to envy or possessiveness, the hopeless hunger to <em>merge</em> with it, to <em>capture</em> it as you’ve been captivated by it.</p>
<p>Creative types certainly know the experience of wanting to breathe beauty in and then exhale it as writing or photography, music, or speech. They want to <em>be</em> the beauty, or at least the <em>maker</em> of beauty. But as Virginia Wolff once said of our attempts to capture the beauty around us, “The senses are easily overwhelmed. Nature has given us six little pocket knives with which to cut up the body of a whale.”</p>

<p>The English polymath John Ruskin tells us we should try anyway, because the best way to “possess” beauty—and its accompanying benefits—is to understand it. And the best way to understand it is to either 1) try your hand at capturing it in a drawing or poem, regardless of whether you have any talent for it (the point isn’t learning to draw, but learning to <em>see</em>), or 2) to give thought to what it is about beauty that <em>moves</em> you, thus coming to understand what you love.</p>

<p>For instance, my contemplations on the beauty of nature have helped me understand that what moves me about it isn’t just awe or aesthetic pleasure but a kind of nostalgia, even homesickness. Perhaps it’s the paleolithic remembrance—the genetic memory—of <em>belonging</em> there, immersed and indistinguishable from the natural world. In the Native American O’odham language, the term for wildness is linked with the words for wholeness, health, and aliveness, and gazing at wildness feels like it confers similar benefits.</p>

<p>Gazing on ancient cities and ruins, too, confers on me an analogous benefit—it acts as a corrective, if not a rebuke, to the relative ugliness of the modern cities I’ve lived within honking distance of for most of my life.</p>
<p>Some years ago, for example, I spent a month in Italy, and Italy is an object lesson in a kind of beauty and ornateness largely gone from the world, a piercing contrast between the ravishing craftsmanship in stone, wood, and mosaic that graces its ancient buildings—reminding me what can happen when people build with eternity in mind—and the comparatively dreary and uninspired architecture of my own time.</p>

<p>And gazing at such beauty soothes not just my sense of aesthetics, but my sense of <em>perspective</em>. Standing in the Pincio Gardens at sunset and looking over the entirety of Rome, across millennia, puts life in perspective, helping me take my nose off the grindstone of day-to-day life and take in a bigger picture and a deeper sense of time.</p>

<p>And the magnificent ruins of the Roman Empire (or, frankly, even a simple display of dried flowers) remind me that death and beauty aren’t strangers to one another—they share a wall—and that mortality itself is a thing of beauty, in that it teaches me to have a deeper gratitude for life, a keener appreciation of its pleasures, and a greater commitment to keeping my priorities in order.</p>

<p>As Achilles says in the movie <em>Troy</em>, “The Gods envy us. They envy us because we're mortal, because any moment might be our last. Everything is more beautiful because we're doomed.”</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/passion/202602/the-health-benefits-of-looking-at-beauty" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/passion/202602/the-health-benefits-of-looking-at-beauty</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/passion/202602/the-health-benefits-of-looking-at-beauty</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Gregg Levoy]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-photo-12268359_0.jpeg.jpg?itok=5Qetv4kS" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Death of Romance?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/AllanFinal007C9crop_-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=MsreRqlZ" alt="Allan Roberts Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Mating</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Death of Romance?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why Gen-Z is not pursuing relationships.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Gen-Z is less involved in romantic activities than previous generations.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Anxiety undermines the development of relationships.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Online daters face too many choices and not enough (perceived) good ones.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Young men and women are drifting farther and farther apart politically.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>With the passing of another Valentine’s Day, a day which, for centuries, has served as an opportunity for couples to celebrate their love, it’s worth reflecting on the state of romantic love in our own age. Even a cursory examination of the state of romance today reveals a bleak picture. Marriage is at, or very near, an all-time low (StatRanker.org, 2025) and loneliness has reached epidemic proportions (Jeste, et al., 2020). Perhaps more disturbing, many young people are eschewing romantic involvement altogether. According to a 2025 poll by Rassmussen, 37% of single adults under 30 in the US report that they are “not interested” in dating at all. It appears that many young Americans have effectively given up on romance.</p>

<p>This begs the question of why so many young people would forego one of the most basic physical, social, and emotional human needs: an intimate relationship with a loving partner. The reasons, as is always the case with human behavior, are varied. Here are a few that may be particularly relevant.</p>
<p>More than anything, those in the Gen-Z generation are known for their high levels of anxiety (Drinko 2024) and for many in this generation, dating does not feel safe. Many of them suffer from extreme social anxiety and often avoid face-to-face, and even phone-to-phone, contact with strangers. This makes approaching potential partners in person difficult. (In addition to fears of rejection, some also voice concern over an in-person rejection being captured and posted online by observers, thus magnifying the humiliating experience.) This type of social anxiety may be why most young people prefer dating apps (Huang &amp; Gong, 2025) but online dating carries its own set of concerns. For example, dating apps are associated with elevated levels of emotional distress and appearance concerns in women (Cela &amp; Wood, 2026). The reality is, no matter how we do it, dating is stressful and always carries the risk of rejection. And because women tend to be more selective than men, and men usually initiate encounters, the risk of rejection is especially high for men. This may explain why there has been a greater decline in the number of men seeking relationships than women during the last few years (Gelles-Watnick, 2022).</p>

<p>In addition to elevated levels of anxiety, members of Gen-X also tend to be perfectionistic (Shafiq, Ali, &amp;, Iqbal, 2024). Within the context of relationships, this means they may be reluctant to “settle” for anyone who is not at least close to their ideal. Furthermore, since most mate selection now occurs through social media apps which allow for the viewing of literally hundreds of potential partners in a single sitting, that ideal is often unrealistically high as people extract the most positive traits from each individual to create a composite “ideal." Although most people tend to view many options as a good thing, research, such as that conducted by psychologist Barry Schwartz, points to the problems with having too many choices (Schwartz, 2000). It can lead to a form of psychological paralysis whereby we become overwhelmed by the sheer number of choices—and, importantly, it may also lead to lower levels of satisfaction than when we have fewer choices. Having many choices means that no matter what (or whom) we choose, we are prone to comparing it, sometimes unfavorably, to what we <em>didn’t </em>choose. Focusing on missed opportunities can, therefore, lead to a form of “buyer’s remorse." This can result in an endless quest for the “perfect” mate, while rejecting many highly eligible suitors whose primary flaw is they fail to match the pursuer's perfect and often completely unrealistic fantasy.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The problems don’t end with the failure to establish new relationships or the failure to maintain current ones. There is also evidence of a growing chasm, and mounting antipathy, between men and women in general. The sexes seem to be growing farther apart and, if social media posts are any indication, there is growing hostility between them. This phenomenon appears to be part of the broader political polarization that has swept the country in recent years. It is no secret that the country is more politically polarized the ever. What is less well known is that males and females increasingly fall on different sides of the political spectrum. In recent years, young males have been drifting to the right while young women have become increasingly progressive (Harvard Youth Poll<strong>, </strong>2024). This political divergence is impacting dating behavior. A 2019 study conducted by Pew found that 71% of Democrats stated that they “probably” or “definitely” would not seriously consider a serious relationship with someone who voted for President Trump. Given the growing political divide, this figure is probably even greater today. The echo chamber of social media promotes ever more extreme rhetoric on each side. Women wax about the oppressive patriarchy and the dreadful existence of a traditional housewife while many men are embracing the “tradwife” (traditional housewife) movement and condemning AWFUL (Affluent White Female Urban Liberal) women. Moreover, there is some evidence that the political differences between men and women are most pronounced around gender issues (Off, et al., 2025) which are the issues most likely to directly impact their romantic relationships. It is increasingly difficulty to see how we salvage this thing known as heterosexual romance.</p>

<p>Perhaps the answer doesn’t lie with individuals. The difficulties experienced by young would-be lovers may be a canary in the coal mine, a signal that something has gone deeply awry in our culture. Increased individualism, social isolation, unrealistic expectations, social media algorithms, and affordability concerns have all made dating and marriage feel like a high-cost, low-reward endeavor for Gen-Z. So, our most cautious generation feels well served by that long-held admonishment: “Marry in haste, repent at leisure.”</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/personality-in-relationships/202602/the-death-of-romance" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/personality-in-relationships/202602/the-death-of-romance</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/personality-in-relationships/202602/the-death-of-romance</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Allan Roberts Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/alexander-mass-H_-M3Hh6qGY-unsplash.jpg?itok=x1Jyz7L-" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Goodness Test: Dunk, Baelor, and Why Heroes Still Matter]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/ludmila_praslova.jpg?itok=ITnrgggg" alt="Ludmila N. Praslova, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Ethics and Morality</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Goodness Test: Dunk, Baelor, and Why Heroes Still Matter</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What "A Knight of the Seven Kingdoms" understands about human psychology.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">We have been told that goodness is naïve, that moral grayness is sophistication and cynicism is cleverness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Turns out, we still want an old-fashioned hero, and there are psychological reasons for it.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">"A Knight of the Seven Kingdoms" resonates with a human need for goodness and moral heroes.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Four criteria can help distinguish heroes from pretenders.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Publishing%20Passions%20and%20Practicalities%20%E2%80%9CSustainable%20scholarship%20for%20busy%20faculty%20is%20possible.%E2%80%9D%20(10).jpg?itok=IL3JVMvH" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="Generated with AI: DALL-E" alt="Generated with AI: DALL-E"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Generated with AI: DALL-E</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>A Knight of the Seven Kingdoms</em>, HBO’s new adaptation of George R.R. Martin's novellas,<sup>1</sup> has no dragons other than puppets and heraldry. Yet it has received 94% positive ratings on Rotten Tomatoes and became one of HBO’s most‑watched debuts.<sup>2,3</sup></p>
<p>Because who needs dragons when people are starved for decency? </p>

<p>For decades, we smallfolk have been told that goodness is naïve, that moral grayness is sophistication, and cynicism is cleverness.</p>
<p>Turns out, we do not want it.</p>
<p>Most of us can only take an endless string of villains, liars, and normalized nastiness for so long. Our battered nervous systems want a hero to root for who would not lie to us or betray us—and a show that does not overindulge in gore for the sake of gore, and darkness for the sake of darkness.</p>

<p>Call it naïve but this is what the human psyche is wired for. In a world that is already unstable, we are looking for believable goodness. Flawed, costly, non‑saccharine goodness that can nevertheless stand up to brutality. Goodness that may have to sleep under the stars, but has a working moral compass.</p>

<p>A hero is not just some “tired trope.” A hero serves a true psychological and cultural need of protecting others and providing moral examples. And when life is hard, we need heroes even more.</p>
<p>Of course, the moment moral hunger becomes visible, pretenders arrive to seize on it. Propaganda dresses up tyrants as heroes. Sophisticated performers demonstrate all the visible moves: the vulnerability display, the championing of sympathetic underdogs.</p>

<p>And that’s where <em>A Knight of the Seven Kingdoms</em> can help, too. Because it gives us vivid, memorable examples of what could constitute a test of true goodness and expose false heroes.</p>
<p>Following is the test to which I put two of the characters from <em>A Knight of the Seven Kingdoms</em> – the lead, a penniless young hedge knight, Sir Duncan the Tall (Dunk), and the viewers' favorite, Baelor Breakspear, Prince Baelor Targaryen, heir to the Iron Throne. I mostly rely on the first season of the adaptation, which closely follows the first novella,<sup>1 </sup>but refer to other books by Martin as necessary.<sup>4,5</sup></p>

<h2>The Goodness Test </h2>
<p><strong>1. Harm criterion: Do they refuse avoidable harm to the vulnerable?</strong></p>
<p>A good person isn’t someone who never causes damage, but someone who has a pattern of refusing deliberate harm and cruelty, even if cruelty is easier, safer, or more profitable.</p>
<ul>
<li>Duncan the Tall: Dunk’s default is not hurting people unless he absolutely has to, a pattern seen across his life. During the Trial of Seven, he even restrains himself from doing more damage than necessary to his main opponent, Aerion – in the heat of battle, and with Aerion being anything but innocent. <em>PASS</em></li>
<li>Baelor Breakspear: Baelor checks the cruelty in his own family. He chooses options that make fairness possible instead of rubber‑stamping his family members’ rage, when it would have been easier to let them punish the innocent. <em>PASS</em></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>2. Power criterion: Do they handle power with restraint and accountability? </strong></p>
<p>Power exposes people; it gives them more opportunities to treat others as objects. A “good enough” person uses formal and informal checks and restraints themselves.</p>
<ul>
<li>Duncan the Tall: Early on, his only power is his physical size and strength, and he uses it to protect others. As his power and position grow, he doesn’t pivot into bullying; he continues to serve as a shield for others. <em>PASS</em></li>
<li>Baelor Breakspear: In contrast to Dunk, Baelor was born a royal. As Hand of the King to his father, Daeron the Good, he is the second-most-powerful person in the realm. He uses that massive power to support peace, and, counterculturally, treats lowborn people like Dunk and Ser Arlan as humans with names, stories, and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/positively-different/202602/what-we-get-wrong-about-human-dignity">dignity</a>. <em>PASS</em></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>3. Cost criterion: What they’re willing to lose</strong></p>
<p>This one asks: Are they willing to pay real, personal costs to live by the values they claim? Do they pay the cost without using it to demand worship or building a martyr narrative?</p>
<ul>
<li>Duncan the Tall: He risks death, mutilation, and livelihood, over and over, for people and principles that do not guarantee him advancement; often quite the opposite. He walks away from lucrative offers because they would require him to become the sort of man he could not respect. <em>PASS</em></li>
<li>Baelor Breakspear: To give a chance to a fair trial, he puts on armor made for someone shorter and smaller than he is (his son Valarr) and joins the Trial of Seven, risking his body, paying the emotional and social cost of going against his family, and taking a political risk of his actions being twisted and misinterpreted. <em>PASS</em></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>4. Humility criterion: Do they see themselves accurately?</strong></p>
<p>Humility is the reality check the other three tests require to mean anything. Genuine humility isn't modesty or deference; those can be performances, too. It's an accurate assessment of your own reality, without inflation or self-punishment. It matters because you cannot see others clearly if your self-image requires <a href="https://ed.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/self_defense.pdf">constant protection</a>.</p>



  


<ul>
<li>Duncan the Tall: Dunk is humble almost constitutionally. He does not mistake himself for more than he is, which is precisely what makes his commitments real rather than performed.<em> PASS</em></li>
<li>Baelor Breakspear: He has every reason to lack humility— not just as a royal, but as someone genuinely accomplished, the best man in most rooms. And yet he subordinates himself to the Trial of Seven rather than making it his own narrative. He knows who he is; he doesn't need every situation to confirm it. <em>PASS</em></li>
</ul>

<h2>Why Pretenders Fail Where Heroes Pass</h2>
<p>The goodness test is not about sainthood. Neither Duncan nor Baelor is perfect. This is about patterns under pressure. A “good enough” person will fail these tests sometimes, but across a life, you can see if they engage in gratuitous harm or use power responsibly.</p>

<p>By this test, the usual “celebrity hero” propaganda collapses quickly. Would‑be saviors may pass for heroic on first glance because they talk about sacrifice, loyalty, and protection. But look at their patterns, and they fail: They punch down, abuse power, and demand everyone else pay the costs. They claim that what they do is not about themselves – but watch them be challenged by someone with a lower status, and the false humility mask falls off.</p>

<p>The heroes we need honor the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/positively-different/202602/what-we-get-wrong-about-human-dignity">dignity</a> of others. Shiny armor and dragons are optional.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/positively-different/202602/the-goodness-test-dunk-baelor-and-why-heroes-still-matter" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/positively-different/202602/the-goodness-test-dunk-baelor-and-why-heroes-still-matter</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/positively-different/202602/the-goodness-test-dunk-baelor-and-why-heroes-still-matter</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Ludmila N. Praslova, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Publishing%20Passions%20and%20Practicalities%20%E2%80%9CSustainable%20scholarship%20for%20busy%20faculty%20is%20possible.%E2%80%9D%20%2810%29.jpg?itok=GyRkdFzL" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Hidden Practices That Make Accountability Work]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-06/Janelle%20E%20Wells%20and%20Doreen%20MacAulay.png.jpg?itok=j_jqj1aU" alt="Janelle E. Wells, Ph.D., and Doreen MacAulay Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Leadership</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Hidden Practices That Make Accountability Work</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How 'feedforward' and growth mindset fuel continuous improvement.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A culture of accountability is shaped by the structures, systems, and support of leadership.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When expectations are clear and support is offered, accountability becomes a choice.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">With a feedforward approach and a growth mindset, leaders shift accountability from blame to development.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>“People just don’t follow through anymore.”</p>
<p>“No one takes ownership anymore.”</p>
<p>“Why can’t they do what they said they would do?”</p>
<p>While most leaders have said this, what if the problem isn’t a lack of discipline, motivation, or work ethic? What if the real issue is that leaders aren’t fully considering the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-invisible-work/202406/what-invisible-work-looks-like-in-the-21st-century">invisible work</a> of accountability? They ignore the behind‑the‑scenes structures, conversations, conditions, and mindsets that make accountability possible in the first place.</p>

<p>Accountability does not begin with correcting poor performance; it begins long before that, in the norms, expectations, and communication practices a leader creates. When you are a leader, accountability is never something that happens in isolation. Accountability cannot be demanded into existence. Instead, accountability is co-created through clarity, support, and <a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1186/s12909-023-04622-5.pdf?error=server_error">psychological safety</a>. For example, take a leader who is reprioritizing a report due this Friday and has an open conversation with the coordinator who has previously mishandled deadlines. The leader no longer sees laziness as a potential issue, as they’ve created the open space, and the coordinator expressed the three competing priorities and asked for clarity on which mattered most.</p>

<p>Situations like this are where the concepts of <a href="https://www.marshallgoldsmith.com/post/try-feedforward-instead-of-feedback">feedforward</a>, a concept developed by Marshall Goldsmith as a future‑focused alternative to feedback, and growth mindset, developed by Carol Dweck, become essential. Both emphasize learning, continuous improvement, and forward progress rather than dwelling on blame or past mistakes.</p>

<p>To make sense of accountability, it helps to return to the basic definition: being responsible for your actions and decisions, and following through on your commitments. But for leaders, this definition becomes incomplete. Leadership accountability is not just about holding others responsible; it is also about creating the conditions in which others can be responsible. You must ensure that structures, systems, support, and expectations are shaped in ways that make accountability realistic, not aspirational.</p>

<h2>Accountability Needs a System</h2>
<p>Leaders must go beyond the surface-level expectation of “Tell them what to do, and they should do it.” Expectation without support is not accountability. It’s wishful thinking. And hope is not a system. The invisible work of accountability requires leaders to ask themselves:</p>

<ul>
<li>Does this person have the time to do what I’m asking?</li>
<li>Do they have the resources?</li>
<li>Do they have authority or decision rights?</li>
<li>Do they understand the why, the how, and the desired outcome?</li>
<li>Do they know which trade-offs are acceptable?</li>
<li>Do they feel safe raising concerns or asking for clarification? </li>
</ul>
<p>When these underlying conditions are absent, accountability breaks down. You may see delays, excuses, avoidance, or inconsistent performance. These, however, are not causes of problems; they are symptoms. When systems are unclear or poorly designed, people will find ways to work around them, often unintentionally. They may avoid taking ownership because it feels risky. They may blame “the system,” other departments, bureaucracy, or unclear expectations because, from their perspective, those barriers are real. And in many cases, they are right.</p>

<p>Many employees are asked to complete tasks or make decisions without having the time, authority, or resources they need to be successful. A person cannot be accountable for something they do not have the means to accomplish. Yet, in workplaces where psychological safety is low, employees may not feel comfortable saying, “I don’t have what I need,” or “This deadline is not realistic.” </p>

<p>When employees do not feel safe raising these concerns, leaders become unintentionally complicit in the breakdown of accountability. If they don’t feel like they can come to you, then you are just as liable as they are for the outcome. Accountability becomes compromised not because people don’t care, but because the environment does not support honesty, transparency, or dialogue.</p>

<h2>Accountable Leaders Clear the Path</h2>
<p>A leader’s role is not simply to assign work but to clear the path. You must scan for obstacles, anticipate barriers, and remove friction that keeps people from doing their best work. This includes structural barriers (e.g., processes, workload, resource constraints), interpersonal barriers (e.g., fear of conflict, disappointing others), and cultural barriers (e.g., an outdated belief that questioning authority is punishable). Leaders who overlook these elements create a mismatch between what is promised and what is delivered. Not out of lack of effort, but out of misalignment.</p>



  


<p>Creating a culture of open communication, trust, and clarity requires intentional action. It will not emerge on its own. Two powerful tools that support this culture are feedforward and growth mindset.</p>
<p>Goldsmith’s feedforward approach shifts the focus from what went wrong in the past to what can be done differently in the future. It redirects the conversation toward possibilities, opportunities, and actionable next steps. Instead of saying, “You didn’t meet the deadline,” a feedforward approach includes verbiage like, “For the next project, let’s discuss what support or resources you’ll need to deliver on time.” This reduces defensiveness and increases collaboration. It keeps accountability productive rather than punitive.</p>

<p>Growth mindset, based on Dweck’s research, reinforces the idea that abilities and skills are not fixed traits but can be developed through effort, feedback, and learning. When leaders adopt a growth mindset, they approach accountability conversations with curiosity rather than judgment. They ask questions like:</p>

<ul>
<li>“What got in the way?”</li>
<li>“What did you learn from this?”</li>
<li>“How can we set this up for success next time?” </li>
</ul>
<p>This shifts accountability from a moment of blame to a moment of development. It encourages people to take ownership of mistakes, not because they fear punishment, but because they feel supported in learning from them.</p>

<h2>Accountability Is Shared</h2>
<p>Creating the right conditions doesn't offset personal responsibility. Accountability is shared. It’s up to leaders to create the environment and individuals to choose how they show up in it. Psychological safety isn’t permission to not fulfill commitments without consequences. A growth mindset doesn’t mean standards are lowered. Feedforward doesn’t replace clear expectations.</p>

<p>When expectations are clear and support is offered, accountability becomes a choice. At that point, patterns of missed commitments are no longer systemic; they are behavioral. And behavior can and should be addressed directly.</p>
<p>In the end, accountability is not about catching people doing something wrong. It is about creating an environment where people can do things right. It is about making the invisible visible: the conversations, the expectations, the resources, the psychological safety, and the mindset that allow people to show up fully and take true ownership of their work. When leaders understand and invest in this invisible work, follow-through improves, trust strengthens, and performance becomes not just an expectation but a shared commitment.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-invisible-work/202602/the-hidden-practices-that-make-accountability-work" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-invisible-work/202602/the-hidden-practices-that-make-accountability-work</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-invisible-work/202602/the-hidden-practices-that-make-accountability-work</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Janelle E. Wells, Ph.D., and Doreen MacAulay, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-yankrukov-7640467.jpg?itok=RMZxratH" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>