<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 14:51:14 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 14:51:14 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are You Constantly Monitoring Your Partner’s Mood?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/-4_10.jpg?itok=UGPhgN-_" alt="Stephanie A. Sarkis Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Emotional Labor</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Are You Constantly Monitoring Your Partner’s Mood?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How hypervigilance becomes part of emotional labor.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Constant mood monitoring is a form of emotional labor.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Hypervigilance is a survival mechanism often started in unpredictable families of origin.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">You are not responsible for managing another adult's emotional state.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In healthy relationships, partners initiate communication when there is an issue.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/stocksnap-happy-valentines-day-2603521_1920_0.jpg?itok=giz9vhIw" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Monitoring your partner's moods is a form of emotional labor. " title="StockSnap / Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption">Monitoring your partner's moods is a form of emotional labor.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: StockSnap / Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Emotional labor comprises various behaviors meant to regulate a relationship and anticipate a partner’s needs. Sometimes emotional labor includes monitoring and anticipating your partner’s moods and reactions in order to keep the relationship running smoothly. </p>
<h2>What Emotional Monitoring Looks Like</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Emotional monitoring is the ongoing habit of scanning another person’s feelings and adjusting yourself in response. It is part of emotional labor in a relationship. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Ask yourself if you do any of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Check your partner’s tone and nonverbal cues to see if something is wrong</li>
<li dir="ltr">Replay conversations to see if you upset your partner</li>
<li dir="ltr">Change your behavior to prevent conflict</li>
<li dir="ltr">Feel responsible for keeping things calm</li>
<li dir="ltr">Repeatedly ask your partner, “Are you okay?”</li>
</ul>
<p>At first, monitoring feels like caring. You may equate monitoring with attentiveness or support. You may have even learned from an early age that being very focused on the other person’s moods is what a good partner does. But over time, it becomes exhausting.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Why Some People Monitor More Than Others</h2>
<p dir="ltr">If you grew up in a home where people had unpredictable moods, you may have learned to monitor or scan for potential danger. Anticipating your parents’ moods may have helped keep you safe. </p>
<p dir="ltr">You learned to:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Notice shifts early</li>
<li dir="ltr">Fix problems fast</li>
<li dir="ltr">Keep things steady</li>
<li dir="ltr">Stay quiet and small</li>
<li dir="ltr">Deny your needs</li>
</ul>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Those skills may have helped you survive childhood. But in adult relationships, they can turn into you being overly responsible. You may react to any mood changes and prepare accordingly.</p>
<h2>The Cost of Hypervigilance</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Constant emotional monitoring can cause you to feel anxiety and fear. Even small changes in your partner’s mood can feel overwhelming. When you sense something might be wrong, you may experience:</p>

<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Tightness in your chest</li>
<li dir="ltr">Racing thoughts</li>
<li dir="ltr">Catastrophic thoughts</li>
<li dir="ltr">Trouble relaxing</li>
<li dir="ltr">Fear of saying the wrong thing</li>
<li dir="ltr">Difficulty enjoying the present moment</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr">Instead of feeling connected, you feel on guard or hypervigilant. When you constantly monitor, your relationship becomes unbalanced. You may feel resentful that you are doing the emotional labor of your relationship.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In healthy relationships, both partners notice mood shifts and talk about them directly. In unbalanced relationships, one partner does most of the monitoring and emotional labor.</p>
<p dir="ltr">If your partner is quiet, you ask what is wrong. If there is tension, you start a conversation to fill the silence. If something feels off, you repair it. Over time, your partner may, consciously or unconsciously, rely on you to regulate the relationship.</p>

<h2>What Happens When You Stop Monitoring</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Monitoring can feel productive. You tell yourself that if you can predict your partner’s mood shift, maybe you can prevent conflict. If you manage your words carefully, maybe you can avoid distance.</p>
<p dir="ltr">But you cannot control another adult’s emotions. Trying to monitor your partner keeps you anxious and gives you a false sense of control. It also prevents your partner from taking equal responsibility.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">If you stop scanning and monitoring your partner’s moods and behaviors, you may feel uncomfortable at first.</p>
<p dir="ltr">You may worry:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">“What if something is wrong?”</li>
<li dir="ltr">“What if I miss something?”</li>
<li dir="ltr">“What if they think I don’t care?”</li>
</ul>
<p>But stepping back allows something important to happen. You give your partner space to:</p>

<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Name their own feelings</li>
<li dir="ltr">Bring up their own concerns</li>
<li dir="ltr">Initiate repair</li>
<li dir="ltr">Take emotional responsibility</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr">If your partner doesn’t respond when you step back, it can feel distressing. However, it is important to have that clarity.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">Moving Away From Monitoring</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Even small changes in monitoring behavior can help your well-being. </p>



  


<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Pause before asking if something is wrong. It’s your partner’s responsibility to share how they’re feeling.</li>
<li dir="ltr">Remember that normal mood shifts don’t constitute an emergency.</li>
<li dir="ltr">When you find yourself monitoring your partner’s moods, shift your focus to how you are feeling.</li>
<li dir="ltr">Pay attention to patterns. Does your partner initiate conversation or affection when you take a step back from monitoring?</li>
<li dir="ltr">Speak to a licensed mental health professional about monitoring and emotional labor in your relationship. </li>
</ul>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">It is possible to be present without monitoring your relationship. It may feel uncomfortable, and even scary, to back away from monitoring at first, but it can improve your quality of life.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In an emotionally healthy relationship, you don’t feel the need to constantly monitor. Your partner speaks to you if they are having an issue. When there is a disagreement, there are mutual apologies and a plan to get things back on track. You are not expected to bear the weight of the relationship. There is a mutual initiation of conversations, plans, and physical affection. In a healthy relationship, your partner wouldn’t want you to be subjecting yourself to monitoring.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Healthy intimacy doesn’t require monitoring. Monitoring may make you feel temporarily safe, but it is preventing you from having a mutually fulfilling relationship.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>Copyright 2026 Sarkis Media LLC</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/here-there-and-everywhere/202602/are-you-constantly-monitoring-your-partners-mood" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/here-there-and-everywhere/202602/are-you-constantly-monitoring-your-partners-mood</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/here-there-and-everywhere/202602/are-you-constantly-monitoring-your-partners-mood</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie A. Sarkis Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/stocksnap-happy-valentines-day-2603521_1920.jpg?h=2ca2db45&amp;itok=wY0sq5sv" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Can Spirituality Improve Relationships?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/kensilvestri_05-15-19_074_1_-removebg.jpg?itok=vYsrsbmO" alt="Kenneth Silvestri Ed.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Spirituality</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Can Spirituality Improve Relationships?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: A segue to better understanding each other.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>"There is in us an instinct for newness, for renewal, for a liberation of creative power...To be born again is not to become somebody else, but to become ourselves" -Thomas Merton</p>
<p>"Be the change that you wish to see in the world" -Mahatma Gandhi</p>
<p><br>Since the map is not the territory, it is essential to distinguish spirituality from religion, as it is usually understood. This is especially important when looking at its positive influence on relationships. Asta Kallo writes about a recent Pew Research Center Survey indicating how "Americans are far more likely to say they have become more spiritual rather than becoming more religious." Cultural anthropologists have long described how relationships can manifest in stressful ways. Religion itself doesn't always allow for flexibility in resolving relational problems and mostly creates a dependency on conformity. This can also be seen in certain cults that appear to be religious. However, in contrast, how we communicate with our own uniqueness, as is the case with each snowflake, is the core of our relational spirituality.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/heart-to-heart.jpg?itok=HUwt3Kda" width="320" height="427" data-insert-type="image" alt="&quot;Heart to Heart&quot;" title="(c) with permission, NatashaRabin.com"></div>
<div class="caption">"Heart to Heart"</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: (c) with permission, NatashaRabin.com</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><br>This occurs in the space in-between us where we could communicate fully. It is a transitional win-win place that can go to exciting depths and profound possibilities. When this occurs, we enter the spiritual realm of how we can interact with a hint of simultaneity to something larger, i.e., our environment, community, and its many institutions that educate. Spirituality becomes what creates an understanding of how we are all interdependently connected.<br><br>Regardless of the security that can accompany a commitment to a religious doctrine, the downside can be the exclusion of other beliefs or agnostic views. Thankfully, there are examples of "mystical" frameworks within all religions that supersede dependency on exclusive indoctrination. Individuals such as Thomas Merton, Martin Buber, Shunryu Suzuki, and Zain Hashmi to mention a few are examples of this. The energy of spirituality, especially in 2026, is getting a boost from the major sects in the United States including the celebration of the lunar New Year, as they begin their fasting rituals and meditative periods simultaneously.<br><br>This is an unusual and positive opportunity to cultivate a collective side by side, people-to-people mutual sharing of the religious commonalities that can lead to a more universal spiritual Intimacy without any institutional restrictions. It is a time when the valuable global objectives that all religions have for the good of humanity are articulated; however, what follows the rituals is not always a continuation of the harmonious sharing that once-a-year events can achieve.<br><br>How can that level of collective non sectarian spirituality be sustained? The commonality that can emerge from these rituals could benefit relationships year-round. There are many similar beliefs that thread through the major religions available to be a catalyst for the enduring essence of spiritualism. One does not have to be part of a fasting ritual to feel the energy that beckons spirituality, it can be available to all.<br><br>After the fasting is over, forums can and should be organized to discuss the different contexts to explore common basic needs relevant to our lives, such as family, community, economics, media, schooling, etc. This will extend to ways to consider how tending to the needs of others can occur. This exercise will foster a shared sense of what it means to be human. It also reveals how it is to be yourself in relationships.<br><br>If you look deeper, you'll see that all religions encourage us to share values despite recognizing differences. They emphasize similarities such as the desire for peace, justice, and community service. Personal and communal growth often leads to profound mutuality in regards to relationships, underscoring the importance of fostering a spirit of empathy and altruism.<br><br>The source of these efforts, although seemingly wholesome, do in certain cases still exhibit gender and diversity discrimination as well as unequal distribution of power and enforcement. However, to create a more peaceful and connected world, what is needed is to highlight without constraints the needed humanity to influence reforms that respect all, whether within a given religion or without one. This process of articulating the common needs and patterns that connect offer hope for a true process of spirituality. It not only recognizes our common needs but also understands our interdependence.</p>

<h2><br><br>Suggestions and prompts to help tend to and understand the needs of others <br> </h2>
<p>In all your relationships, pledge to be an active listener, with non-judgmental communication and a win-win format to understand others and their inner worlds.</p>
<p><br>Regularly engage in shared aesthetic spiritual activities, such as nature walks, gratitude journaling, Aikido, Tai Chi, Yoga meditation, Qicong, music, etc.</p>

<p>Discuss the impact of the educational process regarding our youth including the future of technology and A I.<br><br>Support collaborative spiritual growth individually and with others.<br><br>Encourage and understand others' unique spiritual journeys.<br><br>Actively work on being forgiving, ridding yourself of resentment without condoning or minimizing past hurts.<br><br>Discuss with another or others how spirituality is about the right relationship between ourselves and something larger.<br><br>Discuss what Thomas Merton believed about the importance of silence, and authentic self-discovery being "the possibilities and challenges offered by the present moment, and to embrace them with courage, faith, and hope."<br><br>In a small group, share what you feel Martin Buber meant by "the world is not comprehensible, but it is embraceable through the embracing of one of its beings." Also, what do you think was the message in his sense of “I and Thou” compared to “I and it”.<br><br>Share what comes to your mind regarding what Shunryu Suzuki means by having a beginner's mind, where there are "many possibilities, but in the expert's mind there are few”.<br><br>According to Zain Hashmi, poetry, aestheticism, and the dissolution of the ego lead to the idea that "Happiness comes from helping others, by being with others, and by sharing, even if it's only a smile." How can this be manifested in your relationships and group discussions?<br><br><strong>Final word:</strong><br><br>What I have found to be the most common theme coming from the major religions when stripped of their opposing doctrines is to listen and learn from others without judgment. This is the essence of being spiritual which is to be empathetic and altruistic as you experience and respect all the interdependent contexts we travel through in our lives. This is spiritualism and how it can improve relationships with others and nature.<br><br><br><br> </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-wider-lens/202602/how-can-spirituality-improve-relationships" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-wider-lens/202602/how-can-spirituality-improve-relationships</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-wider-lens/202602/how-can-spirituality-improve-relationships</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kenneth Silvestri Ed.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/heart-to-heart.jpg?itok=0qHmJ5xh" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>