<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 02:10:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 02:10:33 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Importance of Safe Spaces in Fandom]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/zubernis-c.jpg?itok=zr1Hku_f" alt="Lynn Zubernis Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Media</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Importance of Safe Spaces in Fandom</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">"Heated Rivalry" fans get media attention — and an invitation to the Cottage.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Fandoms are communities, providing a safe space for fans to express their real selves, feelings, and desires.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Genuine interaction within fandom provides what Yalom called "disconfirmation of uniqueness."</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Outsiders who are unaware of fandom norms can violate expectations of privacy which threaten that safety.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">"Heated Rivalry" fans can now experience the benefits of fan tourism by "coming to the Cottage" from the show.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/surprising_media%20pixabay.jpg?itok=J1oYnQrk" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" title="Surprising_Media/Pixabay" alt="Surprising_Media/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Surprising_Media/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>This blog has weighed in before on the popularity of <em>Heated Rivalry</em>, the runaway hit series about Shane and Ilya, professional hockey players turned lovers, and why so many viewers are passionate fans of the show. The series has continued to be popular, with constant media coverage of stars Hudson Williams and Connor Storrie. For fans, that coverage has been welcome, providing plenty of new content, interviews, photos and videos to nourish an active fandom. As with any other group of humans, there have been disagreements within the fandom, from intrusive theorizing about the actors’ real life relationships and identities to thoughtful discussions of racism to less in-depth arguments about abs and fashion choices. This week, however, the <em>Heated Rivalry</em> fandom came together over a unique opportunity and a controversial <a href="https://www.vulture.com/article/heated-rivalry-fujoshi-fan-fiction.html"><em>New York Magazine</em> article</a>.</p>

<p>Both caused emotional reactions in fans; one with varied opinions and one with a more uniform positive response – and both are examples of the importance of safe spaces in fandom.</p>
<p>From the outside, it may seem surprising that the article in <em>New York Magazine</em>’s "Vulture" drew so much negative response from <em>Heated Rivalry</em> fans. To understand why, it’s important to realize that fandom is first and foremost a community. It has a shared lexicon that includes in-jokes and rapidly evolving language that would be difficult to keep up with from the outside. Like any community, it has norms and values and standards of behavior. Fandom is also a marginalized community, perhaps less so now than twenty years ago, but still outside the mainstream and frequently ridiculed for being too passionate, too invested, too hyperfocused, too <em>much</em>. One of the benefits of fandom is the permission to love what you love, however much you love it, and celebrate that with a group of people who share your passion. When that is something considered frivolous – like a television show or a romance novel -- too much investment in something that is not "work and family" can be looked at as subtly dangerous in a society that emphasizes constant productivity.</p>

<p>Fans are aware of that subtle criticism, so fandom communities have historically tended to be insular and boundaried. Within the community, because it feels protected from outside judgment, fans can express their authentic feelings, fears, creativity – and yes, desires – more openly, providing an opportunity for validation and connection. What Irvin Yalom called the "disconfirmation of uniqueness," which is so powerful for people, can happen in any group, but only if the person is sharing their real self. For fan communities whose members are mostly women, the space to be “real” may feel like a rare and important aspect of life. This applies to the <em>Heated Rivalry</em> fandom, as the article made clear, though not all the show’s fans are women and certainly not all are straight women.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>This week’s <em>Heated Rivalry</em> article, which promised to answer the question “Why are so many women losing their minds over gay smut?” put a spotlight on the community, which made it more visible to outsiders and less protected and left many fans upset. Although some were not happy that it was an article about women's interests written by a man, more took issue with the characterization of fans’ passion for <em>Heated Rivalry</em> as a “mass-psychosis event,” a pathologizing description that was familiar to fans, going all the way back to descriptions of the “hysterical female fans” of the Beatles. Fans were also not pleased with their love of the series reduced to being solely about gay smut, which minimized the show’s quality, the uplifting message about queer love, and that the series is based on a book in the wildly popular Romance genre. Fans responded with accusations that once again something that appeals to women was being belittled solely because it <em>does</em> appeal to women, with the assumption that the content in question must somehow be frivolous.</p>

<p>While writer E. Alex Jung did his research, he also was not a part of the fandom he was writing about, and may not have understood the community’s norms or why those were so important. The article included examples of <em>Heated Rivalry</em> fanfiction and linked directly to those fanworks, making them visible to people outside the community. When fans post fanfiction to a website like Archive of Our Own, which was founded as a repository for whatever fans want to write about, the expectation is that only other fans will be reading it. Having fanfiction directly linked in a major publication was a violation of some of fandom’s most important norms. The magazine responded to fan outcry and has since de-linked the fanworks, but fans criticized the publication for shining an unwanted spotlight on one of the only safe spaces for women, who are so frequently shamed for their interests and passions.</p>

<p>The other mainstream media mention of <em>Heated Rivalry</em> this week, on the other hand, has been a universally welcome one. Yesterday, a new and exciting opportunity opened up – Airbnb announced that fans will be able to book a vacation at the Barlochan Cottage in Canada that was featured in the series. </p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/airbnb%20ig.jpg?itok=_XSqy2IV" width="320" height="389" data-insert-type="image" title="Airbnb/Instagram" alt="Airbnb/Instagram"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Airbnb/Instagram</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p> I’ve written before here about the benefits of fan tourism and why immersing yourself in the fictional world that you love can be so much fun – fans can feel like part of the story that they have strong emotional ties to. <em>Heated Rivalry</em> fans are about to do just that, with even the furniture from the show remaining the same, making it easy to picture Ilya and Shane right there. Fans can leave their everyday stresses behind and just play in the familiar location, connecting them to the fictional characters they love.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>For <em>Heated Rivalry</em> fans, sharing a trip to that iconic location can be another safe space in which to interact and share genuine feelings without fear of judgment. </p>
<p>Starting March 1, it seems likely that many fans will be eager to say “I’m coming to the Cottage”. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-science-of-fandom/202602/the-importance-of-safe-spaces-in-fandom" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-science-of-fandom/202602/the-importance-of-safe-spaces-in-fandom</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-science-of-fandom/202602/the-importance-of-safe-spaces-in-fandom</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Lynn Zubernis Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/surprising_media%20pixabay.jpg?itok=tWaN0T5g" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Body Love Isn’t Required for Eating Disorder Recovery]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/Jennifer%20Rollin%20%283%29.png.jpg?itok=0Emr24Dp" alt="Jennifer Rollin MSW, LCSW-C" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Eating Disorders</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Body Love Isn’t Required for Eating Disorder Recovery</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Body compassion is often a better path to recovery from an eating disorder.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The reality is that our bodies will change over time.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It is imperative to treat your body with compassion, regardless of how you feel about its appearance is key.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The concept of ‘body love’ can feel unattainable.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article_inline_full">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_full_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_full_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/happywomen.jpeg.jpg?itok=GfAMg02K" width="639" height="426" data-insert-type="image" title="Pexels: Free to Use" alt="Pexels: Free to Use"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pexels: Free to Use</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">As an eating disorder therapist, I know that many individuals in eating disorder recovery feel like they have to work to ‘love the appearance of their body.’ </p>
<p dir="ltr">This is far from the truth for a variety of reasons. Feeling like you have to work to ‘love your body’ is a lot of pressure that can cause people to feel hopeless and even give up when it comes to eating disorder recovery. The following are a few reasons and some research, which suggests that a far better goal is body compassion. </p>

<ol>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Our bodies change over time, so attaching our self worth to our appearance is akin to boarding a sinking ship.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">The reality is that our bodies will change over time. Skin will sag, wrinkles will form, body shape and size often changes. Thus, attaching your sense of self-worth to something that is only bound to keep changing is utterly unhelpful.</p>

<ol start="2">
<li dir="ltr"><strong>You can treat your body with compassion and respect, regardless of how you feel about its appearance.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">Learning how to treat your body with compassion and respect, regardless of how you feel about its appearance is a key skill that I work with clients on in therapy. The emotions that we feel more generally and about our bodies also fluctuate throughout the day. Therefore, if we are only compassionate towards our body when we are feeling great about the way that it looks, this is problematic.</p>

<p dir="ltr">If you had a beloved dog that hadn’t been groomed in a while and you didn’t love how his fur looked, would you treat them with less compassion and care? Likely, the answer to that is no. The way that you treat your body should not be conditional on how you feel about its appearance. If this is something that you struggle with, it’s indicative that this is important to work on.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<ol start="3">
<li dir="ltr"><strong>For some people struggling with eating disorders, language around ‘body love’ can feel invalidating.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">For individuals who deal with chronic illness and chronic pain, messaging like ‘be grateful for your body's function” or “focus on loving your body” can fall flat. Additionally, for survivors of trauma or really anyone who doesn’t resonate with a message of ‘body love’ this language can feel both invalidating and unhelpful. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Further, the concept of ‘body love’ can feel unattainable for some when they are currently bogged down in body hatred.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Eating disorder recovery is about connecting to your true values and reclaiming your life-not necessarily about needing to ‘love your reflection at all times.’</strong></li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">I always say that the aim is to work to live a life that is meaningful and in alignment with your true values, not necessarily to love the appearance of our body. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Rather, the intention is to have the appearance of your body take up less real estate in your mind, as well as to treat your body and yourself with compassion. </p>
<h2>What The Research Says</h2>
<p dir="ltr">In the <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC12683921/?utm_">Journal of Eating Disorders 2025</a>, a qualitative study was conducted to explore how people in recovery or recovered from eating disorders experienced body compassion.</p>


<p dir="ltr">The study found that practicing compassion towards one’s body was crucial when it came to sustained eating disorder recovery.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Body compassion in this study was defined as developing a caring relationship towards one’s body that wasn’t dependent on appearance. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Participants of the study emphasized that it is challenging to recover without practicing body compassion. Thus, it seemed to be an integral aspect to the participants recovery.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>How This Is Important In Clinical Practice</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Shifting focus as therapists from a focus on ‘body love’ to one of ‘body compassion,’ while also helping clients to connect to their true values is key in eating disorder treatment.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Many individuals with eating disorders also have a harsh inner critic so in addition to body compassion, it’s helpful to work on self-compassion as a whole.</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Pushing a narrative of ‘body love,’ may also turn some people away from eating disorder recovery, particularly those with co-morbid chronic illness.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Eating disorder recovery is not about loving your reflection, but about choosing compassion and care so you can live a fuller more values-driven life.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/body-love-isnt-required-for-eating-disorder-recovery" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/body-love-isnt-required-for-eating-disorder-recovery</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/body-love-isnt-required-for-eating-disorder-recovery</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jennifer Rollin MSW, LCSW-C]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/happywomen.jpeg.jpg?itok=5UC87yaG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[If Aristotle Was Your Marriage Therapist]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/screen_shot_2020-03-06_at_1.39.24_pm.jpg?itok=I5G1dZy-" alt="Jason Whiting Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Marriage</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">If Aristotle Was Your Marriage Therapist</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How practicing virtues strengthens intimate relationships from the inside out.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Marriage problems are less often skill deficits, but a disconnection from virtues.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The “golden rule” perspective shift helps partners examine their own impact within the relationship.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Virtues such as loyalty and gratitude are not fixed traits but habits strengthened through repeated choices.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Strong marriages are built by practicing virtue daily, not by waiting for feelings to improve.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>It was a tense session with clients I will call Steve and Leticia. They were <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202512/4-tips-to-stop-fighting-and-be-friends">arguing</a> over who had hurt the other more, and I was struggling to help Steve see beyond his own perspective. I asked him, “If you woke up tomorrow as Leticia, what would it be like to be married to you?” He paused as he considered how she had been burned by the many times he had been checked out while he was tangled in <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202505/when-the-game-plays-you-how-online-gaming-becomes-a-compulsion">addiction</a>. The question is designed to promote unselfish self-reflection, and it is also Aristotelian.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/richardsdrawings-philosopher-8206757_1920%20(1).jpg?itok=tCn5rCkq" width="320" height="427" data-insert-type="image" title="RichardsDrawings/Pixabay" alt="RichardsDrawings/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: RichardsDrawings/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>More than two thousand years ago, Aristotle argued that the good life is built through practicing virtue. Not in a moralistic or religious sense, but as a matter of making choices to benefit relationships or humanity. Aristotle suggests that the best intimate relationships are not simply a byproduct of chemistry or compatibility. They are the fruit of both people being their best self. The ancient philosopher turned therapist would tell us that strong marriages are not found, they are formed.</p>

<p>This question for Steve was a variation on the “golden rule,” which emphasizes treating others how you want to be treated. This principle is so fundamental to human relations that at least twenty-one of the world’s major religions have some variation of it as a core teaching. How do <em>you</em> want to be treated? That is your starting place for deciding how to treat your mate. This question is about virtue, not skill. Some therapy interventions emphasize skills, like using active listening or I-messages. But these are insufficient without virtues like kindness and patience backing them up.</p>

<p>Attributes such as fairness and humility are not fixed traits that some have and others don’t, but muscles that can be strengthened. Couples almost always are their best self when they are getting to know each other. They show understanding, forgive each other, and are patient. But too often, after marriage partners allow their virtue biceps to go soft. They get busy with other things or become complacent.</p>

<p>To stay strong, couples need to intentionally choose good attitudes and actions. Aristotle argued that virtues involve actions, but also feelings, and these are cultivated through repeated choices to do right.<sup> </sup> Aristotle said that to be good, is not, as Kant was to later argue, to go against our nature, but it is our nature — our cultivated nature. We become good through persistently choosing to be good, like showing kindness and unselfishness. But Aristotle did admit: “It is no easy task to be good.”<sup> </sup> But it is worth it, since relationships grow as partners continue to try. With Steve and Leticia we focused on two key virtues: loyalty and gratitude.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Loyalty</h2>
<p>Being loyal is a virtue that keeps partners feeling safe. During their marriage <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202301/your-fight-or-flight-reflex-and-your-relationship">struggles</a>, Leticia had been confiding in a male friend at work. She <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202109/why-partners-lie-to-each-other-so-much">didn’t tell</a> Steve, and she excused this because she was still furious about Steve’s debts occurred from his sports gambling. As Steve <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202112/the-one-essential-ingredient-for-a-happy-relationship">took responsibility </a>for his lapses and worked on recovery, she told him what she had done. He was stung, but appreciated her honesty, and this helped him work harder. They became more vigilant in how they talked about their marriage with their friends and family. Leticia also helped their son become more loyal in his new marriage. He had been making jokes about his wife’s cooking and teasing her in front of the family. Leticia told him his first priority was his spouse, and he needed to show this in his actions.</p>

<h2>Gratitude</h2>
<p>Partners have an amazing capacity for taking each other for granted. In most relationships, there are all kinds of things to be happy about; why else would people partner up? But often, couples stop thinking about their strengths and instead become complacent. One comedian was discussing how quickly people become entitled and ungrateful. He was on an airplane where they offered high speed internet for the first time. People tried it and it was great. He said: “And then it breaks down. They apologize and the guy next to me says, ‘Pfffff! This is $#@*!’ Like, how quickly the world owes him something he knew existed only 10 seconds ago!”</p>


<p>Like the ungrateful flyer, couples can take each other for granted; but being grateful pays off. Research has found that appreciative words increase relationship commitment and stability, and expressing gratitude is the most consistent, significant predictor of happy marriages. Scholars have found that grateful words to a spouse inject enjoyable feelings that persist until the next day and decrease the odds of breaking up. It feels good to be grateful, and it is nice to be appreciated. Steve and Leticia started noticing even the small things the other did, and this benefited both.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Exercising virtues does not take specialized training. As Aristotle realized millennia ago, it is a matter of commitment. When people come for couples therapy, it isn’t usually because they need to learn a technical skill; it is because they have gotten disconnected from their best self. Steve and Leticia worked hard, and as Steve said, “We are better than we have ever been. We are more unified, more open. It feels like a real partnership instead of two people who are just dealing with each other.” When couples seek what is best for the other, they create unity and also benefit themselves. If Aristotle were leading this couple therapy session, he would say this is what virtue looks like in action. Not perfection, but practice.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202602/if-aristotle-was-your-marriage-therapist" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202602/if-aristotle-was-your-marriage-therapist</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-lies-and-conflict/202602/if-aristotle-was-your-marriage-therapist</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Whiting Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/richardsdrawings-philosopher-8206757_1920%20%281%29.jpg?itok=U43_ZkBs" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Value of True Crime]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Katherine-Ramsland.jpg?itok=GhjYqfVB" alt="Katherine Ramsland Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Law and Crime</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Value of True Crime</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Horror psychologist dissects our cultural fixation on criminal cases.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Evolutionary psychology explains true crime fascination as a species survival response.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Criminal cases teach us how to identify and manage predatory threats.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Yet the theory fails to address why the most successful predators still thwart our efforts.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_0283.JPG.jpg?itok=T7rlZMzm" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by K. Ramsland" alt="Photo by K. Ramsland"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by K. Ramsland</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>Werewolf</em> is a multi-player “social deduction” game that pits an informed minority of predators (werewolves) against an uninformed majority (villagers). The purpose is to uncover hidden roles through dialogue, reasoning, and detection. The “good” team must identify and eliminate those who intend them harm, while the “bad” team aims to stay hidden so they can pick off the villagers. The werewolves’ best strategy involves deceptive bonding with villagers to deflect objective analysis.</p>

<p>And that’s how successful predators operate in real life: they blend in, befriend, and deceive so no one suspects what they intend.</p>
<p>Dr. Coltan Scrivner, an expert on the psychology of horror, discusses this game in his intriguing new book, <em>Morbid Curiosity</em>. He argues that interest in what’s scary and macabre is good for us because it helps us to identify threats and practice an effective response to them. He defines morbid curiosity as “that peculiar feeling of fascination that motivates us to face fear, disgust, and the unknown,” then supports his stance via the logic of evolutionary psychology. However, one part seems incomplete. </p>

<p>Scrivner says that <em>bad</em> hooks us more forcefully than <em>good</em>. “Negative events capture our attention faster, increase our arousal more, provoke stronger responses, and are remembered with ease compared to positive or neutral events.” And within bad stuff like true crime and gory horror scenarios, threat grabs the most attention. “Threat-related information is seen as more important than other kinds of information, and people who spread threatening information are seen as more reliable and trustworthy.” (Politicians and influencers seem to think so, anyway.)</p>

<p>This response is biological. Thanks to the amygdala, our immediate instinct is to assess threats. They make us alert, especially if they're life-threatening. “Our estimation of a threat’s power and danger is directly related to the amount of damage it can do to the body,” Scrivner asserts. “This is a key reason why bodily injuries demand our attention and arouse our morbid curiosity.” Of all the threats, among the worst is a predator. But we’re not entirely helpless. We prepare for it by learning about it. Our curiosity is what saves us.</p>

<h2>Prepared Learning</h2>
<p>Prepared learning psychology holds that organisms more easily learn associations related to their survival than any other. Thus, we share common fears like snakes, heights, and noises in the night. Stories that exploit these fears often draw a large audience. True crime thrives on tales about predators: a stranger with evil intent enters the house or follows us or captures us. Or a familiar loved one transforms into a malignant stranger. Scrivner says that our ancestors learned about threat signals that they could see and react to. They avoided or subdued these people. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>I was more interested in what he'd say about the “werewolves”—those who bond with us while planning to harm us. Scrivner guides us there by showing how we evolved from reactive aggression to the more cold-blooded proactive aggression. He uses covert serial killers Ted Bundy and John Wayne Gacy as examples. Such people seek out trusted roles so they can dupe whole communities. <em>That’s </em>what drives much of our fascination with true crime. We're curious about their minds and their ability to live doubled lives for years. I thought Scrivner was going to now tell us how our efforts over the past fifty years at learning about these hidden killers has helped us to spot them more effectively. However, he moved into conspiracies and then paranormal subjects. </p>

<p>Since this is what drives at least a large segment of true crime fascination, I had hoped he'd extend his analysis. He doesn't quite show how our morbid curiosity about these hidden, calculating offenders helps us to improve our preparation for them. In fact, I don't think we have improved by very much. So, I thought about why.</p>

<p>We’ve learned a lot about such predators. We have plenty of analyses. Yet these individuals keep harming us. For all the time our experts have spent focused on these “werewolves,” we still can’t spot clear red flags in those who successfully blend in. </p>
<p>Here's my idea: The hidden predator—the chameleon—confronts us with competing motivations: safety vs. community. We develop certain expectations about behavior that make community bonds possible, and predators exploit them. So, to improve our ability to see the predators, we’d have to stop trusting these expectations. In other words, we’d have to be more suspicious about ministers, cops, nurses, scout leaders, psychology students, security installers, journalists, contractors, etc., etc. But then our social bonds would quickly fray, leaving us vulnerable in other ways. So, we choose community, which weakens our predator identification system. </p>

<p>I don't know if this is the answer, but it seems to follow the same logic. Learning about them doesn't necessarily prepare us if that preparation comes at a cost we're not willing to pay.</p>
<h2>There’s Still Some Gain</h2>
<p>It makes sense that we fixate on true crime due to its value for threat management. Engaging with these stories lets us safely consider what we might do. “When we open the door to safe experiences with bad feelings,” Scrivner says, “we can more easily conquer them.”</p>



  


<p>It’s no surprise, then, that the audience for true crime is largely female. They’re learning how to stay safe in a threatening world. They’re making the threat more predictable, which helps to reduce their anxiety. They can identify a clear source for the threat and experience how it gets neutralized through arrest and punishment. Vicariously, they gain a sense of agency, especially with participatory true crime, e.g. puzzling out unsolved cases.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Scrivner’s argument about our "morbid curiosity" for true crime is a worthy contribution, but the “prepared learning” part seems to need a more complex explanation. Despite how much we’ve studied the threat from camouflaged “werewolves,” they’re still successfully blending in.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/shadow-boxing/202602/the-value-of-true-crime" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/shadow-boxing/202602/the-value-of-true-crime</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/shadow-boxing/202602/the-value-of-true-crime</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Katherine Ramsland Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_0283.JPG.jpg?itok=YZYs2Pea" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We've Lost the Spaces That Foster Friendship]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-02/Alicia%20Walker.png.jpg?itok=xVfnLu8d" alt="Alicia M. Walker Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Friends</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">We've Lost the Spaces That Foster Friendship</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why the decline of in-person community matters more than self-help advice.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The U.S. Surgeon General has declared loneliness a public health crisis.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Americans participate in fewer in-person civic and community groups than they did decades ago.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Close friendships typically form through repeated, face-to-face interaction, not through intention alone.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Some marginalized communities are preserving the kinds of social spaces that mainstream life has lost.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Every time someone says we’re in a loneliness epidemic, the advice sounds suspiciously individual: join a gym, download a friend app, go to therapy, try harder. But what if loneliness isn’t a personal failure at all?</p>
<p>The U.S. Surgeon General has declared it a public health crisis. Research has shown that chronic loneliness is<a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC5831910/"> associated</a> with depression, <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11886-021-01495-2">cardiovascular disease</a>, and even increased mortality risk. Headlines warn that Americans have fewer friends than ever before and give us advice on how to make more friends, as though the issue is simply our unwillingness or our lack of know-how. We debate whether smartphones ruined us, whether remote work isolated us, whether dating apps replaced real intimacy.</p>

<p>But what if we are asking the wrong question? Instead of asking why individuals feel lonely, maybe we should be asking where the infrastructure for belonging went.</p>
<p>For decades, sociologist Ray Oldenburg argued that healthy societies depend on “third places,” informal public gathering spaces outside home and work where people interact regularly and build relationships. (Think: neighborhood bars, bowling leagues, churches, hobby groups, volunteer organizations.)</p>

<p>“Third places” are places where we can connect with others that isn’t our home (our first place) or our workplace (our second place). A “third place” is where we once bumped into people over and over again until they turned into real friends in places like bars, clubhouses, or church. Third places are now <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S135382921930735X">on the decline</a> as fewer people go to bars, join in-person social clubs or associations, or attend religious services.</p>

<p>Third places matter because they create the <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S135382921930735X">routine,</a> low-stakes contact that keeps people from drifting into <a href="https://www.proquest.com/openview/4d792a1d692af561b35c270949859c2f/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=18750&amp;diss=y">isolation.</a></p>
<p>We tend to frame loneliness as an internal feeling, something happening inside individual people. But what if loneliness is less about emotion and more about environment? What if it’s the predictable outcome of dismantling the spaces that once made repeated, in-person connection routine? When we began studying BDSM communities, I expected to be writing about sex. Instead, I found myself documenting something much more structural: networks that many mainstream spaces no longer seem able to generate.</p>

<p>The majority of participants were embedded in some form of community, whether online or in person. A substantial proportion had close friends within that community. Many reported receiving emotional support, practical help with moving or repairs, even financial assistance or job referrals from people they met through those networks. The more involved someone was in repeated, face-to-face gatherings, the denser their network became and the more tangible support they reported receiving.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>That pattern should not surprise anyone familiar with friendship research. Sociologists of <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1996-97613-000">friendship</a> have long shown that close ties rarely form because someone sets out to “make friends.” They form through repeated exposure, shared activity, and gradual self-disclosure. You show up and see and talk to the same people. Then, you reveal a little more of yourself each time and so trust accumulates. That is how social capital is built.</p>

<p>What struck me was not that a kink community could generate friendship. It was that it had preserved something many mainstream spaces have lost: structured, recurring, interest-based, in-person interaction among adults.</p>
<p>It would be easy to assume that the more someone invests in a stigmatized subculture, the narrower their world becomes. That isn’t what we found. The people most active in in-person BDSM spaces were somewhat more likely to also participate in other hobby and interest-based groups. So, community didn’t appear to replace other ties. If anything, it coexisted with, and perhaps reinforced, broader social engagement.</p>

<p>This mirrors broader research. Studies consistently show that participation in voluntary associations is <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11266-020-00274-x">associated with</a> higher life satisfaction, greater trust, and stronger mental health outcomes. In other words, social capital is cumulative: the more networks you are part of, the more resources you have access to, both emotional and material.</p>

<p>If we want to understand why so many adults feel disconnected, it is not enough to tell people to practice self-care, get a therapist, or put down their phones. Those interventions may help individuals cope, but they don’t rebuild infrastructure.</p>
<p>We have quietly dismantled many of the spaces where adults repeatedly encounter one another around shared interests. We often work alone, only to go home and stream and scroll alone. Even when we gather, it is often one-off and transactional rather than sustained and embedded, and then we wonder why we feel lonely.</p>



  


<p>The takeaway is not “go join a kink club.” (Kink communities benefits their members because those members are interested in kink.) Adults need repeated, face-to-face interaction around shared interests. They need to see the same people often enough that familiarity turns into trust. Romantic relationships are important, but they cannot replace a broader network of ties. Expecting one person to meet every emotional and social need was never realistic.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>We keep asking how to make people less lonely, as though loneliness were a skill deficit. A better question is structural: where are the recurring spaces where adults encounter the same people long enough for connection to become inevitable? Until we grapple with that, we will keep misdiagnosing the problem.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/hidden-desires/202602/weve-lost-the-spaces-that-foster-friendship" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/hidden-desires/202602/weve-lost-the-spaces-that-foster-friendship</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/hidden-desires/202602/weve-lost-the-spaces-that-foster-friendship</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Alicia M. Walker Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/lukas_rychvalsky-man-2915187_1280.jpg?itok=yplJ0AN7" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Is Adult ADHD Different in Women Than It Is in Men?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-01/DSC_3264-crop-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=Xz6gmfqz" alt="Scott S. Shapiro M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">ADHD</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Is Adult ADHD Different in Women Than It Is in Men?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why so many high-achieving women miss the signs of ADHD.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">ADHD in women often presents as internal overwhelm.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perfectionism and chronic self doubt are more common than hyperactivity.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many high-achieving women mask symptoms for years.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many women are diagnosed later than men.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>ADHD in women is often missed. Many people and even psychiatrists miss the diagnosis because it presents differently in women than it does in men. </p>
<p>For years, the stereotype of ADHD focused on disruptive boys in classrooms. Meanwhile, many girls who were quiet and appeared focused were often trying harder, compensating, and internalizing their struggles. Many adult women are finally starting to ask, "Could this have been ADHD"?</p>

<p>In my practice, I work with many people who want clarity. They may appear successful and like they have it all together. However, they feel chronically behind. What I have noticed is a very common pattern.</p>
<h2>The Subtle Signs of ADHD in Women</h2>
<p>ADHD symptoms in women frequently show up as feeling frazzled. Rather than hyperactivity, there is mental clutter. Because women in our culture are encouraged to be team members, to "be nice," and to collaborate, they often accept more work than it's possible for them to do. I see that many women describe difficulty starting tasks, even when they are important to them, whether they are work-related or personal. They procrastinate. On the other hand, when they feel an urgency to activate focus because of fixed deadlines, they feel the pressure and are less likely to procrastinate.</p>

<p>Forgetfulness is common. So is losing track of time. Emotional sensitivity can also be pronounced. Small setbacks feel large. Criticism lingers.</p>
<p>Importantly, many of these women appear successful on the surface. However, there is a cost. Women with ADHD often work longer hours than necessary. They stay up late finishing tasks they could not initiate earlier. Supposedly high-functioning women with undiagnosed ADHD tend to appear in my office with burnout, depression, and anxiety. The way they have been coping is no longer sustainable. </p>

<h2>Why So Many Women Are Diagnosed Later?</h2>
<p>Late diagnosis of ADHD in women is common. During childhood, inattentive symptoms were frequently overlooked. </p>
<p>In addition, many girls learned to mask symptoms early. What does ADHD "masking" in women look like? Often, I will see women with undiagnosed ADHD overprepare, double, triple, and quadruple check, and err on the side of extreme perfectionism. On the surface, they appear organized, and emotionally, they are compensating constantly.</p>

<p>Not only that, but as life becomes more complex, their coping systems begin to strain. Career advancement, parenting, leadership roles, and hormonal shifts can all increase executive demands. </p>
<h2>The Costs of Untreated ADHD</h2>
<p>Untreated ADHD in women often erodes confidence. I frequently hear some version of the same sentence: “I know I am capable, but I cannot seem to execute consistently.”</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Over time, repeated inconsistency leads to self-doubt, anxiety, and feeling like an imposter. Many even develop depression. ADHD and depression overlap in women more often than many realize.</p>
<h2>The Role of Hormones</h2>
<p>And, what is the story about ADHD, women, and hormones? Estrogen influences dopamine, which is central to attention and motivation. Many women report worsening ADHD symptoms during the luteal phase of the menstrual cycle. Others notice shifts during postpartum or perimenopause.</p>

<p>As estrogen declines, cognitive fog and distractibility can intensify. Therefore, ADHD treatment in women should consider the hormonal context. As a physician, I am always taking a holistic approach and assessing the situation from both a medical and psychological perspective. If this isn't part of the assessment and treatment, things can be missed. Someone might be diagnosed with ADHD who is really dealing with perimenopause. Or, their doctor may attribute their symptoms to PMS or fibroids when in reality the woman has PMS and undiagnosed ADHD.</p>


<h2>A Case That Illustrates the Pattern</h2>
<p>Nicki*, a 42-year-old account executive at a real estate company and mother of two teenagers, sought consultation after years of pushing herself to meet high standards. On paper, she was thriving. Privately, she described staying up past midnight to complete work she could not start earlier. She felt perpetually behind, despite strong evaluations at work.</p>

<p>A thorough evaluation of her situation involved discussions with her therapist and husband, the completion of extensive questionnaires, and a collaborative and extensive psychiatric assessment by me. Also, I reviewed comments from her elementary school teachers as well as her work performance reviews over the past fifteen years. Furthermore, I conducted neuropsychological testing using new computer software for more objective findings. </p>



  


<p>This process revealed that she had been struggling with severe ADHD her entire life. With a carefully monitored medication plan, structured cognitive behavioral therapy, workplace accommodations, and executive function coaching, her performance, relationships, and overall quality of life greatly improved. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Nicki felt more present with her husband, children, and friends. Additionally, she was able to relax during the evenings and on weekends. Her insomnia and chronic anxiety also significantly improved. Most importantly, her self-perception shifted. She no longer viewed herself as undisciplined; instead, she began to understand her neurobiology.</p>

<p>Within months, evenings became more predictable. Stress decreased. Performance stabilized.</p>
<h2>What Effective Treatment Looks Like</h2>
<p>ADHD in women requires a thoughtful, holistic, and comprehensive approach. In my work, I begin with a careful diagnostic evaluation. ADHD is not diagnosed casually. We examine developmental history, current impairment, and coexisting conditions. </p>

<p>When appropriate, medication can significantly improve executive function. However, medication alone is rarely sufficient. Sustainable change requires skill-building.</p>
<p>Cognitive behavioral therapy provides structure. We focus on task initiation, prioritization, planning, and realistic scheduling. Instead of adding more tools, we refine systems that align with how the brain works.</p>

<p>In addition, collaboratively with the patient, we address long-standing beliefs. Many high-achieving women with ADHD carry narratives of not being disciplined enough. </p>
<h2>A Clear Path Forward</h2>
<p>ADHD in women is often subtle and frequently masked by competence. As awareness increases, more women are recognizing themselves in descriptions they once dismissed.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>With accurate diagnosis and structured treatment, outcomes can be excellent. Executive function improves. Emotional stability increases. Confidence returns.</p>
<p>For women who suspect ADHD may be part of their story, clarity is possible. And with clarity comes a strategic plan for moving forward.</p>
<p>*Disclosure: The case example above is a composite illustration. Identifying details have been altered to protect confidentiality. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-best-strategies-for-managing-adult-adhd/202602/how-is-adult-adhd-different-in-women-than" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-best-strategies-for-managing-adult-adhd/202602/how-is-adult-adhd-different-in-women-than</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-best-strategies-for-managing-adult-adhd/202602/how-is-adult-adhd-different-in-women-than</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Scott S. Shapiro M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/iStock-arms%20up%20woman%20victory.jpg?itok=q2iRPw0T" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Environmental Sensitivity: A Transdiagnostic Trait?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/-2_23.jpg?itok=gXcT5Rwb" alt="Noam Shpancer Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Environmental Sensitivity: A Transdiagnostic Trait?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Environmental sensitivity is strongly linked to multiple mental health problems.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Environmental sensitivity is a trait whereby individuals show highetened reactivity to contextual stimuli.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Environmental sensitivity appears to be a biologically-based, evolved trait.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Environmental sensitivity has been linked to mental health problems.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Environmental sensitivity is best regarded and treated as a transdiagnostic risk factor for mental health.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Here’s a quick quiz:</p>
<ol>
<li>Are you more than others affected by the moods of other people?</li>
<li>Do you become unpleasantly aroused when a lot is going on around you?</li>
<li>Are you deeply moved by the arts or music?</li>
</ol>
<p>What does it measure, and why does it matter? Well, read on…</p>
<p>Research has amply documented the relationship between <a href="https://www.viacharacter.org/big-five-personality-traits?gad_source=1&amp;gad_campaignid=21963586784&amp;gbraid=0AAAAACbGcSq5ilvGmXXlVHuipaZWDZEq0&amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMIi7a2w7rykgMVOIrCCB3aSQM4EAAYAyAAEgKUGfD_BwE">Big Five </a>personality traits and psychopathology. For <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-010-9780-7">example</a>, high trait neuroticism is associated with greater depression and anxiety, while low neuroticism coupled with higher levels of extraversion, agreeableness, and conscientiousness is <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S027273581830285X">linked</a> to better overall mental health adjustment.</p>

<p>More recently, research has honed in on a less-discussed but no less potent trait: environmental <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/buy/1997-05290-010">sensitivity</a> (ES), characterized by a heightened degree of sensitivity to physical, emotional, and social stimuli. In other words, some people are highly attuned and reactive to their environment, while others are much more oblivious to it. </p>

<p>Swiss psychiatrist C. G. Jung was perhaps the <a href="https://www.excelcentre.net/psytypes.pdf">first</a> to point out this “<em>innate sensitiveness,</em>” but the empirical basis has been established via converging lines of evidence since the mid-1990s, labeling the phenomenon variably as <a href="//doi.org/10.1037/a0017376">differential susceptibility</a>, biological sensitivity to <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/development-and-psychopathology/article/abs/biological-sensitivity-to-context-i-an-evolutionarydevelopmental-theory-of-the-origins-and-functions-of-stress-reactivity/2163EB3424FF3B40824916B17CA4DF9F">context</a>, or sensory-processing <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/buy/1997-05290-010">sensitivity</a>.</p>

<p>Research supports the notion that sensitivity is a moderately heritable, normally distributed <a href="//doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2017.0161">trait</a>, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0149763418306250">linked</a> to genetic and prenatal/postnatal environmental factors that affect central nervous system sensitivity, and marked by higher activation in brain regions involved in empathy, social processing, and reflective thinking. </p>

<p>Differences in sensitivity were selected into our repertoire for <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00787-014-0567-2">evolutionary</a> reasons. Indeed, while environmentally sensitive <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/development-and-psychopathology/article/abs/differential-susceptibility-to-the-environment-an-evolutionaryneurodevelopmental-theory/721733A3D8F132B483E69DD1DA4255B2">individuals</a> are more vulnerable to the negative effects of adversity, they are also more likely to benefit from positive, supportive environments. Thus, high ES can, under certain circumstances, confer advantages. </p>

<p>Research on environmental sensitivity suggests that it is comprised of three main factors: (1) Ease of Excitation (Q1 above; being easily overwhelmed by internal or external stimuli; (2) Low Sensory Threshold (Q2; unpleasant sensory arousal from external stimuli); (3) Aesthetic Sensitivity (Q3; susceptibility to beauty and the arts).</p>

<p>As with the Big Five, trait research is most useful insofar as it provides robust predictions that relate to mental health outcomes. Indeed, a growing body of research since the early 2000s has been pointing to a positive correlation between ES and mental health.</p>
<p>A <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/21677026251348428">recent </a>(2025) meta-analysis by the psychologist Tom Falkenstein and colleagues looked to summarize this literature. The authors included 33 high quality studies published between 2000 and 2024 (five longitudinal, 27 cross-sectional, one case study) from countries across the globe, (including Japan, the United States, Iran, China, Lebanon, and Ireland, South Korea, Serbia, Turkey, Germany, Israel, Denmark, Austria, Norway, and the UK) for a total sample size of 12,697, (62.51% female; mean age 25.35 years).</p>


<p>The results were quite robust. The authors note: “The systematic review ...revealed positive and moderate correlations between sensitivity and various mental-health outcomes, such as depression, anxiety, psychosomatic symptoms, OCD, PTSD, agoraphobia, social phobia, and avoidant personality disorder…This supports our hypothesis and confirms that sensitivity is significantly correlated with common mental-health outcomes.” </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>One implication of this finding is that it offers support for a <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7027356/">transdiagnostic approach</a> to mental health—the notion that mental health problems are dimensional rather than categorical, and that many different conditions are underlaid by similar vulnerability factors. In recent years, this notion has risen to challenge the old diagnostic dogma that, borrowing from medicine, takes a categorical approach, looking for specific conditions, separate and distinct from each other, and devising specified treatment plans for each. </p>



  


<p>Empirical <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7027356/">evidence</a> has chipped away at this traditional, medical model, showing that 1) most mental illnesses, unlike physical ones, have multiple, oft-unknown causes that interact in dynamic, poorly understood ways; 2) mental health conditions do not obey the "present vs. absent" categorical worldview and are best appraised by using a "more or less of" dimensional approach; 3) comorbidity among psychiatric diagnoses is the rule rather than the exception, and single, uncomplicated clinical presentations are rare; 4) individuals receiving the same diagnosis can present with very different symptoms; 5) mental health conditions can morph over life time so that individuals may satisfy criteria for different diagnoses or develop different symptom clusters within the same diagnosis.</p>

<p>Given these data, the transdiagnostic model proposes that: 1) mental health problems are best viewed and analyzed dimensionally along several continua rather than as discrete categories; 2) the processes implicated in mental health problems, whether rooted in biological, environmental, or psychosocial factors (or, most often, a combination of all three), are not specific for specific diagnoses, but rather apply across multiple diagnostic categories. </p>

<p><a href="https://zaguan.unizar.es/record/134923/files/texto_completo.pdf">Research</a> has identified several such transdiagnostic risk factors, including cognitive processes such as rumination, worry, and negative thinking, intolerance of <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0149763423000921">uncertainty</a>, trait neuroticism, and <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36242943/">anxiety sensitivity</a>. Transdiagnostic clinical <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1745691611419672">interventions</a>, in turn, “aim to apply similar underlying treatment principles across mental disorders, without tailoring the protocol to specific diagnoses.” </p>

<p>ES appears to be another <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/psychology/transdiagnostic-factors#:~:text=In%20Nolen%2DHoeksema%20and%20Watkins,are%20expressed%20(divergent%20trajectories).">transdiagnostic risk factor</a>, bound to play a role in the development and maintenance of various diagnosed conditions. Clinicians could therefore look to identify and target ES across diagnoses, as high ES individuals stand to benefit from treatment that focuses on strengthening emotion regulation, attentional focus skills, and overall resilience.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/insight-therapy/202602/environmental-sensitivity-a-transdiagnostic-trait" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/insight-therapy/202602/environmental-sensitivity-a-transdiagnostic-trait</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/insight-therapy/202602/environmental-sensitivity-a-transdiagnostic-trait</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Noam Shpancer Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/geralt-magnifying-glass-2884240_1280.jpg?itok=6jJiTHI6" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>