<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 14:50:14 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 14:50:14 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Expert Predictions So Often Fail]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/matt-grawitch_1.jpg?itok=XyCWuAg0" alt="Matt Grawitch Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Intuition</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Expert Predictions So Often Fail</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Forecasting is the wrong test of real expertise.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">True expertise is about judgment under constraints, not predicting uncertain futures.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Prediction strips away the context and evidence that expert judgment depends on.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">As problems move beyond familiar patterns, expert forecasts drift toward chance.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Picture2.png.jpg?itok=id9EQYq0" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Image created by ChatGPT 5.2 / OpenAI" alt="Image created by ChatGPT 5.2 / OpenAI"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Image created by ChatGPT 5.2 / OpenAI</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>A while back, I came across an article titled “<a href="https://www.realclearscience.com/articles/2025/12/03/trust_the_experts_its_a_bad_bet_1150895.html">Trust the Experts? It’s a Bad Bet</a>,” and at first glance it seemed to echo a familiar claim: that expertise itself has become less trustworthy<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>. But reading past the headline revealed a much narrower and very different argument. The real target wasn’t expertise in general; it was expert <em>prediction</em>. In essence, the claim was that experts are often poor forecasters of the future, and trusting their predictions is usually a losing proposition.</p>

<p>On that point, the author is largely right. Trusting expert predictions often <em>is</em> a bad idea. But it's not because true expertise itself is hollow or overrated. It’s because what makes someone a legitimate expert is rarely their ability to function as an oracle.</p>
<p>That's an important distinction. Judging expertise by its ability to predict uncertain futures almost guarantees disappointment—and it sets up a false dichotomy in the process: either we defer to expert authority, or we decide expertise itself is overrated. Neither position is especially useful.</p>

<p>The more interesting question isn’t whether we should “trust experts” in some broad, abstract sense. It’s what we should expect true expertise to actually deliver—and where its limits lie. Experts aren’t hired to see the future. They’re hired to help us make sense of the present: to diagnose problems we already face, interpret evidence we already have, and weigh tradeoffs under real constraints. When we confound that kind of judgment with prophecy, we end up misunderstanding both the value and the limits of expertise. </p>

<h2>What Expertise Actually Is</h2>
<p>Expertise isn’t primarily about prediction. It’s about judgment—specifically, the ability to recognize which kind of situation you’re in and to respond in ways that have worked before under similar conditions, also known as recognition-primed decision making. Across domains, what distinguishes experts from novices isn’t superior logic or broader knowledge in the abstract, but experience with recurring patterns. Over time, experts learn which cues matter, which ones can be ignored, and which tradeoffs are likely to follow from different courses of action—ultimately giving rise to what <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/26798603_Conditions_for_Intuitive_Expertise">Kahneman &amp; Klein (2009)</a> describe as skilled intuition.</p>

<p>When faced with a problem, experts don’t start from scratch by weighing every possible option. Instead, they recognize familiar elements, generate a small set of plausible responses, and then evaluate whether those responses fit the specifics of the situation at hand. When the context aligns with their prior experience, this process can be remarkably fast and effective. It’s also why expert intuition can look effortless from the outside—much of the work has already been done through repeated exposure to similar problems.</p>

<p>But that strength comes with a clear limitation. Expert judgment is tightly bound to context. It works well within what I’ve referred to elsewhere as an <a href="https://mattgrawitch.substack.com/p/when-experts-overstep">expertise “bubble”</a>: the range of situations where an expert’s experience provides reliable guidance. As problems move farther from that bubble—toward novel conditions, unfamiliar environments, or long time horizons—the cues that support recognition begin to fade. At that point, experts are no longer drawing on well-calibrated judgment; they’re extrapolating beyond what their experience can reliably support.</p>

<h2>Why Expert Predictions Often Look Like a Coin Toss</h2>
<p>Imagine an expert is brought into an organization to help solve a problem. They’re given a general description of what’s going wrong and then asked, on the spot, to say what the organization should do. No opportunity to dig deeper. No chance to gather additional information. Just a judgment call.</p>

<p>In that situation, even a genuine expert has little choice but to guess. Some of the assumptions they make will be reasonable. Others won’t. And unless the problem is unusually simple or well-structured, there’s no reason to expect the final judgment to be much better than chance. That isn’t a knock on expertise; it’s what happens when judgment is forced to operate without the evidence it needs to do its job.</p>

<p>What differentiates experts in real settings isn’t their ability to issue answers on demand. It’s their ability to guide the collection of evidence in ways that make judgment possible. They know which questions to ask next, which information is worth gathering, and when additional data will no longer meaningfully improve the decision. That process refines and calibrates the pattern recognition that underlies expert judgment.</p>



  


<p>Prediction short-circuits that process. When we ask experts to forecast the future, we give them a problem that is explicitly future-oriented and, by definition, thin on direct evidence. There’s no opportunity for guided information gathering, iteration, or meaningful feedback. The expert is forced to fill in the gaps with assumptions about how people, organizations, or systems will behave. Some of those assumptions will be right. Others won’t. Averaged out, accuracy drifts toward a coin toss.</p>

<p>This is why expert predictions so often disappoint us. It’s not that experts suddenly lose their competence when asked about the future. It’s that prediction removes the very mechanism that makes expertise useful in the first place: context-sensitive judgment refined through selective evidence. When we strip that away, what remains isn’t expert insight so much as guesswork—and the results look exactly like you’d expect.</p>

<h2>What Expertise Is (and Isn’t) Good For</h2>
<p>None of this means expertise is useless, or that skepticism toward experts is misplaced. It means we’ve been asking experts to do the wrong job. Expertise isn’t a crystal ball. It’s a way of making sense of messy situations in the present—of diagnosing problems, interpreting evidence, and helping decision-makers navigate tradeoffs under real constraints.</p>

<p>When used that way, expertise still matters a great deal. Experts are most valuable when they’re allowed to interact with a problem: to ask questions, gather targeted evidence, test assumptions, and revise their judgments as new information comes in. That’s where recognition-primed judgment shines—and where expert insight genuinely improves decisions.</p>

<p>Trouble starts when we collapse that process into a demand for prediction. When we treat experts as forecasters of uncertain futures, we strip away the context and evidence their judgment depends on, then fault them when accuracy collapses. The result is predictable disappointment, followed by an unhelpful backlash against expertise itself.</p>

<p>If we want better decisions, the solution isn’t to stop listening to experts—or to trust them blindly. It’s to stop confusing judgment with prophecy, and to expect expertise to deliver what it actually can: informed guidance about what to do now, not guarantees about what will happen next.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-hovercraft-full-of-eels/202602/why-expert-predictions-so-often-fail" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-hovercraft-full-of-eels/202602/why-expert-predictions-so-often-fail</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-hovercraft-full-of-eels/202602/why-expert-predictions-so-often-fail</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Grawitch Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Picture2.png.jpg?itok=f_DjlU4B" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Quintessential Secrets of Psychotherapy: The Trauma of Evil]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/new-photo-.jpg?itok=-Vc-lmod" alt="Stephen A. Diamond Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Trauma</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Quintessential Secrets of Psychotherapy: The Trauma of Evil</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How can we constructively cope with the existential reality of evil?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Confronting and coming to terms with the existential problem of evil is essential today.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Evil is inevitably one of life's "ultimate concerns."</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Denying or minimizing the existential reality of evil in the world renders us even more vulnerable to it.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2025-08/Broken_glass_001.jpg?itok=9rYyMeR7" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" title="Violetbonmua / Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA-3.0" alt="Violetbonmua / Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA-3.0"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Violetbonmua / Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA-3.0</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>This post is Part 1 of a series.</em></p>
<p>In my view, the problem of human evil has, with few exceptions (see, for example, Jung, Frankl, Lifton, May, Milgram, Fromm, Peck, Becker, Baumeister, and Zimbardo, among others), been ignored, neglected, minimized, or dismissed by mainstream psychology but can no longer be denied or avoided without serious consequences. As C.G. Jung (1961) presciently put it, "Today we need psychology for reasons that involve our very existence. . . . We stand face to face with the terrible question of evil and do not even know what is before us let alone what to pit against it." I propose that the perennial and increasingly ubiquitous problem of evil must be given its proper due in psychology and psychotherapy, placing it alongside <em>isolation</em>, <em>meaninglessness</em>, <em>suffering</em>, <em>freedom</em>, <em>responsibility</em>, <em>spirituality</em>, and <em>death </em>or <em>mortality</em> as one of life's "ultimate concerns" (see Yalom, 1980).</p>

<p>When evil strikes suddenly and unexpectedly in the form of mass shootings, psychopathic serial killings, racism, antisemitism, bullying, domestic violence, genocide, terrorism, fascism, or war, or in cataclysmic cosmic occurrences like cyclones, volcanic eruptions, earthquakes, pandemics, floods, and tragic accidents that wreak untimely death, destruction, and suffering on multitudes of innocent beings, how can we constructively cope with it? Human suffering stemming from the trauma of evil takes myriad forms, such as grief, rage, sorrow, anxiety, alienation, guilt, and various neurotic or psychotic symptoms like depression, mania, delusions, hallucinations, etc. </p>

<p>Close encounters with evil can evoke an <em>existential crisis</em>. Such traumatic evils psychologically (and sometimes literally) shake the ground of our existence, causing us to question the fundamental nature and meaning of life and death. They obliterate our illusory sense of safety, forcing us to face the frightful fact that existence, like the mythical Sword of Damocles, hangs by a tenuous, slender thread, and is intrinsically uncertain and insecure; that <em>being </em>can at any moment become <em>non-being</em>; that death is always but a final breath away; and that the basic structure or reality we depend upon daily for a sense of significance, predictability, meaning, purpose, continuity, security, safety, and protection is, in reality, transitory, groundless, unstable, illusory, ephemeral, and exceedingly precarious. In such dreadful moments, we can experience the existential void of emptiness, nothingness, meaninglessness, absurdity, the inevitability of death, and the abject terror of being abandoned, isolated, alienated, and totally alone in a cold, callous, uncaring cosmos.</p>

<p>Fundamentally, it is this traumatic confrontation with evil itself, the seemingly senseless suffering it causes, and the existential and spiritual questions it inevitably confronts us with that frequently brings people into psychotherapy. Many, if not most, patients explicitly or implicitly seek psychotherapy when they can no longer comprehend, make sense of, tolerate, or come to terms with the distressing reality of evil in others, themselves, and the world, and the immense suffering such evil engenders. When the psychologically and emotionally devastating phenomenon of both cosmic and human evil—death, destructiveness, violence, loss, sadism, cruelty, hatred, and "man's inhumanity toward man"—renders life subjectively meaningless, we instinctively try to make some sense of it, to put it into some spiritual, philosophical, scientific, or psychological context. </p>

<p>Encountering the existential reality of evil for the first time can be a devastating, disillusioning, and disorienting experience that can precipitate a predictable pattern of reactions, symptoms, and suffering described in detail in the<em> Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</em> (<em>DSM-5-TR</em>, 2022) as acute stress disorder or posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD)<em>.</em> Indeed, we could say that the diagnosis of acute stress disorder and PTSD (which, by definition, requires "exposure to actual or threatened death, serious injury, or sexual violence" is an accurate phenomenological description of an archetypal response to the trauma of evil <em>in</em> <em>extremis</em>. As Jung (1951/1959 ) noted, “it is quite within the bounds of possibility for a man to recognize the relative evil of his nature, but it is a rare and shattering experience for him to gaze into the face of absolute evil.” Yet, with greater frequency and intensity than ever before, such "absolute," archetypal, or radical evil is not only on the rise but increasingly and unavoidably visible to us every day in gory detail on television, the internet, cinema, and social media, etc. </p>

<p>Even for the emotionally detached, spiritually enlightened, or geographically remote observer passively viewing someone being brutally beaten or soldiers killed in action or witnessing some catastrophic natural disaster taking place 10 or 10,000 miles away on the television or cell phone screen from the secure comfort and safety of their own living room, the grotesque spectacle of both human and cosmic evil can be vicariously traumatizing. This is particularly true for those individuals with a significant prior personal history of trauma, who are prone to being retraumatized by exposure to evil in the present. But being vicariously traumatized by evil is something to which every empathic, caring, and sensitive human being is susceptible at any time. People suffering from such an unexpected and precipitous traumatic encounter with evil—be it natural or human, or both—are initially in a severe state of emotional shock or “psychic numbing” (Lifton, 1986). They are, at least temporarily, unable to psychologically process the experience. Denial of the reality of evil for them is no longer a viable defense mechanism.</p>

<p>Victims of evil—and, to some extent, we are <em>all </em>victims—tend to feel anxious, out of control, helpless, powerless, abandoned, disoriented, and deeply discouraged. Frequently, they also feel angry, enraged, resentful, and embittered about what has so unfairly, undeservedly, or unjustly happened to them—furious at God if they are religious; or with fate, fortune, or life itself. They have been brutally and abruptly robbed of their innocence and sense of safety. Their once secure, familiar, and comforting worldview has been decimated. Many traumatized victims of evil will—for worse or better—never be the same. Their previous perception of reality, and sometimes of themselves, others, and the world, has been irrevocably altered. In such tragic cases, psychotherapy can help, but only when the therapist truly appreciates the intensely traumatizing power of evil on the fragile yet remarkably resilient human psyche, and the crucial importance of assisting traumatized individuals to consciously acknowledge, recognize, confront, and, in their own way, accept and come to terms with, the existential reality of evil. (See my <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202602/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-role-of-acceptance">prior post</a> and Part Two of this posting.) </p>


<p><em>(This article is partially adapted from my book chapter "The psychology and psychotherapy of evil: Encountering the daimonic," in Hoffman, L. (Ed.) (2026). </em>The APA Handbook of Humanistic and Existential Psychology. Vol. 1,<em> APA Press.)</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202508/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-trauma-of-evil" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202508/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-trauma-of-evil</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202508/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-trauma-of-evil</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephen A. Diamond Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2025-08/Broken_glass_001.jpg?itok=9Vt348_d" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Maintaining a Youthful Gut Microbiome Can Slow Aging]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/thumbnail_bill-sullivan-photo-by-eric-schoch-107-web-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=7J8VLSGa" alt="Bill Sullivan Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Microbiome</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Maintaining a Youthful Gut Microbiome Can Slow Aging</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Could the Fountain of Youth be right under your nose…in your gut?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The gut microbiome changes with age.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cultivating a youthful microbiome decreases age-associated inflammation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Proper diet and exercise can help maintain a youthful microbiome.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>People have long given up on the search for the Fountain of Youth, a mythical spring that could reverse aging. But for some scientists, the hunt has not ended; it’s just moved to a different place. These modern-day Ponce de Leóns are investigating whether gut microbes hold the secret to aging well.</p>
<p>The gut microbiome refers to the vast collection of microscopic organisms – bacteria, fungi and viruses – that largely inhabit the colon. These microbes aid in digestion and produce molecules that <a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/gutjnl-2021-326789">affect your physiology</a> <a href="https://theconversation.com/bacteria-in-your-gut-can-improve-your-mood-new-research-in-mice-tries-to-zero-in-on-the-crucial-strains-220935">and psychology</a>. The composition of the microbiome is <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/femsec/fiab043">influenced by a combination of factors</a>, including genetics, diet, the environment, medications and age.</p>

<p>I’m a <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=mN6ZaFkAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">microbiology professor</a> and author of <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/608709/pleased-to-meet-me-by-bill-sullivan/"><em>Pleased to Meet Me: Genes, Germs and the Curious Forces That Make Us Who We Are</em></a>, which describes how the gut microbiome contributes to physical and mental health. The discovery that the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-genet-112618-043650">gut microbiome changes with age</a> has ignited studies to determine whether the Fountain of Youth might be right under your nose, down inside your gut.</p>

<h2>You’re only as old as your gut microbes</h2>
<p>People are most familiar with outward signs of aging, such as wrinkles and graying hair, but there are also microscopic changes taking place deep inside. The gut microbes of older people tend to be less diverse, with <a href="https://theconversation.com/gut-bacteria-and-the-immune-system-how-aging-changes-the-microbiome-and-can-lead-to-inflammaging-226105">more bacteria that promote inflammation</a> and other hallmarks of aging. Changes to the microbiome across age are so consistent that algorithms can reliably predict a person’s <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aaw6459">age based on their microbiome composition</a>.</p>

<p>There are exceptions to this rule. Older adults and supercentenarians who age well, research shows, have gut microbiomes that <a href="https://theconversation.com/what-the-gut-microbiome-of-the-worlds-oldest-person-can-tell-us-about-ageing-266161">look more like those of younger people</a>. These findings support the idea that maintaining a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s42255-021-00348-0">youthful microbiome fosters healthy aging and longevity</a>.</p>
<p>To confirm that the microbes of youth influence aging, scientists use a technique called fecal microbiota transplantation. This procedure involves obliterating a person’s current gut microbiome and replacing it with microbes harvested from a donor’s feces. Transplanting microbiota from a young mouse into an elderly mouse <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s40168-022-01243-w">reverses age-associated inflammation</a> in the gut, brain and eyes. Conversely, transplanting microbiota from an old mouse into a young one accelerates these aging parameters. Other studies suggest that microbiota from young mice <a href="https://doi.org/10.1128/msystems.01601-24">alter metabolism</a> in ways that reduce <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574-018-0059-4">inflammation that accelerates aging</a>.</p>

<p>The evidence that aging is linked with the microbiome is compelling. However, <a href="https://doi.org/10.5946/ce.2021.072">fecal transplantation is not without risk</a> and is approved only as a last resort to <a href="https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-approves-first-orally-administered-fecal-microbiota-product-prevention-recurrence-clostridioides">treat severe <em>C. difficile</em> infections</a>. These shortcomings have prompted researchers to search for safer and more refined ways to cultivate an age-friendly microbiome.</p>

<h2>Diet and exercise may slow aging</h2>
<p>Proper diet and exercise have long been tied to better aging and longevity. One way these lifestyle habits may be beneficial is through their <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/nu17101686">influence on gut microbes</a>.</p>
<p>What people eat – or fail to eat – has a demonstrable effect on their gut microbiomes. The <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0884533610386234">standard American diet</a>, enriched with ultraprocessed foods high in sugar, fat, and salt and low in nutrients and fiber, <a href="https://theconversation.com/hangry-bacteria-in-your-gut-microbiome-are-linked-to-chronic-disease-feeding-them-what-they-need-could-lead-to-happier-cells-and-a-healthier-body-199486">depletes microbiome</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2016.1270811">diversity within days</a>. Moving from a non-Western country to the U.S. is also associated with <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2018.10.029">loss of gut microbiome diversity</a>, partly due to dietary changes.</p>

<p><a href="https://theconversation.com/fiber-is-your-bodys-natural-guide-to-weight-management-rather-than-cutting-carbs-out-of-your-diet-eat-them-in-their-original-fiber-packaging-instead-205159">Lack of fiber</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms10122507">is a major reason</a> the microbiome adopts a configuration associated with poor aging. Studies in <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2020.104341">roundworms</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jare.2023.04.014">mice</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/s0007114508975607">rats</a> found that fiber supplements improved overall health and extended lifespan by 20% to 35%. A 2025 study showed that increasing the amount of fiber in your diet is linked to as much as a <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2025.11056">37% greater likelihood of healthy aging in women</a>.</p>

<p>Fiber functions as a prebiotic, a nondigestible food component that nourishes the microbiome. Gut bacteria process fiber into compounds such as <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnins.2023.1197759">short-chain fatty acids</a> that promote better aging by improving metabolic, brain and immune function while reducing chronic inflammation. Good sources of prebiotics include most fruits and vegetables, whole grains, legumes, nuts and seeds.</p>

<p>Certain foods, such as yogurt and kefir, or dietary supplements contain probiotics – living microbes that may benefit the gut microbiome. Research on probiotic foods and supplements is mixed, complicated by the variation in bacterial species and dosage in these products. The health benefits that different types of probiotics may confer is still under study.</p>



  


<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/3831972">Physical activity</a> is also linked to a youthful microbiome. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/mbo3.1053">Regular exercise can reshape the microbiome</a> of older adults to resemble those seen in younger adults. One study showed that when people ages 50 to 75 underwent 24 weeks of cardiovascular and resistance exercise, their <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/20499361211027067">microbiomes became populated by healthier bacteria</a> and their blood had elevated levels of aging-friendly, short-chain fatty acids.</p>

<h2>Treatments to manipulate the microbiome</h2>
<p>Making healthy lifestyle changes is a noninvasive way to cultivate a youthful microbiome that may slow aging. Scientists are also exploring <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-021-00667-9">treatments to tailor the gut microbiome</a> for better health outcomes.</p>
<p>One option may be <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2018.03.009">postbiotics, </a>nonliving but active compounds that probiotic microbes produce. For example, mouse studies have found that short-chain fatty acid supplements can improve <a href="https://doi.org/10.59368/agingbio.20240033">age-related heart</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1152/ajplung.00296.2022">lung problems</a>. Similarly, elderly mice given <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11357-019-00137-4">heat-killed bacteria from a human infant</a> saw reduced metabolic dysfunction and inflammation, as well as improved cognitive function.</p>

<p>The microbiome can also be modified with drugs, particularly antibiotics. A low-dose oral antibiotic can trigger gut bacteria to release factors that may promote good health and aging by, for example, strengthening the intestinal barrier or reducing inflammation. One such antibiotic, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002749">cephaloridine, extends the lifespan of roundworms and mice</a> by triggering gut bacteria to make <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2017.05.036">colanic acid, an anti-aging compound</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://theconversation.com/phage-therapy-could-treat-some-drug-resistant-superbug-infections-but-comes-with-unique-challenges-207025">Bacteriophages, or phages</a>, offer yet another potential way to manipulate the microbiome for health. Phages are <a href="https://theconversation.com/viruses-are-both-the-villains-and-heroes-of-life-as-we-know-it-169131">highly selective viruses</a> that infect and kill specific species of bacteria. Phages have been <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s40560-024-00759-7">used to treat severe infections</a> from bacteria resistant to antibiotics. Given that phages can <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2019.05.001">alter the gut microbiome of mice</a>, researchers are studying whether they could be used to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/1753-0407.70024">eliminate gut bacteria associated with unhealthy aging</a>.</p>

<p>Aging is a natural process that can bring many rewards. Cultivating a healthy microbiome could help people enjoy their golden years more fully.</p>
<p><em>Originally published at </em><a href="https://theconversation.com/your-gut-microbes-can-be-anti-aging-scientists-are-uncovering-how-to-keep-your-microbiome-youthful-275380"><em>https://theconversation.com</em></a><em> on February 18, 2026.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/pleased-to-meet-me/202602/maintaining-a-youthful-gut-microbiome-can-slow-aging" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/pleased-to-meet-me/202602/maintaining-a-youthful-gut-microbiome-can-slow-aging</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/pleased-to-meet-me/202602/maintaining-a-youthful-gut-microbiome-can-slow-aging</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Bill Sullivan Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/mehedi-hasan-ILIHswFu8Cw-unsplash.jpg?itok=gTJYXDzg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Common Cognitive Patterns Experienced by People With ADHD]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/kerryheadshotcropped.jpg?itok=-wn2hkQ_" alt="Kerry Chillemi Prof Doc Psych" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">ADHD</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Common Cognitive Patterns Experienced by People With ADHD</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Perceptions associated with autonomic nervous system states.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Polyvagal theory links autonomic states to ADHD perceptions and behaviors.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotional contagion heightens ADHD awareness and stress.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Managing dorsal vagal collapse involves rest and activities for regulation.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Polyvagal theory, introduced in 1994 by psychologist Stephen Porges, highlights the role of the autonomic nervous system in regulating our health and behavior. Our lived experience of engaging with the world is impacted by external environmental cues, internal physical sensations, and relational experiences (e.g., an impression of connection, safety, and trust between individuals). Neuroception is our body's unconscious surveillance system that shifts us into one of three autonomic states needed to respond to a situation: rest-and-digest (social and safe), fight-or-flight (mobilization), or shutdown/collapse (immobilization). </p>

<p>The <strong>ventral vagal state </strong>is associated with a sense of safety and calm. When we are grounded in our ventral vagal pathway, we are at our greatest capacity for connection. The following vignette is a commonly reported ADHD perception associated with feeling grounded in a ventral vagal state of safety and homeostasis (i.e., characterized by feeling grounded, mindful, curious, and collaborative). </p>

<blockquote><p>"<em>When I am in a ventral vagal state of regulation, I have a baseline of energy to enjoy doing what I love. I rediscover my love of learning and creativity. I have an urge for social engagement. I feel present in the moment. I feel hopeful."</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Sympathetic mobilization </strong>activity increases when you are stressed, physically active, or if there is a perceived threat. Many of the mechanisms required to intuitively tune out environmental distractors, control impulses, and sustain attention are dysregulated in ADHD. Neurodivergent people are susceptible to emotional contagion (the tendency to absorb, catch, or be influenced by other people's feelings) and can distinguish very subtle clues that others would not. This can be an overwhelming experience that can lead to a hypervigilant, alarmed state (i.e., the body's sympathetic nervous system is activated). The following vignette depicts commonly reported ADHD perceptions associated with a perpetual state of exhaustion and chronic levels of stress. </p>

<blockquote><p>"<em>When I am experiencing a heightened state of anxiety (mobilization) I feel a sense of urgency, like time is running out. I worry about what needs to be done and I feel distressed by my to-do lists. I experience survival mode thinking and an overwhelming sense of responsibility. I am hyper-focused on productivity, often at the expense of my own needs."</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>If the sympathetic system is too aroused, dorsal vagal activation triggers your body to move into a state of shutdown. The autonomic state of a <strong>dorsal vagal collapse </strong>helps to protect against life threat by immobilizing (in this state, the parasympathetic system is activated). During immobilization, our metabolism slows down, our heart rate and breathing slow, and blood pressure drops, which can present as fatigue and brain fog.</p>

<p>The following vignette depicts commonly reported ADHD perceptions associated with a state of collapse. </p>
<blockquote><p>"<em>When I experience an autonomic state of a dorsal vagal collapse, I compare myself to others. I feel like I have been left behind and I don't measure up. I feel like the world is an overwhelming place. I psychologically withdraw and detach. I can't see my way out. I experience hopelessness and I feel lost in a spiral of existential thinking (e.g., what is the meaning of life, who am I connected to, what is my purpose). I feel fatigued, numb, and I experience brain fog. I need to sleep more than usual."</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Polyvagal theory describes a physiological and psychological understanding of our autonomic nervous system and depicts a pathway for shifting in and out of different states. We can activate out of shutdown by engaging in activities that are regulatory (e.g., meditation, yoga, spending time in nature), rhythmic (e.g., listening to music, dancing, exercising), involve movement, and/or connection (e.g., enjoying the calming presence of my dog and reaching out for support from loved ones). </p>


<p>Environmental factors play a significant role in determining our ability to regulate our nervous system. For neurodivergent people, this is especially important. Neurodiverse minds need to rest and recharge. There are many different types of rest, including sensory, creative, emotional, and social rest. Adults with ADHD are acutely aware of their differences energetically, physically, emotionally, and mentally, giving them a remarkable view of the world. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/functional-legacy-mindset/202602/3-common-cognitive-patterns-experienced-by-people-with-adhd" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/functional-legacy-mindset/202602/3-common-cognitive-patterns-experienced-by-people-with-adhd</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/functional-legacy-mindset/202602/3-common-cognitive-patterns-experienced-by-people-with-adhd</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kerry Chillemi Prof Doc Psych]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-sarazhizmailov-17191718.jpg?itok=cHsPFgCT" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Wind Phones Can Help Kids Feel Connected to Late Parents]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/michelle_shreeve_0.jpg?itok=4lHDmURd" alt="Michelle Shreeve MA" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Grief</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Wind Phones Can Help Kids Feel Connected to Late Parents</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A wind phone can be a helpful coping tool for grieving children and teens.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Grieving children need helpful tools to navigate their grief.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Coping mechanisms like a wind phone can be very therapeutic for grieving children.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The more support and tools a grieving child has the better.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>In Otsuchi, Japan in 2010, something was built that touched those who were trying to navigate the difficult terrain of grief. Separate from the hustle and bustle of the city, or the noise of traffic jams connecting rural to urban counties, something wonderful was built in nature. They called it a wind phone.</p>

<p>It looks like something out of a <em>Doctor Who</em> episode featuring the time-traveling Tardis, but in actuality it mirrors what most phone booths looked like once upon a time. There is a phone inside, but there aren’t any connecting cords. You go into the booth just like long ago, pick up the rotary or push button phone, and simply say what you need to say to the person you lost. Fast forward to 2026, and there are hundreds of wind phones scattered all over, made by people who are trying to honor their late loved ones.</p>

<p>Talking to a loved one who has passed on can be highly therapeutic. Nature is also healing, so to be out in a phone booth, someplace where it is serene and quiet, even while your emotions on the inside are tumultuous, can be a cathartic experience.</p>
<p>Not everyone can go to Japan to experience a wind phone but anyone can recreate it in some form at home. The experience can be especially therapeutic for grieving children.</p>

<p>Surviving parents and family members can help grieving teens and children who are trying to navigate the death of their parent by creating a homemade wind phone in the space they have available to them. The goal is not to try to convince children that their late parent will actually answer; it is a coping tool instead to help them grieve. They are going to have hard days when they really want and need to talk to their late parent. This is one of the most therapeutic ways they can do that.</p>

<p>If you have a backyard, dedicate some space and work with what you’ve got to create the phone booth part. If you don’t have access to affordable materials, then at least have a dedicated space in the best part of nature and quiet you can access in your backyard to place an old rotary or push-button phone. Let the grieving children and teens know that this phone is available to them any time they wish to speak to their late parent. It is a safe space where they can say what they need to say in those hard moments in private. If you don’t have a backyard, then use the space you have inside to dedicate a homemade wind phone. Place some plants or trees near a special dedicated corner or area where the grieving child or teen can get some quiet special time to use the phone on difficult grief-triggering days.</p>

<p>For younger children, you can use a toy phone as a homemade wind phone. This can be deeply comforting for them, especially if they used to play with that same toy phone with their parent.</p>
<p>It is important to explain to the grieving child or teen up front that this phone will not deliver an answer back from their late parent in the way they might deeply wish. It is more for them to feel as if they are still sharing their life—their emotions, their pain, or even happy days—with their late parent, as if they were still here. It is also a helpful therapeutic way to find a peaceful connection in the midst of their grief. </p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/coping-with-parental-death/202602/how-wind-phones-can-help-kids-feel-connected-to-late-parents" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/coping-with-parental-death/202602/how-wind-phones-can-help-kids-feel-connected-to-late-parents</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/coping-with-parental-death/202602/how-wind-phones-can-help-kids-feel-connected-to-late-parents</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Michelle Shreeve MA]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/%C3%A2%C2%80%C2%94Pngtree%C3%A2%C2%80%C2%94classical%20british%20style%20red%20phone_15457058.jpg?itok=KGeWBbcp" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Diagnosing Schizophrenia With Machine Learning]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-08/Sarah%20An%20Myers.png.jpg?itok=7WIVFqFt" alt="Sarah An Myers" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Diagnosing Schizophrenia With Machine Learning</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How machine learning can stop delays in diagnosing a serious disorder.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Machine learning is a type of artificial intelligence that is trained on data and applied to make predictions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research has shown that machine learning models can predict cases of schizophrenia within five years.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Machine learning methods work better on patients with schizophrenia than bipolar disorder.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/vitaly-gariev-tw-mAZXr6H4-unsplash.jpg?itok=teQZ0ols" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="Vitaly Gariev/Unsplash" alt="Vitaly Gariev/Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Vitaly Gariev/Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Diagnosing serious mental illnesses like schizophrenia can take up to 10 years after the first episode. As one can imagine, this can have very negative repercussions. Catching psychosis early on helps create a better prognosis. Although there are many cases where those who have a late diagnosis go on to lead fulfilling lives, the hope is that future patients can get to that place faster. </p>

<h2>Machine Learning Study</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Using machine learning to identify early signs of psychosis, a cohort of 24,449 participants were enlisted. The participants’ data were gathered from the Psychiatric Services of the Central Denmark Region between 2013 and 2016. Notes from the hospital in which the participants stayed were analyzed through their text and keywords.</p>

<p dir="ltr">A machine learning model was then developed on the existing text data to train the model to assess whether future patients would develop schizophrenia within five years. By doing so, the machine learning model used 1092 “predictors,” which are factors related to the disorder that are seen in people who already have it. When predictors are identified in a cluster or increased severity (or even a decreased frequency), a machine learning model can make predictions that a person would have schizophrenia. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Some of the major text predictors for identifying schizophrenia included: hearing voices, discharge or admission from an inpatient hospital visit, contact (or no contact) with female friends, inpatient admission, wake or sleep time in the morning, words like “play” and “the game” (like board games and interacting with hospital staff), and the ability to explain their symptoms, to name a few. </p>

<p dir="ltr">The model trained on these data was able to identify those who would progress from a less severe mental illness to receiving a diagnosis like schizophrenia. The machine learning model was trained and applied on the same or very similar demographic. While the study was designed to attempt to identify both bipolar disorder and schizophrenia, the results mainly showed that the machine learning model was more accurate in determining the diagnosis of schizophrenia. </p>

<h2>Limitations of the Study</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Since this is an early study for the effectiveness of machine learning, there are some things to watch out for before bringing the technology for widespread use, clinically. </p>
<p dir="ltr">These models were used on patients who already exhibited symptoms, and were progressing from less severe mental illness to a full diagnosis of schizophrenia. The model might use different predictors for those who have minimal to no symptoms, and the researchers stressed that it was important for any machine learning models to be tested on the same or similar demographic of the training sample. A general application of a specific machine learning model might provide a poorer ability to make a diagnostic confirmation.</p>

<p dir="ltr">While novel, there is still much research to be done on the applications of machine learning to diagnosing serious mental illness. Schizophrenia is one of the disorders of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM) that shows evidence that it is a distinct disorder both biologically and psychologically through brain imaging and self-report measures. The brains of patients with schizophrenia show distinct differences, while it is more difficult to find among those with mood disorders or personality disorders, for example. </p>

<p dir="ltr">However, since it is so distinct, there is hope for advancing the diagnostic process, treatment, and care for patients with schizophrenia. While schizophrenia was once severely neglected in research and public image, now there are methods and treatment options that can help people with schizophrenia spectrum disorders lead more fulfilling lives. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-as-an-outlier/202602/diagnosing-schizophrenia-with-machine-learning" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-as-an-outlier/202602/diagnosing-schizophrenia-with-machine-learning</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-as-an-outlier/202602/diagnosing-schizophrenia-with-machine-learning</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah An Myers]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/vitaly-gariev-tw-mAZXr6H4-unsplash.jpg?itok=P-0IdMxd" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How the Brain Chooses What Matters]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-07/Hari_S.png.jpg?itok=N_QK_ant" alt="Hari Srinivasan" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Autism</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How the Brain Chooses What Matters</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Clarity, competition, and sensory strategy in autism and ADHD.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The brain doesn’t always work best by combining everything it senses.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sometimes, clarity comes from letting one signal lead while others fall back.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">For many autistic and ADHD people, this isn’t avoidance—it’s a way of staying oriented.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Sometimes things become clearer when I stop trying to take everything in. Not quieter. Not simpler. Just cleaner.</p>
<p>In a noisy café, I find that if I close my eyes, I can hear the person across from me more clearly. I can even speak better. Not because my hearing improves, but because vision stops competing for the same interpretive space. The sound doesn’t get stronger. It just gets room to matter.</p>

<p>We tend to assume that the brain works best when it combines everything it senses, layering sight, sound, movement, and context into a single stream. In neuroscience, this process is called multisensory integration, and under the right conditions, it can be remarkably effective. But integration isn’t the brain’s default goal. It’s a strategy, one the brain uses selectively. </p>

<h2>When Integration Helps—and When It Doesn’t</h2>
<p>In research lab studies, multisensory integration can improve performance on tasks like detection (<em>Is something there? </em>) or localization (<em>Where is it?</em>). These benefits tend to show up when multiple sensory signals are <em>redundant</em>—when they point to the same answer and arrive in a way the brain can easily coordinate. In neuroscience, this is often described as reliability-based integration or <em>cue weighting</em>: the brain gives more influence to the signal that’s most useful for the task at hand. When cues agree, combining them reduces uncertainty. When they don’t, integration can backfire. Adding extra sensory information doesn’t always sharpen perception. Sometimes it softens it—making experience feel fuller or more confident without making it more precise.</p>

<h2>Sensory Competition and Cognitive Effort</h2>
<p>This distinction matters for understanding autism, ADHD, and AuDHD. In many autistic and ADHD individuals, perception appears to rely less on automatic fusion and more on <em>active selection</em>. Instead of quickly blending signals into a single stream, the brain may keep inputs more distinct, weighing them carefully before deciding what belongs together. In neuroscience, this is often described as <em>sensory competition:</em> multiple signals vying for the same interpretive space. When signals arrive together but don’t align cleanly, the brain has to coordinate them in real time.</p>

<p>The issue isn’t confusion. It’s interpretive load.</p>
<p>This helps explain why environments with many simultaneous cues—overlapping conversations, visual motion, competing sounds—can feel effortful even when no single input is intense. Each signal is clear on its own. What’s demanding is deciding how they relate.</p>

<h2>Why Timing Matters More Than Intensity</h2>
<p>Timing plays a role here as well. The brain uses a brief window of time to decide which sensory events belong together. Neuroscience calls this the <em>temporal binding window.</em> When sights and sounds fall within that window, they’re likely to be treated as part of the same event. Research suggests that, on average, autistic individuals may operate with <em>different temporal binding dynamics,</em> meaning that signals are not automatically bound unless their relationship is especially clear. This doesn’t make perception worse, but it can make it more effortful in fast-moving or poorly coordinated environments.</p>

<p>Again, the challenge isn’t noise. It’s deciding what belongs together.</p>
<h2>Selection as a Legitimate Strategy</h2>
<p>From this perspective, multisensory “benefit” doesn’t always come from combining signals. Sometimes it comes from selection—allowing one sensory stream to guide action while others recede into the background. That choice can stabilize perception rather than fragment it. For autistic, ADHD, and AuDHD individuals, what looks from the outside like “tuning things out” or “needing less input” is often a way of managing sensory competition. It’s a strategy for preserving clarity when integration would demand constant negotiation.</p>


<p>Sometimes, the most effective way to work with the world isn’t to take everything in—but to let one thing stand out long enough to matter.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/giving-voice/202601/how-the-brain-chooses-what-matters" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/giving-voice/202601/how-the-brain-chooses-what-matters</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/giving-voice/202601/how-the-brain-chooses-what-matters</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Hari Srinivasan]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-01/Combinesignals.png.jpg?itok=tn-9Zkj0" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When OCD Wrecks Love]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Karen_in_coffee_shop_holding_mug_of_coffee_copy_2-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=GatpHtmE" alt="Karen Cassiday Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">OCD</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">When OCD Wrecks Love</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to recognize romance-related OCD.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Romance-related OCD interferes with your ability to trust your own judgment about a relationship.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Romance-related OCD focuses on "What if this is the wrong person?"</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Romance-related OCD avoids looking at the here and now of a relationship.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Romance-related OCD over-interprets the meaning of small or insignificant flaws in a relationship.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Do%20you%20Love%20Me,%20.jpg?itok=LKVkn6J0" width="193" height="183" data-insert-type="image" title="Adobe/shutterstock/open access" alt="Adobe/shutterstock/open access"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Adobe/shutterstock/open access</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Valentine’s Day is supposed to be a celebration of love and romance, but if you have romance-related OCD, also known as ROCD, then the recent celebration of love may have instead been a trigger for obsessions and compulsions around trying to determine if the person you are with is the right person. Doubt about whether your partner is truly the love of your life can become overwhelming and trap you in a vicious cycle of constantly questioning the quality of your love or your partner’s. It can prompt you to break up prematurely, then make up, and then repeat the cycle repeatedly without ever reaching any certainty about whether you made the right decision. You are left with the burning question, “How do I know if this person is the right one for me?”</p>

<p>When ROCD invades a relationship, it can become difficult to discern when OCD is in operation versus normal caution about wanting a high-quality relationship. It is easy for both clients and their well-intentioned therapists to end up in a pointless argument with OCD that leads only to more doubt, confusion, and despair. What are the ways you can clearly identify when OCD is the culprit as opposed to the personality or character of your partner?</p>

<ul>
<li>OCD focuses upon the imagined “What if?” future in which someone lets you down after it is too late. OCD asks questions like, “What if I chose the wrong person? What if they cannot be a good partner/parent/worker?” It is based on conjecture rather than the here and now.</li>
<li>Helpful thinking focuses on things that have happened or are happening in the present moment and are easy to detect. For example, if you have set yourself a standard for a partner that does not allow drinking alcohol, then you only get worried when you see your partner drinking after they have said they do not. OCD, on the other hand, gets triggered by your non-drinking partner mentioning how much they used to drink and how much they used to like drinking. It asks, “What if this means I cannot trust them, and they will go back to drinking alcohol?” The focus is on imagined harm.</li>
<li>OCD creates confusion and doubt by focusing upon trivial behaviors that what-ifs turn into harbingers of terrible character defects. For example, your partner forgets to text you goodnight with lots of romantic emojis, and you end up believing they are inconsiderate, selfish, and untrustworthy even after you discover they were tired and fell asleep early. OCD does not allow for normal human mistakes and blows little things out of proportion.</li>
<li>OCD always references perfection, the unattainable ideal. OCD gets you stuck on being unable to accept or get past a typical human mistake because it imagines, “What if this means something big and terrible?” OCD takes normal human issues, like sometimes thinking your partner is not sexy, smells bad, or said something poorly, and turns them into imagined representations of terrible flaws in your love or theirs. OCD tends to select problems that others easily forgive and accept.</li>
<li>Flaws that harm love and romance are obvious in the here and now, and others may be readily willing to share your observation that these behaviors are flaws. For example, if you have a disagreement with your partner, exchange harsh words in the heat of anger, and then calm down and listen to each other, you are probably in good standing. If you have a disagreement and your partner screams at you and will not let you say a word, then threatens to hit you, you should be asking yourself whether this person is ready for a relationship. OCD, however, blurs the distinction between these two, equating harsh words with someone truly expressing contempt or being unwilling to hear your point of view.</li>
<li>OCD makes you seek reassurance by grilling your partner about their intentions—what they really meant or what they might do in the future. It makes you review the triggering situation repeatedly to figure out what it <em>might</em> mean, or repeatedly grill ChatGPT about characteristics of your partner, their personality, or their behavior to see if it means something pathological. It can also make you grill everyone else you talk to about their relationships to try to obtain a favorable or unfavorable comparison. Then it can make you doubt the entire process of seeking reassurance, as if you were trying to convince yourself to stay or leave.</li>
</ul>

<p>If any of these bullet points seem like they describe you, then you may feel assured that your OCD is interfering with your relationship. You have been inadvertently caught up in compulsive analysis and reassurance-seeking, rather than trying to uphold high standards. If you are caught in this vicious trap, then my best advice is to seek help from an experienced OCD-knowledgeable therapist who is familiar with Inference-based Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (ICBT) or Exposure with Response Prevention Therapy (ERP).</p>

<p><strong>To find a therapist, </strong><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><strong>visit the Psychology Today Therapy Directory</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-no-worries-guide-to-thriving/202602/when-ocd-wrecks-love" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-no-worries-guide-to-thriving/202602/when-ocd-wrecks-love</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-no-worries-guide-to-thriving/202602/when-ocd-wrecks-love</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Karen Cassiday Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Do%20you%20Love%20Me%2C%20.jpg?itok=k_g9M3vW" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stop Playing Whac-A-Mole With Trauma]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/HURFORD-48-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=KEgGRKGY" alt="Irene Hurford MD" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Trauma</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Stop Playing Whac-A-Mole With Trauma</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why do some people have so many psychiatric diagnoses?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Symptoms don't always mean diagnoses.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Trauma drives many symptoms that can lead to multiple diagnoses.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">These symptoms can be thought of more as communications than as discrete conditions.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_7htumf7htumf7htu.png.jpg?itok=ZOp2GN_X" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Generated with AI/Gemini" alt="Generated with AI/Gemini"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Generated with AI/Gemini</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Because I specialize in treating complex patients, I often see people who come to me with four, five, sometimes six psychiatric diagnoses. Often these patients think that they lost the genetic lottery; how else could they be so unlucky as to have five or six separate biological brain disorders?</p>
<p>To help people understand why I think that they do not have a terrible genetic destiny, I talk about Whac-A-Mole, the arcade game where a player whacks a plastic mole as it pops out of a hole, only to have it disappear and be replaced by another mole somewhere else. Sometimes, psychiatric symptoms are like the moles. You whack down the suicidality, and restrictive eating pops up. You whack down the restrictive eating and obsessions and compulsions pop up. You whack those down and mania pops up, then self-harm behaviors. Then paranoia and hallucinations pop up. Then back to restrictive eating, and so on. Does this person have: 1) major depressive disorder, 2) anorexia nervosa, 3) obsessive-compulsive disorder, and 4) schizoaffective disorder? This is exactly how many people come to me, with multiple serious psychiatric diagnoses under their belt.</p>

<p>But the issue with the Whac-A-Mole game isn’t the moles; it’s the machine in the box under the moles. It turns a crank that pushes the moles out of the holes. You can whack them down as much as you want, but as long as the crank is turning, more moles are going to pop out.</p>
<p>In my long experience with hundreds of complex patients, the machine driving the crank is usually trauma. More specifically, it is frequently early trauma — abuse, neglect, and sometimes insecure or disorganized attachment that occurred before the person’s sense of self was fully established, and sometimes before the child could use language to describe their experiences. Instead of being described with words, the trauma becomes inscribed as symptoms. And these symptoms emerge as <em>communications</em> to the person and others to attempt to describe unrelenting and unprocessed distress. The symptoms themselves are like a language from the wordless, unconscious mind, and they are saying “Help me, I am suffering and I can’t fix this alone." They are not unique illnesses. But in our era of biological psychiatry, they are often treated as distinct disorders, each needing a specific medication or specialized therapy.</p>

<p>Instead, I treat these symptoms as the communications I believe them to be, and the patient and I together come to ask, from a place of safety and curiosity: What is this symptom trying to tell us? As we continue to remain curious, non-reactive, and non-judgmental together, slowly the machine slows down and the moles stop popping up. Trauma is a machine that drives many symptoms. We must look inside the box of the Whac-A-Mole game to shut it down.</p>

<p><strong>To find a therapist, </strong><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><strong>visit the Psychology Today Therapy Directory</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/reality-in-dialogue/202602/stop-playing-whac-a-mole-with-trauma" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/reality-in-dialogue/202602/stop-playing-whac-a-mole-with-trauma</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/reality-in-dialogue/202602/stop-playing-whac-a-mole-with-trauma</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Irene Hurford MD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_7htumf7htumf7htu.png.jpg?itok=2BAJoU9U" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Can You Lose Weight and Still Be Body Positive?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-11/CSW_2817-Edit-Edit-2-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=c_AiFAuB" alt="Carolyn Karoll LCSW-C, CEDS-S" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Body Positivity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Can You Lose Weight and Still Be Body Positive?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What body positivity was meant to be.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Body positivity was meant to challenge weight stigma, not celebrate weight loss.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Care for the body does not have to mean shrinking it.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Weight loss can reinforce beliefs that keep eating disorders alive.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Health and worth are not determined by body size.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-01/fuu-j-Fu7RNjl-pW0-unsplash.jpg?itok=75tI6XVF" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Fuu J on Unsplash" alt="Photo by Fuu J on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Fuu J on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The question, "Can you lose weight and still be body positive?" has been coming up more often lately, especially as GLP-1 medications for weight loss have entered the mainstream and complicated already fraught conversations about bodies, health, and care.</p>
<p>On the surface, it sounds reasonable: People want to take care of themselves. Bodies change. Weight fluctuates. Wanting to feel better in your body is human.</p>

<p>But the question itself reveals something deeper. It reflects how tightly we have fused weight with worth, health, and virtue. And that fusion is exactly what body positivity was meant to challenge.</p>
<p>The honest answer is that it’s complicated. Context matters. But before trying to answer, it helps to revisit what body positivity was originally about.</p>

<h2>What Body Positivity Was Meant to Be</h2>
<p>Body positivity did not begin as a self-love slogan or a marketing campaign. It grew out of fat activism, led largely by fat, Black, and queer activists pushing back against anti-fat bias. At its core, it was about dignity, safety, and equal worth for people whose bodies are marginalized.</p>

<p>It was never about changing your appearance so you could finally feel good about yourself. It was about challenging systems that equate thinness with morality, health, and value.</p>
<p>As the concept moved into the mainstream, its edges softened. Today, it is often framed as confidence-building or personal transformation, sometimes centered on weight loss. When that happens, the original intent gets diluted. If body positivity only feels accessible when a body is shrinking, it stops disrupting the hierarchy and starts reinforcing it.</p>

<h2>Care Does Not Have to Mean Shrinking</h2>
<p>Many of us were taught early on that being healthy means being thinner. Over time, self-care and weight loss became intertwined.</p>
<p>But caring for the body does not have to mean shrinking it.</p>
<p>Eating regularly. Moving in ways that feel supportive rather than punishing. Managing stress. Getting enough rest. Taking medication when needed. Following up on labs. These are forms of care that can exist independent of weight loss.</p>

<p>When weight loss becomes the primary measure of success, it subtly reinforces the idea that a smaller body is a better body. That message does not disappear simply because it is packaged as empowerment.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/i-yunmai-5jctAMjz21A-unsplash.jpg?itok=oAhKbHON" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by i yunmai on Unsplash" alt="Photo by i yunmai on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by i yunmai on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Weight, Health, and Stigma</h2>
<p>Weight and health are more complex than we have been led to believe. Many people improve blood pressure, blood sugar, and stamina through behavior change alone, regardless of what happens to the scale.</p>
<p>At the same time, weight stigma is real. Larger-bodied people often encounter dismissive care, delayed diagnoses, and biased assumptions. Those experiences themselves contribute to poorer health outcomes.</p>

<p>A body-positive approach to health does not ignore well-being. It insists that respectful, evidence-based care should not depend on body size.</p>
<h2>What This Means in Eating Disorder Recovery</h2>
<p>For individuals in eating disorder recovery, this conversation can be destabilizing.</p>
<p>When weight loss is framed as self-improvement or empowerment, it can blur important boundaries. For many people healing from anorexia, bulimia, binge-eating disorder, or chronic restriction, a renewed focus on weight can quietly reactivate old patterns of control, shame, and self-surveillance.</p>

<p>In eating disorder recovery, the goal is rarely to love how your body looks every day. The goal is peace: Peace with food. Relief from constant body checking. Freedom from the belief that life will finally begin once the body changes.</p>
<p>For many, body neutrality offers a steadier path than constant positivity. It means treating the body with respect without making appearance the central project of your life.</p>

<p>So, can someone lose weight and still identify as body positive? Perhaps. But when the focus remains on weight, we risk missing the larger point: Body positivity was never about celebrating weight loss. It was about dismantling the belief that worth must be earned through changing your body.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/eating-disorder-recovery/202601/can-you-lose-weight-and-still-be-body-positive" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/eating-disorder-recovery/202601/can-you-lose-weight-and-still-be-body-positive</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/eating-disorder-recovery/202601/can-you-lose-weight-and-still-be-body-positive</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Carolyn Karoll LCSW-C, CEDS-C]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-01/fuu-j-Fu7RNjl-pW0-unsplash.jpg?itok=gvUr1wWK" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to View the Concept of Shaming]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/thumbnail_001_me_11.2020_monalong-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=fzbeyHLs" alt="Michael R Edelstein Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Shame</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How to View the Concept of Shaming</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">No one can make you feel ashamed—only you can.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Your emotions are caused by your thinking.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">You can change your thinking.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Rational thinking exercises can help reframe negative self-beliefs and emotions.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>If you feel shame, recognize that no one else can shame you; only you can make yourself feel ashamed. Only you have the power to create your emotions—positive, negative, helpful, or unhelpful. </p>
<h2>The Stoics</h2>
<p>Hundreds of years ago, the Greek and Roman Stoics advanced that insight. </p>
<p>In his treatise the Enchiridion, Epictetus wrote: Men are disturbed not by the things that happen but by their opinions about those things. </p>

<p>In his Epistles, Seneca stated: Everything depends on opinion. Ambition, luxury, greed, all look back to opinion.</p>
<p>Cicero, Montaigne, Schopenhauer, Shakespeare, and many others throughout history have all echoed similar sentiments. </p>
<p>If, for example, you experience an emotion when someone insults you, it's natural to assume that the opinion and judgment of others can make you feel a certain way. In fact, this is false. Should someone insult, mock, ridicule, or disparage you on social media, for example, for saying something they disagreed with or claimed was uninformed, like, "you are ignorant," keep in mind it's just their judgment, their opinion. And their opinion cannot change you as a person. </p>

<p>No matter what anyone says, you always remain the same imperfect human who, at the very worst, acts imperfectly. You never become a worthless or bad person. </p>
<p>For example, someone insulting you about being overweight is sometimes called "fat shaming." If you do feel ashamed, here's the good news: it's unnecessary to lose weight in order to get over your feeling of shame. No one can make you feel ashamed of your appearance. If you're overweight or even obese, no matter how much others disapprove or critically point it out, you can refuse to make yourself feel hurt. </p>

<h2>Irrational Beliefs and Shame</h2>
<p>Avoid telling yourself one or more of the following irrational beliefs:</p>
<ol>
<li>I must not be fat. </li>
<li>I must not be disapproved of. </li>
<li>I must not look like a glutton.</li>
<li>I should be in control of my eating.</li>
<li>I must be at a perfect weight.</li>
<li>I am an inferior, weak, disgusting person. I must be thin to be acceptable.</li>
<li>I can't stand this uncomfortable feeling of shame. </li>
<li>It's awful to be overweight. </li>
</ol>

<p>Suppose you're disturbed because you have a demand, for example, "I must not be fat."</p>
<h2>A Practical Approach</h2>
<p>You can practice the Three Minute Therapy exercise to address this. Here's an example: </p>
<p>A. (Activating Event) I was called "fat."</p>
<p>B. (Irrational Belief) I must not be fat. </p>
<p>C. (Undesirable Emotional Consequence) Shame.</p>

<p>D. (Disputing or Questioning the Irrational Belief) What is the evidence that proves I absolutely must not be fat?</p>
<p>E. (Effective New Thinking) There exists no evidence to prove I must not be referred to as fat. Although I strongly prefer never to be viewed this way, there is no reason why I must not. Since I don't run the universe and I don't control others, I will be thought of the way others choose to view me, not necessarily the way I wish to be thought of. Although I do not like this possibility I definitely can rationally stand what I do not like. </p>

<p>F. (New Feeling) Concern, disappointment, displeasure. </p>
<p>Practice writing out these exercises daily to change your thinking with the goal of avoiding shame by developing unconditional self-acceptance. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-three-minute-therapist/202601/how-to-view-the-concept-of-shaming" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-three-minute-therapist/202601/how-to-view-the-concept-of-shaming</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-three-minute-therapist/202601/how-to-view-the-concept-of-shaming</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael R Edelstein Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-busranur-aydin-3800407-16662472.jpg?itok=Eo2ZgBup" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>