<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 21:34:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 21:34:20 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Who Doesn't Want to Join the Happiness Club?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-11/ritaluss.png.jpg?itok=aIeddRSU" alt="Rita Lussier" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Personal Perspectives</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Who Doesn't Want to Join the Happiness Club?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: No meetings. No requirements. No dues. Just joy!</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article_inline_full">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_full_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_full_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/edu-lauton-TyQ-0lPp6e4-unsplash.jpg?itok=wSo3OpZY" width="639" height="435" data-insert-type="image" alt="Oh what a feeling!" title="Edu Lauton/Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption">Oh what a feeling!</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Edu Lauton/Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>During the fall, at a nearby high school, there was a period set aside for the students to sign up for clubs. From what I heard, there are clubs available for just about every imaginable interest.</p>
<p>There’s the Jewish Federation Club. (You don’t have to be Jewish to join.) The Christian Fellowship. (You don’t have to be Christian either.) There are clubs for chess, debate, fantasy sports, and Frisbee. There’s even a Cake-of-the-Month Club that might be about baking, or maybe it’s for eating. (Probably both).</p>

<p>As I learned about all the possibilities opening up in their young world, I couldn’t help thinking how great it is to have these opportunities for students to lead and belong and stretch in new directions. But I must say there was one organization that fascinated me above all the rest, that I’m still thinking about today.</p>

<p>The Happiness Club.</p>
<p>Apparently, the way it works is simple. You’re not required to attend meetings. (Makes sense to me. A Happiness Club would understand that you don’t need another thing on your schedule.) </p>
<p>Well, if there are no meetings, then what’s this club about?</p>
<p>From what I understand, the idea is to promote positive energy as a way to offset the stress and drama that seem to be as much a part of high school life these days as, well, geometry and chemistry. The way you do that, apparently, is very simple. All you have to do is go around and give compliments.</p>

<p>How many kids signed up? Just about everyone. I’m not surprised.</p>
<p>If you think this sounds like a silly idea, think again. When was the last time you received a compliment? When did someone take the time to tell you that they genuinely appreciated something about you? Something as simple as saying they liked your jacket, they admired the way you presented your ideas at a meeting, they enjoyed the chicken casserole you made, or how they loved the story you told about getting stuck in the parking lot at the mall so much that they wanted to hear you tell it again? Be honest. Didn’t it make you feel good? Didn’t it make you feel worthwhile? Didn’t it put a little spring in your step as you moved forward to take on the rest of your day?</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The problem is that we all get so busy, so narrowly focused on what it is we have to accomplish, that we don’t often look up and see the efforts of those around us. We tend to take a lot of things for granted. We’re all going so fast we barely notice the jacket, the presentation, the casserole, the mall parking lot story. And even if we do, we fly right by and on to the next thing.</p>

<p>When we’re traveling so fast, the scenery around us begins to blur until it’s almost invisible. Sadly, all that tends to get a reaction from us anymore are the potholes. The impossible assignment from our boss. The plumber who kept us waiting for hours. Our property taxes went up again.</p>
<p>I know we’re not in high school anymore, but maybe there’s still room for new members of The Happiness Club. After all, you don’t have to fill out any forms, you don’t have to go to any meetings. There are no dues and no expectations. Except for one. When you go about your day, keep your eyes open for the good things. The people around you who are doing a good job. Helping. Trying. Giving. Loving. Smiling. Compliment them. Maybe two.</p>

<p>And someday, with any luck, they just might return the favor. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/for-the-moment/202602/who-doesnt-want-to-join-the-happiness-club" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/for-the-moment/202602/who-doesnt-want-to-join-the-happiness-club</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/for-the-moment/202602/who-doesnt-want-to-join-the-happiness-club</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Rita Lussier]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/edu-lauton-TyQ-0lPp6e4-unsplash.jpg?itok=ZatlMWF6" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Can Any Good Come From Guilt?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Krystine-Batcho.jpg?itok=LcStDQdr" alt="Krystine I. Batcho Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Guilt</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Can Any Good Come From Guilt?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Guilt can help transform empathy into prosocial action.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Someone can feel guilty about what they have done or failed to do, whether their choice harmed someone or not.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Guilt can help prevent harm to others but can be counterproductive when undeserved, obsessive, or excessive.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Coping with guilt can motivate personal growth, prosocial behavior, and the search for meaning and purpose.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Wall%20Small%20IMG_3136.JPG.jpg?itok=yih79PVj" width="300" height="400" data-insert-type="image" title="Krystine I. Batcho" alt="Krystine I. Batcho"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Krystine I. Batcho</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Guilt may be the most unpopular emotion. If you feel guilty from time to time, you’re not alone. It is not limited to criminal, cruel, or extreme behaviors. Guilt is felt in some way and to some degree by people throughout the world and throughout the lifespan. </p>
<p>A core element in human experience, guilt is a surprisingly complicated emotion. Theorists have distinguished among types of guilt. Guilt can be objective when a person violates an accepted rule or law or subjective when someone violates their own personal moral code. One can feel guilty about something they have done or failed to do, whether their behavior harmed another or not. Survivor’s guilt, for example, can be directed inward toward oneself, in contrast to situations in which action or inaction resulted in another’s suffering. Someone can feel guilty over a false memory or an event they remember inaccurately.</p>

<h2>What if there were no guilt?</h2>
<p>One of the most important distinctions is between adaptive and maladaptive guilt. Is guilt useless at best and harmful at worst? Can any good come from guilt? Thinking about the helpful or harmful consequences of guilt raises the question of whether guilt serves a psychological, emotional, or social purpose. </p>

<p>Imagine if guilt did not exist? Does the absence of guilt necessarily indicate innocence? Imagine a perfect world where there would be no need for guilt. But we are not in a perfect world. In our imperfect world, imagine a person who never feels guilt, not because they are perfectly innocent, but because they do not, will not, or cannot feel guilt. They may not be capable or willing to feel remorse. </p>

<p>Research suggests that only a very small portion of the population possesses such a trait—individuals who display behaviors and traits characteristic of antisocial personality disorder. The absence of guilt or remorse can permit a range of actions that endanger or harm others, increase the likelihood of impulsive or reckless behaviors, damage relationships, and lead to unhealthy choices such as substance abuse that contribute to a shorter lifespan.</p>

<p>If the absence of guilt can be problematic, is the presence of guilt beneficial? Guilt can prevent harm to others by inhibiting criminal or antisocial behavior. But how can guilt for inaction, unintended acts, or behavior that has harmed no one serve a purpose? Guilt associated with imagined responsibility, illogical or erroneous reasoning, or what can never be restored or remedied seems to serve no healthy purpose. When such guilt is severe, persists, and interferes with living a fulfilling, meaningful life, it can become maladaptive.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Guilt can become destructive</h2>
<p>Guilt can be counterproductive when it serves no social purpose or personal good. </p>
<p>Unrelenting or extreme feelings of guilt can stem from or contribute to depression.</p>
<p>Individuals who misinterpret neutral or superficial events as evidence of their personal inadequacies and/or an exaggerated sense of their responsibility for negative events can experience unhealthy guilt.</p>

<p>Unrealistic or obsessive guilt can lead to feelings of worthlessness, self-hate, and, over time, contribute to reclusive behavior and loneliness.</p>
<p>When someone becomes preoccupied with guilt, their feeling can escalate into a cascade of illogical thoughts of unfounded responsibility for adverse events. For example, someone can feel guilty for being ill, for a loved one not overcoming addiction, or not being able to end homelessness, war, or poverty.</p>


<h2>Unrelenting guilt can be difficult to overcome</h2>
<p>In some cases, being forgiven doesn’t alleviate guilt. Guilt is a self-conscious, self-imposed emotion. We can’t depend upon others to control our feelings, and we wouldn’t want to. When what we have done or have failed to do hurts someone, the fact that the hurt happened is impossible to change.</p>

<p>The past cannot be undone or redone. Time cannot be rewound or permit a do-over.</p>
<p>Whether or not loss can be restored, the hurt that was inflicted occurred, and nothing can change that.</p>
<p>Imagined harm or harm that someone is not responsible for can inflict undeserved feelings of guilt that are especially difficult to counteract.</p>



  


<h2>What good is guilt, if any?</h2>
<p>The universality of guilt suggests that it serves a purpose. Guilt can serve a social purpose when it restrains harm to others, prompts someone to apologize or make restitution to an injured person, prevents harm to future potential victims, and motivates prosocial, altruistic, or charitable behavior.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The purpose, if any, of guilt in cases of unintended harm or no actual harm at all is not clear. As with cases in which there is responsibility, guilt can inspire and invigorate compassion and empathy.</p>
<p>Guilt can be thought of as a proverbial fork in the road. It can urge us to choose a path to diminished self-worth, self-hate, and isolation, or it can inspire us to grow through inner reflection and the search for meaning and purpose.</p>

<h2>Coping with guilt</h2>
<p>It is possible to travel a constructive path in dealing with guilt. A number of approaches have been identified as helpful in dealing with guilt.</p>
<ul>
<li>Making restitution when possible</li>
<li>Apologizing and seeking forgiveness</li>
<li>Helping others, supporting efforts to prevent future harm to others (e.g., informing others about risks of social media engagement)</li>
<li>Gaining constructive insight into the reasons for feeling guilty</li>
<li>Discovering and correcting errors in perception, memory, or reasoning</li>
<li>Extending our empathy and compassion for others to ourselves to develop self-compassion and self-forgiveness</li>
<li>Using mental imagery, meditation, and reflection to discover our valuable potential to benefit others</li>
</ul>

<p>Consistent with the principle that "nature abhors a vacuum," translating thoughts and feelings into actions can interrupt the cycle of self-perpetuating non-productive guilt and promote growth beyond guilt.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>In many cases, it may be less about eliminating feelings of guilt and more about transforming them into personal growth and prosocial behaviors to benefit others. Professional resources are available for individuals when severe guilt becomes overwhelming, interferes with living a fulfilling life, and/or contributes to depression, anxiety, and loneliness.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>We might not always be able to put the guilt behind us. In some cases, we may need to carry it along. But we can become stronger by gaining self-respect for the positive qualities of compassion and empathy that make us who we are and enable us to transform guilt into good.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/longing-for-nostalgia/202602/can-any-good-come-from-guilt" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/longing-for-nostalgia/202602/can-any-good-come-from-guilt</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/longing-for-nostalgia/202602/can-any-good-come-from-guilt</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Krystine I. Batcho Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Wall%20Small%20IMG_3136.JPG.jpg?itok=Vt0lQfyb" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Be Less Miserable, a Review]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/untitled_2_1.jpg?itok=y16lfrvH" alt="Christopher Lane Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Happiness</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">"How to Be Less Miserable": A Review</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A new book discusses the science of unhappiness and how we can suffer less.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Misery—like disappointment—has different cultural causes, meanings, and traditions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A new book on reducing misery looks at neuroscientific research on comparison-making and self-destructiveness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">"How to Be Miserable" urges greater tolerance for discordance, detachment, and self-acceptance.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Ma,%20How%20to%20Be%20Less%20Miserable%20(2025).png.jpg?itok=YR5g1TOS" width="320" height="421" data-insert-type="image" alt="Lybi Ma, How to Be Less Miserable" title="Blackstone Publishing, 2025, with permission"></div>
<div class="caption">Lybi Ma, How to Be Less Miserable</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Blackstone Publishing, 2025, with permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Nearly 75 years ago, in 1952, when positive psychology set off a wave of religiously inspired self-help in the U.S. with the release of Norman Vincent Peale’s popular bestseller <em>The Power of Positive Thinking, </em>the psychiatrist and psychoanalyst Wilhelm Reich asked in war-torn Austria, in a now-famous exchange with his colleague Kurt Eissler, “Where does the misery come from?”</p>

<p>The timing in each case was not a coincidence. Frustrated by Freud’s argument that psychical suffering was mostly due to internal warfare—a despotic and implacable superego, ruled by unappeasable death instinct—Reich wanted the focus turned outward, “out where the people were,” to take more of the war into account and somehow to treat social dynamics and oppression, tied to the poverty that was then regionwide.</p>

<p>Rethinking the causes of misery appeared necessary in war-torn Europe. However, Reich’s spin on one of Freud’s last best models for our “discontents” oversimplified the type of internal divisiveness that was said to remain, leaving the superego more like a guardian to societal values than, per Freud’s late work, the vehicle for an almost insurmountable hostility, redirected at us without filter or mercy, making us far more miserable than is necessary or useful.</p>

<p>As relevant for the path taken: While Freudian psychoanalysis struggled to calibrate misery’s internal and external causes, the religiously inspired self-belief that Peale marketed across North America eventually hit a roadblock with self-doubt, failure, and self-sabotage, as Freud predicted. By 1957, Peale made the pressure for self-affirmation so unrelenting that he began to view a low opinion of oneself as “an affront to God.” “Never entertain a failure thought,” he admonished fellow Americans, cheering presumptions of their exceptionalism while channeling Alfred Adler on their inferiority complexes, as if imitating a superego the country had lost. “You’re disintegrating. You’re deteriorating. You’re dying on the vine.”</p>

<h2>Where does the misery come from?</h2>
<p>The 20th-century debate over the origins and implications of our misery has an important update. In <em>How to Be Less Miserable: End the Negative Mind Loops and Find Joy, </em>a new book by author-editor Lybi Ma, the debate is recast to incorporate neuroscientific findings showing that, under pressure, “the brain wants us to suffer.” With an in-built disposition to bias and exaggerated threat—likely a holdover from evolution—we not only overcompensate for what are frequently distorted and misperceived threats, but also, as a species, have an in-built “tendency for suffering” that, with self-awareness, patience, and humor, we can learn to counteract, to make our internal lives a lot more bearable.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>“The brain makes errors in judgment to protect us,” Ma extrapolates from studies that repeatedly corroborate the overreaction as a type of emotional flooding tied to the rapid release of dopamine. “It wants to protect us from unknown certainties, but it does too good a job sometimes, and this results in our daily lives being hijacked by unhappy thoughts.”</p>

<p>Ma’s more-benign, less-tragic emphasis on patterns of <em>overreaction,</em> rather than on <em>deficits</em> and <em>failures,</em> shifts the ground for recovery, from treating and mistreating individualized disorders to engaging more with ill-considered behaviors, including self-destructive ones, that are often exaggerated by cultural biases and blindspots requiring a different approach. This, in turn, modifies how we think about the problem and how we can resolve it.</p>

<p><em>How to Be Less Miserable </em>is especially relevant for those of us prone to overthink casual and throwaway remarks, not to indulge them as part of an arsenal of disappointments and regrets, but to reset them as part of a broader challenge of engaging socially and professionally, of dealing with a world that can have very sharp elbows. “Sometimes,” Ma writes of the stress and endless chatter we internalize, “it gets so noisy that it spirals in a perpetual loop, which can drive anyone out of their mind. We wind up rolling around in our thoughts, finding ourselves in limitless unease.”</p>

<h2>Cultural mistranslation and bicultural fluency</h2>
<p>Ma’s story: Her family is Hui (Chinese Muslims) from the Tibetan-Qinghai plateau in Northwest China. Her parents and older siblings fled the Cultural Revolution for Hong Kong, where she was born, and the family later emigrated to the United States. Ultimately, she took up long-term tenure (almost 26 years) as executive editor of <em>Psychology Today, </em>a periodical that focuses on bringing the behavioral sciences to a large public. This is especially well-suited to her argument and her approach. (Full disclosure: Ma has been my main editor at this publication<em> </em>since 2009.)</p>



  


<blockquote><p>My Hui cousins, in our homeland of Northwest China, don’t slosh around in what could have been or ought to be. Instead, they frequently use the expression<em> </em>bai le<em> </em>(败了)<em>,</em> a saying used to convey <em>defeat</em>, but in fact meaning much more than that. It’s used to express, Let it go. Oh, well. That’s too bad.<em> </em>He missed the train. Bai le. She didn’t get the job. Bai le.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The saying applies to both minor and major events. And rather than endorsing flippancy or fatalism, it allows a person to detach from the problem, to accept that “hardship is part of our everyday existence”—that we can find room for its ambiguities and uncertainties without being thrown by them.</p>
<p>To Ma, <em>bai le </em>is in this respect a useful remedy to the U.S. cultural tendency to overdramatize and catastrophize, to personalize and polarize, and to indulge too much in all-or-nothing thinking. (<em>Why does life suck? Why do I always mess up? Why does everybody hate me?</em>) A tolerable life in a complex and dynamic society requires large doses of self-compassion and a willingness to accept multiple shades of gray.</p>

<p>The beauty of Ma’s approach is that it restores movement to relationships that have become paralyzed by dysfunction. It starts by putting the self at a distance, either by writing or third-person speech (Ma’s funny examples: <em>Jane is feeling sorry for herself because she didn’t get that party invitation; The shop clerk was not kind to Auntie Lin</em>) to reframe what can seem tragically inevitable as what is mostly learned but a rote reaction.</p>

<h2>The mind’s tendency to hamstring us</h2>
<p>Rather than accepting we must be our own worst enemy, with self-sabotaging behaviors and negative states of mind that lead to rumination and paralysis, Ma builds insight and compassion into self-examination to help show thoughts and actions in a different light. A key step is becoming “alert to the mind’s tendency to hamstring us. It is not designed to deal with discordance.”</p>

<p>Coupled with her shared findings from neuroscience, Ma’s emphasis on cultural blindspots reframes compensatory behaviors and reactions that can spiral into substance abuse. Related—and as helpful—is her warning that Westerners chasing “extreme positivity” are likely fighting a losing battle with hedonic adaptation. They are “working too hard to find bliss.”</p>

<p>Brimming with insight and wisdom, <em>How to Be Less Miserable </em>is succinct, readable, and pragmatic. It offers a way to change perspective that can recast the problem entirely. Its goal is appealing and irresistible: to replace fruitless self-berating with greater acceptance, self-compassion, and trying not to fight with oneself, with others, and with life.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>“Looking inward is what we need to be doing,” Ma notes. “However, we can’t do that when we suffer a disingenuous relationship with ourselves. Not being ourselves is problematic because we must live with ourselves all our lives. No one else can do it for us.”</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/side-effects/202602/how-to-be-less-miserable-a-review" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/side-effects/202602/how-to-be-less-miserable-a-review</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/side-effects/202602/how-to-be-less-miserable-a-review</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Christopher Lane Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_154811264.jpg?itok=TH8RvthN" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Therapy Can Make Us More Interested in Others]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/nicholas-balaisis.jpg?itok=ZZmEqlTk" alt="Nicholas Balaisis Ph.D., RP" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Therapy Can Make Us More Interested in Others</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Therapy is not "navel-gazing."</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Myths of therapy producing self-obsessed people still exist.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychological symptoms tend to narrow one's life focus internally.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Treating symptoms can free a person from narrow self-focus and make others more interesting.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Upon first glance, therapy often seems like an exercise in intensive self-inspection, introspection, and even indulgent navel gazing. It is sometimes dismissed as a luxury or life "extra," like a spa day or a massage. A <em>nice-</em>to-have, not a <em>need-</em>to-have, in the general world of wellness and self-care. At worst, it is thought of as a narcissistic enterprise that merely strengthens the ego or self-concept. It might make us smugly secure in ourselves as our therapist symbolically "high-fives" our goals, attributes, and achievements to date.</p>

<p>There is probably some truth in these claims, and clinical training warned against <em>benign therapy</em>: therapy that merely flatters the client’s ego and does not challenge or question certain patient narratives or worldviews. Ironically, this form may be most evident in certain AI bots like ChatGPT and their overly sycophantic design structure.</p>

<h2>Clinical Symptoms as Narcissistically Oriented</h2>
<p>In most clinical cases, however, it is the symptoms we experience that are self-indulgent and "me-oriented." When we are gripped by mild or major symptoms, we often have little grander perceptive on things and are locked into a narrow and deeply personalistic gaze.</p>

<p>A panic attack forces us dramatically inwards—into our racing thoughts or somatic feelings. When we are gripped by such strong symptoms, all we can think about is our embodied distress—we are too much in ourselves. It can feel psychologically claustrophobic. It is this intensity of self-inwardness that can lead to violent self-harm, like cutting, as a way to try and symbolically and literally escape from the pain of interiority.</p>

<p>Treatment here, in a therapeutic setting, often involves the very opposite of navel-gazing. We are encouraged via mindfulness to take notice of the world—the sky, birds, moving clouds. We may distract ourselves with music, an activity with others, or listen to a guided meditation. Therapy here is a way of bringing us out of ourselves, the heretic cage of our psyches, and back in touch, often literally, with grass, objects, and other people. It can be a lifeline back to the world.</p>

<p>Even milder fixations or presenting issues narrow our focus onto ourselves. Think about a career anxiety, a preoccupation with a family member, or a lingering regret. We may replay memories and images of past experiences related to ourselves. These fixations often come at the expense of the present—of being able to take notice of what is in front of us. They can rid themselves of the power of surprise and novelty as we remain trapped in a stubborn filter of reality rooted in past triggers, past versions of ourselves.</p>

<h2>Finding Interest in the World and Others</h2>
<p>Good therapy can free us from ourselves, from past experiences or previous notions of the world that impede our ability to be present or move forward. Freud famously talked about the cure as being able to return to the simple joys of love and work: an <em>ordinary unhappiness</em>. To someone trapped by recurrent neuroses, it is like the world is an extension of our anxiety or depression. It filters everything through this lens, and some people speak of losing their sense of colour, taste, or <em>seasoning</em> for the <em>greyness</em> of life. Excessive symptomology, like addiction, makes the world a boring place.</p>


<p>Managing and weakening the hold that symptoms have on us—addiction, anxiety, simmering resentments—returns the world to its rightful empirical place as something <em>interesting</em>. People, animals, societies, and cultures are, without a doubt, fascinating. Enough to hold our attention and motivate interest in this life. Anxious or depressed feelings rob us of that objectivity as they imprison us in our minds.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Therapy is thus an ironic or contradictory exercise when carried through to success. The more we attend to our symptoms, the less we are held captive by them, and the more we can return our attention to others and the world. Our preoccupations become less interesting, and we may have more bandwidth for others. Our parents’ stories are more compelling, a movie more fascinating, and a walk in the park can yield surprises.</p>



  


<p>Played out even further, of course, therapy makes itself redundant. When we treat the symptoms, we lose the need to focus on ourselves in therapy and make our way back into the world. A successful therapy, therefore, is not one that cloisters us within ourselves, creating self entitled narcissist. Rather, successful therapy opens new mental space for the reception of the novelties of reality that are indeed marvellous and surprising. </p>

<p><em>To find a therapist, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-devices-our-selves/202602/how-therapy-can-make-us-more-interested-in-others" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-devices-our-selves/202602/how-therapy-can-make-us-more-interested-in-others</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-devices-our-selves/202602/how-therapy-can-make-us-more-interested-in-others</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicholas Balaisis Ph.D., RP]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-italo-melo-881954-2379005.jpg?itok=veLUGPE4" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Importance of Media Psychology in Cybersecurity]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Bernie-Luskin.jpg?itok=eC8GyhzK" alt="Bernard J. Luskin, Ed.D., MFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Media</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Importance of Media Psychology in Cybersecurity</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Cyber threats are ominous, real, affect millions, and are increasing.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cybersecurity breaches often target human psychological vulnerabilities.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cyber threats affect millions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cybersecurity is an important new career opportunity.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Media psychology is fundamental in cybersecurity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/download%20(1)%20AU%20cyber%20sec%20image.jpg?itok=OmKCcEwF" width="300" height="168" data-insert-type="image" alt="Cybersecurity Protection" title="Amer U, with permission"></div>
<div class="caption">Cybersecurity Protection</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Amer U, with permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Cyber threats are are not only ominous and real, affecting millions of citizens, but growing in sophistication and frequency. Cybersecurity breaches often target human vulnerabilities. </p>
<p>Media psychology, particularly the study of how and why people perceive, process, and act on digital information—offers key insights into why individuals fall for cyber manipulation. In my media psychology courses, we study more than 50 theories that may apply to cybersecurity situations and how they can be used to protect against breach and manipulation. Among the 50 are the following five.</p>

<p><strong>1. Persuasion Theory</strong></p>
<p>Cyber attackers frequently embed persuasion cues such as authority, urgency, and scarcity into their phishing messages. During the COVID‑19 pandemic, for example, the FBI discovered a spike in phishing emails impersonating corporate IT departments by having subject lines like <em>“</em>Mandatory Password Reset—Action Required Immediately.<em>”</em> </p>

<p>Do not respond!</p>
<p>Attempts such as this use the appeal of authority and urgency to increase user compliance.[1] The obvious goal of the deceivers was to persuade a user to provide a password for unsavory purposes. Protecting against this type of <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/deception">deception</a> is fundamental in the cybersecurity of systems design.</p>

<p><strong>2. Attention and Cognitive Confusion</strong></p>
<p>Media psychology postulates that attention is limited and also easily disrupted. Attackers exploit moments of distraction by creating strategic multitasking. For example, a Google/Jigsaw study found that users are twice as likely to click phishing links when cognitively overloaded with tasks and messages. [2] This demonstrates how the design of code layers for purposes of confusion increases susceptibility.</p>

<p><strong>3. Cognitive Bias</strong></p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/download%20(2)%20cyber%20sec%20image.jpg?itok=_NHmy1AN" width="284" height="177" data-insert-type="image" alt="Media Psychology of Cybersecurity" title="Research Gate, with permission"></div>
<div class="caption">Media Psychology of Cybersecurity</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Research Gate, with permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Expressing bias shapes how people react to digital messages, often leading to predictable errors. For example,<strong> </strong>a UPS/FedEx phishing wave succeeded because attackers exploited confirmation bias (people expected package delays) and optimism bias (believing they were unlikely targets).[3]</p>
<p><strong>4. Emotional Arousal</strong></p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Emotionally charged content triggers pressure on decision‑making, bypassing analytical reasoning. For example, cybersecurity research reveals breaches caused by tech support scams through the use of alarming pop‑up messages, such as,“Your device is infected—call support immediately.”<em> </em>[4] The media psychology here identifies how fear-based appeals entice users into compliance with false requests.</p>

<p><strong>5. Social Identity and Group Influence</strong></p>
<p>People trust messages that appear to come from their in-group because they have familiar communication patterns. For example, The Department of Justice reported that at the 2016 Democratic National Committee, a major breach succeeded partly because phishing emails mimicked legitimate internal communication styles, in which social identity cues were used to reduce suspicion. [5] Perpetrators persuaded receivers to respond to false messages of perceived legitimacy.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/div46-logo-sml_tcm12-187266.png.jpg?itok=4IyIEBe5" width="320" height="91" data-insert-type="image" alt="Society for Media Psychology and Technology" title="APA Media Psychology Div., with permission"></div>
<div class="caption">Society for Media Psychology and Technology</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: APA Media Psychology Div., with permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Conclusions</h2>
<p>Cybersecurity is an increasingly important new-collar job and career opportunity. Media psychology is fundamental in cybersecurity because it explains <em>why</em> users fall for digital manipulation. </p>
<p>Cyber threats are rampant, and, as they design new systems to properly protect consumers, cybersecurity experts must understand and work with theories in media psychology. Cybersecurity is an increasingly important field and offers new-collar career opportunities. </p>

<p>Experts in cybersecurity trumpet a major admonition to “pay thoughtful attention.” Development of education programs in cybersecurity is increasingly important, and, because behavior matters, media psychology is an important subject in the technical design of systems.</p>
<p>Within the American Psychological Association, members of the Society for Media Psychology and Technology, Media Psychology, Division 46, study and report on the nature and application of media psychology in cybersecurity design. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-media-psychology-effect/202602/the-importance-of-media-psychology-in-cybersecurity" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-media-psychology-effect/202602/the-importance-of-media-psychology-in-cybersecurity</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-media-psychology-effect/202602/the-importance-of-media-psychology-in-cybersecurity</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Bernard J. Luskin, Ed.D., MFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/download%20%281%29%20AU%20cyber%20sec%20image.jpg?itok=fRQfZ13S" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>