<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 15:55:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 15:55:02 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mental Health and Sickness Benefits: Lessons From History]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-07/Joanna_Moncrieff.png.jpg?itok=bk8tGyE5" alt="Joanna Moncrieff" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychiatry</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Mental Health and Sickness Benefits: Lessons From History</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">History shows us we do not need to medicalise problems to support people.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>Are we spending too much on welfare by classifying people who could work as mentally ill? Politicians may think we are over-diagnosing mental illness but psychiatrists suggest we need to hire more psychiatrists to cure it. The history of welfare shows it has always been contested, but also that we do not need to give people medical labels to provide financial or social support. </p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IFS%20benefits.png.jpg?itok=gsIgdzz0" width="320" height="206" data-insert-type="image" title="Institute for Fiscal Studies / Used With Permission" alt="Institute for Fiscal Studies / Used With Permission"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Institute for Fiscal Studies / Used With Permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>The debate</h2>
<p>There is a heated debate raging in the UK about the benefits bill, which has been rising rapidly, especially among the young. Mental health problems account for the majority of sickness benefit claims, with <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/calls-for-evidence/young-people-and-work-report-call-for-evidence/young-people-and-work-report-call-for-evidence#:~:text=In%20England%2C%20in%202024%20those,health%20issues%20or%20neurodevelopmental%20conditions.">80% of young people </a>on benefits claiming for a mental or neurodevelopmental disorder. Politicians worry there is <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2025/mar/16/wes-streeting-there-is-overdiagnosis-of-mental-health-conditions">‘overdiagnosis’ of mental health problems</a>. Alan Milburn, who is leading the government’s review into Young People and Work, warns of a ‘social catastrophe’ and of a ‘generation <a href="https://genuinefutures.co.uk/news-resources/alan-milburn-warns-of-a-social-catastrophe-as-youth-worklessness-nears-one-million">destined for the scrapheap’</a>.</p>

<p>Outgoing president of the Royal College of Psychiatrists, Lade Smith, responded to this situation on <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/m002rdxb">BBC radio</a> by calling for more funding for psychiatry and mental health services.</p>
<p>Smith claimed there is a ‘pandemic’ of mental illness that affects one in eight people, is clearly distinguishable from the mental health challenges we all experience and requires medical treatment. People don’t just get better on their own, she said, as they might with an infectious disease. ‘If you don’t get treated, things get worse’.</p>

<p>Thankfully, she concludes, effective psychiatric treatments are available that can prevent the chronicity that leads to people going on benefits. So people just need more treatment earlier on.</p>
<p>But Smith’s claims may be a pipe dream. At best, psychiatric treatments <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35918097/">reduce symptoms by a few points</a> on <a href="https://eiko-fried.com/depression-scales-are-not-unidimensional-or-measurement-invariant/">dubious measurement scales</a> in the short-term. There is no evidence that treatment effects translate into better real-world <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapsychiatry/fullarticle/2802547">outcomes or long-term benefits</a>. And rising prescriptions of antidepressants over the last few decades have been accompanied by <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27703749/">rising rates of sickness and disability </a>benefit claims for mental health problems.</p>

<p>Moreover, telling people they can’t get better through their own efforts, as Smith does explicitly, and as medical labels and treatments do implicitly, is hardly conducive to lasting recovery. Indeed, research shows that people who are signed up to the medical model have worse outcomes, are more pessimistic about their <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32807732/">chances of recovery</a> and more likely to <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/41506391/">end up on long-term treatment</a>. </p>

<h2>Lessons from history</h2>
<p>As long as there has been welfare, people have worried about the possibility that it will be abused. When the original Poor Laws were introduced into England in the 16th and 17th centuries, they distinguished between the able-bodied and ‘impotent’ poor and the ‘deserving’ and ‘undeserving’ poor.</p>

<p>The impotent poor, that is the sick and disabled, including those with what we would recognise as severe mental disorders, were given unconditional ‘relief,’ consisting mostly of the provision of food and clothes. ‘Relief’ was usually granted on a temporary basis, with the expectation that the mentally afflicted would recover. The able-bodied, 'deserving' poor (those willing to work) were also granted ‘relief’ and were provided with materials for work. The underserving poor — the ‘vagrants’ and ‘vagabonds’ who were unwilling to work — were supposed to be punished.</p>


<p>Over the succeeding centuries, members of the community who paid for this system through a local tax (the Poor Rate) worried they were being exploited by idlers and shirkers and various attempts were made to tighten the eligibility for ‘relief’. These culminated in the <a href="https://www.victorianpoor.org/pages/the-new-poor-law">Victorian Poor Law of 1834</a>, which required people to enter the dreaded <a href="https://www.workhouses.org.uk/intro/">Workhouse</a> to obtain food and shelter, where they were set to work in a system of harsh discipline. Those who were sick or confused (the impotent poor) were excused from this regime and housed in the Workhouse hospital or the asylum, which, despite its fearsome reputation, was intended to be a therapeutic space where people were treated kindly.</p>

<h2>Alternatives<strong> </strong></h2>
<p>Modern welfare benefits are a bit like the old Poor Laws, providing subsistence for people in the community. Although the system is now funded through national taxation, the same tensions exist.</p>
<p>I agree with <a href="https://www.madintheuk.com/2025/03/the-dignity-of-work/">left-wing, critical commentators</a> who highlight how modern social and economic conditions drive anxiety, stress and demoralisation and constantly raise the bar for performance and productivity, making it more difficult for people to work. Yet people’s reactions to these conditions are not illnesses (in the usual sense of that term). Conceiving of them as such undermines people’s self-belief and exposes people to unhelpful and sometimes positively harmful medical interventions.</p>



  


<p>We can afford to be and should be generous and caring in our welfare system, but that doesn’t mean the current situation is OK.</p>
<p>Work can be demanding, exploitative, insecure and stressful, but it also brings financial independence, or a degree of it (many people in low-paid jobs are still reliant on benefit subsidies), which can boost self-esteem and widen people’s options in life. It gives people a role in society and provides structure and social interaction. It is difficult to sustain good mental health when there is no reason to get up in the morning and nothing to stop you spending the day in your bedroom.</p>

<p>We need a framework for welfare and support during times when people are struggling or in crisis that, like the early Poor Laws, does not require them to be labelled as having a medical disorder, with the implications of limitation, chronicity and dependency this confers. As with all such systems, there will need to be a system of gatekeeping to decide who is in need and who is not, something that is never easy. Alternatively, a proper system of universal basic income would do away with the need for selective welfare benefits altogether, and is <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2023/jun/04/universal-basic-income-of-1600-pounds-a-month-to-be-trialled-in-england">being tested in the UK</a>.</p>

<p>Most importantly, perhaps, we need to prioritise decent jobs that provide a living wage and accommodate people with varying strengths and abilities. Everyone deserves a chance to contribute and to receive recognition and a fair reward for doing so. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/chemically-imbalanced/202602/mental-health-and-sickness-benefits-lessons-from-history" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/chemically-imbalanced/202602/mental-health-and-sickness-benefits-lessons-from-history</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/chemically-imbalanced/202602/mental-health-and-sickness-benefits-lessons-from-history</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna Moncrieff, M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-pixabay-159211.jpg?itok=7fI3pJDU" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Holding the Boundary That Breaks Your Heart]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-10/Borg_0.png.jpg?itok=JybMUPeq" alt="Mark B. Borg, Jr, Ph.D., and Haruna Miyamoto-Borg LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Boundaries</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Holding the Boundary That Breaks Your Heart</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How couples decide to step back when extended family pushes too far.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Effective intervention in boundary violations by extended family needs to be thought out collaboratively.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Collaboration helps couples clarify shared parental values that will determine their boundaries.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Resetting helps a couple work as a team after a painful but necessary boundary setting.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Blog16-PT.jpg?itok=VPDjqaAD" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="jackf/123rf.com" alt="jackf/123rf.com"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: jackf/123rf.com</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Rachel didn’t expect the question to come from her eight-year-old.</p>
<p>They were folding laundry together when her daughter asked, quietly, “Mom, are you and Dad going to hell?”</p>
<p>Rachel froze.</p>
<p>Eli heard it from the hallway and stepped into the room slowly. They both knew where the question had come from.</p>
<p>This wasn’t the first time something like this had happened. Rachel’s parents had visited the weekend before. They had brought books again—Bible stories “for the children,” her mother said, smiling. Over dinner, there were comments about how confusing the world had become and how children “need strong spiritual foundations before it’s too late.” During bath time, Rachel overheard her father asking their son whether he prayed at school.</p>

<p>Rachel felt uncomfortable and angry. Then she told herself she would address it later, the way she had told herself many times before.</p>
<p>Eli had stayed quiet at the table. He had learned over the years that pushing back too quickly only escalated things. But being quiet had started to feel less like patience and more like swallowing his feelings and pretending.</p>

<p>Rachel was raised in a fundamentalist Christian home. Eli grew up in a Jewish family. Neither of them practices religion now. Early in their marriage, they agreed their children would be raised secularly. They would teach ethics, curiosity, and respect, and leave spiritual choices to their children when they were older.</p>

<p>Despite Eli and Rachel describing their spiritual decision to Rachel’s parents, Rachel’s parents never accepted that decision and instead pushed their ideas onto their grandchildren. They framed their concerns as love. They said they were “just planting seeds.” They insisted that eternity was too serious to leave to chance. When Rachel gently redirected conversations, her mother would nod and then circle back later when the children were alone.</p>

<p>Over the past year, the pattern had grown more pointed. There were whispered side conversations. A small cross was left in a bedroom drawer. A warning that “confusion about truth can have consequences.” A suggestion that children sometimes need guidance when their parents are “still figuring things out.” Each incident on its own could be minimized. Taken together, they formed a steady undermining of Eli and Rachel’s parenting choices.</p>

<p>The comment that changed everything came after dinner that weekend. Rachel’s father had pulled their son aside again. The next morning, their son repeated it.</p>
<p>“Grandpa says you and Mom are confused,” he said. “He says you’re raising us wrong, but he’ll pray for us.”</p>
<p>It was the clear overriding of their authority.</p>

<p>As this was the Nth time something like this had happened, Eli felt heat rise into his face. Rachel felt mixed intense feelings—anger, frustration, shame, and the old reflex to want to defend her parents even when she disagreed with them.</p>
<p>That night, after the kids were asleep, they argued. Eli accused her of minimizing her parents' disrespect of their authority and parenting choices. Rachel accused him of moving too quickly toward cutting her parents off. Beneath the argument was a full of fear and pain: fear of choosing sides, fear of losing family, fear of failing their children. The rupture wasn’t only between them and her parents. It was between Rachel and Eli.</p>

<h2>Pause</h2>
<p>They decided not to decide anything that night. Instead of escalating further, they agreed to stop. They would revisit the conversation the next evening, when neither of them felt flooded with anger or frustration. They chose to do some intentional self-care and talk to their closest friends about it the next day, and then revisit the topic again. That pause prevented further escalation, a potentially impulsive decision born entirely of fury. It created space for clarity.</p>

<h2>Accountability</h2>
<p>When they sat down again, the tone had shifted. Rachel spoke first. “When they start talking like that,” she said, “I’m not 38. I’m 14 again. If I push back, I feel like I’m betraying them. And if I don’t, I’m betraying you as their father and abandoning myself as their mother.”</p>
<p>She admitted she had hoped the behavior would taper off. She had minimized her parents' disrespect of their parenting choices because confronting her parents felt like tearing something permanent. She didn’t want to believe they would choose their certainty over her boundaries.</p>



  


<p>That was her accountability—not agreement with them, but acknowledgment that avoidance and being in denial had protected her from conflict with her parents while leaving children exposed to fear and threat repeatedly. Eli listened.</p>
<p>“I’ve been angry at you,” he said. “Not just at them. At you.”</p>
<p>He explained how humiliating it felt to hear their son repeat those words. How it stirred old memories of being shamed for questioning authority. Speaking up had once carried consequences. Staying silent now felt like reenacting that pattern in his own home. He admitted he had expected Rachel to fix it because they were her parents. He felt resentful towards Rachel and his in-laws. That was his accountability—not for being upset, but for letting resentment build instead of expressing it sooner.</p>

<p>They weren’t solving the problem yet. They were naming their parts in the distance between them. The room steadied.</p>
<h2>Collaboration</h2>
<p>After the anger cooled, the focus shifted.</p>
<p>“What do we want to do?” Eli asked.</p>
<p>Rachel looked at him.</p>
<p>“About the kids,” he clarified. “Not about your parents. About us.”</p>
<p>They realized they had been reacting to her parents without fully articulating their own stance. They talked about what they wanted for their children: freedom from fear-based messaging, freedom to explore belief without pressure, and trust in their own parents’ authority. They agreed that spiritual exploration should never be framed as a threat or warning. This wasn’t about rejecting religion. It was about rejecting <em>coercion based on fear</em>.</p>

<p>“If we let this continue,” Eli said quietly, “what are we teaching them?”</p>
<p>Rachel felt the weight of that. “If we let it continue,” she said, “we’re teaching them that we accept my parents’ fear-based ideas.”</p>
<p>That clarified everything. During collaboration, they agreed that their children’s emotional safety and their unity and authority as parents came first. They outlined steps:</p>

<ul>
<li>A direct, explicit boundary conversation with grandparents</li>
<li>Clear written expectations</li>
<li>Immediate consequences if those boundaries were crossed again</li>
</ul>
<p>They moved from reacting to responding based on the outlined steps.</p>
<h2>Experiment</h2>
<p>Rachel told her parents clearly that religious instruction, warnings about spiritual danger, and private conversations undermining their parenting were not acceptable. If it happened again, visits would be put on hold. Her parents said they understood. The next visit was careful; one could say, controlled.</p>

<p>Then, during a quiet moment in the kitchen, Rachel overheard her mother telling their daughter, “Sometimes grown-ups don’t see the whole picture yet. That’s why God gives children wise grandparents.” It was gentle, and it was soft. But it was the same pattern.</p>
<p>Rachel did not freeze this time. “We talked about this,” she said. “If it continues, we need to take a break from the visits.” Her father responded, “We can’t lie to them about the truth.”</p>

<p>They ended the visit. Two weeks later, another call came. It was another warning framed as love. Still, the experiment had answered the question.</p>
<h2>Reset</h2>
<p>Eli and Rachel decided to take a break from having the grandparents over for three months for now. Rachel grieved the parents she wished she had—the ones who would respect her parenting choices and could separate belief from fear-based control. Eli grieved the extended family his children would now see less of.</p>

<p>Reset did not erase the grief. It helped them carry it without turning on each other. They reminded themselves that this decision was not about punishment; it was about protecting their decision as parents. They revisited their values when doubt crept in, and they supported each other when loneliness surfaced.</p>

<p>No contact for three months was not impulsive. It was a deliberate decision made by both Eli and Rachel.</p>
<h2>Why This Matters</h2>
<p>In our book, <em>Love. Crash. Rebuild., </em>our conflict resolution model (PACER) does not prescribe no contact. It supports couples in slowing down, acknowledging their reactions, defining their shared values, coming up with healthy boundaries thoughtfully, and working as a team afterward. You cannot remove the grief from a boundary like this. But you can prevent that resentment and grief from breaking your marriage.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-crash-rebuild/202602/holding-the-boundary-that-breaks-your-heart" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-crash-rebuild/202602/holding-the-boundary-that-breaks-your-heart</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/love-crash-rebuild/202602/holding-the-boundary-that-breaks-your-heart</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark B. Borg, Jr, Ph.D., and Haruna Miyamoto-Borg LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Blog16-PT.jpg?itok=FOvr6Bez" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Deal With Parental Guilt When It Shows Up]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-06/Lumanlan.jpg?itok=u-qf3M5y" alt="Lumanlan" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Guilt</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How to Deal With Parental Guilt When It Shows Up</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The repair practice breaks the parental guilt cycle better than trying to be perfect.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When parental guilt shows up, notice it without judgment, then ask: Is meeting my needs hurting or helping?</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Comparison doesn't help you parent better — your hard is your hard, regardless of others' circumstances.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The repair practice teaches children that mistakes don't have to break connection.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr"><em>This post is Part 4 of a series. In </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/why-exhausted-parents-keep-snapping-at-their-kids"><em>Part 1</em></a><em>, we looked at the science behind why you may keep snapping at your kids — how hunger, exhaustion, and isolation narrow your window of tolerance until even small things feel unbearable. In </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/parental-burnout-symptoms-and-the-shame-cycle-explained"><em>Part 2</em></a><em>, we explored how guilt keeps you stuck in that cycle — and what actually happens to your children when you're running on empty. In </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/self-care-tips-for-overwhelmed-parents"><em>Part 3</em></a><em>, we got practical — the HALT framework, small concrete changes, how to talk to your kids about what's going on, and how to build the kind of ongoing support that actually helps.</em></p>

<p dir="ltr">But even when you understand all of this — even when you have the tools — guilt can still show up. It tells you that taking care of yourself is selfish. That a good parent wouldn't need a break. That you should be able to handle this.</p>
<p dir="ltr">So in this post, let's talk about what to do when guilt shows up, because it will.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">How to Deal with Parental Guilt</h2>
<p><strong>Reframing your thinking</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">The shift is a practice. From "I should be able to handle this" to "What do I actually <a href="https://yourparentingmojo.com/captivate-podcast/needy/">need right now</a>?"</p>
<p dir="ltr">Something that might help: Research on attachment and child development tells us that repairing ruptures matters more than avoiding them in the first place. You don't have to get it right every time — or even most of the time. What matters is coming back.</p>

<p><strong>When guilt shows up</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Because it will. Even after you've intellectually understood that meeting your needs helps your children, the guilt will still show up sometimes.</p>
<p dir="ltr">When it does, try this:</p>
<p dir="ltr">Notice it without judgment: "I'm having thoughts that I'm selfish for needing a break."</p>
<p dir="ltr">Challenge it gently: "Is meeting my needs actually hurting my child? Or is it helping them have a parent who's more present?"</p>

<p dir="ltr">Look at the evidence: When you recharge even briefly, you have more capacity to hold space for your child's big emotions instead of erupting back at them. Meeting your needs helps you be the parent you want to be.</p>
<p><strong>Letting go of comparison</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Kelly, a parent I spoke with, shared that her turning point came when she stopped caring so much about what others thought of her parenting. This wasn't easy — she described it as one of the things she had to work on with her therapist. But dropping Facebook helped enormously. No more seeing everyone else's perfectly curated parenting moments.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Iris, another parent I worked with, learned something similar. She'd been stuck in what she called "the terrible endless math of comparison". Her mother had worked long hours with fewer resources. Other parents seemed to manage better. Her daughter should be easier than she was.</p>
<p dir="ltr">What helped was recognizing, "My struggles are my struggles". Not better or worse than anyone else's. Just hers. And they were real, even though she had material advantages her mother didn't have.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275507421_Social_comparison_social_media_and_self-esteem">Comparison doesn't help</a>. Your hard is your hard.</p>
<p><strong>The repair practice</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">You're going to snap sometimes. You're human. Your window of tolerance will get narrow, and you'll react in ways you wish you hadn't.</p>
<p dir="ltr">What matters more than getting it right every time is <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39999721/">coming back.</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">"I was grumpy earlier. That was about me being really tired, not about anything you did."</p>


<p dir="ltr">"I yelled, and that scared you. That wasn't okay. I'm sorry."</p>
<p dir="ltr">"I wasn't able to hear you properly this morning. Can we try again now?"</p>
<p dir="ltr">This repair practice teaches your child something important: People make mistakes. And when you make a mistake, you can acknowledge it and reconnect. You don't have to be perfect to be loved.</p>

<p dir="ltr">AJ Bond, who studies shame, talks about how rupture and repair actually strengthen relationships. The repair creates a deeper level of understanding and connection than if the rupture had never happened.</p>
<p dir="ltr">So your imperfection, followed by genuine repair, might actually teach your child more than if you somehow managed to be calm and patient 100% of the time.</p>



  


<h2 dir="ltr">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Guilt is a response to impossible standards combined with inadequate support. The voice that says "I should be able to handle this" is telling you how much pressure you've been carrying, often without enough help.</p>
<p dir="ltr">And the research actually shows that your children don't need you to be perfect. They need you to come back. Every time you repair, you're teaching your child something more valuable than a parent who never loses it. You're teaching them that people make mistakes, and mistakes don't have to break connection.</p>

<p dir="ltr">That's what breaks the guilt cycle.</p>
<p dir="ltr">So when guilt shows up — and it will — try to remember this: You don't become a better parent by pushing harder or sacrificing more. You become a better parent by recognizing when your tank is getting low and doing something about it before you completely collapse.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Your hard is your hard. Your struggle is real. And meeting your needs isn't something to apologize for — it's what allows you to actually show up for your kids.</p>

<p dir="ltr">So what's one need you can meet today?</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/how-to-deal-with-parental-guilt-when-it-shows-up" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/how-to-deal-with-parental-guilt-when-it-shows-up</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/how-to-deal-with-parental-guilt-when-it-shows-up</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jen Lumanlan M.S., M.Ed.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-kampus-6297572.jpg?itok=R0b_LlEh" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>