<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 01:58:45 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 01:58:45 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Compassionate Goals and Parenting]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/holly.jpg?itok=ZxdBvdE5" alt="Holly Parker, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Parenting</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Compassionate Goals and Parenting</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">New research reveals a possible win-win mindset for parents and kids.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Compassionate goals center on another person's needs and giving them care.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Self-image goals emphasize how we appear to someone else.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A new study looked at how compassionate and self-image goals relate to how parents and kids feel and act.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Compassionate goals were linked to greater wellness for parents and better behavior among kids.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Arguably, being a parent is the most challenging and important job a person can have; it's a position unlike any other. Needless to say, there’s no designated time you clock on and off the job, and you’re on call unceasingly. There are fervent <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39649242/">societal</a> views abound about how a parent is “supposed” to act, prompting the notion that parents must achieve perfection in their role. Flawlessness? Talk about an impossible standard, not to mention an unimaginable one. (What does perfection even look like anyway?) </p>

<p>Let’s just name this outright–it’s not fair. I can’t imagine anyone hitting 100% (whatever that means) in any sphere of life all of the time, and certainly not in a role with no “off” button. On top of this, the standard of immaculate parenting appears to sabotage itself (another point of unfairness), as <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39649242/">research</a> reveals a link between feeling urged to be an unblemished parent and engaging in some parenting approaches that are less effective. Is there anything that could help parents shift focus away from being an ideal, flawless parent and toward another viewpoint that might be more sustainable and fulfilling over time?</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-pixabay-51953.jpeg.jpg?itok=x87De-Jk" width="320" height="212" data-insert-type="image" title="Pixabay/Pexels" alt="Pixabay/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pixabay/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>In a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/41642822/">new study</a>, researchers looked at how compassionate goals and self-image goals are linked to how parents and their kids feel and behave. When we’re aiming toward compassionate goals in our interactions with someone, we’re trying to be thoughtful and considerate in the interest of being good to that person and advancing their wellness. On the other hand, when we’re going after self-image goals when we’re engaging with another, we’re zeroing in on how we seem to that person and attempting to cultivate or hold onto a favorable impression. How would these goals compare in parenting? </p>

<p>The researchers gave an example of how a parent might approach their child after a tough interaction. A self-image goal could lead that parent to decide not to say sorry because they’re worried about admitting they made a mistake, whereas a compassionate goal could point the way toward “I’m sorry” out of a desire to engage effectively and mend the disconnect.</p>

<p>Their study showed that compassionate goals were tied to greater emotional wellness for parents, including reduced nervousness and strain and a greater sense of purpose and contentment. Parents with compassionate goals were also more apt to feel intrigued by their kid’s inner world, and their children were more likely to behave well. On the flip side, the children of parents with self-image goals were less well-behaved. The study’s design can’t tell us that goals cause the feelings and behaviors we’re talking about. Hopefully, later research will clarify that. All the same, it’s still worth considering the potential upsides of giving oneself permission to let go of appearance a little more and focus on giving love, with all its imperfections. </p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/your-future-self/202602/compassionate-goals-and-parenting" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/your-future-self/202602/compassionate-goals-and-parenting</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/your-future-self/202602/compassionate-goals-and-parenting</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Holly Parker, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-josh-willink-11499-2274162.jpeg.jpg?itok=PHG-ovG5" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do You Have Difficulty Sustaining Your Exercise Program?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Pirkko-Markula.jpg?itok=YjkAAZ14" alt="Pirkko Markula Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Health</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Do You Have Difficulty Sustaining Your Exercise Program?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Let’s ask women who exercise regularly what motivates them to exercise.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">If we are internally motivated, we are likely to stay with an exercise program.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">External pressures create negative feelings toward exercise.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Exercise is empowering, because becoming physically and mentally strong increases self-confidence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Exercise is time for enjoyment and self-care.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>We all know that it is good to exercise for both physical and psychological health. Many of us have also made a promise to start the new year with regular workouts. But many of us do not manage to persevere for more than a couple of weeks. How do some women maintain their regular exercise regimes? What motivates them to continue when many of us drop out?</p>

<p>In their research, Cara Deininger, Akorede Teriba, and Megan Foley-Nicpon asked 11 experienced women exercisers (aged between 21 and 55 years) what kept them exercising. These women currently worked out at least five days a week. All weight trained, but also participated in a range of activities such as running, walking, HIIT, yoga, or crossfit.</p>

<p>The researchers used what they called a phenomenological research design. It helped to understand women’s lived experiences and the meanings they attached to their exercise participation. The results showed several motivations behind maintaining regular fitness regimes.</p>
<h2>Enjoyment and happiness</h2>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-mralpha-13451902%20(1).jpg?itok=AiqrKKHd" width="320" height="569" data-insert-type="image" title="mralpha/Pexels" alt="mralpha/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: mralpha/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>While the women found value in sustaining a healthy lifestyle to avoid illnesses, they particularly emphasized the mental benefits of exercise. Working out helped to clear the mind and get rid of stress. Some found their exercise sessions almost like therapy. Patricia said: “I can kind of get lost in my thoughts and I think that’s my own therapy session.”</p>

<p>These exercisers also enjoyed their workouts. They gained self-love through exercise and this created happiness in other parts of their lives. Elizabeth explained: “Now I’ve realized it’s not something that has to be done. It just is something that is enjoyable. It’s a supplement to everything else going on in my life . . . [I] feel like I found my best self.”</p>

<h2>Finding time for oneself</h2>
<p>Exercise was the time that the women devoted themselves. Linda explained that physical exercise was “time that you give yourself, and how can that whole process not be better?"</p>
<p>This was empowering: Becoming physically and mentally stronger when taking the time for self-care came with an increased sense of confidence and power.</p>

<h2>Accountability</h2>
<p>The women did, however, emphasize the need to create clear goals and then be "accountable" to oneself for achieving them. Jessica was clear that “you have to put in the work if you want to see changes… it’s just hard work, and I think it’s accountability and just showing up and relying on yourself.” These women also wanted to sweat and raise the heart rates during a successful workout.</p>

<h2>Internal satisfaction</h2>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-angela-roma-7480087.jpg?itok=aFHQtzC_" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Angela Roma/Pexels" alt="Angela Roma/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Angela Roma/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The researchers pointed out that these positive motives to exercise were intrinsic: The women kept exercising because working out itself was enjoyable and gave them personal satisfaction. It was also empowering to feel stronger and more confident as a person. The researchers further suggested that women persist with exercise if participation is intrinsically motivated: Instead of thinking of exercise as a necessary duty, it was important to enjoy it. This was one key to sustaining an exercise program.</p>

<h2>External pressures: the fit body ideal</h2>
<p>The women in this study embraced the fit lifestyle in which exercise was planned on their schedule. While successfully maintaining their fitness programs, the exercisers were not immune to social expectations of the fit, feminine body.</p>
<p>Many exercisers initially started to work out because of fear of gaining weight. Although they felt this had become less of a motivation, worrying about ideal looks was still deep in their minds. For example, Elizabeth explained:</p>

<p>"It’s hard, I think there’s times where I know that I work out because I want to be healthy but then other times it’s hard because I need to work out so that I look good…trying to fight those thoughts is really difficult. And then when I can’t, it leads to a snowball effect of being down about myself in other aspects."</p>



  


<p>Some of the women were frustrated with the social expectation that equates fitness only with thinness, not muscle definition. Some had also shifted from "cardio" workouts (for weight loss) to emphasize weight training, particularly as they aged. For example, Sharon, who had turned 50, shared: “You lose muscle with age, and it was important to me to maintain some muscle mass as I age. So it wasn’t about being big and bulky, it was just maintaining strength to be healthy as I continue to age.”</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pourquoipas-exercise-841167_1920.jpg?itok=3tv3XH9d" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Pourquoipas/Pexels" alt="Pourquoipas/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pourquoipas/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>It was clear that Sharon was careful with how much muscle she built not to look too "big." Patricia also revealed: “I have a body type that puts on muscle easily, so I always try to be mindful that I don’t get too bulky, only because I don’t want to look a certain way.” Therefore, the emphasis on strength still took place within the acceptable limits of not looking muscular.</p>

<p>The researchers pointed out that when exercise participation is driven by the social expectations of "looking good" (external motives), the women struggled with negative feelings about themselves.</p>
<p>If we work out only thinking of "external goals" such as expectations to look a certain way (thin and toned), we are likely to quit the program. While the experienced exercisers may have started based on a fear of weight gain, they had to discover different, internal reasons to persist with exercise.</p>

<h2>Finding joy</h2>
<p>Finding joy, self-confidence, and time for oneself empowered these women to continue with their fitness activities and to navigate the negative feelings of social expectations.</p>
<p>Exercise does not always have to be high intensity and there are many different exercise forms to choose from. If we can turn our workouts into enjoyable times devoted to our level of physical and mental strength, we also may be able to stick with them long term.</p>

<p>Let’s enjoy!</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fit-femininity/202602/do-you-have-difficulty-sustaining-your-exercise-program" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fit-femininity/202602/do-you-have-difficulty-sustaining-your-exercise-program</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fit-femininity/202602/do-you-have-difficulty-sustaining-your-exercise-program</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Pirkko Markula Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-olly-3855207.jpg?itok=W_cPTcF3" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Making of a Meaningful Moment]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-04/UTF-8CRB_to_right_of_tree-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=evlukVfx" alt="Carolyn Roy-Bornstein M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Mindfulness</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Making of a Meaningful Moment</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to stay open to sacred moments every day.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sacred moments can be described as brief meaningful connections between human beings.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Our expectations of certain situations often predict reality.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Setting intentions can be a way of setting our expectations and making sacred moments more likely to occur.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Reflective writing can cultivate the openness needed to recognize and embrace sacred moments.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Recently the <em>Journal of the American Medical Association</em> published a study by Jessica Ameling and Sanjay Saint out of the University of Michigan called “Sacred Moment Experiences Among Internal Medicine Physicians”. In it, over 600 doctors were asked if and how frequently they experienced brief periods of meaningful connection with their patients. More than two-thirds of those surveyed reported experiencing such a moment.</p>

<p>It got me wondering what goes into the making of such a moment, not just with patients, but also with colleagues, family, or friends. One factor I think might be important to the development of these experiences is mindfulness: staying in the moment. Being mindful allows us to be aware of small occurrences that might otherwise slip by us. A tiny gesture. A meaningful look. A weighty pause. Any one of these could signal something bigger or deeper is going on than might be obvious at first blush. Exploring them could pave the way for a sacred moment.</p>

<h2>Setting intentions</h2>
<p>Setting intentions for our day can prime us for these experiences. Setting an intention is not the same as setting a goal. It is not so much a to-do list as a <em>to-be </em>list. It is a decision about the kind of human being we want to be today, the values we want to remind ourselves we hold, and an awareness of how we want to show up for those we love or work with. The University of Utah School of Medicine uses intention-setting as part of their “pausing practice” program designed to enhance wellness, noting that “our expectations often shape our reality.” Once we prime ourselves to expect a certain outcome, our senses tend to look for evidence of that outcome all around us. We can “harness the power of positive expectations…by being deliberate about our intention to focus on something positive.” In doing so, we improve satisfaction and our sense of well-being.</p>

<h2>Expectations shape reality</h2>
<p>The Michigan study found that people who identified as being spiritual or having a strong sense of purpose were more likely to experience sacred moments. This gets back to the idea that expectations prime us for certain outcomes. If we are joyful, if we look for joy, we are very likely to find it. Likewise, being open to these kinds of moments make us more apt to find them.</p>

<p>This kind of openness is one of the five personality traits that might help us to recognize sacred moments when they happen. A reflective writing practice has proven effective in cultivating the kind of openness that keeps us attentive and available – attentive to novel ideas, available to be surprised, and open to sacred moments.</p>

<p>Sacred moments don’t have to be monumental. Dr. Lisa Rosenbaum published a piece in the <em>New England Journal of Medicine</em> a couple of years back about a resident she worked with who, after her shift was over, brought a patient a package of Milk Duds she had been craving. She remarked that it was the most meaningful moment of her entire day.</p>

<p>In their research, Ameling and Saint of the Michigan team found that most physicians never spoke to their colleagues about these sacred moments they had with their patients. Those few who <em>did</em> experienced less burnout. Christine Sinsky, in a related commentary on the research, advises “naming and norming” such moments.</p>


<h2>Cultivating openness through reflective practice</h2>
<p>These are conversations worth having. We should not shy away from the possibility of a sacred moment with another human being because it sounds too religious or it feels too “touchy-feely.” In the field of healthcare, doctors and nurses are still burning out with unacceptable frequency. Everyone in caring professions—teachers, social workers, therapists—face the risk of burnout as well.</p>

<p>When I was in medical school and residency years ago, we were taught not to get too close to our patients and to keep our distance. Perhaps some of that warning may have been about professional boundaries, which are important. But largely, I think our mentors were trying to protect us from burnout.</p>
<p>Studies like this one from Ameling and Saint are pointing us in a different direction. We are learning that the very relationships that may at times cause the most suffering—to our patients and by extension to us—are also the ones with the potential to carry the greatest meaning. By developing a mindful, reflective practice such as a daily writing practice, we can open our minds and our hearts to the sacred moments all around us just waiting to happen. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/last-stop-on-the-struggle-bus/202602/the-making-of-a-meaningful-moment" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/last-stop-on-the-struggle-bus/202602/the-making-of-a-meaningful-moment</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/last-stop-on-the-struggle-bus/202602/the-making-of-a-meaningful-moment</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Carolyn Roy-Bornstein M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/hands%20Sebastian%20Dumitru.jpg?itok=WVyThd8l" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>