<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 23:33:49 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 23:33:49 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why We’re Not Polar Bears]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Sam%20Goldstein.png.jpg?itok=kLaUD2vO" alt="Sam Goldstein Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Social Life</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why We’re Not Polar Bears</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What evolution says about solitude, screens, and modern life.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Humans evolved for cooperation, not long term physical isolation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Digital connection cannot fully replace embodied social contact.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Chronic isolation strains health, trust, and social stability.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Polar bears thrive in solitary lifestyles. They travel across large expanses of snow and ice, hunt quietly, and only come together when mating or rearing young. As solitary hunters, polar bears are well-suited to a life alone because they do not rely on the cooperation of others for survival. They have a highly dispersed and limited food supply; thus, the presence of another polar bear is more likely to be viewed as a competitor than a helper. While polar bears thrive alone, humans are social beings, and our need for social interaction is biologically ingrained in our evolution and physiology (Dunbar, 2009; Wilson, 2012).</p>

<p>Some species are solitary because it works for them. Others are social because they have to be. Survival mathematics is incorporated into animal behavior to enhance survival. Whether animals occur singly or in groups is affected by the availability of food, predators, how they reproduce, and competition for limited resources. Tiger hunting is generally performed by solitary hunters and provides limited benefit from sharing. On the other hand, wolves hunt cooperatively because the prey they pursue is both difficult and dangerous for individual wolves to kill without help. Meerkats have sentinels guarding over the colony to help protect the greater number of eyes, resulting in additional protection for the survival of the entire group. None of these strategies is a matter of moral choice; rather, they are based on species survival (Wilson, 2012).</p>

<h2>Humans Sit Firmly On the Social Side of That Divide</h2>
<p>Humans were not designed to be fast, strong, and well-armed. We came into existence because we were able to work. Our ancestors survived as a group by sharing food, protecting each other's children, issuing warnings of danger, and sharing knowledge. Language itself is a tool for social interaction. It appears to allow humans to coordinate their behavior more effectively than working on their own (Dunbar, 2009). A single human being cut off from their group could not survive alone. They would die. The way we have survived has influenced our brains. We are hardwired to look at faces, monitor connections, feel pain when lonely, and feel secure when we belong (Cacioppo &amp; Hawkley, 2009; Dunbar, 2009). Social connection is something we prefer because it's part of how we function as human beings. Throughout most of history, solitude was not common and frequently not desired. In previous times, humans generally lived in close proximity and worked with others, relying heavily on face-to-face interactions on a daily basis. Even when there were conflicts, those interactions would still occur in person. The communities we developed were often messy, demanding, and tiring, but constant.</p>

<h2>That Is Changing Fast</h2>
<p>Working from home has disconnected us. Where people used to watch TV shows together, now everyone has their own screen and watches it in the privacy of their home. Friendships now exist in either threads of conversations or voice communications. And, in some cases, people have gone days without ever being in the same room with someone who is not a member of their household. For some, this is the ultimate freedom; for others, it feels extremely unnatural. The problem is not the available technology. The tools we use for communication are neutral. It is how we are using the tools to eliminate the social friction that we evolved to require (Cacioppo &amp; Hawkley, 2009).</p>

<p>Video games can be social; however, they lack the visuals, touch, smell, and other forms of physical presence needed to accurately be considered as social entertainment. Text messaging allows you to stay connected with people, but removes some of the most important aspects of human communication: tone, timing, and other small signals used to establish trust. Remote working may provide an increased level of productivity and efficiency, but it removes all of the informal interactions that contribute to creating weak ties (i.e., connections between people) that provide resiliency for communities (Holt-Lunstad, Smith, &amp; Layton, 2010).</p>

<p>The replacement of informal connections with more efficient tools of communication has unique consequences over time. Our brains do not recognize these forms of electronic communication as sufficient forms of social interaction. This is why we see increasing loneliness in our society, even though we see increasing levels of online communication (Cacioppo &amp; Hawkley, 2009). Also, we see increasing levels of anxiety and depression rising with societal levels of connectivity. Many feel socially drained and empty when they are connected; this is not a failure on their part, it is a failure of biology to evolve with the pace of technology (Holt-Lunstad et al., 2010).</p>

<h2>We Are Trying to Live Like Polar Bears with Primate Brains</h2>
<p>Solitary species are built for independence. Humans are built for interdependence. When we remove regular, embodied social contact, we stress systems that evolved to expect it. Immune function weakens. Elevated levels of stress hormones lead to erosion of trust, making cooperation much more difficult; therefore, the difficulty of cooperating makes feeling safe in physical isolation feel like a better option. This is a self-perpetuating cycle (Cacioppo &amp; Hawkley, 2009).</p>

<p>This trend does not bode well for us. While physical isolation allows us to fragment easily, as there are no shared spaces or norms, it also increases the speed and intensity of disagreements between us due to our lack of frequent, low-stakes interaction. And, without a community, we either retreat internally or pursue membership based on an abstract type of identity, one that gives us a sense of belonging without any obligation. However, this does not mean that we need to give up on remote work or our digital social lives. Rather, we need to stop treating either as a replacement for being physically together (Wilson, 2012).</p>

<p>Both remote and digital social lives serve as an adjunct to physically gathering together. Neither can serve as the foundational element of agency. In order to achieve a state of thriving as individuals, we must design a way of living that reflects who we all are as human beings. One way to do this is to provide us with meaningful reasons to physically gather together, rather than simply creating excuses for remaining in isolation. Additionally, we must value the importance of togetherness through shared routines, local spaces, and personal collaboration, even when such experiences may be less efficient and entail some level of friction, while understanding that each of us as humans will experience some level of friction in our relationships with each other. Polar bears can walk alone across the ice and be fine. We cannot. We never could.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202601/why-were-not-polar-bears" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202601/why-were-not-polar-bears</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202601/why-were-not-polar-bears</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Common Sense Science]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-01/IMG_0170.JPG.jpg?itok=RgaCqXip" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hearing Loss and Its Link to Dementia]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Richard%20Restak%20MD%20.png.jpg?itok=p8vM21KH" alt="Richard Restak M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Dementia</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Hearing Loss and Its Link to Dementia</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">While hearing loss is expected with aging, dementia is not.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Hearing loss increases dementia risk and affects millions of adults.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Hearing loss has many social implications, including frustration and isolation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Treating hearing loss may help protect long-term brain health.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>What would be your best estimate of the number of people in the United States with significant hearing loss? You may be as surprised as I was to learn the answer: about 73 million, or approximately 1 in 5 persons. Moreover, the incidence of this loss increases over the lifespan, nearly doubling with every decade. By age 60, more than two-thirds of people are afflicted with hearing loss. Even more troubling is the well-established link between hearing loss and cognitive decline, impaired communication, and dementia.</p>

<p>According to the Lancet Commission on Dementia (2020), hearing loss in middle age and beyond is the single biggest risk factor for dementia. In 2023, the National Health and Aging Trends Study (NHATS) published findings that people older than 65 with moderate to severe hearing loss are afflicted with 61 percent greater prevalence of dementia compared to a similar group with normal hearing.</p>

<h2>Degraded speech</h2>
<p>Key to these associations between hearing and dementia is the concept of "degraded speech." Actually, the term degraded speech is a misnomer: The speech is clear enough to those with normal hearing, but the<em> perception</em> of the speech is degraded in those with hearing loss, usually by background noise or electronic transmission.</p>

<p>Picture yourself in a frantically busy trattoria with voices bouncing off the tiled walls, ceiling, and floor. While you may hear the lion’s share of what your companion is saying, certain words may remain ambiguous. Did he say “safe lane” or “save lane”—you just couldn’t quite catch the <em>f v </em>distinction. In such a situation, the topic of conversation often provides the correct word choice. Was the conversation about traffic (safe) or finance (save)?</p>

<p>Such distinctions are perceived in the primary auditory cortex, located within the temporal lobe, which is concerned with the acoustic forms of speech (what you actually hear). Speech intelligibility, in contrast, is the responsibility of the temporal and frontal regions.</p>
<p>Under ideal circumstances, hearing, understanding, and replying to speech proceed smoothly, even in people with mild speech impairment. But conversations in everyday life don’t always occur under ideal circumstances; they often involve background noises such as crowds, loud music, or the clinking of glasses in a dining room or kitchen. Under such circumstances, even people with normal hearing must force themselves to concentrate in order to prevent mishearing.</p>

<p>Research by Connor Wild of The Brain &amp; Mind Institute at Western University in London, Ontario, employed a PET scan, a measure of brain activity, to gauge how normally hearing people respond to speech that is unclear. Attention was increased, and additional portions of the brain became active. “Our findings unequivocally demonstrate that the extent to which degraded speech that is unclear is perceived depends on the listener's attentional state.”</p>

<p>Simply put, a person with a hearing impairment has to expend more mental energy concentrating on and deciphering the words being said. As a consequence, those portions of the brain ordinarily used for thinking, analyzing, and responding to what is being said must now be used to correctly identify words.</p>


<p>As an additional effect, conversations in noisy settings often prove exhausting because of the increased mental effort needed to concentrate on another person’s speech.</p>
<p>Among the hearing impaired, speech misperceptions often lead to errors in understanding, which can trigger inappropriate responses that may, under certain circumstances, be interpreted as expressions of dementia.</p>

<p>Consider these three conversants in a moderately loud restaurant. They are talking about their favorite pets:</p>
<p>“I definitely prefer dogs. They are wonderful companions.” </p>
<p>“Since childhood, I’ve never been around anything other than cats. So, I guess I prefer them.”</p>
<p>“Me? I prefer vicious pets.”</p>
<p>“You prefer vicious pets!?” one of the two conversants—the one with impaired hearing—exclaims with astonishment.</p>



  


<p>“I didn’t say vicious pets; I said <em>fish as pets</em>.”</p>
<p>Although such mishearings may prove amusing to others, they are anything but amusing to the person with a hearing problem. In this example, “vicious pets” spurs the hearing-impaired conversant to disbelief, shock, and even a smidgeon of annoyance. </p>
<h2>Social consequences of mishearing</h2>

<p>Now consider the ramifications that are likely to result from these mishearing episodes.</p>
<ol>
<li>When a hearing-impaired person does not hear what has been said and makes no comment, others may think the person just sits there staring blankly when spoken to. Such a behavior could easily be interpreted as either a sign of impaired hearing or, more likely in the elderly, an early sign of dementia.</li>
<li>When the hearing-impaired person erroneously hears something that hasn’t been said secondary to misperception resulting from degraded speech (the vicious pets example), responses can range from mild expressions of puzzlement to outright hostility.</li>
<li>When the hearing-impaired person responds sparingly in a free-flowing conversational exchange, secondary to the fear of making mistakes, social isolation is likely to follow. Social isolation is a universally recognized contributor to dementia.</li>
</ol>

<p>As a result of these experiences, the hearing-impaired person is likely to keep conversations—particularly those involving several people at once—to a minimum.</p>
<h2>Preventing the progression from hearing loss to dementia</h2>
<p>Fortunately, this sad progression from hearing impairment to dementia can be interrupted. First, if you are experiencing significant difficulty, don’t try to hide it. Eventually, people are going to notice that you’re not “catching” some of the things said to you. By admitting upfront that you are experiencing difficulty, people are encouraged to take special efforts to increase their audibility by speaking louder, slower, and more precisely. Best of all, they may avoid lowering their voices at the tag end of a sentence (a frequent speech quirk that most of us display, especially when we are fatigued). </p>

<p>Second, consult a hearing specialist. Despite the high prevalence of hearing impairment, only 1 in 5 of hearing impaired people currently use hearing aids. If the specialist determines that you will benefit from hearing aids, purchase the best instruments you can afford, keeping in mind the World Health Organization’s conclusion that nearly twice the number of people with mild hearing loss go on to develop dementia compared to those without hearing loss. So, identifying and improving even mild degrees of hearing loss confers current and future benefits.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-changing-brain/202602/hearing-loss-and-its-link-to-dementia" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-changing-brain/202602/hearing-loss-and-its-link-to-dementia</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-changing-brain/202602/hearing-loss-and-its-link-to-dementia</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Restak M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-marcus-aurelius-6787761.jpg?itok=HBYwCRcJ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>