<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 18:36:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 18:36:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rethinking Emotion: It May Not Be What You Think]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/_Beatrice%20Ng-Kessler.png.jpg?itok=9uSxtCGv" alt="Beatrice Ng-Kessler MsC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Emotions</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Rethinking Emotion: It May Not Be What You Think</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Emotional change may depend less on control and more on experience.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotions may reflect predictions, not just reactions to events</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Change happens when feared outcomes don’t occur.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Avoidance can reinforce fear; staying present allows learning.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Most of us assume emotions work like this: <strong>Something happens → we feel something → we react.</strong></p>
<p>An email arrives.<br>Your chest tightens.<br>You feel anxious.</p>
<p>A comment is made.<br>You feel hurt.<br>You withdraw.</p>
<p>It is exactly how we experience emotions in our daily life. Emotions are reactions to events. And if those reactions are too intense or disruptive, the task is to regulate them—calm down, reframe, cope better.</p>

<p>Much of therapy is built around helping people manage emotional reactions more effectively.</p>
<p>But what if emotion isn’t simply a reaction? Emotions may reflect <em>predictions</em>, not just reactions to events.</p>
<h2>The Brain Predicts Before It Reacts</h2>
<p>Research in neuroscience suggests that the brain is constantly making predictions. Rather than waiting for events and then responding, the brain is continuously asking:</p>

<p><em>What is happening?</em><br><em>What does this mean?</em><br><em>What should I prepare for?</em></p>
<p>To answer those questions, it integrates:</p>
<ul>
<li>Signals from inside the body (heart rate, breathing, muscle tension)</li>
<li>Information about movement and posture</li>
<li>Sensory input from the environment</li>
</ul>
<p>It then interprets those signals based on past experiences, learning, and cultural meaning. The result is a best guess about what’s going on—and that “best guess” may be what we experience as emotion.</p>

<p>From this perspective, emotion isn’t just triggered by events; it is constructed by the brain as part of its attempt to prepare and protect us.</p>
<h2>Emotion as the Brain’s Working Hypothesis</h2>
<p>Consider anxiety. In the traditional model, a situation causes anxiety. But in a predictive model, anxiety may reflect the brain’s hypothesis: <em>Something uncertain is happening. Prepare for threat.</em></p>

<p>Similarly:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sadness might reflect a prediction of loss.</li>
<li>Anger might reflect a prediction of violation.</li>
<li>Shame might reflect a prediction of social rejection.</li>
</ul>
<p>Emotion, in this sense, is the brain’s best attempt to regulate and survive.</p>
<p>That changes how we think about emotional distress.</p>
<p>Instead of asking, “How do I get rid of this feeling?” we might ask, “What is my brain predicting right now?”</p>

<h2>How Change May Happen</h2>
<p>In neuroscience, learning often occurs through <em>prediction error</em>—the gap between what we expect and what actually happens.</p>
<p>Imagine someone believes: “If I let myself feel this sadness, I will fall apart.”</p>
<p>In therapy, they slowly allow themselves to feel it. They stay present. Their body tightens, tears come—and yet, they don’t collapse. The feared outcome does not happen.</p>

<p>That mismatch—between expectation and reality—creates an opportunity for the brain to update.</p>
<p>Over time, the prediction may shift: “Sadness is painful, but survivable.”</p>
<p>The same can happen with anger, anxiety, or shame. When we remain with an emotion long enough to discover that the predicted catastrophe doesn’t occur, something in the nervous system recalibrates.</p>

<h2>Regulation vs. Avoidance</h2>
<p>Of course, emotional regulation is important. No one benefits from being overwhelmed but sometimes, we regulate so quickly that we never learn anything new.</p>
<p>If every surge of anxiety is immediately numbed, avoided, or escaped, the brain never gets disconfirming evidence. The prediction—“This is dangerous”—remains intact.</p>

<p>In behavioral terms, avoidance can become negatively reinforced: Relief confirms the belief that escape was necessary.</p>
<p>By contrast, carefully staying with sensation—without being flooded—can allow the nervous system to register: “I thought this would destroy me. It didn’t.”</p>
<p>That is a powerful corrective experience.</p>



  


<h2>The Role of the Body</h2>
<p>This is why many therapists increasingly pay attention not just to thoughts, but to bodily signals:</p>
<p>Subtle shifts in breath.<br>A tightening in the throat.<br>Heat in the chest.</p>
<p>These are not just symptoms. They are part of the predictive system itself.</p>
<p>Learning often happens in those moments when a person:</p>

<ul>
<li>Notices the sensation</li>
<li>Stays with it</li>
<li>Discovers it can move, shift, and pass.</li>
</ul>
<p>Change is less about eliminating emotion and more about increasing flexibility.</p>
<h2>Why This Is Hard</h2>
<p>Two major challenges arise in this process.</p>
<p>First, many predictions operate outside conscious awareness. A person may not know they expect rejection, failure, or catastrophe. The therapist and client often need to uncover these implicit expectations together.</p>

<p>Second, language has limits.</p>
<p>We rely on words to describe experience. But emotional experience is deeply embodied and often nonverbal. Language can clarify what we feel—but it can also simplify or narrow it.</p>
<p>Language is a powerful vehicle for communication, yet it cannot fully contain the nonverbal dimensions of lived experience. Interoceptive shifts, subtle affective tones, and implicit expectations often emerge before they can be named. When we translate experience into words, something is inevitably shaped, filtered, or reduced.</p>

<p>Sometimes change happens in ways that are sensed before they are spoken. This reminds us that therapy is not only a conversation. It is also an experience.</p>
<h2>A Different Way to Think About Emotion</h2>
<p>If emotion reflects the brain’s predictions, then it is not simply something happening to us; it is something our nervous system is generating in an attempt to help us adapt.</p>

<p>This doesn’t mean painful emotions are pleasant or desirable but it does mean they may carry information.</p>
<p>When therapy helps someone remain present with their experience long enough for new learning to occur, emotional patterns can shift because the underlying predictions were revised.</p>
<p>In that sense, emotion may not be the problem to eliminate. but a primary way the brain learns.</p>

<p><strong>To find a therapist, </strong><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><strong>visit the Psychology Today Therapy Directory</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-therapy-meets-cultures/202602/rethinking-emotion-it-may-not-be-what-you-think" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-therapy-meets-cultures/202602/rethinking-emotion-it-may-not-be-what-you-think</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/when-therapy-meets-cultures/202602/rethinking-emotion-it-may-not-be-what-you-think</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Beatrice Ng-Kessler MSc]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_2592156353.jpg?itok=nVzwBRYu" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Benefits and Burdens of Keeping Secrets]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/Dale.jpg?itok=XbIVnNyr" alt="Dale M. Kushner" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Trust</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Benefits and Burdens of Keeping Secrets</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">New research explores the impact keeping secrets has on us, for good or ill.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Ein_s%C3%BC%C3%9Fes_Geheimnis_von_Adolf_Hering,_1892.jpg?itok=N4DUOpk0" width="320" height="405" data-insert-type="image" alt="&amp;quot;Ein Süßes Geheimnis&amp;quot; (A Sweet Secret) (1892) by Adolf Emil Hering (1883-1932) published in Die Gartenlaube – Illustrirtes Familienblatt  ('The Garden Arbor – Illustrated Family Journal') " title="Kröner-Verlag / Public Domain"></div>
<div class="caption">"Ein Süßes Geheimnis" (A Sweet Secret) (1892) by Adolf Emil Hering (1883-1932) published in Die Gartenlaube – Illustrirtes Familienblatt  ('The Garden Arbor – Illustrated Family Journal')</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Kröner-Verlag / Public Domain</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Once upon a time during my girlhood, I was a teller and keeper of secrets. Secrets among friends were a form of bonding, and keeping someone’s secret was a sign of loyalty. Who told you their secret, and to whom you told your secret, reflected a hierarchy of trust. Best friends were lost or found through their ability to be a container for what you did not want others to know. Such is the power of secrets: to be shunned by the secret-telling circle is to feel excluded, less worthy, left out. Humans are social pack animals that thrive in small cooperative, interdependent groups. Our connection to others is crucial for our well-being, mental and physical.<sup>1</sup></p>

<p>We all have secrets, including secrets from ourselves. The secrets we keep from ourselves are often facts about ourselves or our lives we find uncomfortable, unacceptable, or even frightening. Swiss analytic psychologist Carl Jung used the term “shadow” to describe aspects of ourselves we believe are undesirable and repressed. These would include our fantasies, desires, instincts, negative feelings like anger, or positive aspects like creativity. What frightens us about ourselves, what feels endangering, we keep blocked off from our conscious mind—in other words, our private secrets.</p>

<p>In recent literature, popular memoirs describe the role of a victim in keeping the secret of an abusive relationship, or in protecting a predatory family member or trusted elder. Others of us may keep secret our sexual orientation, gender orientation, or our mental or physical illness.<sup>2</sup> Something in these stories touches our own experience of unexpressed private and transgressive feelings that go against the norm. Relief arrives when we share what has been hidden, and our whole authentic self is recognized and accepted.</p>

<p>Secrets also intrigue us. They are a source of mystery, even excitement, and make up the structure of thrillers and true-crime stories, fantasy literature, fairy tales, or fiction of the best-selling, page-turner variety. Plot-driven novels succeed on the premise that readers are enthralled by chasing down a secret. Spies keep secrets, governments and nations keep secrets, presidents, prime ministers, monarchs, and dictators keep secrets of state, as well as secrets that may be crimes against those they govern. Conspiracy theories thrive on secrets. The Merriam-Webster Dictionary defines “conspiracy theory” as “a theory that explains an event or set of circumstances as a result of a secret plot usually by powerful conspirators.” Though conspiracy theories often lack evidence, these add fuel to the belief that there is a secret, well-hidden, nefarious scheme.</p>

<p>In a 2017 study, social psychologist Michael Slepian, who studies secrets, and his research team identified 38 common categories of secrets that people keep about themselves, ranging from infidelity and illegal behavior to pregnancy and planned surprises for others. At any given moment, the average person has about 13 secrets.<sup>3</sup> One intriguing finding Slepian found was that people’s minds wander to their secrets far more often than they actively try to conceal their secrets from others. The frequency of concealment didn’t seem to have much effect on well-being, but the more people’s minds wandered to their secrets, the worse off they were.<sup>4</sup></p>

<p>“It’s not how much you hide a secret that’s harmful, but how often you find yourself thinking about it,” Slepian said in an interview.<sup>5</sup></p>
<p>In many circumstances, the weight of keeping a secret is burdensome, a difficult choice. We feel the risk of being judged, condemned, punished, ostracized, humiliated, and ridiculed if we believe our secret is unacceptable to others. But by keeping ourselves hidden, we risk loneliness and isolation. In our personal lives, we may keep a terminal diagnosis secret from a loved one to mitigate their worry and fear. We may keep the news of a pending divorce from our young children to spare them the prolonged pain of a family rupture. Shame and guilt visit us when we are confused about how and when to keep a secret. Ethicists, lawyers, religious leaders, and counselors of all stripes deal daily with the inner conflicts of those who need to make moral decisions on breaking the silence of a secret.</p>

<p>When it comes to revealing secrets, researchers make an important distinction. Revealing a secret to a person that the secret is kept from is termed <em>confession</em>, whereas revealing a secret to a third party is termed <em>confiding</em>. Little research exists on confession. Confiding, by contrast, has received more attention, and confiding secrets in others typically goes better than expected. By age six, children understand that sharing a secret with another is a signal of relationship closeness.<sup>6</sup></p>

<p>The good news is that secrets have a positive side and can be a source of wonder and joy. In a 2023 study, Slepian and his team identified two common secrets that are uniquely positive: surprises and marriage proposals.<sup>7</sup> Think of the happy face of a celebrant who has just stepped into a surprise birthday party. Other secrets can be a sacred covenant with ourselves, a wish we keep secret that entails hope and faith. In fairy tales, secrets are related to magic and positive outcomes, such as knowing a secret word, or obtaining a secret talisman like a magical cape. These tropes point to a hidden world in which all things are possible. Consider the secret wonder of discovering a bird’s nest filled with sky-blue eggs, or poems written in secret to a lover, or the secret drawer in a desk where you keep a note from a beloved friend.</p>

<p>Let yourself dwell for a moment on the secrets you have kept, the secrets you wish to share. Are there secrets that have changed your life?</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/transcending-the-past/202602/the-benefits-and-burdens-of-keeping-secrets" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/transcending-the-past/202602/the-benefits-and-burdens-of-keeping-secrets</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/transcending-the-past/202602/the-benefits-and-burdens-of-keeping-secrets</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Dale M. Kushner]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Ein_s%C3%BC%C3%9Fes_Geheimnis_von_Adolf_Hering%2C_1892.jpg?h=b9feb1b6&amp;itok=8mPu0iqW" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Be Social Without Spiraling]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/florkocropped.jpg?itok=LZ2HSE8h" alt="Lauren Florko Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Anxiety</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Be Social Without Spiraling</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Practical tools for dealing with social anxiety at work.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Social anxiety is common and can intensify in high-stakes work settings.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Start with awareness, not avoidance. Mindfulness builds awareness and creates distance from anxious thoughts.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Calming the body through breath and imagery reduces anxiety’s grip on you.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Prepared, values-driven conversations weaken avoidance and build confidence.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-yankrukov-7640492.jpg?itok=jrarR9Lo" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Yan Krukau / Pexels" alt="Yan Krukau / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Yan Krukau / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>About 12 percent of people experience social anxiety at any given time, and for roughly a third, it causes serious impairment. At work, that anxiety can spike because you are already striving to put your best work forward, give public speeches, and/or challenge others' ideas.</p>
<p>For those experiencing moderate to serious impairment due to their social anxiety, working with a mental health professional is critical. Therapy offers structured, evidence-based care. If your symptoms are mild or you are waiting to find the right clinician, there are practical tools that can help you reduce anxiety and step forward.</p>

<h2>1. Begin With Self-Awareness</h2>
<p>Social anxiety thrives on autopilot. Your mind predicts rejection. Your body braces for threat. You react before you reflect. Mindfulness interrupts that loop.</p>
<p>Mindfulness can be simple. Notice the sounds around you. What is a constant hum? What's intermittent? Then shift your attention to the sensation of sitting—the weight of your body in the chair, your feet on the floor. Finally, widen your focus to what you can see around you. Notice where your anxiety sits in your body: tight chest, flushed face, clenched jaw.</p>

<p>Next, notice your worries. Are they about your work performance? Relationships with your colleagues? Your boss? When you notice the worry, gently label it: “I am having the thought that I will mess up my words.” Then once you have labelled it, let it float by. A thought is not a fact. Then, return to the present.</p>

<p>If anxiety resurfaces, label it again: “I am worrying again.” You are not trying to eliminate the feeling. You are learning to observe it without being pulled under.</p>
<h2>2. Learn Relaxation Techniques</h2>
<p>An anxious brain sends signals to the body to panic. A calm body can send signals back to the brain to relax. Practice relaxation techniques when you aren't in worry mode. This helps you build the skill and memory of how to do it when you are feeling anxious.</p>

<p>Start with diaphragmatic breathing. Sit upright. Place one hand on your belly and one on your chest. Breathe normally. Which hand moves? If your chest rises more than your belly, gently shift your breath downward so your abdomen expands. It will feel unnatural at first—stay with it.</p>
<p>Gradually extend your inhale and exhale to about five seconds each. Find a time where you can practice this daily: before bed, while watching TV, in the bath, or during your morning coffee. </p>

<p>You can also use imagery to create distance from your intrusive thoughts. Picture yourself sitting on a grassy hill. Sunlight warms your face. Birds call from a nearby tree. A slow train passes about 30 feet away. Now, place each anxious thought onto one of these train cars. Watch it roll by. One car for one thought. If no thoughts arise, imagine a car labeled “no thoughts.” The point is not to stop thinking. It is to see thoughts as passing events.</p>

<p>If you aren't into trains, find an image that does work for you: clouds in the sky, leaves in a stream, balloons drifting upward.</p>
<h2>3. Practice</h2>
<p>Avoiding social situations will keep the anxiety alive. Gentle, planned exposure will weaken it.</p>
<p>You can practice for a social interaction at work. First, shift your focus to what you want to gain from the social situation. Are you asking for support? Giving feedback? Wanting to raise a concern? Then draft a short script or key messages of what you would like to say. Use “I” statements: “I feel concerned about…” or “I think we might consider…” Identify what you specifically need. It usually will help give you courage if you also explain how your request benefits the other person or the team. Also, note in advance where you may be willing to compromise.</p>


<p>Practice aloud—in front of a mirror or with a trusted friend. Expect anxiety to show up. But now, it's showing up on your own terms. Then practice your relaxation techniques to release any tight body posture and slow down your heart rate. This helps expose you to the anxiety, but under your own terms. It also gives you the tools to see anxiety as just a passing event, which you can calm yourself out of. </p>

<p>Like any skill, assertive communication improves with practice. Each conversation becomes evidence that discomfort is survivable—and often productive. Anxiety may still whisper. Let it. You are learning to respond, not react.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/people-planet-profits/202602/be-social-without-spiraling" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/people-planet-profits/202602/be-social-without-spiraling</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/people-planet-profits/202602/be-social-without-spiraling</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Lauren Florko Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-yankrukov-7640492.jpg?itok=2IeOrbBg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[On Diagnosis and Formulation]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/ruffalo_0.jpg?itok=plWDBWwY" alt="Mark L. Ruffalo LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychology</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">On Diagnosis and Formulation</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Formulation does not replace diagnosis but is instead dependent on it.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Diagnosis and formulation answer different questions; neither can substitute for the other.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Diagnosis identifies what illness is present; formulation explains why it takes this form in this person.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sound formulation depends on diagnosis to anchor understanding in the realities of psychopathology.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Kraepelin.jpg?itok=unAudZVt" width="271" height="395" data-insert-type="image" alt="Emil Kraepelin (1856-1926), the father of modern scientific psychiatry." title="Public domain"></div>
<div class="caption">Emil Kraepelin (1856-1926), the father of modern scientific psychiatry.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Public domain</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>In contemporary psychotherapy, we often hear that "diagnosis does not replace formulation." This is true, but it is only half the story. It is equally true that <em>formulation does not replace diagnosis</em>. These two activities answer different clinical questions and rely on different kinds of knowledge. When they are conflated, clinical thinking quickly becomes muddled, and treatment often suffers.</p>

<p>The problem is not that formulation is emphasized too much. It is that diagnosis is increasingly treated as optional or even dispensable. This represents a fundamental misunderstanding of what diagnosis actually is.</p>
<h2>What Is Psychiatric Diagnosis?</h2>
<p>Diagnosis is a descriptive and phenomenological act. It is grounded in the form of symptoms, their patterning, and longitudinal course. It answers the question: <em>What kind of illness is present?</em></p>

<p>This mode of thinking belongs to the domain of explanation (<em>Erklären</em>) and to the natural-scientific tradition in psychiatry. It was articulated most clearly by Emil Kraepelin and later by Karl Jaspers. Diagnosis, in this sense, is necessarily resistant to speculative narratives. It does not ask why a patient is ill in a biographical or historical sense; it asks what the illness is, based on observable phenomena and their evolution over time.</p>

<p>In modern psychiatry and psychopathology, this tradition was restored in the 1970s by psychiatrists at Washington University in St. Louis, particularly Eli Robins and Samuel Guze, whose work was instrumental in the development of the<em> DSM-III.</em></p>
<h2>What Is Formulation?</h2>
<p>Formulation belongs to a different domain: understanding (<em>Verstehen</em>). It is concerned with the patient's subjective experience of illness—their life history, developmental trajectory, personal meanings, and interpersonal relationships. Formulation asks a different question: <em>How can we make sense of why this person is ill?</em></p>

<p>This approach belongs to the interpretive traditions of psychoanalysis and existential psychology, in which the clinician's task is not primarily to classify illness but to understand the patient's subjective world and life history.</p>
<p>These considerations are indispensable to humane and effective clinical care. They help us understand how symptoms develop, are experienced, defended against, and embedded in relationships. But formulation does not determine diagnosis, nor can it substitute for it. A detailed narrative does not establish a diagnosis, and psychological understanding does not define the nature of a disease or psychiatric condition.</p>

<h2>Diagnosis Is the Basis for Formulation</h2>
<p>It is a generally accepted tenet of scientific medicine that diagnosis comes before treatment. One must first know <em>what</em> one is dealing with before attempting to understand <em>why</em> it has taken a particular shape in a particular person.</p>
<p>Sometimes the patient has a biological disease (such as manic-depressive illness or schizophrenia). Other times, it is a problem with significant environmental etiology (such as posttraumatic stress disorder or borderline personality disorder). Either way, diagnosis is the necessary starting point for understanding the nature of the patient's particular problem.</p>

<p>When clinicians are taught formulation without diagnosis, the result is often a kind of free-floating narrative, untethered from the science of psychopathology. Formulation becomes a substitute for classification rather than a complement to it, and clinical reasoning drifts toward explanation without first establishing what is being explained.</p>

<p>Only when diagnosis establishes what the condition is can formulation illuminate how it is experienced, ensuring that clinical understanding remains both scientifically anchored and humanly meaningful.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/from-freud-to-fluoxetine/202602/on-diagnosis-and-formulation" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/from-freud-to-fluoxetine/202602/on-diagnosis-and-formulation</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/from-freud-to-fluoxetine/202602/on-diagnosis-and-formulation</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark L. Ruffalo D.Psa.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/KarlJaspers2.jpg?h=785786c7&amp;itok=6eUa5vUj" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Authenticity Myth]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-03/Shannon%20Sauer-Zavala%20%281%29.png.jpg?itok=gCfV10SZ" alt="Shannon Sauer-Zavala Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Authenticity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Authenticity Myth</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why “just be yourself” might be keeping you stuck.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Personality traits describe your patterns, but they don’t define your potential.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Self-acceptance and intentional change can coexist.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Discomfort during growth doesn’t mean you’re being fake; it means you’re practicing something new.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">Just be yourself. It’s some of the most common advice we’re given. And it’s certainly well-intentioned, usually offered to help us feel more at ease in our own skin.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In fact, there is so much emphasis on being “authentic” in recent years that acting outside your usual patterns can start to feel untrue to who you are.</p>

<p dir="ltr">As a practicing clinical psychologist, I am a strong advocate for self-acceptance. As a researcher who studies how people intentionally shift personality traits that aren’t serving them, however, I sometimes wonder whether we’ve misunderstood what authenticity really means.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The question I keep coming back to is this: Is it possible to be authentic while actively trying to change?</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Striking the Balance Between Acceptance and Change</h2>
<p dir="ltr">At first glance, acceptance and change can seem like opposing forces. If you accept yourself as you are, why would you need to change? And if you’re working on self-improvement, doesn’t that imply something is wrong?</p>
<p dir="ltr">With my clients, we work on holding both at the same time.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Acceptance means acknowledging your current patterns without shame. It means getting clear on how you tend to think, feel, and act, along with understanding why those patterns may have developed. An example of this type of acceptance might sound like: “It makes sense I’m guarded around others since I’ve been hurt in the past.”</p>

<p dir="ltr">Change, on the other hand, is not about rejecting yourself. It’s about evaluating whether your current patterns are aligned with the life you want to build. That might sound like: “Even though being guarded has protected me, it is also keeping me from developing the close relationships I want.”</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">When “Authenticity” Becomes an Excuse</h2>

<p dir="ltr">The cultural push for authenticity is a problem because it tips the scale too heavily toward acceptance, leaving little room for growth.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The authenticity myth tells us that if something feels natural or comfortable, it must be the real you. And pushing yourself out of your comfort zone? You’re being fake.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Here are some examples of how the authenticity myth is costly:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">You don’t negotiate your salary because you tell yourself, “I’m just not an assertive person.”</li>
<li dir="ltr">You waste hours double-checking everything because you believe “I’m just a perfectionist.”</li>
<li dir="ltr">You stay quiet in meetings because you’ve accepted that you’re “not the visionary type.”</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">In each of these examples, authenticity is actually unwavering loyalty to your default patterns, even if those patterns are keeping you stuck.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">Personality Science Tells a Different Story</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Personality traits are descriptions of your typical patterns of thinking, feeling, and behaving. They summarize how you’ve approached the world in the past, but they don’t tell you what you’re capable of in the future.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In other words, traits don’t cause your behavior. They just describe what it looked like in the past. And cutting-edge personality science tells us that we can intentionally shift our traits to be better aligned with a life we value. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Shifting personality traits means practicing new ways of thinking and behaving, like speaking up sooner, tolerating imperfection, or initiating vulnerability. Of course, when you step outside of your comfort zone like this, it can feel, well, uncomfortable. </p>



  


<p dir="ltr">When that discomfort shows up, it’s easy to retreat to “This just isn’t me” or “I don’t want to be someone I’m not.” But discomfort isn’t evidence that you’re being inauthentic; it’s often evidence that you’re practicing something new.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">Growth That Isn’t Fake</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Authenticity is not about preserving your default patterns. It’s about acting in line with what matters most to you, even when doing so requires stretching beyond what feels familiar.</p>

<p dir="ltr">You don’t become less yourself when you practice new ways of thinking and behaving. You become more aligned with the version of yourself your goals require.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/self-made/202602/the-authenticity-myth" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/self-made/202602/the-authenticity-myth</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/self-made/202602/the-authenticity-myth</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Shannon Sauer-Zavala Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/priyanka-arora-lNkfSVKlkDA-unsplash.jpg?itok=AAflwXCu" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Caring for the Caregivers]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/robin_headshot1-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=YudhzAyA" alt="Robin Stern Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Caregiving</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Caring for the Caregivers</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Mindful solutions for overwhelmed caregivers.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Caregivers are often the unseen scaffolding in vulnerable moments.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sustainable caregiving begins with honoring your own well-being.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mindful pauses and emotional awareness help prevent burnout and empathic distress.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When caregivers model boundaries and support, resilience ripples through families and communities.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p><em><strong>Co-authored with Sharon Salzberg </strong></em></p>
<p dir="ltr">Caregivers are often the unseen scaffolding holding our worlds together. They provide presence, stability, and love during life’s most vulnerable moments. But what happens when the very people who hold everything together begin to unravel?</p>
<p dir="ltr">This year, consider the 63 million Americans who are family caregivers—roughly <a href="https://www.aarp.org/pri/topics/ltss/family-caregiving/caregiving-in-the-us-2025/">one in four</a> adults. Many are carrying out complex medical tasks without formal training, navigating a balance between selflessness and personal sacrifice. Yet, the toll of this labor rarely makes the headlines. Instead, it shows up in the long, blurred days, in conversations that center on others’ needs, and in the quiet realization that your own life now orbits around someone else’s.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Whether you’re caring for a newborn, supporting a spouse through illness, or juggling a career while managing a parent’s dementia, one truth stands clear: Your well-being isn’t a luxury. It’s the very foundation that makes everything else possible. As we set goals, it’s time to make self-care a priority—because without it, everything else starts to falter.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In moments of broader uncertainty—like the community caretaking and mutual aid efforts unfolding in places such as <a href="https://19thnews.org/2026/02/minnesota-mutual-aid-caregiving-ice-resistance/">Minneapolis</a> during periods of political unrest—we are reminded that caregiving is not just a private act but a public one. Neighbors check on neighbors. Volunteers distribute food and supplies. Just as communities tend to collective well-being to remain resilient, individual caregivers must also be cared for. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Caregiving pulls us outward, toward others’ pain, schedules, and crises, but sustainable care requires something counterintuitive: turning inward first. Without that, the strain doesn’t just build; it compounds. Over time, it can harden into <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6005077/">empathic distress</a>—a slow burn of emotional depletion and physical exhaustion. It may show up as irritability, difficulty setting boundaries, or even a sense of disconnection from the very people you’re trying to help. </p>

<p dir="ltr">The first step is recognizing these warning signs, which creates emotional self-awareness, the ability to notice what you're feeling before it overwhelms you—and without blaming yourself or declaring that you are failing. These are very normal reactions to high-stress situations, but we don’t want to have them govern us. Mindful awareness creates a pause to make room for deliberate choices instead of being swept away by exhaustion. From there, mindfulness becomes not an abstract practice, but a practical way forward. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Far from requiring extended silence or hours of meditation, mindfulness can be built through simple, repeatable moments of presence woven into the day. Some simple rituals can help you move from surviving to sustaining include:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Morning grounding. </strong>Before your feet touch the floor in the morning, take one slow breath in for four counts, hold for four, and exhale for six. In less than a minute, you’ve shifted your nervous system from reactive to responsive.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Emotion check-ins. </strong>Ask yourself: What am I feeling right now? Naming an emotion such as frustration, worry, fatigue can soften its grip. Tools like the free, research-backed <em>How We Feel</em> app can help you build your emotional vocabulary and discover healthier regulation strategies.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Transitions with intention. </strong>Between tasks, take a pause: Splash cold water on your face, sit down with a cup of tea, or let your gaze rest on something calming such as a window view or a favorite photo. These small breaks help close one moment before you step into the next, giving your body and mind a chance to reset.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Movement breaks.</strong> Stress doesn’t live only in your mind; your body carries it, too. Get your circulation going with a quick walk down the hall, a few steps in place, or by shaking out your arms and legs. Even small bursts of movement restore energy and keep stress from settling in.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Reach out and recall.</strong> During stressful moments, reconnect with someone you trust, whether it’s to share how you feel, gain perspective, or simply remember a joyful moment you’ve shared. Support and shared memories can defuse tension and remind you that you’re not alone.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Reframe and redirect.</strong> When negative thoughts spiral, pause and ask if there’s another way to see the situation. Talk to yourself with the same kindness and encouragement you’d offer a friend, shifting from criticism to calm acceptance.</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">These practices don’t require perfection. They require permission to care for yourself alongside those you love. As caregivers, your steadiness becomes the template others rely on but that doesn’t mean you have developed endless patience. It means being honest and recognizing when you need a break or asking for help before resentment hardens. </p>


<p dir="ltr">When you model boundaries and self-care, you’re proving that caring for others and caring for yourself are not opposing forces, but essential partners. When caregivers thrive, their love becomes a source of strength that ripples far beyond themselves.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.sharonsalzberg.com/"><em><strong>Sharon Salzberg</strong></em></a><em><strong> </strong>is a meditation pioneer, teacher, and New York Times bestselling author. She is among the first to bring mindfulness and lovingkindness meditation to mainstream American culture over 50 years ago, inspiring generations of meditation teachers and wellness influencers.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/power-in-relationships/202602/caring-for-the-caregivers" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/power-in-relationships/202602/caring-for-the-caregivers</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/power-in-relationships/202602/caring-for-the-caregivers</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Stern Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_2096877145.jpg?itok=q-7XGgpN" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Non-Traumatic Events Trigger Trauma Responses]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/daniel_lobel_headshot_cropped.jpg?itok=nFpCGc09" alt="Daniel S. Lobel Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Trauma</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Non-Traumatic Events Trigger Trauma Responses</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Emotional dysregulation can make everyday life traumatic.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotional dysregulation can lead some people to experience trauma responses to non-traumatic events.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">These individuals become anxious and dysregulated when required to function independently.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Codependent relationships often develop, enabling continued avoidance of daily activities.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Exposure to daily activities facilitates development of coping skills to improve functioning.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Traumatic responses to life-threatening events activate the nervous system in a unique way that focuses all attention, energy, and other resources on survival at the cost of daily function. When the threat subsides, the nervous system returns to baseline and allows for usual daily function. Some individuals respond to non-traumatic events as though they were traumatic. This results in chronic overstimulation of emergency patterns of nervous system stimulation associated with chronic neglect of daily functioning. Desensitization of trauma-level responses to non-traumatic events will result in improved daily function and a greater sense of stability.</p>

<p>According to the American Psychiatric Association, a traumatic event is “[e]xposure to actual or threatened death, serious injury, or sexual violence” (APA, 2013). These are extraordinary events that are not part of daily living. For this reason, people are almost always unprepared. Under these circumstances, even well-regulated individuals can experience traumatic reactions.</p>

<p>The psychological impact of traumatic events depends on two factors: the intensity of the traumatic event and the individual’s ability to regulate their emotions during and after the event. Individuals with strong coping skills recover from traumatic events quickly and resume regulation of their emotions. When individuals develop symptoms of trauma in reaction to daily (non-traumatic) occurrences, it indicates that the individual has inadequate resources to regulate themselves during daily life. Some live in a constant state of dysregulation, often associated with substantial dysfunction or nonfunction.</p>

<p>The initial reaction to a traumatic event is often shock. The individual is overwhelmed with unexpected and life-threatening circumstances without a chance to prepare. This is a transient state of powerlessness. Well-regulated individuals develop tools to cope with trauma by restoring their sense of power and control over their destiny. This is necessary to become a survivor.</p>

<p>For example, the victim of an assault might take a class in self-defense or get a dog. A car accident survivor might take a defensive driving class or buy a safer vehicle. In both of these examples, the subjects of trauma add skills and strategies so that they might be prepared in the future should there be another threatening event. They cannot develop these skills and strategies if they avoid going outside.</p>

<p>Individuals who are traumatized or triggered by daily events will continue to experience these reactions until they develop coping strategies for daily life. Unfortunately, many of these individuals avoid daily activities rather than learning how to cope effectively. They report being “triggered” by being around other people, shopping, crowds, public and private transportation, etc. Some of these individuals can’t function to any significant extent.</p>

<h2>Codependency in Traumatic Response</h2>
<p>These individuals often develop codependent relationships with others and depend on them for basic functions like food shopping/preparation, transportation, and, in some situations, for hygiene and basic self-care. Rather than empowering themselves by developing strategies for regaining agency, they identify themselves as victims and remain powerless. In some circumstances, these individuals surround themselves with caretakers who provide basic functions around the clock.</p>


<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/redleaf_lodi-fear-7587715_1920_0.jpg?itok=DsYotJki" width="320" height="481" data-insert-type="image" alt="Redleaf_Lodi/Pixabay" title="Redleaf_Lodi/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Redleaf_Lodi/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>These individuals generally present themselves to others with severe anxiety symptoms, which justify their avoidance of daily functioning. These symptoms of dysregulation include severe anxiety, often with panic attacks, obsessive thought patterns and compulsive behavior (OCD), and phobic avoidance, often to the extent that it causes agoraphobia, the fear of leaving home alone.</p>

<p>Relatives, friends, and caretakers often feel sorry for these individuals and placate them to avoid panic symptoms or other extreme forms of distress. Unfortunately, while placating these individuals reduces their symptoms in the short term, it makes their illness worse over time. This is because serving and sympathizing with these individuals encourages them to sustain their victim identity and continue to avoid daily activities. This increases their dependence on others, which prevents them from developing healthy coping strategies.</p>



  


<p>The longer individuals avoid developing skills for coping with daily activities, the more severe their trauma-like reactions will be when they attempt daily functioning. The sooner they stop depending on others, the sooner they can develop healthy coping strategies. If they are persistent, these individuals can gain functionality and independence quickly as competence increases confidence. Helping these individuals involves encouraging them to participate in daily activities, even though they are anxious, and discouraging avoidance.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/my-side-of-the-couch/202602/how-non-traumatic-events-trigger-trauma-responses" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/my-side-of-the-couch/202602/how-non-traumatic-events-trigger-trauma-responses</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/my-side-of-the-couch/202602/how-non-traumatic-events-trigger-trauma-responses</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Daniel S. Lobel Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/szabojanos-shadow-4553062_1920.jpg?itok=YRJ2gmO2" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Power of the Intentional Pause]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-01/663ED81E-51E8-4D11-A545-EB65EE06FD17-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=_9EvRi5q" alt="Shahram Heshmat Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Habit Formation</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Power of the Intentional Pause</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Embrace the rewards of slowness.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Awareness prevents old habits favored by automatic thoughts from having the final say in our behavior.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Pausing is essential to the process of reflection.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Slow practice is the optimal starting point for learning unfamiliar material.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-framesbyambro-3617332.jpg?itok=UKe847OI" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Ambady Kolazhikkaran/Pexels" alt="Ambady Kolazhikkaran/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Ambady Kolazhikkaran/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>We are seeing a steady decline in attention spans across all age groups. For example, research shows attention spans to be about 47 seconds (the average time we pay attention to one screenshot). There are several reasons for the decline of our capacity to pay attention. Digital distraction, multitasking, and economics (which rewards speed and efficiency) all have the potential to fracture attention span (Reed, 217).</p>

<p>But we all have a degree of control over how we choose to live. By living slowly, we can find life much less stressful and more fulfilling. Slowness isn’t so compatible with modern life, with all its pressures and demands. A slower pace of life reduces mental and emotional fatigue. Slowing down is also a strategic advantage for boosting productivity and creativity.</p>

<p><strong>1. The power of pause</strong></p>
<p>Pausing is essential to the process of reflection. Psychologist Rollo May (1981) equates pause with freedom. That is, freedom is the capacity to pause in the face of stimuli from many directions at once and, in this pause, to choose our response. The pause momentarily suspends our automatic reaction, and our responses no longer blindly follow stimulus (e.g., we remark before making an important decision, “Let me sleep on it.”). A pause can be created by a walk or 20 minutes of meditation.</p>

<p><strong>2. Slowing things down</strong></p>
<p>Slowing things down and deliberately paying attention to each aspect of our sensory experience can reveal things that we may have never noticed before. Awareness keeps old habits favored by automatic thoughts from having the final say in our choices. For example, mindless eating is an important reason for overeating. Research shows that the faster a person eats, the more likely (42 percent more compared to a slow eater) he or she is to be overweight. When you eat fast, the body doesn’t get a chance to signal to the brain that you have eaten enough (Hurst and Fukuda, 2018).</p>

<p><strong>3. The power of slow learning</strong></p>
<p>Attention to the process of learning a new skill is essential. Practice for new skills should be thoughtful, slow, and deliberate rather than rushed. When you work slowly, things become simpler. You don’t perform better when you speed through a course. Slowness and speed are interdependent. Mastering a subject requires time and patience before speed becomes possible.</p>

<p><strong>4. The importance of repetition</strong></p>
<p>Repetition (doing the same thing repeatedly) is essential for learning and mastering new skills. When an experience is complex, it’s a good idea to repeat it. Task repetition is a key to transforming short-term memories into long-term memories. Repetition helps to reinforce new ideas and behaviors in your mind, making them more familiar and easier to recall. Repetition allows you to turn the mundane into the extraordinary. Examples from the world of sports and music illustrate the pervasiveness of this principle. Whether you’re learning to play an instrument, speak a new language, or excel at a sport, repetition is key for building muscle memory and improving your performance. Every repetition brings you closer to your desired outcome.</p>

<p><strong>5. Becoming a better listener</strong></p>
<p>Research on happiness has shown that what really makes us happy is how much love we feel coming back to us (Lyubomirsky and Reis, 2026). To feel more loved requires listening better. However, that kind of genuine, focused listening is rare and quite powerful. Rather than being good listeners, we tend to impatiently wait our turn to speak or fail to ask follow-up questions. When someone feels deeply understood and valued by you, they become more willing to do the same for you. By paying attention to someone, you make that person a priority (giving value).</p>

<p>In sum, slowing things down and deliberately paying attention to each aspect of our sensory experience can reveal things that we may have never noticed before. Slowing the mind down in favor of slow deliberation takes vigilance, willpower, and training. Slow thinking involves analyzing information, weighing evidence, deferring interpretation, and making careful inferences.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/science-of-choice/202602/the-power-of-the-intentional-pause" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/science-of-choice/202602/the-power-of-the-intentional-pause</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/science-of-choice/202602/the-power-of-the-intentional-pause</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Shahram Heshmat Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-framesbyambro-3617332.jpg?itok=DodPqc22" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>