<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 19:34:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 19:34:50 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Should You Pick a Therapist? What Should You Consider?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/132935_2-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=p4999wXQ" alt="F. Michler Bishop Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Should You Pick a Therapist? What Should You Consider?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Nine questions and answers on how to pick a therapist.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">You should research and interview a therapist the same way you check out a company you might work for.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A good therapist will ask you about your goals.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A good therapist will suggest between-session work as well as be helpful in session.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">If you don't "click" with the person, look for someone else.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Let’s assume that you’re about to meet with a potential counselor or therapist. It is best to think of this initial meeting—whether it be a 10-minute free phone call or a paid-for first session—as an interview. Most coaches advise you to interview the company that is interviewing you. You are considering working there. Is it a good fit?</p>

<p>Of course, they are interviewing you because they are looking for someone to fill a vacancy. That’s their goal. But you need to keep your goal in mind, too. <br><br>When meeting a therapist for the first time, ask yourself, "Will this be a good therapist to work with?"</p>
<h2>What do you think of their online presence?</h2>

<p>Before the meeting with a potential therapist—whether by phone, Zoom, or doxy.me (a HIPAA-compliant platform like Zoom)—check them out online. You can read their Psychology Today and LinkedIn profiles, and you can look at and read some or all of the material they have on their website.</p>
<p>What do you think? Are there any “red flags,” things that cause you to wonder, “Can I work with this person?”</p>

<h2>Are there any “red flags” in their online presence?</h2>
<p>In the description of their practice, do they seem to suggest that they can “treat” everything—e.g., anxiety, depression, bipolar disorder, borderline personality disorder, PTSD, eating disorders, etc.? Research suggests that no therapist or counselor is good at working with every type of problem. In one study of twelve kinds of problems, most therapists were good at treating six. Some weren’t very good at any, and some did harm, so it is reasonable to be careful.</p>

<p>Other aspects of what you read online may be orange or red flags. For example, frequent errors in writing may suggest a lack of care and attention to detail, which could understandably make you wonder how careful they are with confidentiality and record keeping.</p>
<h2>Did the person ask about your goals for therapy?</h2>

<p>In the first session, did the therapist ask you about your goals for therapy? In the past, most therapy was not explicitly goal-focused. Most therapists encouraged people to talk, and they listened. Now many good therapists are going to specifically ask you what you hope to accomplish in therapy. (For what I think is good modern, integrative therapy, see my post "<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/managing-addictions/202110/the-6-critical-parts-most-modern-therapy-sessions">The 6 Critical Parts of Most Modern Therapy Sessions</a>."</p>

<p>If you go back for a second session, did they review your goals with you? Or does the session turn into what I call “E &amp; E therapy”: empathy (“That sounds very painful—tell me more”) and encouragement (“I’m sure things will get better with therapy”)? No doubt this may make you feel better; just talking to someone about a problem almost always makes us feel better. But feeling better is only one goal. Do they aim to help you learn new strategies and skills for handling old problems? Most people want to do better going forward, not just feel better.</p>


<h2>Did they ask “open-ended” questions or mostly “closed-ended” questions?</h2>
<p>Do they mostly ask open-ended questions, or are they primarily closed-ended yes/no questions?</p>
<p>Closed-ended questions—“Did you go to the gym this week?” “Have you tried cutting down?”—can feel interrogative. In contrast, open-ended questions communicate curiosity and genuine interest:</p>

<p>“You said one of your goals is to improve your relationship with your partner. How is that going?”<br>“You wanted to reduce your phone use. What has helped since our last session?”</p>
<h2>Did they suggest anything for you to do between sessions?</h2>
<p>When psychoanalysis started, it was thought that only what happened in session might help. The idea that you could do therapy on yourself outside of a session was thought to be absurd. The theory was that the source of your troubles is deeply—very deeply—repressed and defended against—strongly defended against—ideas. These ideas are so repulsive that you had to repress them deeply and defend yourself against them. So therapists cannot take a direct approach. They have to wait for leaks in your defenses to occur, like slips of the tongue or missing a session, which could be analyzed in session.</p>



  


<p>There is absolutely no research to support this theory, and it has largely been discarded by most therapists, but there are hangover effects. Therapists still rely primarily on what happens in session. Between-session work, sometimes called “homework,” is not a key part of therapy—but it should be. And it can be a good indicator of what type of therapist you have started to work with. If no between-session work is suggested, you may want to get another therapist.</p>

<p>Modern therapy increasingly resembles skill-building—much like training for a sport. You need to practice new behaviors between sessions. Insight is valuable, but it is rarely sufficient by itself.</p>
<h2>How do they describe the way they work? What “school” or schools of psychotherapeutic thought do they subscribe to, if any?</h2>

<p>New therapy schools are a bit like new religions: they provide hope, the key ingredient in change. There are hundreds of kinds of therapy, so if you are confused, join the crowd. Traditional therapy evolved from the psychoanalytic “talking cure” and focused on gaining insight into how our past continues to affect our present thoughts, feelings, and behaviors. This can be very helpful, but insight is usually not sufficient. You have to learn and practice new ways of responding to the pluses and minuses of everyday, modern life. Consequently, modern therapy is more skills-based.</p>

<p>The reasons you are considering therapy will also determine the kind of questions you ask. If you want to work on trauma-related issues, you may want to ask if they do trauma-focused CBT or if they use EMDR. If they do, how did they get trained? If they don’t, why not? How do they work on trauma?</p>
<p>If anxiety and panic attacks are your reasons for seeing a therapist, do they primarily use CBT? What do they think of ACT (Acceptance and Commitment Therapy), a CBT approach that puts more emphasis on mindfulness and values-guided action?</p>

<p>Most therapy research suggests that there are common factors that have the biggest effect on whether or not therapy works—factors such as a client’s motivation and the quality of the working relationship between the client and the therapist. It is not the “brand” or particular technique that makes a huge difference.</p>

<p>But if they specialize in a form of therapy—e.g., CBT, DBT, Schema Therapy, Internal Family Systems Therapy, chairwork—why do they do so? This may be especially important if they adhere to a form of therapy that you have never heard of.</p>
<h2>Do you like their sense of humor?</h2>
<p>You may be thinking, what does a sense of humor have to do with picking a therapist? I’m assuming that you intend to try to change. That is often difficult to do and may involve falling on your face more than once. Being able to chuckle—gently—about your idiosyncrasies, shortcomings, and pratfalls will help.</p>

<p>It is also possible that a suggestion made in a friendly but somewhat amusing way may get through to you when a more direct, unamusing way won’t.</p>
<h2>Should you ask a friend?</h2>
<p>I always tell people that I really don’t know how a colleague may work during a session. I usually know another professional because I have met them at a conference, sat on a panel, worked on a committee, or shared a meal with them. I may respect their research or what they have written, but do I really know how they work with a client in their office? No.</p>

<p>Some people, including your friend, may only want someone to talk to—to listen to them and support them. And they may benefit immensely from working with such a person. Gaining insight in many cases won’t by itself be sufficient, but when some people gain insight into their problems, they are able to make the changes between sessions by themselves. Many other people, however, benefit from more structured sessions and from discussing, deciding upon, and doing work between sessions.</p>

<h2>Finally, is it a “click”?</h2>
<p>The reality is that we “click” with some people and not with others. Often we cannot explain why there is a click or why something is putting us off. Even if you work hard to examine your biases, a sense that something doesn’t feel right shouldn’t be dismissed. Of course, if you have tendencies toward perfection, you will have to be careful not to reject everyone you interview. But if it is not a “click,” and you ignore or push those feelings aside, you will probably regret it.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/managing-addictions/202601/how-should-you-pick-a-therapist-what-should-you-consider" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/managing-addictions/202601/how-should-you-pick-a-therapist-what-should-you-consider</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/managing-addictions/202601/how-should-you-pick-a-therapist-what-should-you-consider</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[F. Michler Bishop Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-01/frank-mckenna-OD9EOzfSOh0-unsplash.jpg?itok=QAEqeY7A" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Science for Social Coherence?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-12/Lawson-Wulsin.jpg?itok=KmhzAaOM" alt="Lawson Wulsin M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Social Life</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">A Science for Social Coherence?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">One promising way to to measure how we make contact.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mechanical coherence offers a template for understanding "personal coherence."</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Heart rate variability measures offer a good measure of personal coherence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Social coherence proposes to measure the physiological synchrony among groups of people.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">HRV biofeedback is one proposed measure of social coherence.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>If you have ever marveled at a murmuration of starlings or the harmonious motions of a school of fish, you may have wondered how these species achieve such communion of action. Apparently, even the biologists who study such questions are still wondering. By what instinct can thousands of birds fly as a coherent unit? They don’t need to practice for hours, days, and weeks on end, like our marching bands. And yet, we humans might also have some instinct for harmony. </p>

<h2>The Incoherent Mind </h2>
<p>In the practice of psychiatry, we like to think we have better radar than most doctors for identifying incoherent thinking in our fellow humans. Incoherence is one of the crucial signs for potential disasters in the central nervous system—delirium, psychosis, mania, intoxication, stroke, encephalitis. And yet, now in the waning years of my career, I confess that I’ve practiced this skill of identifying incoherent thinking with only the vaguest definition of coherence, and no measure. For me and most of my colleagues, identifying the incoherent mind is more of an art than a science. </p>

<p>But writing a book recently about our stress response system (Toxic Stress, 2024) got me thinking we doctors—no, all clinicians—should take a closer look at how we think about coherence on several levels, and take a tip from engineers. In the engineering world mechanical coherence refers to the extent to which two or more oscillating systems are synchronized, or coherent. The laser beam, for example, synchronizes two bands of light, both temporally and spatially, to achieve a sharp focus and a narrow frequency, a highly coherent light system compared to sunlight. </p>

<h2>Personal Coherence</h2>
<p>To the extent that we can think of our body as a complex system of systems, particularly our stress response system, does it make sense to ask if our bodies operate by some form of mechanical coherence? Applying the concept of mechanical coherence to our bodies, with all its component organ systems oscillating in various rhythms, quickly becomes a forbidding intellectual feat for most scientists.</p>

<p>And yet we all do this daily, from birth to death, at least intuitively. That is, we have evolved a sophisticated sense for how harmoniously synchronized our own organ systems are—our brains with our hearts, our muscles with our nerves, our hormones with our digestion, our immune system with our energy system, and each organ with all the others. When we’re fit, fed, and well rested, we feel good—that’s high “personal coherence” on a physiological level. When we feel bad or sick, maybe one or more of these systems is not functioning in harmony with the others; that would be low “personal coherence.”</p>

<p>Modern medicine has plenty of measures for the functioning of each of our organ systems. Cardiologists, pulmonologists, gastroenterologists—every specialty has its tools and measures for its organs. But so far, modern medicine has no standard measure for the coherence of the whole system. We rely on our patients’ intuitive sense of personal coherence and their ability to function well to tell us if they are healthy. </p>

<h2>Heart Rate Variability</h2>
<p>One of the major voices promoting this concept of personal coherence belongs to Rollin McCraty, PhD, the director of research at the HeartMath Institute in Boulder Creek, CA. In a <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/public-health/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2017.00267/full">review</a> published in 2017, McCraty summarized the evidence for heart rate variability (HRV) as a sound measure of personal coherence, based on some promising research over the prior three decades showing that HRV correlates strongly with good health, emotional regulation, and the efficient functioning of several major organ systems, especially the heart and the brain. HRV measures go up with fitness, relaxation, and restful sleep, while they go down with age, severe stress, and most chronic illnesses. </p>

<h2>Social Coherence</h2>
<p>Though the use of HRV measures for general health has been studied for several decades, McCraty’s term “personal coherence” has not yet found common use in mainstream medicine. In his 2017 review in “New Frontiers in Public Health” McCraty proposed extending the concept of personal coherence to social coherence, which he described as “pairs, families, groups or larger organizations in which there is a stable and harmonious alignment of relationships that allow for an efficient flow and utilization of energy and communication required for optimal collective action.” One intriguing feature of social coherence, he suggests, is “physiological synchronization,” citing research on mother-infant bonding, speakers and listeners, and couples’ sleeping patterns to support the notion that people can unconsciously synchronize key physiological patterns in concert with others. </p>

<p>This is a fascinating idea. Are we as a species capable of synchronizing our physiologies when we also harmonize our thoughts and behaviors? Do members of an orchestra synchronize their hearts as well as their instruments? Do members of an audience share a common physiologic state while listening to a speaker or watching a performer? Are humans in a line dance capable of something close to the harmony of a beehive or the murmuration of starlings? Answers to these questions could open the way to a deeper understanding of how we humans make and lose contact with others. </p>



  


<h2>HRV Biofeedback</h2>
<p>Another fascinating aspect about this idea is that in the decade since McCraty proposed the development of social coherence research, relatively little formal research has been published about it. One of the barriers has been technology. Monitoring HRV for a single person in a laboratory is complicated, and interpreting HRV data is even more complicated. In spite of popular wearables that record a rough estimate of “HRV,” only in the past five years has it become practical to record and interpret scientifically rigorous HRV data for individuals in daily life outside a laboratory. Now, says McCraty, we can begin to apply these HRV technologies and HRV biofeedback to groups.</p>

<p>McCraty’s team has proposed that one way we might be sensing the inner states of those close to us is through our heart’s electromagnetic forces. This force from the heart is apparently five times stronger than that of the brain, and his group has shown that it is possible to record the electromagnetic signal of a person’s heart up to five feet way. Whether we sense that signal and how remains to be clarified.</p>

<p>The HeartMath Institute has for many years developed both hardware and software for collecting HRV data. In 2022 McCraty published a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35731454/">history</a> of HRV research at HeartMath. The story, as he presented it, is a scientist’s dream career, closing with his hopes for applying a science of social coherence to the betterment of our social and physical lives by exploring “group coherence and synchronization and if and how this is associated with increased group performance, pro-social behaviors, cooperation and improved communication.” Who could argue against such a mission? </p>

<h2>A Science?</h2>
<p>What puzzles me is that in several searches through Google Scholar I can find no publications or reviews of research on social coherence since 2022, not even by McCraty himself. As respectable as his work has been over the past three decades, it has always needed confirmation by investigators who are not supported by the HeartMath Institute or other institutions that benefit directly from HRV research. </p>

<p>To flourish as a branch of science, the field of social coherence will need working definitions, protocols for measuring HRV coherence in groups, and guides for interpreting data on social coherence. Until then, we have a promising idea that has made its way to the marketplace, but is still waiting to be rigorously studied—a reminder that science moves more like a glacier than like a murmuration of starlings.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/deep-dives/202602/a-science-for-social-coherence" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/deep-dives/202602/a-science-for-social-coherence</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/deep-dives/202602/a-science-for-social-coherence</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawson Wulsin M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-thirdman-6194028.jpg?itok=rUaLPN9L" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>