<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 20:37:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 20:37:55 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What We Get Wrong About Death]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-12/JordanGrumet.png.jpg?itok=iMVSYujM" alt="Jordan Grumet M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Fear</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What We Get Wrong About Death</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How understanding the realities of dying can reduce fear and help us live fully.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Most deaths from chronic illness are quieter and less dramatic than portrayed in media.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Modern hospice care can control most end-of-life pain and physical distress.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotional and spiritual support often helps patients find peace before dying.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Grief and guilt tend to burden surviving loved ones more than the dying person.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/chiemseherin-sunset-8516639_1280.jpg?itok=zDxusj0Q" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Pixabay / Chiemseherin" alt="Pixabay / Chiemseherin"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pixabay / Chiemseherin</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>After witnessing countless deaths, both personally and professionally as a hospice physician, I have encountered nearly every misconception about this inevitable part of life. Death is often feared and rarely discussed. In fact, a recent YouGov survey in the U.K. found that roughly 41 percent of adults reported being afraid of their own death. Among those, three in 10 said that this fear had affected their enjoyment of life.</p>

<p>Fear of death is pervasive, but it is not inevitable. When some of the major myths about dying are understood, anxiety can lessen, and peace can emerge in unexpected ways. Here are three realities that often surprise people when they confront the dying process.</p>
<p><strong>Death is often quiet</strong></p>
<p>Pop culture frequently portrays death as dramatic, painful, and loud. Television dramas, like <em>Grey’s Anatomy</em>, or blockbuster films, often show gasping patients, violent agitation, or climactic last breaths. These depictions reinforce the idea that dying must be chaotic and painful.</p>

<p>In reality, while brief episodes of distress can occur, they are typically short-lived and manageable with appropriate care. As terminal illness progresses, people tend to turn inward. Consciousness softens, breathing stabilizes, and the final hours are often quiet. The last moments may be spent in a calm, almost meditative state as the body gradually shuts down.</p>

<p>When hospice is involved, this peaceful transition is even more common. Loved ones may be present in a familiar, comforting environment, witnessing the quiet closing of a life rather than a dramatized struggle. Death, in many cases, is anticlimactic. For those who fear loud or traumatic endings, the reality can be surprisingly gentle.</p>

<p><strong>Pain should be the exception, not the rule</strong></p>
<p>I do not wish to imply that the dying process is without discomfort. Chronic illnesses can cause pain or shortness of breath, and patients may experience agitation or anxiety. Yet, modern medicine, especially hospice care, is remarkably effective at managing these symptoms. Pain, for most people, is controlled through medications, positional adjustments, and careful monitoring.</p>

<p>Even non-physical suffering is addressed. Chaplains, social workers, and therapists often help patients reflect on life, resolve conflicts, or find closure. While decades of unresolved issues cannot always be fully reconciled, opportunities for reconciliation and emotional processing exist. Patients can frequently achieve a sense of peace and acceptance with their lives, and that emotional comfort can be as profound as relief from physical pain.</p>

<p>End-of-life care today aims not just to prevent suffering, but to create dignity, meaning, and calm in those final days. It is possible to die comfortably, with both mind and body at ease—a truth that is rarely portrayed in media or discussed openly.</p>
<p><strong>The real suffering is often for the living</strong></p>
<p>One of the more surprising lessons of working with the dying is that suffering is rarely prolonged for those leaving the world—it falls instead on those who remain. When my father died suddenly at age 40, his suffering ended immediately. Our family, however, carried grief for decades. The weight of loss, questions of whether we “did enough,” and replaying decisions from his care haunted us.</p>


<p>This experience mirrors what I see professionally. Families often ruminate over whether they administered medications correctly, made the right calls, or should have pursued additional treatment. My message to families is always the same: death is not a result of error or neglect. It is a biological inevitability, a natural conclusion to life. Our bodies are born to live and, eventually, to die. No one escapes this truth.</p>

<p>Grief can be profound, but understanding the dying process itself is often more reassuring than obsessing over what might have been done differently. Acceptance of the natural order allows the living to redirect energy from worry to memory, care, and celebration of the life that was.</p>
<p><strong>No one escapes unscathed</strong></p>



  


<p>To be alive is to experience death. If you live long enough, someone you love will die—and eventually, you too will die. This is an unavoidable reality. Yet the good news, which took me years of professional experience to fully appreciate, is that death itself is often far less terrifying than imagined.</p>

<p>Perhaps our fear of death is often disproportionate to its reality. Rather than fixating on the final moments or potential suffering, it may be wiser to focus on living a life worth mourning. By cultivating relationships, pursuing meaningful work, and fostering kindness, the impact we leave behind becomes the legacy of our lives. Death may be quiet, ordinary, and inevitable—but the life that precedes it can be rich, deliberate, and extraordinary.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-regret-free-life/202602/what-we-get-wrong-about-death" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-regret-free-life/202602/what-we-get-wrong-about-death</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-regret-free-life/202602/what-we-get-wrong-about-death</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jordan Grumet M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/chiemseherin-sunset-8516639_1280.jpg?itok=AoHkzcAE" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[For the Love of Boredom]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/Danckert.png.jpg?itok=aYSHpSaq" alt="Danckert" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Boredom</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">For the Love of Boredom</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How Phineas Gage drew me to a life of ennui science.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">There are many myths about boredom that need busting.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Boredom won't make you creative.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Boredom is not (at least chronically) good for you.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Everybody knows the story of Phineas Gage. The fascinating and gory tale of the railroad worker who miraculously survived a three-foot eight-inch iron bar shooting through his skull. The story is so ubiquitous that it is hard to choose which of the multitude of YouTube videos that chronicle his fate would be best to watch.[1]</p>

<p>For me, Gage is a good starting point for understanding how myths are made and why they might be problematic, which will eventually lead me to debunking some modern myths around boredom that really get under my skin.</p>
<p>Gage’s story hardly bears summarizing. We have all seen the sepia photographs of the aftermath. What is remarkable to me about his story is the sheer amount of myth-making it has engendered.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Phineas_Gage_GageMillerPhoto2010-02-17_Unretouched_Color_Cropped.jpg?itok=eL7Onk3Q" width="320" height="544" data-insert-type="image" alt="Gage with the tamping iron. " title="Photographer unknown, public domain, retrieved from Wikicommons February 24th, 2026. "></div>
<div class="caption">Gage with the tamping iron.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photographer unknown, public domain, retrieved from Wikicommons February 24th, 2026.</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The initial, and it should be said, widely differing impressions of Gage’s case, came from his treating physician, John Harlow, and his surgeon, Henry Bigelow. Harlow’s version won the day. We learn from Harlow that shortly after his injury, Gage began acting in a childish manner, not fit for polite society. From there things just get wilder (and more divorced from the truth). Gage apparently struggled to maintain employment (not true, he held several jobs, some of which would have required a high level of responsibility). He had poor relations with his wife and children (not true – he didn’t have either as far as we can tell). Truth did not seem to matter to the myth makers, for them Gage was clearly “no longer Gage”. [2] </p>

<p>And for me, the myth fit with some very personal experiences I was having just as I was being indoctrinated into Gage’s tales of woe. My brother had crashed his car and suffered a traumatic brain injury. As he recovered, he began telling me about how often he now felt crushing boredom. Boredom for things he knew he loved before his brain injury. Gage and my brother had both had their frontal lobes damaged. The myth would take off for me because it connected, however tenuously, with my brother’s reality.</p>

<p>Why not just add to the Gage myth that he found himself bored all the time. Clearly, he couldn’t maintain employment or good relationships because his injury had made him bored, unable to effectively engage with the world around him! (Never let the truth get in the way of a good story as the saying goes.)</p>

<p>Why does this matter? Myths are just a specific kind of story and stories shape the way we think about things. For Gage’s story it shaped the way we began to think about the frontal lobes, that they were somehow, the seat of our personalities — damage them and you change the essence of who we are. The Gage myth, because of its sensational nature, worked really well to get me interested in the brain, which ultimately led me down the career path that has been very good to me and anything but boring.</p>

<p>But myth-making can also lead us down the garden path in ways that are misguided and at best may mean we waste our time and at worst may guide choices that are simply not good for us. I think there are some boredom myths that do just that.</p>
<p>In this blog, I aim to bring you discussions of cutting-edge research on boredom to highlight what I think is a fascinating phenomenon while also trying to debunk what in my view, can be harmful myths about ennui. What are some of the biggies?</p>

<h2>Myth #1: Boredom is just laziness.</h2>
<p>Born of the adage “Only boring people get bored,” this one is a moralizing myth. Somehow, if you get bored there must be something wrong with you. But boredom is functional and not unique to humans. It signals that what we’re doing now is not working for us in whatever way and we should explore the world for something better.</p>

<p>This myth also conflates boredom with apathy — a bored person is no different than a couch potato. But that misses the point of boredom. Boredom is a motivational state, not an apathetic one.</p>
<h2>Myth #2: Boredom can make you creative.</h2>
<p>We love this myth. It has spawned a few very popular <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c73Q8oQmwzo&amp;t=1s">TED talks</a>, countless news articles and I think a popular, but misguided hope. That inviting more boredom into your life will somehow make you more creative. We hear it from people we look up to as creative geniuses. Hendrix once told a fellow guitarist that he was bored with old styles of playing, which spurred him to develop his unique sound.</p>



  


<p>But boredom didn’t make Hendrix a guitar virtuoso — practice and exploration did. Just hoping that more boredom will spark creativity undersells creativity and oversells boredom! Sure, boredom is a push to explore for new things to do, but it won’t choose for you what that new thing might be or how to effectively engage with it — that’s up to you.</p>

<p>Put another way, if you want to believe that boredom can magically turn you into a creative genius then you also have to believe that it could turn you into a problem gambler, a vandal, or even a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/aug/28/german-nurse-niels-hoegel-suspected-murdering-90-patients">killer</a>.</p>
<h2>Myth #3: Boredom is good for us.</h2>
<p>The creativity myth is a subset of the broader claim that boredom can be good for us, and that somehow this generation has lost the ability to live with boredom (this spins off into the kinds of hyperbolic claims that the internet and social media are ruining our brains!). It’s worth pointing out that this contrasts with Myth #1 — how is it that boredom can be good for us if it is only boring people who succumb to it? </p>

<p>When people claim that we need more boredom in our lives, from the admonition that our children no longer know how to deal with it, to the performatively ludicrous displays of rawdogging boredom (see my next post), I think they are really saying that what we need is some down time. And I couldn’t agree more. We need to disconnect from our devices, leave the seedier, cesspool parts of social media alone, and just give ourselves time to recharge.</p>

<p>The thing is, more boredom in your life won’t achieve that for you. It’ll just mean that you’re more bored, more often and we know that is a recipe for a wide range of negative outcomes.</p>
<p>***</p>
<p>Like Gage’s story, these myths have at least one use — they’ve got us talking about them. For Gage that meant rethinking our conception of a part of the brain that up until that point had been dubbed the “silent lobes”. Damage the frontal cortex and many patients can still walk and talk just as they did before — clearly, it’s superfluous. Gage, myths and all, helped change that thinking.</p>

<p>For boredom, the myths have done something similar. Boredom is having a moment in our culture and in our scientific endeavours. It is no longer simply a part of the furniture of life, but something worth considering for the role it plays in our daily lives.</p>
<p>Our task now is to dig a little deeper in order to understand more clearly what boredom is and what kinds of actions it demands of us. To sort through the myths to get to the truths about ennui. <br> </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/modern-boredom/202602/for-the-love-of-boredom" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/modern-boredom/202602/for-the-love-of-boredom</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/modern-boredom/202602/for-the-love-of-boredom</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[James Danckert, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Phineas_Gage_GageMillerPhoto2010-02-17_Unretouched_Color_Cropped.jpg?itok=oivzauHH" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Best Persuasion Involves Sex Appeal, Humor, and Comparisons]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/pt-nicholson_square_edited_2-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=NtLRWBQk" alt="Jeremy Nicholson M.S.W., Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Persuasion</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Best Persuasion Involves Sex Appeal, Humor, and Comparisons</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How the best persuasion tactics balance effectiveness and affiliation.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When we try to persuade, we often face a choice between focusing on being effective or liked by others.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">This occurs because effectiveness comes from creating arousal, whereas liking comes from positive feelings.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Fortunately, approaches that promote both excitement and positivity are also most liked and successful!</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Persuasion can be challenging because it often involves two different goals. On one hand, we want our persuasive approach to be successful at changing the opinions and behaviors of others in our favor. On the other hand, we also want the appeal to be likeable and improve our relationships with others, too.</p>

<p>Sometimes, however, those two goals can be in conflict. Specifically, a persuasive approach may be successful and effective at changing behaviors, but disliked and destructive to our relationships. With that problem in mind, Hornik, Ofir, and Rachamim (2016) conducted a meta-analysis on over 1,200 advertising experiments to explore the relationship between the likeability and success of various types of persuasive appeals. Their results highlighted the best approaches we can take to be both likeable and persuasive. So, let’s take a look!</p>

<h2>Types of Messaging</h2>
<p>Hornik, Ofir, and Rachamim (2016) began their analysis by reviewing different kinds of persuasive messaging. The goal was to identify specific types of messages and categorize them through various features. In doing so, the team identified 7 types of persuasive appeals:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sex Appeals</strong> involve using attraction and physical desirability to create positive emotions and arousal in others. This approach both maintains attention and is psychologically rewarding.</li>
<li><strong>Humor Appeals</strong> incorporate irony and playfulness to initiate positive emotions and arousal. As a result, this method also captures attention and is rewarding.</li>
<li><strong>Comparative Appeals</strong> highlight various similarities and differences to impact the decision-making of others. This technique influences how people experience and compare their options when making a choice.</li>
<li><strong>Fear Appeals</strong> communicate undesirable or loss-related possibilities to induce negative emotions and arousal. This tactic also captures attention but motivates others to avoid punishing outcomes instead.</li>
<li><strong>Metaphor Appeals</strong> use stories, images, or associations with tangible things to influence what something means to a person (either emotionally or rationally). This approach also highlights similarities and differences, but often in a more subtle manner.</li>
<li><strong>Framed Appeals</strong> focus attention on what can be gained or lost in a situation to engage the reasoning of others. This process impacts choice by directing thoughts toward positive outcomes and rewards (gain-framed) or negative outcomes and punishments (loss-framed).</li>
<li><strong>Two-Sided Appeals</strong> employ a balanced presentation of reasons for and against a choice to fully engage the logic and reasoning of others. This approach helps to better inform the individual of the pros and cons of a decision.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Effectiveness vs. Likeability</h2>
<p>Further comparisons by Hornik, Ofir, and Rachamim (2016) found that all 7 approaches were significantly more effective and likeable than neutral control messages. Beyond that, however, appeals differed in terms of whether they were targeted more toward excitement or reason, as well as whether they were more positive or negative in tone. Those differences also related to how successful each message type was in persuading the recipient, and how much the recipient came to like the message too.</p>

<p>First, they found that <strong>arousal is often more effective than logic</strong>. Persuasive approaches that hooked people’s feelings and got them excited were generally more successful than those appealing to cooler logic. Thus, the most effective approaches involved sex and humor (<em>r </em>= .46, .35), followed by comparison and fear (<em>r </em>= .19, .16), and with framed, metaphor, and two-sided appeals as least effective ((<em>r </em>= .14, .13, .11).</p>

<p>Second, they determined that <strong>positive is often more likeable than negative</strong>. Persuasive approaches that had a positive tone (e.g., focused on rewards) were generally more liked than those that had a neutral or negative tone (e.g., focused on punishments). As a result, sex and humor appeals were also the most liked (<em>r </em>= .39, .38), followed by comparison and metaphor (<em>r </em>= .15, .15), with fear, framed, and two-sided approaches as least liked (<em>r </em>= .12, .11, .09).</p>

<h2>Being Persuasive and Appealing</h2>
<p>Given the results above, there appear to be three main steps for being a successful and likeable persuader. First, use sexy appeals to create attraction and arousal. Second, add some humor to keep things positive and exciting too. Third, make favorable comparisons to affiliate with others and motivate them toward your way of thinking.</p>

<p>As I discuss in my book <em>Attraction Psychology</em>, those persuasive approaches are also essential skills for appealing to romantic partners and developing intimate relationships (Nicholson, 2022). On the relationship psychology side of things, however, those terms simply have different names. Instead of sex appeals, relationship information discusses <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-attraction-doctor/201606/3-central-elements-of-romantic-attraction">ways of being attractive</a>. Appeals to humor and playfulness become flirting techniques and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-attraction-doctor/202012/what-is-your-flirting-style-how-do-you-flirt">flirting styles</a>. Making comparisons turns into deciding <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-attraction-doctor/201401/who-is-attractive-and-compatible-as-a-romantic-partner">who is attractive and compatible</a> as a partner. The words are different, but the underlying processes are the same.</p>

<p>In fact, these similarities occur because both persuasion and romantic attraction operate on the same foundation—emotion. Specifically, as explained by Russell (1980), our emotions are created from the combination of two different experiences. On one hand, they contain our feelings of <em>arousal</em> (high vs. low excitement) toward a person or object. On the other hand, emotions also encompass our feelings of <em>valence</em> (positive vs. negative) about a person or object.</p>



  


<p>That link to emotions explains why <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/persuasion-bias-and-choice/202209/using-arousal-and-excitement-persuade-and-influence">creating excitement</a> and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/persuasion-bias-and-choice/202106/using-positive-reinforcement-influence-the-behavior-others">using rewards</a> are essential components of persuasion. It also explains why <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-attraction-doctor/201307/how-to-keep-a-relationship-or-marriage-exciting">exciting activities</a> and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-attraction-doctor/201703/how-build-rewarding-romantic-relationship">rewarding interactions</a> are necessary to build satisfying relationships. Taken together, then, by being arousing and positive, you help to ensure both persuasion success and relationship solidarity too!</p>

<p><em>© 2026 by Jeremy S. Nicholson, M.A., M.S.W., Ph.D. All rights reserved.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/persuasion-bias-and-choice/202602/the-best-persuasion-involves-sex-appeal-humor-and" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/persuasion-bias-and-choice/202602/the-best-persuasion-involves-sex-appeal-humor-and</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/persuasion-bias-and-choice/202602/the-best-persuasion-involves-sex-appeal-humor-and</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeremy Nicholson M.S.W., Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-olly-3781538jn2.jpg?itok=conYcU5h" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You Are Not Your Project]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-04/Faisal%20Hoque.png.jpg?itok=MG89GLH7" alt="Faisal Hoque" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Wisdom</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">You Are Not Your Project</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The liberating psychology of strategic quitting.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The sunk cost fallacy isn’t just about economics — it’s also about identity.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Quitting doesn’t always mean failure. There is wisdom in recognizing when persistence has become the obstacle.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">You are not your projects — it is important to separate self from outcome.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AdobeStock_1900828200.jpeg.jpg?itok=_uUHawc2" width="320" height="179" data-insert-type="image" title="Phanupong/Adobe Stock " alt="Phanupong/Adobe Stock "></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Phanupong/Adobe Stock</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>“Winners never quit and quitters never win” goes the famous motivational quote attributed to legendary football coach Vince Lombardi. It’s a great expression of our culture’s veneration of grit and persistence: We celebrate never giving up, we admire people who pushed through when others would have quit. And this makes sense. Persistence <em>is </em>admirable and it <em>is</em> essential for overcoming many of the challenges we face in life. But as the Greek philosopher Aristotle saw 2000 years ago, actions pushed to their extreme turn into vice.</p>

<p>There is a famous fable about the Scottish king Robert the Bruce. Robert had gone into battle six times with the English, and lost each time. After his sixth defeat, he took refuge in a cave, ready to abandon his cause. And there he watched a spider try to anchor its web to the cave wall. The spider tried and failed again and again – six times, in fact – before finally succeeding on the seventh attempt.</p>

<p>After bearing witness to this anthropomorphized life lesson, the Bruce decided to return to the fight, winning independence for the Scots – on the seventh attempt.</p>
<p>This story has come back to me many times over the years. In my twenties, I recalled it when struggling to build my first company; a few years later, it inspired me again when I set out to reboot after being fired from my second business. Robert’s story offers a deep well of inspiration for those who most need it. But lately I’ve been thinking about a possibility the fable ignores.</p>

<p>What if the spider had been climbing the wrong corner of the cave? What if the web, once built, would have caught nothing?</p>
<h2>The Danger of Persistence</h2>
<p>The harder we work at the wrong thing, the more we invest in it. And the more we invest in something, the harder it becomes to see that we have made a mistake. We become less able to ask whether the task is still worth pursuing – and less able to hear when the answer is no.</p>

<p>Economists call this the sunk cost fallacy. It’s their name for the tendency to keep investing in something because of what we’ve already put in, even when the best path forward is to stop. We throw good money after bad, good years after wasted ones.</p>
<p>Money and time are important. But the sunk cost fallacy often comes from something even deeper – our attachment to how we define ourselves. For example, the entrepreneur doesn’t just have a business; she <em>is</em> a founder. The role becomes existential. And so, when she faces the prospect of winding up the business, she’s not just conducting a dispassionate cost-benefit analysis. She’s confronting the loss of who she thought she was.</p>

<p>Our egos get tangled up in our commitments. We start to believe that if a project fails, it means something about who we are. We stop being able to see the situation clearly because seeing clearly might mean confronting something we don’t want to face.</p>
<p>No wonder we find it difficult to quit.</p>
<h2>Separating Self From Outcome</h2>

<p>Here is a truism that sounds trivial but is deeply important to internalize — a truth that we must feel with our hearts, not just know with our minds: You are not the project.</p>
<p>Your worth as a person is not determined by whether a particular project succeeds or fails.</p>
<p>Once we begin to <em>feel </em>this, once we untangle our identity from the outcome, we can, first of all, assess quitting more calmly. It is not a question of you failing or being a failure. It is simply a question of whether the project is worth continuing or not.</p>

<p>Separating ourselves from our projects also allows us to see that the end of a project does not destroy the value of what has gone before. I have had to leave ventures I built, but I carry forward the skills, relationships and insights that I gained from the experience. </p>
<p>Quitting is in fact necessary for growth – as those famous philosophers the Red Hot Chili Peppers argue, destruction may lead to tough times, but it is often a necessary condition of creation. By ending something, we create space for something new to grow. We need to exit the things that don’t work anymore to be able to enter the projects that make sense for who we are today.</p>

<p>In a word, all beginnings require endings. And quitting is therefore necessary for starting anew.</p>
<h2>Five Practices for Learning How to Quit</h2>
<p>Being able to quit is a skill that requires deliberate effort to develop. Here are five practices that may help:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Name what you’re protecting.</strong> Ask yourself honestly: Am I holding on because this still makes sense, or because letting go feels like losing part of myself?</li>
<li><strong>Map what you never controlled.</strong> Write down everything that influenced the outcome – timing, market forces, other people’s choices, luck. See how much was never fully yours to determine.</li>
<li><strong>Give grief a container.</strong> Set a timer for fifteen minutes. Let yourself feel the disappointment, the sadness, the anger. When the timer ends, stand up. Take a walk. You’ve honored the loss without being consumed by it.</li>
<li><strong>Reframe the story.</strong> Instead of “I failed,” try: “I learned something important” or “I made the best choice I could with what I knew.”</li>
<li><strong>Ask the clean question.</strong> If you were starting fresh today – no history, no sunk costs, no identity at stake – would you begin this thing? If the answer is no, that’s important information.</li>
</ol>



  


<h2>The Spider’s Second Lesson</h2>
<p>Let me end by being quite clear about what I’m saying.</p>
<p>To repeat, I’m <em>not</em> saying that persistence is something bad. What I’m saying is that there’s a crucial difference between failing at the right thing and persisting at the wrong one. When we fail at the right thing, persistence makes sense. We learn, adjust, try again. But when we persist with the wrong thing, every ounce of effort takes us further from where we’re meant to be.</p>

<p>I’m saying that we can imagine a different version of the story of Robert the Bruce. In this story, the spider falls a seventh time. It pauses on the stone floor – and then turns, crawling toward a different corner of the cave, where the wind is calmer and the flies more plentiful.</p>
<p>In this new version, the spider understands something it took me years to learn: Quitting is not always weakness. Sometimes, it’s wisdom. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/code-conscience/202602/you-are-not-your-project" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/code-conscience/202602/you-are-not-your-project</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/code-conscience/202602/you-are-not-your-project</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Faisal Hoque]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/AdobeStock_1900828200.jpeg.jpg?itok=S_5x6nWv" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>