<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 19:22:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 19:22:07 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Risks of Children's Use of Chatbots]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-07/hermanputnam.png.jpg?itok=fW73jvW6" alt="Judith L. Herman, M.D., and Frank W. Putnam, M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Adolescence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Risks of Children's Use of Chatbots</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What parents need to know about their kids' potentially harmful use of chatbots.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">At least 13 percent of youth are getting mental health advice from chatbots.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Chatbots may form dangerously intimate "relationships" with vulnerable youth, promoting risky behavior.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Most recommendations to protect children from chatbots place the onus on unprepared parents.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>With growing horror, we have been following news reports of AI chatbots convincing troubled children and adolescents that suicide is a noble and acceptable release from their distress. Reading transcripts of these chatbot-child “conversations” literally brings tears at times—tears of rage that such dangerous devices are unleashed on unsuspecting and vulnerable children and adolescents. </p>

<p>Suicide is the second and third leading cause of death for children and adolescents, respectively. The rate of youth suicide is rapidly increasing, with girls making more attempts but boys having almost three times the number of lethal completions (17.3/100,000 males v. 6.4/100,000 females) (Khushboo et al., 2026). </p>

<h2>What Do We Know about Adolescent Uses of Chatbots?</h2>
<p>Never in the course of human history have children and adolescents interacted with seemingly intelligent entities capable of generating individualized responses to their most deeply personal questions and insecurities. Children are developmentally primed to have intense “personal” relationships with inanimate entities, from teddy bears to Pokémon. One of their primary developmental tasks is learning how to be in reciprocal human relationships where there are mutual expectations and accountability, both joy and disappointment. But chatbot relationships are notably “frictionless,” without mutuality, expectations, or accountability. What children and adolescents learn from relating to chatbots will inevitably transfer into their human relationships.</p>

<p>Chatbots are carefully crafted to be experienced by users as friendly, trustworthy companions. They are low-cost, always available, and perceived to be private. With their still-developing reality-testing, children and adolescents are susceptible to unquestioningly investing these computer-simulated companions with unwarranted omniscience and beneficence. </p>

<p>The unrelenting exposure of today’s youth to AI chatbots is inevitable. Encouraged by web developers who regard AI as essential to their platform’s success, chatbots are increasingly embedded in all manner of applications. Surveys indicated that more than 95 percent of U.S. youth ages 13 to 17 report using the internet (Pratt et al., 2024). In a nationally representative survey, 13.1 percent of U.S. youth (approximately 5.4 million children) reported using AI for mental health advice (McBain et al., 2025). Of the mental health advice seekers, about two-thirds reported at least monthly use, and over 90 percent reported that the chatbot advice was helpful. </p>

<h2>Risks of AI Chatbots</h2>
<p>These types of “therapeutic” interactions are just beginning to be studied. One flagrant red flag of the dangers posed by AI chatbots is that they can be easily “tricked” into giving children dangerous advice. For example, researchers posing as 15-year-olds were able to convince a commonly used chatbot to describe how to avoid detection of drug or alcohol use, how to manufacture explosive devices, and how to outwit surveillance systems.</p>

<p>Chatbots can create risks in other ways. As engaging companions, they may replace important human relationships. As commercial systems, they collect extensive information about users, including children, which may be exploited. Many educators are concerned that a growing dependence on AI to do school work may disrupt the powerful feedback that occurs when doing or solving a task by oneself.</p>


<h2>Problems for Parents</h2>
<p>Realistically, most parents have only a limited knowledge of what their children are doing and seeing on the internet. The older the child, the more parents tend to respect the child’s privacy, and therefore the less they know about the content the child is exposed to. Parents often lack the technical knowledge to examine their children’s digital devices or activate any parental controls that may exist.</p>

<p>In news accounts of chatbot-abetted suicides, grieving parents frequently express shocked bewilderment at how incredibly intimate and irresistibly powerful the “relationship” was between their deceased child and the chatbot.</p>
<h2>Signs That a Child's Chatbot Use Is Unhealthy</h2>
<p>The American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry (AACAP) issued a one-pager listing signs that a child or adolescent’s AI use may be unhealthy (AACAP, No. 145; July 2025). These include:</p>



  


<ul>
<li>Spending time with AI applications at the expense of other interests and responsibilities. </li>
<li>Decreased face-to-face social interactions.</li>
<li>Emotional outbursts, lying, and rule-breaking when limits are set on AI or screen use.</li>
<li>Sleep disturbances related to excessive nocturnal device use.</li>
<li>Sharing inappropriate personal information or images with AI systems.</li>
<li>Using AI to cheat on school assignments.</li>
<li>Using AI tools to bully peers and creating sexual or violent content with AI.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Ways to Help Youth Use AI Safely</h2>
<p>The AACAP flyer includes recommendations that are shared by experts who study the influence of the internet on children and adolescents. Parents should: </p>
<ul>
<li>Explore the AI tools together with their child, both to look for questionable content and become familiar with an AI platform’s features, such as parental controls and access to chatbot logs.</li>
<li>Model skepticism and how to adopt a questioning stance toward information offered by AI.</li>
<li>Encourage children to share and discuss online experiences and help them to understand that images, videos, audio, or depicted events may be fake.</li>
<li>Discuss the difference between a chatbot companion and human relationships, as well as promote and support human social interactions. </li>
<li>Set and enforce clear boundaries around AI and/or screen usage. </li>
<li>Learn and enforce school rules governing AI use on assignments. </li>
<li>Ensure that their child’s sensitive personal information or images are not being shared with AI systems.</li>
</ul>

<h2>The Problem With These Recommendations</h2>
<p>The problem with these recommendations is that they put a great deal of the onus on parents, who are expected to stay up-to-date in a fast-moving, youth-oriented cyberworld that is outside of their experience and interest. Meanwhile, AI and social media providers remain broadly immune from legal liability under a 1996 law (CDA in 47 U.S.C. 230). This 20th-century law was originally intended to protect providers from accountability for libelous content created by others but posted on their platforms (Walker, 2023). </p>

<p>Thirty years later, the internet is a very different world. No longer composed of simple bulletin boards passively accepting user posts, AI-based websites are highly interactive, covertly, but profoundly, influencing users through sophisticated algorithms that are not well understood even by the providers.</p>

<p>In many respects, the situation has the feeling of a runaway train, and the nation’s youth are tied to the tracks ahead. It is past time for Congress and AI chatbot providers to meet their moral and societal obligations to actively deter dangerous AI-driven interactions, such as chatbots that enable suicidal impulses or risky behaviors, especially as they involve minors.</p>

<p><em>If you or someone you love is contemplating suicide, seek help immediately. For help 24/7, dial 988 for the 988 Suicide &amp; Crisis Lifeline, or reach out to the Crisis Text Line by texting TALK to 741741. Outside of the U.S., visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/suicide/suicide-prevention-hotlines-resources-worldwide"><em>International Resources page for suicide hotlines in your country.</em></a></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mental-health-care-today/202602/the-risks-of-childrens-use-of-chatbots" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mental-health-care-today/202602/the-risks-of-childrens-use-of-chatbots</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mental-health-care-today/202602/the-risks-of-childrens-use-of-chatbots</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Judith L. Herman, M.D., and Frank W. Putnam, M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-karola-g-7281588.jpg?itok=p7QfhZS7" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Bureaucratization of the Therapist]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/320x400-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=DoR2rV5d" alt="Mark Shelvock, RP, MACP, MA" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Bureaucratization of the Therapist</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: How institutional anxiety reshapes therapy.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Modern therapy is increasingly governed by risk-management logic rather than relational psychology.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Institutional anxiety becomes internalized by therapists, producing defensive practices.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Healing relational wounds requires context-based discernment and emotional courage from a therapist.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/deepigoyal-ehRsHPvOFlU-unsplash.jpg?itok=j2LThHyM" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by deepigoyal on Unsplash" alt="Photo by deepigoyal on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by deepigoyal on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Psychotherapy is increasingly practiced under conditions that fundamentally mistrust it. The tension arises not from regulation itself, <em>per se</em>, but from how risk-management cultures can unintentionally shape the inner world of licensed psychotherapists and counselling practitioners.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The modern regulatory environment surrounding therapy is shaped less by psychological science than by bureaucratic risk management. Institutions are designed to minimize liability, protect reputations, prevent scandal, and maintain status quo within the broader culture. When rare instances of serious misconduct or harm occur, the response is usually structural tightening: expanded documentation, heightened oversight, and increasing procedural restriction.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Psychotherapy and counselling psychology, however, did not emerge from institutional logic. The field was forged within relational, psychoanalytic, and depth-oriented traditions that prioritize lived experience, symbolic meaning, cultural complexity, and human nuance over procedural standardization. Bureaucracy seeks predictability, yet psychotherapy was built upon a disciplined engagement with uncertainty.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Healing relationships are inherently unique, unpredictable, emotionally charged, messy, and context-specific. Therapeutic relationships require clinicians to engage in wise discernment, relational responsiveness, and the capacity to metabolize ambiguity. In stark contrast, risk-management systems which govern therapy attempt to eliminate or neutralize ambiguity.</p>

<p dir="ltr">When liability prevention becomes the dominant organizing principle, therapists are subtly trained to prioritize relational defensibility over presence; to ask not only <em>what helps this person?</em> but <em>what could be justified if later reviewed?</em></p>
<p dir="ltr">Thus, the anticipation of institutional scrutiny quietly enters the therapy room. Like Medusa’s gaze, it risks turning the clinician to stone: frozen, rigid, vigilant, technically appropriate yet emotionally constricted. In this way, clinical judgment becomes shadowed by institutional anxiety, which can result in spontaneity narrowing, the clinical imagination tightening, and emotional risk-taking on the therapist’s part (which could positively transform a person's life if sincerely expressed) diminished. When the therapist monitors not only the person in therapy, but the possibility of accusation, their clinical insight and interpretation can weaken. </p>

<p dir="ltr">In attempting to eliminate misconduct, the system surrounding psychotherapy in Western societies fosters defensive practice, and in doing so may unintentionally constrain some of the relational processes through which psychotherapy can be most effective.</p>
<h2>Institutional Projection: The Internalized Superego</h2>

<p dir="ltr">From a psychoanalytical perspective, bureaucratic systems function as collective survival defenses against anxiety. Institutions, like individuals, struggle to tolerate uncertainty; they convert vulnerability into rule, surveillance, control, restricted mastery, and procedure. Structural control becomes a way of managing collective fear. Yet anxiety does not disappear when formalized, but becomes displaced.</p>

<p dir="ltr">What cannot be metabolized institutionally is projected downward into practitioners, particularly trainees, graduate students, and early-career clinicians still forming their professional identities. Many therapists unfortunately internalize a regulatory superego: an observing authority that monitors spontaneity, restricts relational presence, minimizes certain cultural expressions, and punishes deviation from procedural norms.</p>


<p dir="ltr">The healer becomes divided, psychologically speaking. One aspect of the therapist remains attuned to the person in therapy, while another remains preoccupied with institutional risk. There is also no such thing as a benign intrapsychic split within psychodynamic traditions. Thus, the clinician’s internal world begins to reorganize painfully and defensively. </p>

<p dir="ltr">The space meant to metabolize survival wisdom and unconscious defences can begin to reproduce them. When institutional anxiety embeds itself in the atmosphere of care, therapy grows cautious, measured, and subtly constricted to life. In this way, the broader culture’s fear of misuse of power can become more psychologically dominant than its trust in relational repair.</p>



  


<h2>Therapy as the Managed Confessional</h2>
<p dir="ltr">As traditional religious institutions decline across Western societies, psychotherapy has inherited many of their psychological functions: confession, moral reflection, witnessing suffering, and the search for meaning. It remains one of the few culturally sanctioned spaces in which vulnerability is permitted in a largely emotionally-phobic world.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Yet unlike earlier confessional traditions grounded in relational authority and shared humanity, contemporary psychotherapy is increasingly regulated through institutional distrust. As a result, the modern therapist occupies a paradoxical position: entrusted with intimate human disclosure, yet governed by systems that assume relational closeness is inherently dangerous.</p>

<p dir="ltr">A broader culture uncertain about its capacity for relational intimacy has attempted to bureaucratize the healer, which often results not in ethical collapse, but relational and communal thinning.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/alvaro-rotellar-BmNSc2GtEl0-unsplash.jpg?itok=k_8uwDaU" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Álvaro Rotellar on Unsplash" alt="Photo by Álvaro Rotellar on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Álvaro Rotellar on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Depth or Compliance?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">None of this suggests abandoning ethical boundaries or values that promote human integrity. Power differentials are real, harm prevention matters, boundaries are important, and therapists must act deliberately.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The issue is that when regulation becomes organized primarily around the anticipation of deviation, psychotherapy risks becoming an institution more concerned with preventing scandal than cultivating authentic and relational or communal-based wisdom.</p>

<p dir="ltr">A profession structured predominantly around liability will inevitably produce clinicians who practice defensively, and, put simply, defensive therapy cannot heal defensive relational wounds in people pursuing therapy (and most people have defensive relational wounds of some type). It is my professional opinion that the future of psychotherapy may depend on whether it can resist bureaucratic colonization and recover a form of professionalism grounded not in emotional distance, but in disciplined relational courage—the courage to remain fully human and sincere within structure.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Boundaries must protect without suffocating the living therapeutic relationship, and ethics must guide without freezing the human encounter. Otherwise, psychotherapy risks becoming ‘safe’ but hollow; a practice governed by fear and defences rather than animated by transformative wisdom.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/navigating-the-serpentine-path/202602/the-bureaucratization-of-the-therapist" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/navigating-the-serpentine-path/202602/the-bureaucratization-of-the-therapist</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/navigating-the-serpentine-path/202602/the-bureaucratization-of-the-therapist</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Shelvock, RP, MACP, MA]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/alvaro-rotellar-BmNSc2GtEl0-unsplash.jpg?itok=qmbfK0qt" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Raising Resilient Children in Uncertain Times]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Sam%20Goldstein.png.jpg?itok=kLaUD2vO" alt="Sam Goldstein Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Adverse Childhood Experiences</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Raising Resilient Children in Uncertain Times</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to help young minds feel safe in an uncertain world.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Children absorb global conflict through media and emotion.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Development shapes how kids understand war and safety.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Calm, honest adults build resilience during uncertainty.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Increasingly around the globe, children live with the threat of mass violence. The current conflict in Iran has once again filled headlines with images of missile strikes, political retaliation, and warnings of wider regional war. Words like <em>annihilate</em> and <em>destroy </em>are used to describe the goals of nations and leaders. Even when fighting is far from home, it rarely feels distant. Bunkers aren’t common places where many children spend time, but technology has changed the way children are exposed to war.</p>

<p>Many adults delay these conversations. Some believe children are better off not hearing about violence. Research suggests otherwise. Children are more aware of media exposure and adult emotion than we assume. After the September 11 attacks, children who watched more news coverage, especially those far from the attacks, reported higher levels of post-traumatic stress symptoms (Pfefferbaum et al., 2001).</p>

<h2>How Development Affects Understanding</h2>
<p>Young children think in concrete, immediate terms. Their primary concern is personal safety. If they hear that a city has been bombed, they may assume their own neighborhood is next. Because they struggle with abstract political motives and distant geography, they interpret events as local and personal (Slone &amp; Shoshani, 2008). They are more likely to ask, “Are we safe?” than “Why are they fighting?”</p>

<p>The child may interpret things literally. Therefore, words like <em>wipe out</em> and <em>destroy</em> could have absolute meanings to them. If there is no reassurance provided to them, your child may think in their mind that the world will cease to exist. Children at this stage are primarily dependent on trusted adults for emotional safety and security. Research has proven that parental calmness and availability are the two strongest protective factors for children dealing with collective trauma (Masten &amp; Narayan, 2012) during this stressful time in history.</p>

<p>Children exposed to ongoing political conflict often show strong emotional responses such as fear and anger, along with increased curiosity about causes and consequences (Slone &amp; Shoshani, 2008). Questions become more complex: Why do people hate each other? Why can’t leaders solve these problems? These reflect growing moral reasoning.</p>

<p>Teens experience war differently than other age groups. While they are able to think abstractly about history, economics, religion, and politics, many also pay attention to global events through the international news they follow and have developed strong opinions about what happens in the world around them. Teens experience intense emotional and identity development during adolescence. Repeated exposure to graphic news has been linked to increased levels of anxiety and depression in teens (Comer et al., 2008). There is a wide range of possible outcomes that exist for teens based on how much family support, friendships, and meaning in their life positively affect their resilience (Masten &amp; Narayan, 2012).</p>

<h2>The Impact of Media and Adult Response</h2>
<p>Regardless of age, children look to adults to decide how afraid they should feel. If adults react with panic or hopelessness, children’s distress increases. If adults acknowledge concern while modeling coping, children feel more secure.</p>
<p>Research indicates that children whose parents respond calmly to news of terrorist attacks and limit their child's exposure to graphic material will demonstrate fewer symptoms of trauma (Pfefferbaum et al., 2001). Training adults in managing media and using coping strategies to assist children in coping with media exposure related to terrorism has demonstrated a reduction in children's distress caused by exposure to terrorism-related media (Comer et al., 2008). Due to the immature nature of a child's cognitive ability to assess probability, children will often perceive that there is immediate danger everywhere if they do not have a parenting adult to place that danger into perspective.</p>


<h2>Five Goals and Practical Strategies</h2>
<p>The first goal in discussing war and peace is understanding. Begin by asking what the child has heard and what they think is happening. This often reveals misconceptions or exaggerated fears.</p>
<p>The second goal is developmental fit. Tailor explanations to the child’s age and cognitive level. Young children need reassurance about safety. School-aged children need help separating fact from fiction. Teens benefit from open dialogue and respectful debate.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>The third goal involves supporting children to express their feelings through words. Allowing space for children to articulate their fear, confusion, or anger aids in regulating their feelings. Naming feelings allows children to better manage their emotions.</p>
<p>The fourth goal aims to limit the amount of time a child is exposed to disturbing images in the media. To the extent possible, watch and/or read the news with children and discuss the content. The media often replay dramatic events many times, so children may feel that these events are happening more frequently than they really are.</p>



  


<p>The fifth goal is founded on the idea of sharing examples of activities that support peace, such as diplomatic efforts, humanitarian aid, and acts of solidarity. Children can also participate in acts of service appropriate to their age at school and at home. Small acts of kindness provide children with a sense of having power.</p>

<p>Children contemplate war, regardless of whether they mention it or not. They think about it, wonder what might happen, and hope for an end. They have basic needs, including safety, love, and reassurance. These needs will continue to exist, but their understanding of these needs will change as they mature. As children grow older, so does their reliance on stable adults. In a world where negative information spreads rapidly and instantaneously, calm conversation is one of the most substantial protective resources we can provide to our children.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/raising-resilient-children/202602/raising-resilient-children-in-uncertain-times" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/raising-resilient-children/202602/raising-resilient-children-in-uncertain-times</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/raising-resilient-children/202602/raising-resilient-children-in-uncertain-times</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Raising Resilient Children]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/DSC02059.JPG.jpg?itok=CFSogpQG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>