<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 17:24:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 17:24:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[5 Things Therapy Can Do for You (and 5 Things It Can't)]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/untitled_2_0.jpg?itok=sNYHTgsC" alt="Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">5 Things Therapy Can Do for You (and 5 Things It Can't)</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Knowing what therapy can and can’t do helps you hit the ground running.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Therapy has limits. It can help you gain skills and new perspectives, but it can't control your motivation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Having clear, achievable goals from the start helps you get the most out of the process.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Don't be afraid to ask questions or shop around to ensure a good fit.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/therapy-8553798_1280.jpg?itok=3KQ4nT_9" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="PhilippeJacquet01/Pixabay" alt="PhilippeJacquet01/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: PhilippeJacquet01/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Over my 50 years of practice, I’ve learned that therapy, like most professions, has both limits and strengths. Here’s my top-five list of what therapy cannot do.</p>
<h2>1. Motivate you</h2>
<p>You’ve probably known people who could benefit from therapy to help them resolve problems, gain a different perspective, learn skills, and make sense of their pasts. But they don’t try it because it seems too overwhelming, or they don’t know how to find someone skilled enough, or they’re afraid they’ll be stuck in it forever. And then there are those who come in once or twice because they are sent by the court, their attorney, their partner, or their boss. They come to comply, to get these others off their back, but basically they believe they don’t need therapy.</p>

<p>A good therapist can make starting and attending sessions as comfortable as possible for the anxious; they can inspire hope, but they can’t get them through the front door. And for those who don’t want to be there, there's little to do—the therapist is providing a service; they’re not a cop.</p>
<h2>2. Directly change other people in your life</h2>

<p>Often, those who come to appease someone else believe the other person is the one with the problem and who really needs therapy. Similarly, many of the couples I see come in with the hope and expectation that, if only they or I can get the other person to change, their lives will improve by 100%. Therapy can provide a safe space for someone to express what they’d like the other person to change, but it’s up to the other person to decide whether they are willing to do it. We’re back to talking about motivation.</p>

<p>That said, therapy can help you become a change agent in the relationship. Because relationships are based on patterns—the ways individuals bounce off each other—one person’s change can motivate change in the other. The dance between them shifts.</p>
<h2>3. Fix vague problems</h2>
<p>Therapy can’t make you happy because happiness is a byproduct of fixing something else—a relationship, your job, or the chemistry of your brain through medication. Ditto for “improving communication” or “getting respect.” The key lies in focusing and fixing the specific underlying issues. </p>

<h2>4. Guarantee you will achieve a concrete goal</h2>
<p>This is the other side of the same coin. If, say, your goal is to make $1 million or find your soulmate, therapy is not the genie in the lamp. Like happiness, the money or soulmate are the end points of a process, and what therapy is good at is helping you navigate the process—for example, increasing your self-confidence or your ability to take risks or to be less impulsive. But delivering on that million dollars or soulmate? Nope.</p>

<h2>5. Guarantee it will work</h2>
<p>Therapy, unlike, say, plumbing, isn’t straightforward, and even plumbers can have trouble fixing certain problems. Successful therapy clearly depends on the therapist's skill, their approach to your problem, as well as your full buy-in as the client. When all these factors align, therapy works, but when they don’t, for any reason, the outcome becomes less certain.</p>

<p>So, if this is what therapy isn't good at, what is it useful for? Here again are my top five.</p>
<h2>1. Teach skills</h2>
<p>If you struggle with anxiety, anger, or depression, therapy can help you learn to control your emotions. If you find yourself arguing with your partner, therapy can teach you effective communication skills.</p>


<h2>2. Help you understand how your mind works </h2>
<p>Again, patterns. Just like a skilled card player takes time to learn the tells of other players, a therapist gets to know you and identifies your emotional and cognitive patterns. Providing you with this feedback helps you become more aware of what makes you tick.</p>

<h2>3. Change your story</h2>
<p>Psychodynamic approaches that explore your past also help you view it from a different perspective. The story you’ve been telling yourself for years may now seem different. This change in how you see your past can, in turn, alter your view of yourself in the present.</p>
<h2>4. Create a safe space for mediating relationship problems</h2>



  


<p>Many couples and families I’ve seen over the years often needed a strong referee to help guide difficult conversations, as well as someone with fresh eyes to ask tough questions and point out the elephants in the room everyone was ignoring.</p>
<h2>5. Encourage new behaviors and provide support.</h2>
<p>A therapist is like a coach, a cheerleader, a strict headmaster, and a kind Mr. Rogers all in one. They can hold you accountable so you don’t slack off, show empathy when you feel discouraged or helpless, and help you get unstuck when you’re feeling stuck. </p>

<h2>Go in with eyes wide open</h2>
<p>The theme here is to have realistic expectations so that you not only avoid feeling disappointed or frustrated, but also hit the ground running and make the most of your time and money. Don’t hesitate to shop around or ask questions, no matter how trivial they may seem.</p>
<p>Most importantly, don’t settle for what you get. </p>

<p><em>To find a therapist, please visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>. </em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202603/5-things-therapy-can-do-for-you-and-5-things-it-cant" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202603/5-things-therapy-can-do-for-you-and-5-things-it-cant</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202603/5-things-therapy-can-do-for-you-and-5-things-it-cant</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/therapy-8553798_1280.jpg?itok=nVgY9ROk" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Talking to Your Child About Sex, Puberty, and Consent]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Cook.png.jpg?itok=6zFBKbhL" alt="Cook" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Parenting</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Talking to Your Child About Sex, Puberty, and Consent</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What parents should know when talking about sex, puberty, and consent.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Early, accurate discussions about anatomy and boundaries strengthens body autonomy and helps protect children.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Honest, developmentally tailored conversations can reduce risk and increase emotional readiness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Parents are best positioned to shape a child’s understanding of consent, relationships, and decision-making.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Few parenting topics make even the most confident adults shift in their seats like sex. Many of us were raised with silence, vague euphemisms, or one awkward “talk” that left more confusion than clarity. So, when our own children start asking questions, it can feel disorienting.</p>
<p>But here is the reality: if you don’t teach your child about sex, someone else will. A classmate with an older sibling. A friend with unrestricted internet access. Social media. Culture will educate your child if you don’t—and it rarely does so with your values in mind.</p>

<p>The goal is not one grand, flawless lecture. It’s thousands of small, steady conversations over time. When we approach sexuality as an ongoing dialogue rather than a single event, we replace shame with safety and secrecy with trust.</p>
<h2>Toddlers and Preschoolers (Ages 2-5): Start With Bodies and Safety</h2>
<p>Sex education begins far earlier than most parents realize. At this stage, the focus is simple: correct body part names, body safety, and normalizing curiosity.</p>

<p>Use accurate anatomical terms—penis, vulva, vagina, testicles, breasts. This is not about being graphic; it’s about being clear. Correct language reduces shame, strengthens body autonomy, and increases safety. Children who know proper terminology are better able to report inappropriate behavior if it occurs.</p>

<p>Keep your tone neutral and calm. No whispering. No giggling. No dramatics.</p>
<p>Body safety conversations should be straightforward: private parts are covered by a swimsuit; no one touches them except to keep you clean or healthy; you can say no to unwanted touch; and secrets about bodies are not okay. These discussions are empowering, not frightening.</p>

<p>Curiosity is also normal. Young children may touch their genitals in public or explore bodily sensations. The task is not to shame, but to guide. “That’s something you do in private” is usually enough. Calm correction teaches boundaries without attaching embarrassment.</p>
<p>When the inevitable question comes—“Where do babies come from?”—be accurate and brief. A simple explanation about a sperm and an egg joining together is sufficient. Answer only what they ask. Overexplaining overwhelms them. Underreacting communicates discomfort.</p>

<h2>Early School-Age (Ages 6-9): Simple Biology and Open Doors</h2>
<p>Children in this phase are concrete thinkers. They are curious and increasingly aware of differences between boys and girls.</p>
<p>If they ask how a baby is made, you can explain that when grown-ups decide to make a baby, a man’s penis goes inside a woman’s vagina and then a sperm can meet an egg. Delivered calmly, this is biology—not scandalous material.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Your reaction becomes their reaction. If you are composed, they learn there is nothing shameful about their bodies.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, many children are exposed to explicit content by this age—often accidentally. Proactively say, “If you ever see pictures or videos of naked people or people doing private things, you won’t be in trouble. Come tell me.” Removing shame before it begins keeps communication open.</p>


<p>This is also the time to introduce the idea of consent in simple language: people should agree before touching, and touching other people’s private parts is a behavior not meant for children.</p>
<h2>Tweens (Ages 10-12): Puberty, Pornography, and Protection</h2>
<p>If you wait until middle school to discuss puberty, you are late. Conversations about body changes should happen before those changes begin.</p>

<p>Both boys and girls need to understand male and female puberty—breast development, menstruation, erections, wet dreams, testicular growth, voice changes. This is human development, not a statement about gender identity.</p>
<p>Separate physical development from intimacy. A discussion about periods does not need to morph into a lecture about sexual relationships. But as emotional awareness grows, make sure to normalize attraction and crushes. Curiosity about romance is developmentally appropriate.</p>



  


<p>Now we must address what many parents hope to avoid: pornography. With smartphones and tablets, exposure is often just a click away. Be direct: online sexual content is created for entertainment, not education. It often portrays unrealistic bodies, distorted power dynamics, and little emphasis on consent or emotional connection.</p>

<p>Make it clear that sending or requesting explicit photos is unsafe and can carry serious legal consequences. These are not threats—they are facts.</p>
<p>This is also the stage to discuss sexually transmitted infections (STIs). Explain that STIs are infections spread through sexual contact; some are treatable, some are lifelong. Discuss condoms honestly—while they significantly reduce risk, they do not eliminate it. Education is not permission; it is protection.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Teens: Independence, Identity, and Informed Choices</h2>
<p>By adolescence, most teens understand what sex is. The conversation shifts from mechanics to maturity.</p>
<p>In the United States, the average age of first sexual intercourse is around 17. Some teens will wait longer. Some will not. Pretending otherwise does not keep them safe.</p>

<p>Ask questions instead of delivering speeches: “What do you think makes someone ready for sex?” “What would you do if you felt pressured?”</p>
<p>Teens deserve accurate information about condoms, birth control, emergency contraception, and STI testing. Research consistently shows that comprehensive sex education does not increase sexual activity; it delays risky behavior and improves safety.</p>

<p>Consent must be discussed repeatedly. Consent is clear, ongoing, freely given, and cannot occur under the influence of drugs or alcohol. Silence is not consent. Pressure is not consent.</p>
<h2>Why School-Based Sex Education Isn’t Enough</h2>
<p>Many parents assume schools will handle this. The truth is that sex education varies widely by state and district. Some programs emphasize abstinence-only approaches. Many provide limited discussion of consent, emotional readiness, or healthy relationships.</p>

<p>Schools deliver general information. They do not teach your family’s values, expectations, or beliefs. That responsibility belongs to you.</p>
<h2>The Bigger Picture</h2>
<p>Sex education is not a single milestone conversation. It is an evolving dialogue that grows with your child.</p>
<p>Stay calm. Curiosity is normal. Provide accurate information without drama. End conversations with an open invitation: “If you ever hear something confusing or have questions, come ask me.”</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>You do not need a perfect script. You need a relationship strong enough to hold hard questions.</p>
<p>When your child can talk to you about sex without fear, you have accomplished something far greater than explaining reproduction. You have taught autonomy, respect, boundaries, emotional intelligence, and self-worth.</p>

<p>These lessons extend far beyond the bedroom. They shape how your child understands safety, connection, and dignity in every relationship they will ever have.</p>
<p>Parenting often stretches us into uncomfortable spaces. This is one of them. You do not have to do it flawlessly. You simply have to show up—calm, honest, and willing to keep talking. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-redefined/202602/talking-to-your-child-about-sex-puberty-and-consent" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-redefined/202602/talking-to-your-child-about-sex-puberty-and-consent</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-redefined/202602/talking-to-your-child-about-sex-puberty-and-consent</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kristen Cook, MD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/pexels-nicola-barts-7944383.jpg?itok=kQQl6KG_" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>