<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 02:12:28 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 02:12:28 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Myth of the Easy Partner]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/jill-weber.jpg?itok=zpYi1X2b" alt="Jill P. Weber Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Myth of the Easy Partner</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How being “chill” can breed distance in a relationship.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The easygoing persona seems emotionally stable, mature, and like a solid romantic partner.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In reality, being consistently "easygoing" can be a defense against conflict or rejection.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Vulnerability through emotional ripples brings people closer.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Knowing yourself and communicating this self (even when it causes conflict) brings greater intimacy.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Sean and Sara have an easygoing relationship. When Sara disappoints him, Sean tells himself not to make a big deal about it. When he is hurt, he tells himself not to be needy or overly dramatic. When what he wants is different than what Sara wants, he says, “No worries, I am flexible.”</p>
<p>Sara has recently expressed that she feels kind of blah in the relationship and lonely. This is confusing to Sean because he tries so hard to be a good partner. At the same time, he does see that for all of their stability, there is a kind of emptiness between them.</p>

<p>The idea of being low maintenance, flexible, and “go with the flow” seems desirable and attractive. This kind of person appears easy to please and emotionally stable… pretty much all the time. Instead of starting fights or being triggered by small disappointments, they adjust, accommodate, and let their partner know that the differences between them are “No big deal…” “I’ve got you…” and “I can make that work….”</p>

<p>This pattern is more likely a way to keep people close than a well-developed skill set for negotiating relationships. In fact, being “low maintenance” can be a kind of shield that protects a person from conflict, negative feedback, feeling needy, or being held accountable.</p>
<p>An over-accommodating relationship pattern is often rooted in a childhood where a person learns early on that their needs, complicated emotions, or demands on the environment were met by caregivers with increased conflict, withdrawal, invalidation, or shame. Over time, a person learns to suppress their needs and difficult feelings as a way to keep people closer to them. And for most in this situation, caregivers praise the person for being so easy and not a problem, which only reinforces that this is the best way to deal with people.</p>

<p>In childhood, this strategy was likely a resilient way to get through the family system, but now in adulthood, it falls short, blocking intimacy and authentic closeness with others. People in this situation are often confused. Why would my partner not attend to my needs when I am so good to them and caring toward their needs?</p>

<p>The forever-easygoing, good-natured partner leads to consequences: namely, resentment and not being fully known by close others in your life. The more your needs go unnoticed, the more upsets start to quietly accumulate and eventually topple over.</p>
<h2>Here are four ways out of the easy partner trap:</h2>
<p><strong>1. Deferring to the other is really a fear of being known:</strong> Although you might seem like you are indifferent toward certain outcomes with others, the reality is you are likely afraid. People keep it chill out of fear of being seen as a problem, of creating conflict, or losing admiration, or being perceived as “too much.”</p>

<p>Work to first get in touch with what you feel emotionally and your preferences. Even if you don’t communicate this deeper self, pause and consider yourself. If you don’t know yourself, how can anyone else?</p>
<p><strong>2. If you can’t communicate your preferences, people start to forget about you:</strong> Over time, people start to take advantage of your low-maintenance way of being and will stop asking you what you need and want. They see you, but you are foggy to them. They forget that you are a real person with your own set of preferences, desires, and upsets. This makes it easy to eventually end the relationship because you aren’t a real fixture in their mind.</p>

<p>Start small, “I’d love to go to the movies, but I am open…what are you thinking?” True intimacy needs you to take up space in the relationship.</p>
<p><strong>3. Emotional upsets bring people closer:</strong> When you keep it chill, there is likely little relationship drama. On the other hand, you might be sacrificing relationship depth for stability. Just because things are calm doesn’t mean it is a deep connection.</p>


<p>Try to take emotional risks. Talk about a feeling you’re having without minimizing it, or let a friend or romantic partner know when something is uncomfortable for you, without hedging it (“I am recognizing I am feeling distant and want to talk about this with you…”).</p>
<p><strong>4. A separate sense of self brings intimacy:</strong> The friction between two separate identities bouncing off one another is often what lights the match of passion.</p>

<p>For a relationship to be truly alive, you need to have two people who are fully themselves with one another. These differences keep the relationship rich, vibrant, and deep. Experiment with little steps to test the waters on whether there is more room for your sense of self and preferences in your relationships.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/the-myth-of-the-easy-partner" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/the-myth-of-the-easy-partner</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/the-myth-of-the-easy-partner</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jill P. Weber Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/luciano-mantovani-Xvv1UDk04kw-unsplash%20%281%29.jpg?itok=tqh8HGQ9" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Fearful Brain]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/David%20Richo.png.jpg?itok=qdPOAWWy" alt="David Richo Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Fear</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Fearful Brain</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How the neuroscience of fear can help us understand our fears.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">We get caught in fears and don't have to.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Neuroscience reveals how fear affects the brain and body.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Understanding these automatic responses can help us make better choices in the future.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-liza-summer-6382725.jpg?itok=jiACZjIN" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Liza Summer / Pexels" alt="Liza Summer / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Liza Summer / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Neuroscience helps us understand how fear works and how we can work with it. A fear-arousing experience that hearkens back to a trauma from long ago will feel to us as though it is happening right now. All emotions, especially fear, include a physiological component. In fear, our amygdala, an organ deep in our primitive brain, instantly signals our autonomic nervous system to go on full alert. We then feel an amplified ability to fight or flee.</p>

<p>Sometimes, a freeze response to fear is safer than fighting or fleeing. This is generated by our parasympathetic system. In all of these reactions, blood flows to our outer organs, away from our brain. We thereby lose full access to our reasoning mind. But if our nervous system has learned a program for dealing with fear, we survive and restore ourselves to our full mental capacity in a short time.</p>

<p>The amygdala in our brain’s limbic system holds on to memories of danger and threat. It does not, however, distinguish past from present. To arouse our fight, flight, or freeze reaction immediately, we have to feel a threat as happening here and now, which mindfulness helps us with.</p>
<p>In addition, the amygdala does not distinguish levels of impact; every event is a catastrophe. This likewise produces a boost of adrenaline. All our years of development in adulthood, all our gains of common sense, make no difference now. Thus, today’s fears make us feel just as powerless as we were in childhood. We lose sight of our adult powers. They are available in our prefrontal cortex, but that part of our brain is offline when the amygdala is online.</p>

<p>The amygdala shuts down our thinking mind. We might say it reduces our I.Q. by 50 points! When things calm down, we think, “I should have said or done this….” But we literally could not have thought so clearly or acted so sanely because the limbic system had taken over.</p>
<p>No wonder we felt powerless. We don’t blame ourselves now. We understand that being human means our life story and all the detritus of the past continue to affect us.</p>

<p>We also know there are state-of-the-art ways to intervene using a program for dealing with fear. Research into neuroscience has shown that we do not have to be at the mercy of our limbic system. Our brains have plasticity. This means that we can reprogram our habitual neurological patterns. We can open new neural pathways in our brain so that when fear strikes, we can pause between stimulus and reaction.</p>

<p>This pause is freedom because, through it, choice is made possible rather than a slavish reflex. Any new ways of thinking or doing things can lead to new neural pathways. Now our brain has joined in our work of self-healing.</p>
<p>During the mindful pause, our prefrontal cortex can remind us that we are in the present: we are not victims of the past; we are not powerless children; we have alternatives and resources. Unfortunately, our automatic tendency to fall prey to the bully of fear does not vanish easily. Even with neural re-wiring, we may still feel afraid of what is not, in fact, dangerous. This is where we can have compassion for ourselves and make our way through as best we can. We can then face our fears without defense or resistance. Gradually, we can become stronger.</p>

<p>This is sure to happen if we keep returning to the spiritual practice of non-violent love. This is how we become both defense-<em>less </em>and resource-<em>full,</em> the winning combination for freedom from the grip of fear. The more you love, the less you fear. You will then find yourself changing in many ways: less fear, more love, less ego territoriality, more generosity, less self-seeking, more compassion, and most of all, more joy at noticing that doors are opening without having to push.</p>


<p><strong>Adapted from </strong><em><strong>When Love Meets Fear</strong></em><strong> (Paulist Press) by David Richo.</strong></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/finding-the-way/202602/the-fearful-brain" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/finding-the-way/202602/the-fearful-brain</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/finding-the-way/202602/the-fearful-brain</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[David Richo Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-liza-summer-6382725.jpg?itok=cdnkxYWN" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Toxic Ties and the Downside of Connections]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/alex-danvers_0.png.jpg?itok=FgO0V7Ge" alt="Alexander Danvers Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Social Life</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Toxic Ties and the Downside of Connections</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How do the difficult people in your life affect your biology?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Nearly 30% of people have at least one "hassler" in their social network who makes life difficult.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Each hassler is linked to a 1.5% faster pace of biological aging and roughly 9 months of extra biological age.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Family hasslers, like parents, siblings, or children, leave the deepest biological imprint.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Women, people in poorer health, and those with adverse childhood experiences are more likely to have hasslers.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Hasslers%20are%20aging%20you.jpg?itok=ngXSWo0-" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" alt="New research shows that negative social ties are associated with faster biological aging." title="Alex Green / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">New research shows that negative social ties are associated with faster biological aging.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Alex Green / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Your Body Keeps the Score... of Bad Relationships</h2>
<p>Most of us know intuitively that difficult people are stressful. The coworker who constantly stirs up drama, the parent who turns every phone call into a guilt trip, the sibling who makes every family gathering tense—we feel the weight of these relationships. But a new study published in <em>PNAS</em> in February 2026 suggests the toll goes far deeper than feelings. It reaches all the way down to your DNA.</p>

<p>A team of researchers led by Byungkyu Lee (NYU) and Brea L. Perry (Indiana University) studied more than 2,300 adults in Indiana, ranging in age from 18 to 103. They collected saliva samples and used cutting-edge "epigenetic clocks"—tools that measure biological aging by reading chemical modifications on DNA—to assess how fast each person was aging at the molecular level. They also mapped out each participant's social network in unusual detail, asking not just who supports them but also who hassles them.</p>

<p>The results were striking. Each additional person in a subject's network who created stress in their life (what the researchers called a "hassler") was associated with 1.5 percent faster biological aging each year. Each hassler was also associated with being about 9 months older, biologically speaking, than peers of the same chronological age. To put that in context, the researchers compared the hassler effect to smoking (one of the best-known accelerants of aging) and found it corresponded to about 13–17 percent of smoking's impact on the same biological measures. That's not trivial, especially because these effects compound over decades.</p>

<p>The study also found that the effects of difficult people extend far beyond epigenetics. People with more hasslers reported higher rates of depression and anxiety, worse self-rated health, higher BMI, greater waist-to-hip ratios, and elevated inflammation scores. Notably, the number of hasslers had no association with adult height—a stable trait that shouldn't change due to social stress—which gave the researchers added confidence that they were observing real biological effects rather than statistical noise.</p>

<h2>Not All Hasslers Are Created Equal</h2>
<p>Perhaps the study's most provocative finding concerns <em>which</em> hasslers matter most. The researchers broke down their results by relationship type—spouse, family (kin), and non-family (nonkin)—and found a clear hierarchy.</p>
<p>Family hasslers were the strongest and most consistent predictors of accelerated aging. Having a parent, sibling, or child who regularly makes your life difficult was robustly linked to both faster aging rates and greater cumulative biological age. The researchers explain this with an elegant insight about network structure: Kin hasslers tend to be embedded in your life in ways that make them nearly impossible to avoid. You can't easily quit your family the way you might distance yourself from a difficult coworker. These relationships carry deep obligations and emotional weight, and when they turn sour, there's often no escape valve.</p>

<p>Nonkin hasslers (coworkers, roommates, acquaintances) also contributed to cumulative aging, though their effects were weaker. What's remarkable is that even these comparatively peripheral, weak-tie relationships left a detectable biological mark.</p>
<p>The biggest surprise was spousal hasslers. Despite decades of research highlighting marital conflict as a driver of health decline, spouses who were identified as hasslers showed no significant association with accelerated aging. The authors suggest this reflects the deeply ambivalent nature of marriage: A hassling spouse is also, in most cases, a source of companionship, support, and shared daily life. That mix of positive and negative may create a buffer that simply doesn't exist in other family relationships, where the strain is less likely to be offset by the same intensity of support.</p>

<h2>What This Means for You and for How We Think About Loneliness</h2>
<p>In recent years, loneliness and social isolation have dominated the conversation about relationships and health. The U.S. Surgeon General declared loneliness an epidemic in 2023, and for good reason: The data on isolation and mortality are alarming. But this new study complicates that narrative in an important way. It suggests that it's not just the <em>absence</em> of relationships that harms us—the <em>presence</em> of bad ones is an independent risk factor. Having a large social network doesn't necessarily protect you if that network includes people who chronically stress you out.</p>

<p>The study also reveals a troubling pattern of inequality. Hassler exposure isn't random. Women, daily smokers, people with worse health, and those who experienced more adversity in childhood are all significantly more likely to report hasslers in their lives. This creates a kind of double burden: The people already most vulnerable are also the ones most likely to be surrounded by difficult relationships, which in turn may accelerate their decline. The researchers describe this as a form of "relational inequality," a mechanism through which social disadvantage reproduces itself.</p>

<p>So what can you do with this information? A few practical thoughts emerge. First, it's worth taking an honest inventory of the relationships in your life and recognizing which ones are sources of chronic stress rather than occasional friction. The study deliberately excluded occasional hassling from its definition: Everyone argues sometimes, and that's normal. What matters is the persistent, frequent pattern.</p>



  


<p>Second, the finding about kin hasslers underscores the importance of setting boundaries with family, even when those relationships feel obligatory. You may not be able to cut ties, but you can limit exposure and seek support in managing those interactions. Third, the spouse finding is actually encouraging: It suggests that relationships where conflict coexists with genuine closeness and support may not carry the same biological cost.</p>

<p>Finally, this research is a reminder that promoting healthy aging isn't just about diet, exercise, and medical care. The social environment, including the people who make your life harder, shapes your biology in ways we're only beginning to measure. Addressing the "dark side" of social networks may be just as important as combating loneliness in the effort to help people age well.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/how-do-you-know/202602/toxic-ties-and-the-downside-of-connections" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/how-do-you-know/202602/toxic-ties-and-the-downside-of-connections</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/how-do-you-know/202602/toxic-ties-and-the-downside-of-connections</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Alexander Danvers Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-alex-green-5700201.jpg?itok=cNHNb0AI" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Identity Fatigue]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/nicholas-balaisis.jpg?itok=ZZmEqlTk" alt="Nicholas Balaisis Ph.D., RP" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Identity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Identity Fatigue</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Are you tired of playing yourself?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Human beings often see themselves in fixed identity-terms.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A strong identity helps developmentally but can be arduous to maintain over time.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Understanding where someone was "excluded" can help them trace their identity roots.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-mastercowley-920036.jpg?itok=cecYF-eu" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="Nathan Cowley / Pexels" alt="Nathan Cowley / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Nathan Cowley / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Freud says, “Whatever you say you are, you are not.” Adam Phillips says that identity is a “self-cure for a feeling of exclusion” and puts us forever in a position to defend that identity.</p>
<p>Identity is thus false to begin with, and on top of that, takes effort and will to manage and reproduce. Both Freud and Phillips seem to say: What’s the point?</p>

<p>How can we metabolize or digest these pronouncements (or warnings?) in a culture that seems synonymous with the branded self, or the profilicity of our brand?</p>
<p>In a mental health context, isn’t this a recipe for rampant confusion—doesn’t it seem that a stable sense of self equates with a stronger ego, better choice of mate, career, and overall sense of direction? If we go to therapy, instead of this, isn’t what we’re in for, after all, a better sense of who we are, a richer sense of our real or true identity?</p>

<h2>The Development of Identity</h2>
<p>Our identity develops, as Phillips argues, out of an experience of exclusion, of being left out. In the Freudian story, we are left out of our parents’ lives in many ways as children. We cannot be as close to our parents as we wish. While loving parents may tuck us in every night and transport us to all activities, they inevitably shut us out by going to bed without us. This is a kind of “leaving out” that marks our first major exclusion—we are excluded from our parents’ intimate lives. To a child, this feels like a failure, and the first of others. Our parents will inevitably fail us in some way. (And this is OK.)</p>

<p>This is the first identity crisis. If we cannot be everything in the eyes of Mom or Dad, who are we then? What might gain their attention, or what might fill the lack of their attention to us?</p>
<p>This can take any number of routes. We may take up an interest in sports, or academics, or drugs, or pornography, or voyeurism. These interests may produce certain kinds of attention that come to reflect who we are (the looking glass theory). We see that winning swim races gets certain kinds of attention from others: interest, envy, and admiration. It feels good, so we lean into that identity. We proudly reflect back to others what we receive from them.</p>

<p>Or, conversely, we take up an interest in something more antisocial like pornography. Our parents may criticize us for this, or we may read online that this is bad for our self-esteem or future love lives. This can produce a kind of perverse or masochistic pleasure, a dark identity. It can feel good to be at the margins, to be othered. We are doubly excluded and can take pleasure in this or convert this exclusion into an identity like an <em>incel</em>.</p>

<h2>Post-Adolescence and the Second Identity Crisis</h2>
<p>At some point, this preferred identity becomes exhausted or outdated. We outgrow an attachment to sports or pornography and find ourselves drawn to other interests, other people. We find that these former identities no longer hold currency in new circles we wish to join.</p>

<p>Or the identity itself demands too much work to produce and reproduce. We become too identifiable to ourselves. We can feel like we are performing a version of ourselves, like we have been typecast by central casting. We tell the same stories, the same jokes, and perform the same party tricks or stunts.</p>

<p>Our version of ourselves has become too narrow, and this narrowness has limited our social roles and spheres.</p>
<p>Sometimes this appears as a crisis of sorts: a mid- or quarter-life crisis. A shift in vocation or partners may be in order. We may sever ourselves from old friends, relocate, or go “no contact” with certain members of the family. We may feel like giving up, and it can feel like exhaustion or even depression. But what might be in need of giving up is only the performed version of ourselves that has become obsolete. We may discover new vitality or energy on the other side of such a dissolution. It wasn’t that we were tired of life, but we were just tired of <em>that life</em>.</p>

<p>Activating a dormant or undiscovered part of ourselves can be very enlivening and energizing. But it also takes risks and courage.</p>
<p>Perhaps we need a new language to present ourselves that is not rooted in a notion of identity. Identity is inescapable, but so is its dissolution and dismantling.</p>
<p>What can we gain if we risk letting go of an earlier version of ourselves? What can we lose if we cling to a preferred and narrow version?</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-devices-our-selves/202602/identity-fatigue" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-devices-our-selves/202602/identity-fatigue</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/our-devices-our-selves/202602/identity-fatigue</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicholas Balaisis Ph.D., RP]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-mastercowley-920036.jpg?itok=thByXX27" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>