<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 20:38:09 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 20:38:09 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Understanding Scrupulosity]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/Sebastien%20Montel.png.jpg?itok=B3CtLucR" alt="Sebastien Montel" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">OCD</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Understanding Scrupulosity</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Recognizing and addressing moral obsessions.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Scrupulosity is characterized by persistent and excessive concerns about moral or religious correctness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Scrupulosity can be effectively managed with a combination of therapeutic approaches.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Understanding scrupulosity can help individuals who are affected find treatment and peace of mind.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/PRO-The%20Weight%20of%20Life-May%2005%202025_0.jpeg.jpg?itok=CDbZaiVv" width="320" height="382" data-insert-type="image" alt="The weight of life (2025)" title="Sebastien Montel"></div>
<div class="caption">The weight of life (2025)</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Sebastien Montel</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>What is scrupulosity? </p>
<p><em>Scrupulus</em> is the Latin word for "a small sharp stone" or "a tiny pebble," often used to describe a sharp stone in a sandal that caused constant, persistent discomfort. Cicero and other Romans used <em>scrupulus</em> metaphorically to describe a source of anxiety or a "pricking of the conscience," likening a moral dilemma to a small stone in one’s shoe that bothers you until it is removed. </p>

<p>Scrupulosity is now known as a form of obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) characterized by persistent and excessive concerns about moral or religious correctness. Individuals with scrupulosity often experience intrusive thoughts about whether their actions, intentions, or beliefs are ethical or spiritually appropriate, leading to significant distress and anxiety.</p>

<h2>What do we know about people with scrupulosity?</h2>
<p>Epidemiological studies suggest that scrupulosity is relatively uncommon compared to other OCD subtypes, but it can significantly impact individuals within religious communities or those with strong moral convictions. Scrupulosity affects 1 in 20 of Western OCD sufferers; in some cultures, more than half of OCD sufferers have some sort of religious obsessions.<sup>1</sup></p>

<p>While precise prevalence rates are difficult to determine due to underreporting and varying diagnostic criteria, research indicates that scrupulosity may affect both adolescents and adults, often emerging during late childhood or early adolescence.</p>
<p>Scrupulosity appears across diverse cultures and faith traditions, though its expression and frequency may be influenced by cultural, religious, and societal factors. It can affect people in any tradition, but faiths with emphasis on sin, confession, strict rules, or personal responsibility breed ground for obsessive religious doubt and excessive guilt.</p>

<p>There is no evidence to suggest a gender predilection, and the condition tends to follow the chronic course typical of OCD.</p>
<p>Scrupulosity is commonly seen in people with strong religious backgrounds or those with obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD), but it can impact anyone who is prone to anxiety about ethical or spiritual matters.</p>

<p>Scrupulosity is associated with more severe symptoms of depression and anxiety, as well as a higher likelihood of obsessive compulsive personality disorder (OCPD; a personality disorder characterized by rigidity, perfectionism, hyper-control, and over-focus on details) and schizotypal personality disorder (SPD; a personality disorder characterized by magical thinking, strange beliefs, unusual perceptual experiences, and interpersonal discomfort and suspiciousness).<sup>2, 3</sup></p>

<h2>What are the symptoms of scrupulosity?</h2>
<p>Because of its religious focus, scrupulosity may be misunderstood as extreme piety rather than a mental health condition, particularly in religious and pediatric populations.</p>
<p>Symptoms of scrupulosity include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Excessive fear of committing moral or religious sins</li>
<li>Frequent doubts about whether one's actions or thoughts are sinful</li>
<li>Compulsive behaviors such as repetitive confession or seeking reassurance</li>
<li>Difficulty accepting forgiveness or feeling forgiven</li>
<li>Persistent anxiety related to religious or moral issues</li>
<li>Intrusive thoughts about blasphemy, morality, or violating religious rules</li>
<li>Avoidance of certain activities or situations for fear of sinning</li>
</ul>


<h2>What is the treatment for scrupulosity?</h2>
<p>Scrupulosity can be effectively managed with a combination of therapeutic approaches. Cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT), particularly exposure and response prevention (ERP), is the most widely recommended treatment. This therapy helps individuals confront their fears and anxieties without engaging in compulsive behaviors or seeking reassurance. In some cases, medication such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) may be prescribed to help manage symptoms. </p>

<p>Consulting with a mental health professional experienced in treating OCD or scrupulosity is important to develop a personalized treatment plan. In addition, education about OCD and scrupulosity and collaboration with religious or spiritual advisors can be beneficial. Addressing guilt and anxiety through structured therapy, and learning to tolerate uncertainty are key components in helping individuals manage their symptoms and improve their quality of life.</p>



  


<h2>In conclusion</h2>
<p>Scrupulosity can be a challenging experience, often marked by persistent moral obsessions and a heightened sense of anxiety about right and wrong. Recognizing the signs early and addressing them with compassion and professional guidance is crucial. By understanding the nature of these moral obsessions and seeking appropriate support, individuals can find healthier ways to navigate their beliefs and regain peace of mind.</p>

<p><em>To find a therapist, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/recasting-reality/202602/understanding-scrupulosity" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/recasting-reality/202602/understanding-scrupulosity</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/recasting-reality/202602/understanding-scrupulosity</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sebastien Montel PhD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/IMG_1364_1.jpeg.jpg?itok=PVkwkPao" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Quintessential Secrets of Psychotherapy: Facing Evil]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/new-photo-.jpg?itok=-Vc-lmod" alt="Stephen A. Diamond Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Ethics and Morality</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Quintessential Secrets of Psychotherapy: Facing Evil</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Psychotherapy helps victims of evil confront trauma and rebuild meaning.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Confronting and coming to terms with the problem of evil is one of today's greatest psychological challenges.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It is useful for clinicians to acknowledge and address the reality of evil when working with trauma victims.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Forgiveness is possible only after accepting one's anger or rage about their traumatic encounter with evil.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2025-06/Broken_glass_001_0.jpg?itok=qFlYokxG" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" title="Violetbonmua / Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA-3.0" alt="Violetbonmua / Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA-3.0"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Violetbonmua / Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA-3.0</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>This post is part 2 of a series. See part 1 </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202508/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-trauma-of-evil"><em>here</em></a><em>. </em></p>
<p>Horrific calamities can cause painful and precarious states of mind, rattling our religious or spiritual faith to its foundation and engendering despair, despondency, desolation, and sometimes, even suicidality. It is therefore essential that psychotherapists are properly trained and prepared to address such trauma-induced existential crises.</p>

<h2>Recognizing the reality of evil</h2>
<p>The initial step toward attaining this state of readiness is to discern, recognize, identify, and acknowledge the existence of evil in ourselves, others, and the cosmos. To do so, we must reclaim and clarify our vision regarding the presence of evil in the world, so as not to fall prey to it too readily. We cannot afford to continue to close our eyes to the existential reality of evil, be it of human or natural origin. The existential trauma of evil, and the intense emotions it inevitably evokes, is not something we can simply forget, rationalize, erase, escape, or run away from, though this is precisely what most trauma victims tend initially to do in various ways.</p>

<h2>Psychotherapy after existential trauma</h2>
<p>In psychotherapy, victims of evil—and I intentionally employ the term <em>victim</em> to acknowledge and encourage clients or patients to admit to themselves their own victimhood and the fact that we may, in certain circumstances, be completely powerless to prevent evil from happening to ourselves or others—must learn to courageously face and accept their suffering and “negative” reactions to trauma. They must also adopt a more mature, realistic perception of existence and themselves: a reconstructed, sturdier, supportive, more flexible platform, worldview, or existential foundation upon which to stand in life, one that can help them tolerate and accept the tragic reality of existential evil and the intrinsic fragility and insecurity of human existence.</p>

<p>During the psychotherapy process, victims must be permitted and willing to learn from the existential crisis that the trauma of evil precipitates. Without this, there can be no true transformation or transcendence of trauma. </p>
<h2>Accepting powerlessness and rebuilding meaning</h2>
<p>Those victims without any conscious or unconscious culpability for what seemingly randomly happened to them must learn to accept, however humbling to the ego it may be, the existential fact that we have no power over and bear no responsibility for a multitude of things in life—that is, we are not personally responsible for every evil that befalls us or those around us—and to consciously integrate such insights into their new and modified perception of themselves, others, and existential reality. Ultimately, such a psychotherapy must encourage and cultivate a revised and expanded world-view or "myth" (May, 1991 ) of themselves, the world, and their place in it, one in which the patient can tolerate, accept and assimilate existence as it truly is, including the reality of evil, rather than distorting and denying (e.g., minimizing or sugarcoating) the tragic and traumatic human condition. </p>

<p>One advantage of choosing to perceive trauma as an encounter with evil is that it provides a means (but not necessarily the only way) of making meaningful what otherwise seems meaningless; making some sense of senselessness, which, as psychotherapists such as Jung, Frankl, and May point out, fulfills an archetypal, universal or existential human need for meaning, without which existence can be unbearable. </p>

<p>Some experience of evil in life is unavoidable. Each of us has been or will be touched by evil in some way or another. It is crucial that we discover constructive avenues to heal or recover from the trauma of evil. As I have elsewhere (1996) written regarding coming to terms with the trauma of evil: </p>

<blockquote><p>[Psychological and emotional] “healing” does not mean forgetting, for to become conscious is to remember and to know. Healing entails the mature acceptance of the traumatic facts of one’s emotional mortification, the causes and the consequences, as well as a resolute willingness to swallow the following bitter pill: We cannot change the past nor undo the wound ... We can, nonetheless, allow ourselves to feel our rage and grief ... We have the power to determine our attitude toward the past, [present, and future]. We may even—with some good fortune, time, and grace—find within ourselves the capacity to forgive those who we feel inflicted our agonizing injuries (Diamond, p. 286). </p>
</blockquote>

<h2>The role of forgiveness in trauma recovery</h2>
<p>While in some discussions of treating trauma in psychotherapy, there is a focus on forgiveness—for example, forgiving the perpetrator of the evil deed or God for permitting some horrific cosmic disaster—it is not generally seen as an essential component in most of today's trauma-informed therapy, which correctly cautions against encouraging or forcing the victim to forgive prematurely, if ever. </p>

<p>Before forgiveness even becomes possible, the traumatized psychotherapy patient must first be encouraged and permitted to acknowledge, experience, and express the intense, passionate, or <em>daimonic </em>(see May, 1969; Diamond, 1996)<em> </em>emotions stemming from their devastating existential encounter with evil, powerful feelings such as fear, anxiety, dread, terror, grief, sadness, and perhaps most challenging of all, their natural anger, rage or outrage: <em>In what kind of world could something awful like this have happened? And, why to me or to innocent others? What did I do to deserve such suffering? If there is some omniscient and omnipotent god or deity, how could he or she condone such terrible evil? And, if not, how can I continue to live meaningfully in an uncaring cosmos filled with evil, violence, hatred, and destructiveness? </em></p>



  


<p>Indeed,<em> </em>if and when forgiveness happens, it can take place only <em>after</em> the natural human response of anger, rage, or resentment and primitive talionic desire for retaliation, retribution, and revenge is consciously acknowledged, accepted, and psychologically assimilated. Ultimately, such radical forgiveness is never about denying the reality of evil in human nature and the world but rather recognizing and accepting evil as an inescapable element of the human and universal condition. And, maybe most importantly of all, acknowledging, accepting, and forgiving our own <em>daimonic </em>reactions to evil, particularly our resentment, anger, or rage. Only then will we truly be able to compassionately forgive the unforgivable.</p>

<p><em>This post is partially adapted from my chapter titled, "The Psychology and Psychotherapy of Evil: Encountering the Daimonic" in the </em>APA Handbook of Humanistic and Existential Psychology (Vol. 1).<em> </em></p>
<p><em>To find a therapist, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202506/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-facing-evil" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202506/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-facing-evil</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202506/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-facing-evil</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephen A. Diamond Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2025-06/Broken_glass_001_0.jpg?itok=FYnklJMX" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Reduce Risk of Physical Illness in People With ADHD]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-04/BigT%C2%A0images%3AAcademy%20of%20Medical%20Sciences.png.jpg?itok=2P_fCdYo" alt="BigT images/Academy of Medical Sciences" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">ADHD</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How to Reduce Risk of Physical Illness in People With ADHD</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Simple steps can protect long-term physical health alongside ADHD care.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">ADHD is associated with higher risk of serious conditions such as heart disease and diabetes.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Primary care, if adequately funded, is well-positioned to play a greater role in ADHD care.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Treating ADHD early while addressing its physical health risks is crucial.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is a neurodevelopmental condition characterised by impairments in attention as well as hyperactivity and impulsiveness that onsets early in development. Generally, ADHD is viewed as a condition that needs to be managed by specialist mental health services. Typically, the focus of most research and clinical interventions is on ADHD and any comorbid mental health or neurodevelopmental conditions.</p>

<h2>Physical health risks associated with ADHD</h2>
<p>What is often not fully appreciated is that ADHD is also associated with many physical health conditions and risks<sup>1</sup>. These include cardiovascular disease, diabetes (and other metabolic diseases), cancers (notably lung cancer), and neurological and allergic conditions, among others. ADHD is associated, for example, with many well-known cardiovascular risks that are modifiable.<sup>2,3 </sup>These include obesity, cigarette smoking, and high blood pressure. If these risks are not addressed or treated, they can lead to ischemic heart disease (heart attacks), stroke, and premature death.</p>

<p>Many of the health risks that accompany ADHD are modifiable. Yet for most health care systems, physical and mental health services are entirely separated. How often does an individual with ADHD have their physical health carefully monitored and managed? Are modifiable physical health risks dealt with early on? Are those with ADHD or a mental health condition who also have severe obesity considered as priority candidates for new anti-obesity medication? An important barrier to integrating physical health care with ADHD management is that clinicians who assess and treat ADHD may not be equipped to assess and treat physical ill-health and risks.</p>

<p>Premature mortality is now a recognised risk associated with ADHD. These findings are deeply concerning. Although some of these early deaths are due to suicide and accidents, among older individuals, premature death is explained by physical ill-health. Several large studies from across the world have highlighted an association between ADHD and premature mortality.<sup>4,5</sup> For example, a recent UK study based on primary care records observed that people with ADHD have a shortened life expectancy of seven to nine years.<sup>6</sup></p>

<h2>Improving ADHD care through integrated services</h2>
<p>I believe we can address these inequities. First, primary care is the one service that not only provides long-term healthcare, but also has skills in physical and mental health. So, if primary care staff are adequately supported, trained, and funded, they are well-positioned to take on a broader long-term role in ADHD care that encompasses physical health. For more complex ADHD, the primary care role will need to be integrated with specialist care. This approach could lead to more person-centric, joined-up service provision that tackles physical health as well as ADHD and mental health. An increased role for primary care was highlighted as a recommendation in the recent <a href="https://www.england.nhs.uk/publication/report-of-the-independent-adhd-taskforce/">NHS England independent ADHD Taskforce</a>, and many countries (e.g., Australia) are training up primary care physicians to take on many aspects of ADHD health care.</p>

<p>Second, the management of physical health and reduction of known and modifiable physical health risk factors (e.g., high blood pressure) needs to be a recognised priority for those with ADHD.</p>
<p>Third, there is evidence from several quasi-experimental and one trial emulation study<sup>7</sup> that ADHD medication treatment reduces some health risks (e.g., substance misuse) and mortality. Thus, a central priority is that ADHD is adequately treated. Just as diabetes is carefully managed to avoid adverse outcomes, similar standards need to apply to ADHD.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>For service and historical reasons, physical health across mental health and neurodevelopmental conditions, including ADHD, has been neglected. Many of the current inequities in terms of ADHD, physical ill-health, and premature mortality are amenable to change.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/youth-adhd-and-youth-mental-health/202602/how-to-reduce-risk-of-physical-illness-in-people" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/youth-adhd-and-youth-mental-health/202602/how-to-reduce-risk-of-physical-illness-in-people</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/youth-adhd-and-youth-mental-health/202602/how-to-reduce-risk-of-physical-illness-in-people</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Anita Thapar, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-chuck-2383750.jpg?itok=dYT5xTbs" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Take a Walk, Think Creatively]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/sally_augustin.jpg?itok=egXbhDEg" alt="Sally Augustin Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Creativity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Take a Walk, Think Creatively</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Need a creative solution? Get a move on.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">For years, writers have understood that walking gets their creative juices flowing.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Current research shows walking supports creative thinking and idea generation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Moderate-paced walking produces benefits whether you do it indoors or outdoors.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>A pleasant stroll keeps our waistline trim and our brain in tip-top shape as well.</p>
<p>Researcher <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2024-26043-001">Christian Rominger</a> and teammates determined that walking is linked to more creative verbal thinking, confirming the results of a study done 10 years earlier by <a href="https://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/xlm-a0036577.pdf">Oppezzo and Schwartz</a>, who tied moving to creativity. This is unlikely to surprise anyone who is a fan of author biographies—writers regularly report that they walk to get their creative juices flowing, perhaps to overcome problems with plot or character.</p>

<h2>Walking and creative performance</h2>
<p>The best sorts of walks are ones that proceed at a pace that’s comfortable for the walker. The work by the Oppezzo and Rominger teams also makes it clear that walks don’t have to be outdoors to boost our creative performance—even a stroll on a treadmill can do the trick—although the idea of strolling across a meadow or a moor does have a certain appeal.</p>

<p>And why shouldn’t it? Being outside, in nature, can be mentally refreshing, and experiencing nature can give our mental performance an extra boost—but the key finding in the two studies noted below is that walking in itself has a powerful effect on what goes on in our minds. These effects continue after a walk comes to an end, whether we are back at our desk or in the armchair where we write.</p>

<h2>Making walking part of your routine</h2>
<p>The lesson: If creativity is important to you, make sure you have plenty of opportunities to walk. If walking outdoors isn't agreeable to you for one reason or another, add a treadmill to your life. If you’re designing or building a home or a workplace, add an inside walking loop around the core of your building—you’ll be able to walk in any weather, the heat, the cold, or even rain.</p>

<p>Landscape your yard, if you have one, using curving paths and pleasant destinations, such as bird feeders (if you like bird watching) or patches of your favorite plants, which may or may not have sprouted, to encourage yourself to stroll onward.</p>
<p>Although we’re focused on creative thinking, all the calories you burn while walking may result in a physique that you’re proud of, one that also boosts your self-esteem. As your self-esteem is elevated, you’ll also be less likely to be distracted by pesky negative thoughts about yourself as you work towards creative solutions.</p>

<p>When you’re trying to resolve a thorny issue, take a walk and think creatively.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/people-places-and-things/202602/take-a-walk-think-creatively" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/people-places-and-things/202602/take-a-walk-think-creatively</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/people-places-and-things/202602/take-a-walk-think-creatively</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sally Augustin Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-pripicart-631986.jpg?itok=9PcvkLOg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>