<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 14:52:12 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 14:52:12 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Surprising Connection Between Creativity and Coffee]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/anthony_fredericks.jpg?itok=re2IR4DV" alt="Anthony D. Fredericks Ed.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Creativity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Surprising Connection Between Creativity and Coffee</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Does drinking coffee stimulate your creativity?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Drinking coffee is a universal habit; but also a habit with misconceptions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Coffee is often viewed as a stimulant for innovation and imagination.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Current research suggests several benefits of caffeine.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Like most readers, I start my day with a tall cup of coffee (or three). My mind awakens, and I’m ready to tackle several projects: writing a new book chapter, crafting a commissioned article, or outlining the initial drafts of this blog. I’m on full alert, I’m stimulated, and I’m engaged. My fingers fly across the keyboard, caffeine is surging through my system, and it’s “full steam ahead!”</p>

<p>But wait a minute! Has my creativity, has your creativity, been enhanced to any significant degree by that jolt of java? </p>
<p><strong>What the Research Says</strong></p>
<p>For most people, a cup of coffee is a daily ritual (current figures show that people around the world drink a staggering 140,625,000 gallons of coffee globally each day). It is not only a ritual; it is a habit. As a habit, we often consider it a necessary part of the creative process, a sensory trigger for generating dynamic ideas or innovative products. We know that brewing, smelling, and tasting coffee, quite often, increases our mental alertness by blocking adenosine (a natural body chemical, one that increases during the day, often leading to sleepiness) receptors in the brain. As a result, coffee sustains our attention, improves our reaction time, and stimulates our working memory.</p>

<p>Although it has been proven to elevate our mood and reduce mental fatigue, coffee’s effect on our creative inclinations is a little more complicated.</p>
<p>A study out of the University of Arkansas involved 88 adults, some of whom were given 200 mg of caffeine, others a placebo. The participants were then randomly assigned to one of two groups: one focused on convergent thinking and problem-solving tasks, and the other on divergent thinking and idea-generation tasks. The researchers noted that caffeine enhanced convergent, problem-solving abilities. That is, participants were able to solve more set tasks after caffeine than after a placebo. In contrast, they also noted that caffeine did not (emphasis mine) significantly influence divergent thinking or the ability to create novel ideas or innovative concepts. They concluded that caffeine seems to help with convergent problem-solving (the search for single correct answers). However, it had little to no impact on divergent, out-of-the-ordinary, or innovative ideas. In short, it affects one type of creative thinking, but not another.</p>

<p>A 2020 report in <em>Science Daily</em> summarized the preceding research, noting that “caffeine increases the ability to focus and problem solve, but it doesn’t stimulate creativity. In addition to the results on creativity, caffeine did not significantly affect working memory, but test subjects who took it did report being less sad.”</p>

<p>An additional review of the University of Arkansas research in <em>Sci News</em> noted, “Caffeine is the most widely consumed psychotropic drug in the world, with numerous studies documenting the effects of caffeine on people’s alertness, vigilance, mood, concentration, and attentional focus.” Also included was this quote, “While the cognitive benefits of caffeine – increased alertness, improved vigilance, enhanced focus and improved motor performance—are well established, the stimulant’s effect on creativity is less known.” Suffice it to say, our coffee habit has some conjectured benefits, others more scientific.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Coffee%20-%202.jpg?itok=btYmm7v-" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="stokpic/Pixabay" alt="stokpic/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: stokpic/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Implications</strong></p>
<p>While additional research is warranted to validate the unique relationship between creativity and coffee, the following can be inferred from the currently available data.</p>
<ol>
<li>Drinking coffee to increase or stimulate our divergent creativity— generating novel or original ideas—may not be as effective as current beliefs suggest.</li>
<li>Coffee does seem to have a positive influence on our desire to solve convergent thinking problems by organizing, selecting, refining, tightening, and improving ideas. It is less effective in sparking original ideas.</li>
<li>Coffee is positively correlated with an elevated mood and reducing mental fatigue. This may be linked to higher levels of cognitive flexibility, thus indirectly supporting some level of creative expression.</li>
<li>Caffeine has been shown to improve our working memory, reaction time, and attention—all necessary elements of the thinking process and intellectual production.</li>
<li>There is evidence to suggest that too many cups of coffee can amplify our anxiety levels, reduce our cognitive flexibility, and limit our attentional focus—all factors associated with the generation of innovative ideas.</li>
<li>Our daily ritual of brewing a pot of coffee, experiencing its aroma, and tasting its savory bitterness may be a “creativity generator”—an emotional stimulant signaling a time to enter at least one phase of the creative process.</li>
</ol>

<p>Bottom line: Keep up the coffee habit, but there’s a little more work necessary to reach your full creative potential.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/creative-insights/202602/the-surprising-connection-between-creativity-and-coffee" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/creative-insights/202602/the-surprising-connection-between-creativity-and-coffee</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/creative-insights/202602/the-surprising-connection-between-creativity-and-coffee</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Anthony D. Fredericks Ed.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Coffee%20-%201.jpg?itok=wShuyrzg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Clinician's Perspective on the Polyvagal Controversy]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-07/choice_10-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=vxZMQmuG" alt="Annie Chen MA, LMFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Vagus Nerve</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">A Clinician's Perspective on the Polyvagal Controversy</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Why I’m not ready to abandon the polyvagal theory.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Neurophysiologists claim core premises are incorrect in polyvagal theory.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Porges responds that critics misunderstand what the theory actually claims.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Further research and discussion is needed to settle the debate.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">There is an interesting controversy resurfacing in the trauma psychology community around Stephen Porges’ polyvagal theory (PVT). The debate has been going on for years, but a recently published paper has brought it back into focus.</p>
<p dir="ltr">I'm writing this for clinicians, particularly those of us who have used PVT as a lens in our work and are now wondering what to make of the renewed push from neuroscientists to reject PVT. What does this debate mean for those of us who practice?</p>

<p dir="ltr">PVT was always ambitious. It was an attempt to weave together evolutionary biology, neurophysiology, observable behavior, and clinical wisdom into an arc about how our nervous system states drive our behavior in the world and with one another. PVT was a bold contribution in a scientific arena where entire careers can be devoted to testing a single mechanism to increasing degrees of confidence. </p>

<p dir="ltr">For many clinicians, PVT has been meaningful.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Neurophysiologist Paul Grossman, along with 38 researchers, recently published a critique outlining scientific objections to some of PVT’s proposed neuroanatomical mechanisms. They conclude that PVT’s core neurophysiology claims do not hold up under scrutiny; therefore, it’s not a viable psychological theory and should not be taught as such. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Porges has formally responded. He welcomes empirical challenges and criticism of his theory, but he argues that the published criticism is so full of straw man arguments and misrepresentations of PVT that the authors undermine their ability to legitimately critique the theory. </p>
<p dir="ltr">As far as I know, Grossman et al. have not responded to the rebuttal.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The debate has reached an impasse. Both sides believe rigorous measurement is important, but don’t agree on which measurement strategies would constitute a real test of PVT’s claims. Grossman continues to critique based on what he believes are narrative overreaches and inaccuracies of anatomy, while Porges tries to get across that an accurate read of the theory doesn't rely on such claims.</p>

<h2>Two Questions</h2>
<p dir="ltr">As this discussion continues to develop, and I hope it does in meaningful ways, I am not ready to abandon PVT. And this isn’t due to blind loyalty or sticking my head in the sand. I have two questions.</p>
<p dir="ltr">First, is the critiquing side giving PVT a fair shake? Despite Grossman et al.'s confident declaration that PVT is "untenable," I’m not convinced they have proven their case. A more congruent back-and-forth between these two sides is warranted, and one that addresses Porges’ concern about theory misrepresentation. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">Second, what exactly is being called into question when it comes to PVT’s clinical insights? PVT’s value has been orienting my attention toward certain aspects of behavior and relationship and the learning and clarity that has ensued in my clinical work as a result. PVT has been like a map that has guided me competently through complex terrain. </p>


<p dir="ltr">PVT served as a useful and reliable guide in my work. It led me, time and time again, to the realization that people in their worst moments aren’t irrational; they’re missing safety and therefore dysregulated. It taught me to think deeply about dysregulation within a relational field. It gave language to patterns I was already seeing, and that language expanded my capacity to intervene.</p>

<p dir="ltr">If it turns out that the map was wrong all along, then it might take a while for us to actually tease out what the failings of the map were and what consequence it has on clinical understanding. If some street names weren’t accurately labeled, it might not change the map much at all. But if the map was referring to a flat earth and the earth is actually not flat, then I’ll want to know what the alternative is. </p>



  


<h2>Clinical "Knowing"</h2>
<p dir="ltr">What also belongs in this discussion is the idea that clinical “knowing” comes from a different place than experimental science. Clinicians look to neuroscience to illuminate what we see in the work we do. We seek language and biology that help us make sense of what we observe in the therapy room. But we are not looking to neurons and synapses to build our understanding of people and behavior.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Our “knowing” comes from practice. </p>
<p dir="ltr">For example, clinicians know trauma. Not in the way you can know about T-cell activation or nerve binding. But in the way you know a language you’ve spoken for 17 years. I have spent that long sitting across from people studying their nervous systems shifting in real time. I’ve watched their breath change, their pupils dilate and open, and their posture collapse or expand.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">When I hear those coming from the hard science perspective that trauma is not well understood, I get the need to speak from humility and scientific precision. But as a clinician, I bristle. My colleagues with decades more experience than I have will tell you the same: We understand it well enough to help people heal. We wouldn’t mind coming across a perfectly mapped neural circuitry, but we are not waiting on one to do the work.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Clinical knowledge is experiential and iterative. We employ pattern recognition built over thousands of human encounters, refined over time, and cross-referenced within the community of practitioners. It isn’t precisely scientific, but it is valid knowledge.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That said, neuroscience frameworks are but one input into our understanding of people and our world. It can be a powerful one if it can help us organize reality and shape our understanding of what is or isn’t possible. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Clinicians also choose to use a variety of frameworks irrespective of scientific rigor. Some use the chakra system. Others use cognitive behavioral therapy. I would argue that an appropriate framework isn’t one that is scientifically proven; it’s one that a clinician can use to sharpen their skill, attune to their client, and intervene effectively.</p>

<p dir="ltr">For me, PVT is one such useful framework, and it remains so. </p>
<p dir="ltr">However, I caution against clinicians claiming authority in areas where we aren't experts. When I wrote<a href="https://www.anniechen.net/iwtc"> <em>I Want to Connect</em></a>, which draws in part from PVT, I intentionally avoided the dorsal vagal and ventral vagal terminology. It did not feel authentic for me to speak as though I were a neurophysiologist. I have never looked at a nerve through a microscope. My authority comes from clinical experience. Instead, I used more everyday language that refers to these concepts.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Hopefully, PVT will continue to be challenged, narrowed, or rejected. That is how science works. And this will evolve my clinical perspectives when it comes to stress, trauma, and social behavior. </p>
<p dir="ltr">But I’m not convinced that the current generation of criticisms has engaged the discussion of PVT accurately enough to move the needle. Because of this, and because PVT continues to add value to my clinical work, I am grateful for and will continue to use it.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/well-connected/202602/a-clinicians-perspective-on-the-polyvagal-controversy" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/well-connected/202602/a-clinicians-perspective-on-the-polyvagal-controversy</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/well-connected/202602/a-clinicians-perspective-on-the-polyvagal-controversy</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Annie Chen MA, LMFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-karola-g2-5836.jpg?h=34cd8c1a&amp;itok=lyAL0Yk5" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Can Acceptance and Commitment Therapy Help With OCD?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/Jennifer%20Rollin%20%283%29.png.jpg?itok=0Emr24Dp" alt="Jennifer Rollin MSW, LCSW-C" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">OCD</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Can Acceptance and Commitment Therapy Help With OCD?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The importance of psychological flexibility and cognitive defusion.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Exposure and response is largely seen as the gold standard when it comes to the treatment of OCD.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Acceptance and commitment therapy helps individuals with OCD.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Further, acceptance and commitment therapy talks about working to take values based action.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Overall, ACT showed moderate improvements in symptom reduction in reducing OCD symptoms.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">OCD is an exhausting mental illness that is characterized by intrusive thoughts often followed by physical and/or mental compulsions. Some individuals who are struggling may rationally understand that their fears are illogical, yet feel completely controlled by them. Fighting and engaging with the intrusive thoughts often backfires. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Exposure and response is largely seen as the gold standard when it comes to the treatment of <a href="https://www.theeatingdisordercenter.com/therapy-for-ocd.html">OCD</a>, however dropout rates can be real barriers when it comes to treatment. Enter acceptance and commitment therapy as a great adjunctive treatment for ERP. Acceptance and commitment therapy helps individuals with OCD change their relationship to their intrusive thoughts and anxiety.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Rather than a focus on eliminating intrusive thoughts, acceptance and commitment therapy has a lens of changing our <a href="https://agroomes.substack.com/p/disengaging-from-unhelpful-thoughts">relationship to unhelpful thinking</a>. One of the core treatment aims of acceptance and commitment therapy is psychological flexibility. Additionally, acceptance and commitment therapy focuses on <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37863583/">cognitive defusion</a> strategies (Assaz et al., 2023). Some cognitive defusion strategies include the following:</p>

<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Creating separation between yourself and the thought by telling yourself “I am having the thought that.”</li>
<li dir="ltr">Singing the thought to the tune of a popular song-this helps people to recognize that a thought is simply words and sounds, not something that you necessarily need to act on or pay attention to.</li>
<li dir="ltr">Rather than asking yourself ‘is the thought true?’ asking yourself ‘is the thought helpful, in terms of getting me in the direction of the life that I want to lead?”</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">Dr. Amber Groomes has weighed in on strategies for disengaging from unhelpful thoughts. Dr. Groomes writes that, “Defusion takes a different perspective. From a defused state, I might start by just noticing “I am having the thought that ‘I am going to look like a loser’ and another thought that ‘everyone will be judging me.’ These thoughts make me feel anxious.”</p>

<p dir="ltr">Dr. Groomes continues. “I may recall that I often have these thoughts before social situations, and usually, everything goes just fine. I no longer have an “awkwardness” problem. I have a thought problem. Thankfully, it is only a problem if I take the thought seriously” (Groomes, 2024).</p>
<p dir="ltr">Further, acceptance and commitment therapy talks about working to take values based action even when anxiety or intrusive thoughts are present. Act utilizes a variety of metaphors that can be helpful when it comes to practicing this. In this metaphor, we imagine that someone’s life is a bus and that some of the passengers on the bus are loud and unruly (the OCD thoughts and urges). In OCD, the passengers may yell things like ‘you didn’t wash your hands enough,’ or ‘how can you be sure that you really love your partner?’ When these passengers start screaming, someone with <a href="https://www.theeatingdisordercenter.com/therapy-for-ocd.html">OCD</a> might feel the urge to turn around and argue with them or pull over. ACT teaches that we can continue to steer the bus in the direction of our values, even if the passengers are on the bus making noise. Individuals with OCD can work to simply notice them, let them be there, and keep their hands on the steering wheel (Hayes, Strosahl &amp; Wilson, 1999; Hayes et al., 2006).</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>New evidence: a meta-analysis </strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">A 2026 meta-analysis looked at ACT for OCD. Researchers examined nine randomized control trials, which compared ACT to controls-that included no treatment and treatments like pharmacotherapy (Loureiro et al., 2026).. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Key findings from this study included:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Overall, ACT showed moderate improvements in symptom reduction in reducing OCD symptoms when compared to controls-that included medication-only approaches.</li>
<li dir="ltr">When compared to other psychotherapies, no significant differences emerged in symptom improvement-meaning ACT held its own against standard talk therapies.</li>
<li dir="ltr">Limitations remain and further research needs to be conducted with additional RCTs.</li>
</ul>


<p dir="ltr"><strong>What does this mean for clinical practice?</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Exposure and response prevention is still the gold standard for the treatment of OCD. However, acceptance and commitment therapy can be a meaningful adjunctive treatment that may serve to improve treatment outcomes, reduce dropout rates, increase psychological flexibility, and provide additional tools for those who are looking to regain freedom from OCD’s grip. </p>

<p dir="ltr">In my work as a therapist in private practice, I’ve seen how combining ERP with ACT-informed strategies can help clients navigate OCD more effectively. It’s validating to see research reflecting what many clinicians observe in practice.</p>
<p dir="ltr">:</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/can-acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-help-with-ocd" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/can-acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-help-with-ocd</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindful-musings/202602/can-acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-help-with-ocd</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jennifer Rollin MSW, LCSW-C]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/benjamin-voros-69mcb1K5dWg-unsplash.jpeg.jpg?itok=T2EmLUUB" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Coping With Our ‘Bad’ Emotions Isn’t Easy]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Glenn-Altschuler.jpg?itok=gBo2fyvc" alt="Glenn C. Altschuler Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Emotion Regulation</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Coping With Our ‘Bad’ Emotions Isn’t Easy</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Are dark emotions inherently bad?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p><em>This post is a review of </em>Hard Feelings: Finding the Wisdom in Our Darkest Emotions. <em>By Daniel Smith. Simon &amp; Schuster. 227 pp.$28.</em></p>
<p>When he has been beset by “unruly and offensive emotions,” Daniel Smith acknowledges, he has looked for only one thing: “a way out,” a “vacuum to clear away the debris, and some help.” But he now realizes that “no emotion is inherently bad.”</p>

<p>In <em>Hard Feelings</em>, Smith (a psychotherapist and author of <em>Monkey Mind</em> and <em>Muses, Madmen and Prophets</em>) draws on works of philosophy, psychology, anthropology, literature, art, and, most of all, his personal experiences, to examine six dark emotions: annoyance, shame, envy, boredom, regret, and despair. To vilify or reject these emotions, he argues, is not only futile, but “a kind of psychological abuse.”</p>

<p>Especially when “emotional regimes (ethnic, national or denominational cultures) and “emotional communities” (families, college friends) have codes governing how emotions should – or should not – be expressed. Moreover, emotions contain essential information we can’t get elsewhere “about our vulnerability, furtive desires, hidden assumptions, and half-remembered experiences.”</p>

<p>Smith makes good use of social science research. In <em>Thinking Fast and Slow</em>, he notes, Daniel Kahneman found that people regret an action they took much more than their decision not to act. But as time passes, roads not taken generate a deeper <a href="https://www-apache.anderson.ucla.edu/faculty_pages/keith.chen/negot.%20papers/GilovichMedvec_Regret95.pdf">ache</a>. The more people use social media, we also learn, the more envious and sad they <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00022/full">become</a>.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, <em>Hard Feelings</em> is most compelling – and moving – when Smith describes his emotions, candidly, and with self-deprecating humor. Although audiences tend not to sympathize with Mr. Wilson, “the patron saint of annoyance,” who just wants Dennis the Menace to leave him alone so he can read his morning newspaper, Smith asks, “Really, while we’re at it, why don’t Dennis’ parents keep the little shit on a tighter leash?” The prevalence of annoyance in families, he adds, “is almost a physical law,” as husbands neglect to turn down thermostats at night, and wives never remove their hair from the shower drain.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-vanessa-loring-5082630.jpg?itok=0Wa6BYlq" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="Vanessa Loring/Pexels" alt="Vanessa Loring/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Vanessa Loring/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The care and feeding of a four-year-old is boring, Smith confesses: “Question after question after question.” Are penguins cold? Is tea hot? After Smith fills and refills sippy cups and toasts toast, he lies: “Daddy has to poop,” heads to the bathroom, reads half a paragraph in the newspaper, plays a word game he no longer likes, “flushes the toilet and runs the faucet, for verisimilitude.” In an imagined study of boredom measuring when people will self-administer electric shocks, he predicts that dads of four-year-olds will press the button in only 15 minutes.</p>

<p>Smith’s elucidation of the power and tenacity of dark emotions, it seems to me, is more persuasive than his claims about the “essential information” about assumptions, desires and vulnerabilities they can produce. Or than his assertion that “no emotion is inherently bad.”</p>
<p>Annoyance, Smith writes, “has a permanent seat at the table.” Smith vows to let it “do its compulsive thing,” admit it has a point, be bothered but “not bothered by being bothered.” Similarly, shame “is an inheritance not so easily shed. It is not shameful. It is just where we start.” Amid “the malignant innovations of consumer capitalism,” envy leaves us, “alas, alack,” armed only with eternal verities about “gratitude, contentment, and the dogged indefinite cultivation of the peaceful self…” As he wrote <em>Hard Feelings</em>, Smith felt his regrets “proliferate, clash, pile up, clamor, and overlap.” And Smith understands that at times, beneath the torment of despair is “a distant chance of return,” felt but seemingly out of reach, to which “a person might consign himself to Hell… to confirm, once and for all, the darkness, the certainty of it.” Smith did emerge from despair, it’s worth noting, but the emotion returns periodically.</p>


<p>Although in deference to the unique circumstances every human being faces, <em>Hard Feelings</em> ends without a one-size-fits-all template for dealing with dark emotions, Smith endorses a rather traditional approach, with a caveat that “it is impossible to follow it with any fidelity or confidence.” He warns against confidence in any prescription. After asking with humility, where is my “splinter of light?” he advises going wherever it leads, while expecting nothing and seeing “what you receive,” devising a plan of practical guidance and listening for an inner voice to whisper, “Nice try. Keep trying. Keep trying.”</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/this-is-america/202602/coping-with-our-bad-emotions-isnt-easy" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/this-is-america/202602/coping-with-our-bad-emotions-isnt-easy</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/this-is-america/202602/coping-with-our-bad-emotions-isnt-easy</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Glenn C. Altschuler Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-vanessa-loring-5082630.jpg?itok=W3Hc8SO5" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>