<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 23:26:27 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 23:26:27 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When Sleep Banking May Be A Viable Strategy]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/ksp_carriekennedy_080b-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=HKKNmreG" alt="Carrie H. Kennedy Ph.D., ABPP" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sleep</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">When Sleep Banking May Be A Viable Strategy</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Sleep banking may be a hedge against upcoming sleep deprivation.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>Fatigue management is a vital consideration for all of us. Being alert when we need to be goes beyond getting good, consistent sleep (though this is obviously a necessity). Think of the times that you became drowsy while driving or had to fight sleep during a boring class. And think about your personal strategies in which you engage when you need to perk up (e.g., get up and walk around, have a cup of coffee, stand in the back of the room, etc.). </p>

<p>These are quick fixes for short periods of time. However, for some, effective fatigue management goes beyond our normal, everyday challenges with wakefulness. For those that have jobs where various missions or off-cycle work negate their ability to sleep or to sleep enough, more significant and/or tailored strategies are needed.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/ai-generated-9616731.jpg?itok=y3-uiamd" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" alt="Could sleep extension help you when you know you are going to have to be awake for an extended period of time?" title="Image by Koi Roylers from Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption">Could sleep extension help you when you know you are going to have to be awake for an extended period of time?</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Image by Koi Roylers from Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Sleep banking is an interesting notion and one that is getting increased attention. Sleep banking is essentially extending your normal sleep hours in the nights leading up to a known period of sleep deprivation. On the face of it, it appears unlikely banking sleep could counter the decreased alertness and other cognitive decrements that we experience when deprived of sleep, or stop that strong sensation we get when our body wants sleep (i.e., sleep pressure).</p>

<p> But in 2009 an <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC2647785/">Army study</a> compared people who got their regular hours of sleep for a week to a group that spent 10 hours in bed during those same nights. This was followed by 3 nights of only 3 hours of time in bed allowed for both groups. Surprisingly, the group that had “banked” sleep, performed better on a measure of alertness during the sleep restricted time period and recovered faster from the sleep deprivation.</p>

<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26194565/">Another study</a> in 2015 found similar results. A group who had 6 nights of extended sleep prior to 21 hours of total sleep deprivation, had improved sustained attention and decreased daytime sleepiness going into the deprivation period as well as during the sleep deprivation period, and recovered from the sleep debt more quickly than the group who engaged in their normal sleep prior to the sleep deprivation period. </p>

<p>A <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32016401/">more recent study</a> looked at the effects of a week of sleep extension on a 40-hour period of total sleep deprivation in which participants had to make quick decisions during a task with emotional/neutral stimuli and attentional interference. Again, findings suggest that sleep extension prior to sleep deprivation facilitates better decision-making.</p>

<p>While there is <a href="https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/48/12/zsaf250/8321788">evidence supporting</a> a potential benefit of sleep banking, there are also <a href="https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article-abstract/48/12/zsaf251/8239174?redirectedFrom=fulltext">viable arguments</a> against the theory. One concern is simply that humans are not designed to sleep when they don’t need sleep, thus the notion of banking does not make physiological sense. And, when you think about trying to force yourself to sleep when you don’t need it, you know that it is difficult. A second argument against the notion of sleep banking is that measurable improvements seen in the studies, were more likely due to the resolution of sleep debt, which also has measurable benefits on cognition and wakefulness.</p>


<p>But back to the original question. Can you bank sleep? And the answer is that we don’t currently know. However, there does seem to be some benefit to sleep extension prior to an upcoming, known period of sleep deprivation. While the jury is out as to the mechanism of action in sleep extension, there is evidence that either the sleep banking or the resolution of sleep debt through sleep extension prior to a period of sleep deprivation may help individuals both during the event and in facilitating recovery afterwards.</p>

<p>Disclaimer: The information presented in this blog is not a substitute for professional advice or medical treatment. If you believe that you have a sleep disorder or other medical condition, seek consultation with your primary care provider.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/alpha-blog-charlie/202602/when-sleep-banking-may-be-a-viable-strategy" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/alpha-blog-charlie/202602/when-sleep-banking-may-be-a-viable-strategy</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/alpha-blog-charlie/202602/when-sleep-banking-may-be-a-viable-strategy</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Carrie H. Kennedy Ph.D., ABPP]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/ai-generated-9616731.jpg?itok=i2NcU8T4" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Compassion as the Doorway to Forgiveness]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-09/Amram.png.jpg?itok=m0bcubY0" alt="Amram" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Forgiveness</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Compassion as the Doorway to Forgiveness</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why we can’t will ourselves to “forgive and forget.”</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Forgiveness often fails because present pain is rooted in unresolved emotional wounds from the past.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Self-compassion shifts the nervous system from threat into safety, creating conditions for healing.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When we hold our pain with compassion, our hearts open naturally toward ourselves and others.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Forgiveness emerges organically once emotional wounds are fully acknowledged, understood, and integrated.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>“The past is the past!”</p>
<p>“Forgive and forget.”</p>
<p>“Let bygones be bygones.”</p>
<p>Our culture has plenty of platitudes to offer when it comes to forgiving each other’s wrongs. Yet anyone who has lived through betrayal knows the reality is more complex. The process of forgiveness is anything but linear.</p>
<p>In my clinical work, I once sat with a couple (whom I will call Peter and Tiana) who had worked hard to rebuild trust in the aftermath of Tiana’s affair two years earlier.</p>

<p>Peter was glad they were reunited, building a life together, and raising their young son. Yet something unresolved remained for him. He had told Tiana (and himself) that he had forgiven her, but the pain would still surface from time to time without warning.</p>
<p>This case study raises a deeper question: If Peter wanted to forgive so badly, why did the hurt remain?</p>

<h2>The Hidden Roots of Present Pain</h2>
<p>Even though all Peter wanted to do is move on from this heartache and pain, I invited him to slow down and be present with it for a moment, encouraging him to explore it.</p>
<p>As he did, a memory surfaced from his childhood. Peter recalled overhearing his father tell his mother that they did not need to keep a promise they had made to him (to buy him a bicycle for his birthday) because he was “only a child.”</p>

<p>Emotionally, this discussion his parents probably didn’t even remember had left a deep imprint on him: the experience of broken trust, of promises that did not hold, of being small and unprotected. The betrayal Peter felt now was not only about the affair; it touched much older wounds.</p>
<p>This is often how emotional pain operates. Present events activate earlier emotional templates, and then younger parts of us that are under-resourced to respond, thus amplifying the intensity of our reactions. What appears to be the reactivity of our adult self is really that of our younger, wounded inner-children. </p>

<h2>The Turning Point: Compassion for the Self</h2>
<p>I invited Peter to notice how he was feeling toward that younger version of himself. After a few moments of reflection, his breathing deepened and his posture straightened. He described feeling a warm, radiant sensation in his chest.</p>
<p>Soon this feeling strengthened into something more: an unexpected wave of compassion and care for his younger self. He described the sensation as a gentle light, coming from within him yet also surrounding him. It felt grounding, stabilizing, and expansive all at once.</p>

<p>In that moment, Peter was no longer defined solely by his pain. Instead, he discovered his capacity to tend to it with care. What had been a source of suffering became a chance to offer himself the understanding he had long needed, surprising himself in the process.</p>
<p>Compassion, especially self-compassion, changes our relationship to suffering. Instead of defending against pain, being consumed by it, or feeling self-pity and victimization, we can learn to hold it with warmth and understanding.</p>

<h2>Compassion Naturally Expands</h2>
<p>From this place of self-compassion, Peter suddenly found himself feeling compassion for Tiana as well. He didn’t excuse her actions, but he could suddenly understand them within the context of her own feelings of neglect and loneliness during a period when he had been frequently absent.</p>


<p>He also felt compassion for his father, recognizing that his father’s broken promise had emerged from financial anxiety after being laid off from his job, rather than indifference. Importantly, these shifts were not forced. They arose naturally for Peter once compassion had been established within himself.</p>

<p>This reflects a key psychological truth: Compassion shifts the nervous system from threat into safety, creating the conditions in which our heart can open and forgiveness can take root. And when it comes to long-term benefits, it’s even been proven that self-compassion predicts lower anxiety, depression, rumination, and fear of failure.<a href="#_edn1">[i]</a> Meanwhile, forgiveness has been found to improve outcomes for those struggling with PTSD.<a href="#_edn2">[ii]</a> </p>



  


<h2>Forgiveness as an Emergent Process</h2>
<p>Forgiveness is often misunderstood as something we must choose through effort or moral discipline. But in reality, while the intention to forgive can be an important ingredient, forgiveness is more often the byproduct of emotional integration. Particularly when it comes to infidelity, recovery must undergo the distinct stages of discovery, decision-making, and rebuilding trust.<a href="#_edn3">[iii]</a></p>

<p>This does not mean forgetting the harm or denying its impact. Rather, it means releasing the emotional constriction around it. In the case of Peter, he learned to no longer experience himself solely as a victim of betrayal. He experienced himself as someone capable of holding pain, his own and others', understanding it, and moving through it—a much more empowering self-image.</p>

<h2>Conclusion: Compassion Is the Doorway</h2>
<p>Ultimately, forgiveness is not something we can command on demand, nor is it achieved by repeating cultural platitudes or willing ourselves to “move on.” When the emotional wounds beneath the surface are seen, felt, and held with compassion, healing unfolds organically.</p>

<p>Peter’s healing did not come from forcing himself to absolve Tiana, but from reconnecting with the younger parts of himself that had long carried the wounds of broken trust. By extending compassion inward, he created the inner stability necessary for compassion and forgiveness to emerge on their own.</p>

<p>This is the secret at the heart of healing: Forgiveness begins not with the other person, but with ourselves. When we learn to meet our own suffering with warmth rather than resistance, the grip of past injuries loosens. We go from victims to powerful, resilient individuals. <a href="#_edn4">[iv]</a> </p>
<p>Through compassion, we reclaim our openhearted aliveness. We won’t erase what happened, but we can transform our relationship to it, alchemizing suffering into connection and care.<br> </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/spiritual-intelligence/202602/compassion-as-the-doorway-to-forgiveness" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/spiritual-intelligence/202602/compassion-as-the-doorway-to-forgiveness</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/spiritual-intelligence/202602/compassion-as-the-doorway-to-forgiveness</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Yosi Amram, Ph.D]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-andrew-5255996.jpg?itok=RSliRweC" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>