<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 21:31:54 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 21:31:54 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Age of Permanent Alarm]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Sam%20Goldstein.png.jpg?itok=kLaUD2vO" alt="Sam Goldstein Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Fear</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Age of Permanent Alarm</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How crisis culture reshaped our sense of security.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Modern life normalizes constant psychological alertness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Media exposure intensifies perceived personal vulnerability.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Global crises accumulate, shaping chronic societal anxiety.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>The most significant threats which modern society faces are not tangible or immediate risks; rather, they are future anticipated catastrophic events. These modern risks are global in nature, whereas previously risks were limited to local, controlled environments. Beck asserts that such a transformation in our sense of risk redirects social energy toward the anticipation and prevention of future catastrophes, creating a continual state of heightened awareness (Beck, 2006). Rebughini (2021) illustrates Beck's argument, noting that anxiety has become part of the normal experience for many people in today's Western culture and that this phenomenon is exacerbated by current crises, such as COVID-19. Consequently, people find themselves in a collective state of unease.</p>

<h2>From Fear to Chronic Anxiety</h2>
<p>A cultural shift has moved us from having episodic fear experiences to an overall anxiety level of general fear in today's society. A huge factor in developing this heightened level of anxiety is media saturation. More continuous media exposure has increased our level of awareness regarding issues affecting us all, including terrorism and natural disasters. One key is that, regardless of whether you directly experience terrorism or natural disasters, knowledge of those events will affect how you perceive yourself when it comes to feeling vulnerable to future dangers; the concern is not whether there is danger, but when it will happen to you. The second factor that has increased our fear levels is the rise of the digital media revolution, in which we consume and share information through new technologies.</p>

<h2>Media Saturation and the Amplification of Threat</h2>
<p>The use of technological innovations to report on a large volume of risk-related events taking place around the globe involves the proliferation of digital technology and its impact on our emotions/decision-making processes. Research has demonstrated that awareness of risk (e.g., via media saturation) has a profound impact on how we perceive and respond to risk.</p>

<p>According to Garfin et al. (2022), increased media exposure throughout the COVID-19 pandemic has led to an increase in general anxiety for individuals compared to their prior levels. In addition to this, Rubatelli et al. (2018) writes that individuals who have been exposed to various forms of media often perceive certain likelihoods of an attack occurring based solely on media exposure. This was particularly the case for individuals who were susceptible to environmental stress. </p>

<p>Various studies throughout Europe found a clear connection between media use and perceived threat during the COVID-19 pandemic, as well as increases in anxiety levels. Research conducted by Vacondio et al. (2021) found that using high amounts of media during the pandemic heightened feelings of worry and influenced the likelihood of adopting protective behaviour. They found similar results with an investigation carried out by Lanciano et al. (2020) into risk perception in Italy during the outbreak; however, risk perception during the outbreak was also found to relate to a broader sense of overall psychological distress than merely fear of contracting COVID-19.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Twenty Years of Cascading Crises</h2>
<p>Additionally, Rubaltelli, Tedaldi, and Orabona (2020) were able to link media exposure to anxiety and health-related decision-making. The results of research into the effects of terrorism are similar to those found in the COVID-19 pandemic. According to Rogers et al. (2007), indirect exposure via the media can produce social and psychological impacts in a way that is similar to direct experience. According to Sheppard et al. (2006), the public does not panic easily; however, perception of threat is still impacted by communication channels, and despite the existence of statistically low levels of objective risk, repeated imagery of high levels of threat and time-sensitive wording will increase the individual's perception of vulnerability.</p>

<p>A sense of safety has become increasingly fragile within today's context of immediacy due to the ubiquity of information; proximity is no longer a factor, as both a bombing in another country and an extreme wildfire on another continent have become immediate and personal events, thanks to the failure of our nervous system to distinguish between what we perceive as close to us and projections of distance from us. The last two decades have seen us face multiple crises simultaneously (from cascading crises since 1990), with the first being the global war on terror (beginning in the early 2000s).</p>


<p>This established new objective and subjective indicators of what it meant to be "secure" with regard to our national security policies and the way we, as citizens, understood ourselves. Then, in subsequent years, multiple financial crises/market meltdowns destabilized our economic assumptions about our role as citizens in a democratic society. In the years that followed, climate change moved from scientific debate into our lived experience as extreme weather events began to take place in various places around the world. Next came the COVID-19 pandemic, some would say the first true global event, not by design but because of its proximity to all of us, changing our routines, economies, and relationships.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Anxiety, Politics, and Democratic Vulnerability</h2>
<p>Albertson and Gadarian (2015) point out the way anxiety affects democratic citizenship and how this affects the way groups process information and evaluate leaders in the context of hostile environments versus non-hostile ones. In hostile environments, we tend to be more alert to threats but also more easily influenced by emotionally charged messages. Kruglanski et al. (2020) also acknowledge that during times of widespread uncertainty, extremist groups have been able to further embed their danger narratives into political discourse.</p>



  


<p>Climate change contributes a particularly enduring layer of unease. The combined effects of more than 20 years of reported crisis have created a cascade of crises. As new crises continue to emerge, the psychological imprint of the previous crisis still lingers; therefore, individuals carry forward unresolved tensions and develop chronic hyper-vigilance over time. However, it would be misleading to assume that no one experiences safety at all. Studies have shown that resilience does exist. According to Wolff and Larsen (2014), perceptions of risk vary from one person to another but appear to stabilise as people adjust to the terrorist attack. Therefore, safety is not completely defined; it has a degree of precision and is made through negotiation. Each person will have their own concept of normalcy as defined by their own perception of uncertainty.</p>

<h2>The Persistence of Perceived Threat</h2>
<p>It is undeniable that a trend is clearly continuing. In recent years, the world has witnessed numerous threats and events of a global scale, leading to a heightened sense of alert. As humans evolved, we were wired for action during immediate perceived threats; however, by being in a constant state of alertness without any endpoint, we have come to experience a collective form of long-term anxiety. Statistically speaking, the world has not become more dangerous based on some measures; the global trend of violence and pandemics has declined when compared to other periods in time. The perception of risk, however, has greatly increased, leading to an individual's sense of omnipresent, personally experienced risk.</p>

<p>The "perpetually on-alert" mindset is also a result of the interrelatedness of global hazards, political messaging, and media. Do people feel safe? It may be that we must shift the way we view risk, rather than eliminate it. Understanding how society's structures, how we communicate with each other, and how our government creates incentives to fear can help us regain equilibrium. In the modern world, it is possible that the absence of risk may not be as important as the ability to find meaning in life, even though you are living in a state of risk.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202602/the-age-of-permanent-alarm" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202602/the-age-of-permanent-alarm</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202602/the-age-of-permanent-alarm</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Common Sense Science]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-10464480.jpg?itok=_j3Z9-Hk" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sexual Abuse in Families: Be Brave and Address the Harm]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-09/XRShaw.png.jpg?itok=duFTxc71" alt="Risa Shaw Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sex</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Sexual Abuse in Families: Be Brave and Address the Harm</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">In cases of sexual abuse, healing can begin in the family, by the family.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Remember that sexual abuse is never the victim’s/survivor’s fault. Reminding them of that is crucial.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Shame and self-blame from incest are insidious for survivors. Left uncontested, they compound the trauma.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Parents are obligated to see and deal with sexual abuse in their families. They can do it. They are doing it.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Normalize talking about incest/intrafamilial sexual abuse. Break the cycle by teaching consent and agency.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Do you want to support sexual abuse survivors? Then work to prevent more kids from being sexually abused, especially <em>in</em> their families <em>by</em> their family members. Bring the reality of sexual abuse and <a href="https://www.incestaware.org/what-is-incest">incest</a> into the light.</p>
<h2>Follow the examples of parents who are addressing sexual abuse in their families</h2>
<p>Over the last two years, I’ve spent a lot of time talking with parents who are dealing with sibling sexual abuse and trauma in their families. Recently, I was on a panel of <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meaning-in-context/202506/what-is-sibling-sexual-abuse-statistics-signs-and-effects">sibling sexual abuse survivors </a><em>and</em> parents of survivors and abusers. Hearing the stories of parents of survivors is one of the most transformative experiences I’ve had in over 50 years since I was sexually assaulted by my brother.</p>

<p>I still have to let this sink in: there are parents who learn about and address the abuse when it is happening. They stop it. They deal with it as a family. Other parents learn about the abuse through <a href="https://www.notchildsplay.com/research">disclosure</a> by survivors after it has stopped, and they confront the harm. </p>
<p>This was <em>not</em> my experience with my parents. So it takes me a minute. </p>

<h2>Generational trauma continues harming, so address it in your family</h2>
<p>I have known for a long time that both of my parents suffered trauma early in their lives that they never addressed. That meant they hadn’t learned how to confront, deal with, stop, or even recognize the trauma that was being inflicted on their own children. </p>

<p>This history left me and my siblings vulnerable, vulnerable both to being harmed and to causing harm. </p>
<p><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/decoding-trauma/202211/the-encouraging-news-about-trauma-and-recovery">Recovering from sexual trauma</a> takes a ton of work. Over the years, I’ve concentrated on putting myself back together emotionally and psychologically, calming my nervous system, and reclaiming my feistiness, creativity, joy, and self-worth. Blaming myself for <em>somehow</em> causing the abuse has been the hardest to see, manage, and overcome. Self-blame, and the shame that comes with it, often have the tightest grip on survivors. That certainly has been true for me. </p>

<h2>Reassure survivors that the sexual abuse was not their fault</h2>
<p>Even after I told my family about my brother sexually assaulting me, they didn’t tell me it wasn’t my fault. I didn’t know how badly I needed to hear that from them; how critical it would be for my recovery to be reminded of <em>the fact that it was not my fault, </em>that I did <em>nothing to cause</em> the abuse, that there was <em>nothing inherently bad in me</em> that made him target me. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content ad--content-loaded" data-google-query-id="CIby2azP-pIDFWqJOgUdfzg94Q">
    
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"><iframe id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0" name="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0" title="3rd party ad content" width="300" height="250" scrolling="no" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" frameborder="0" aria-label="Advertisement" tabindex="0" allow="private-state-token-redemption;attribution-reporting" data-load-complete="true" data-google-container-id="7"></iframe></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_5850%20copy.jpeg.jpg?itok=hj6zhqgc" width="320" height="590" data-insert-type="image" alt="Truth Teller, We Believe You" title="Art by Risa Shaw"></div>
<div class="caption">Truth Teller, We Believe You</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Art by Risa Shaw</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>So this is what I want you to understand. From the day my brother cornered me in the closet where I hid when we were playing hide and seek, I was sure it was my fault he sexually assaulted me. I will repeat that. I was sure it was my fault that someone else assaulted me.</p>
<p>We need others to recognize (and reassure us) that it was not our fault, that we did nothing to bring it on, that there is nothing wrong with us or inherently bad in us that made us culpable. We were victimized. Support your child(ren)/sibling(s) just as you would if someone outside the family had assaulted us.</p>

<p>Blaming myself, mixed with shame that had kept me scared and quiet, cemented my feelings of being bad, unworthy, inadequate, and just plain undeserving of anything good in my life. These still show up <em>today, </em>decades after the abuse began<em>. </em>This is what survivors live with. </p>
<p>And believe me, I have worked doggedly to unearth these feelings, knowing that they were (and are) lies. </p>


<p>By the time I told my family about the abuse, I had felt culpable for a solid 12 years. Do I think that if they had told me then that it was not my fault, it would have made a difference in the next 40 years of my life? I sure do. </p>
<h2>Create a culture of consent in your family</h2>
<p>Here are some other things that could have made a difference, so that I wouldn’t have had to do all this work by myself, so that what happened in our family would have been shouldered by the family and dealt with as a family.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content ad--content-loaded" data-google-query-id="CITy2azP-pIDFWqJOgUdfzg94Q">
    
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"><iframe id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0" name="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0" title="3rd party ad content" width="300" height="250" scrolling="no" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" frameborder="0" aria-label="Advertisement" tabindex="0" allow="private-state-token-redemption;attribution-reporting" data-load-complete="true" data-google-container-id="5"></iframe></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<ul>
<li>If someone had taught me that saying no to someone in my family would be respected. Instead, when I tried to get someone to stop tickling me, they laughed and kept tickling me. </li>
<li>If someone had shown me what it meant to ask for help to be safe, and when I didn’t feel safe. Instead, I felt ashamed for feeling unsafe, kept quiet, and blamed myself for not being stronger and less scared. </li>
<li>If someone had asked me for consent, waited for my answer, and accepted what I said. Instead, I was told to eat what was put on my plate even though I had said I didn’t like the taste. </li>
<li>If someone had asked me why I was frustrated or upset. Instead, powerlessness was drilled into me when I voiced frustration or started to cry at something unfair in our house, and my dad cut me off and told me to go to the den until I could “act right.” </li>
<li>If someone had made and kept a house rule that secrets were not allowed in our house. Instead, I kept secret what my brother was doing to me, not telling them until I was ready to explode (and was out of the house) 12 years later.</li>
</ul>



  


<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Audre%20Lorde%20quote%20hand%20stitched.png.jpg?itok=qMBBE7jv" width="320" height="363" data-insert-type="image" alt="“Your Silence Will Not Protect You” Audre Lorde" title="Art by Risa Shaw"></div>
<div class="caption">“Your Silence Will Not Protect You” Audre Lorde</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Art by Risa Shaw</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Talk. Tell the truth. Seek out the truth. Step up.</h2>
<p>So when I meet and talk to parents who are confronting the fact of sexual abuse in their families, I have hope. I have hope that naming the abuse and talking about how to deal with it and its consequences will be the necessary predicates to recovery and healing. I have hope that they are making a difference in their own kids’ lives and will extend to prevention and healing in other people’s lives. </p>

<p>Don’t put the burden of untangling the tenacious and insidious shame and blame on the one who was victimized. The <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/oct/23/gisele-pelicot-rape-trial-france-court">shame and blame after sexual abuse</a> was not theirs to begin with and never will be. Step up, no matter how hard it is. Step in, take responsibility, and require accountability, no matter how hard it is.</p>

<p>Be brave. Seek truth. Deal with the mess, the trauma, the broken trust, and broken relationships. By confronting what really happened and why, along with the life-long consequences, maybe healing can begin <em>by </em>the family and <em>in</em> the family. </p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>To find a therapist near you, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meaning-in-context/202602/sexual-abuse-in-families-be-brave-and-address-the-harm" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meaning-in-context/202602/sexual-abuse-in-families-be-brave-and-address-the-harm</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/meaning-in-context/202602/sexual-abuse-in-families-be-brave-and-address-the-harm</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Risa Shaw Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/rearview-diverse-people-hugging-each-other%201.jpg?itok=Zn0DN91p" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Religious Freedom Includes the Freedom to Leave Religion]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-08/Untitled_design__5_-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=dP2Cu_in" alt="Steven A Hassan PhD" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Religion</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Religious Freedom Includes the Freedom to Leave Religion</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What happens when someone feels trapped in a religious belief?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">True religious freedom requires the psychological capacity to choose freely.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cults install irrational fears of leaving that often operate below conscious awareness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cognitive dissonance traps members, rather than allowing them to doubt their group.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Clinicians must learn to distinguish religious phobias from organic anxiety disorders to avoid misdiagnosis.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>You are standing in front of a door with no lock, no guard, and no chain. You desperately want to leave, and yet every cell in your body screams that walking out will bring catastrophe. </p>
<p>This is the lived reality of millions of people in highly controlling religions, cults, and coercive situations worldwide. Individuals in such situations are physically free to leave and yet feel psychologically trapped. Some defend such circumstances by invoking the right of religious freedom.</p>

<p>For context, in the United States, the First Amendment protects (among other rights, such as freedom of speech and of assembly) the right to hold any religious belief, free from interference. </p>
<p>However, the legal protection has always applied to beliefs, not necessarily to behaviors carried out in the name of those beliefs. For example, courts have banned rituals involving venomous snakes because of the deaths they cause.</p>

<p>And so, the question I pose is not whether a person is legally free to believe, but whether they are psychologically able to stop believing, and whether they can walk away without being consumed by terror.</p>
<h2>Building the Psychological Cage</h2>
<p>Psychological entrapment, rather than physical confinement, is the common method used by destructive cult groups to keep people in a group they want to leave. </p>

<p>Entrapment serves as an emotional prison: Someone who has thoughts of exiting becomes so emotionally overwhelmed by those thoughts that leaving becomes nearly impossible to consider. A similar dynamic operates in coercive partnerships: ear and coercion create multiple failed attempts at leaving, even in non-physically threatening situations.</p>

<p>In my clinical work, I describe this process as “phobia indoctrination,” creating an extreme fear of leaving or questioning the group by piggybacking it onto an existing fear. The phobia develops when the destructive group creates a strong narrative about horrific situations that will befall the person who leaves or defects. It is not a phobia that develops through lived experience but, rather, is created or utilized by the group to bring about a perpetual state of fear of leaving.</p>

<p>Members are taught to believe that departure will bring catastrophe, which can include the eternal loss of salvation, terminal illness, possession, and more. The specifics vary, but the result is a phobia so strong that leaving feels too dangerous.</p>
<p>Because the phobia can function beneath conscious awareness, the person may genuinely experience continued membership as their “free will” choice. They are not pretending, and they believe they are choosing to stay. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Cognitive Dissonance Theory</h2>
<p>Leon Festinger’s cognitive dissonance theory, the observation that people feel psychological discomfort when holding contradictory beliefs and are driven to resolve it, helps explain why members may dig in rather than walk away.</p>
<p>Festinger studied the phenomenon firsthand in a 1950's cult, The Seekers, that prophesied they would be saved by aliens on doomsday. But when the date arrived and a UFO failed to appear, many members became more committed, not less. Their investment in the cult had been so extreme—many had sold their homes and quit their jobs.in anticipation of alien rescue—that they had to shift their beliefs to justify it: They argued that their faith had been so strong it saved the world.</p>

<p>A similar dynamic plays out in destructive groups every day. The more someone has sacrificed, the more painful it becomes to acknowledge. In such a situation, the mind doubles down, and critical thinking takes a big hit. </p>
<p>Cults exploit this knowledge by engineering escalating commitment early while ensuring that the sword of fear hangs over members. Members are often asked to increase their time demands and take on larger roles within the organization, especially when their leadership notices hesitation. Each new ask represents one new sacrifice by the member, a reminder of the consequences if they do not follow through, and a new way for them to justify their commitment.</p>

<h2>Informed Consent and the Clinical Relevance</h2>
<p>In ethical therapy, informed consent is the process of providing a client with enough information to freely choose whether to start treatment. It is a clear, nonnegotiable element of therapy that protects a client and ensures that they understand that therapy is a form of influence and involves an unequal power dynamic. </p>



  


<p>Informed consent explains such matters as mandatory reporting and confidentiality requirements. A therapist who withholds such information violates professional ethics.</p>
<p>Why isn't the same standard applied to religious recruitment? Many clergy (whether they realize it or not) are mandatory reporters, and they represent themselves in the community as wise, trustworthy people to come to in times of trouble. When destructive cult recruiters lie about who they are and what they want, they deny a person the information needed to make a free choice whether to engage in a process of influence. </p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>True religious freedom requires what might be called “cognitive freedom." It should respect the right not to be deceptively manipulated and ensure the capacity to evaluate alternatives.</p>
<p>Such concepts have inherent relevance for those who eventually leave destructive cult environments. Former cult members frequently come to treatment with symptoms resembling anxiety disorders and identity disturbance. Clinicians who lack cult knowledge risk misdiagnosis or, worse, reinforcing the phobias the group installed. </p>

<p>A former member who experiences intense panic at the thought of criticizing their group is exhibiting a programmed response. Recognizing it as such can be the difference between effective healing and further harm.</p>
<p>I support the existence of structured or unconventional religious communities, as there is room in an open, pluralistic society. The question is whether a choice arises from informed, freely made commitments or from layered psychological pressures that make refusal feel impossible.</p>

<p>The questions that need asking are: Can cult members and our clients leave without fear? Do the psychological conditions exist for genuine choice? What are ethical ways to explore choice, while still holding the line for true freedom of belief?</p>
<p>Ultimately, we must recognize the element of control in defining the line between stated freedom and actual cognitive freedom, and between conscious spiritual expression and psychological imprisonment in the name of belief and faith. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/freedom-of-mind/202602/religious-freedom-includes-the-freedom-to-leave-religion" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/freedom-of-mind/202602/religious-freedom-includes-the-freedom-to-leave-religion</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/freedom-of-mind/202602/religious-freedom-includes-the-freedom-to-leave-religion</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven A Hassan PhD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are Romantic Couples Really the Winners?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-07/Bella%20DePaulo.png.jpg?itok=Y8fOIpFZ" alt="Bella DePaulo Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Friends</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Are Romantic Couples Really the Winners?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What studies of the purported deficiencies of single people aren’t telling you.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>Suppose you read about a study comparing single people to coupled people and supposedly showing that single people are deficient and romantically coupled people are the winners? I’ll start with a hypothetical and then show how it applies to the kinds of studies you really do read about.</p>
<p>In the hypothetical study, the researchers want to know who is better at getting out of boxes, single people or coupled people. A single person starts in one box, and the couple starts in a box right beside the single person. The whistle is blown, and the participants try to get out of their boxes. The researchers are timing them.</p>

<p>They find that the coupled people get out of their boxes more quickly, maybe much more quickly. They publish their study and say that it shows that single people are deficient at getting out of boxes. Maybe it’s a psychological thing, and they should get counseling or therapy. The coupled people, in contrast, have great box-escaping skills. They have no deficiencies that the researchers mention and nothing to work on.</p>

<p>The study gets a lot of attention in the media. Coupled people feel proud of themselves. Single people feel bad because social scientists have shown that they have a box-escaping deficiency, and maybe they should go into therapy to work on whatever is at the root of their problem. What’s more, because of all the media coverage, people everywhere are learning about their deficiency and couples’ superiority.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AI%20generated%202%20boxes_0.png.jpg?itok=TE66Gl3g" width="320" height="179" data-insert-type="image" title="AI-generated from Canva" alt="AI-generated from Canva"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI-generated from Canva</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2><strong>The Hidden Picture</strong></h2>
<p>The researchers think it is fine to tell you only about the time it took each participant to get out of the box. After all, it is a study of box-escaping skill.</p>
<p>Often, there is a highly relevant context to the story that is not mentioned. In my hypothetical example, it looks like this: The single person is in the box on the left. The door is shut, and there are boulders in front of it. The top of the box is taped shut.</p>

<p>The coupled people are in a box that has no door, just a giant opening that they can walk right through onto a beautiful path strewn with roses on both sides.</p>
<p>That’s the context of the comparison, showing that single people are deficient at getting out of boxes. Do you think single people are “deficient” because there’s something wrong with them that makes them bad at getting out of boxes? Or do you think that it was never an even playing field from the outset?</p>

<h2><strong>A More Realistic Example</strong></h2>
<p>Singlehood researchers often look at things like how lonely single people are or how satisfied they are with their lives. They might compare single people with romantically coupled people at one point in time (a comparison rife with problems), or, in a better design, they might look at how single people’s experiences of life satisfaction and loneliness change when they become romantically coupled.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Many <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doiLanding?doi=10.1037%2Fa0025948">studies</a> show that when single people marry, they sometimes become a bit happier at first, but eventually go back to being about as happy or as unhappy as they were when they were single.</p>
<p>Suppose, though, that other researchers publish studies suggesting something different—for example, that adolescents or young adults entering their first romantic relationship are more satisfied with their lives and less lonely than those who stay single (no romantic relationship) while they are young. Those researchers claim that they have documented singlehood deficits. The single people in their studies are deficient in satisfaction with their lives, and they are also lonelier, another deficiency. Maybe they suggest that single people get psychological help for their deficiencies.</p>

<p>But the single and coupled people in real published studies are playing on unequal fields, a fact that sometimes goes completely unacknowledged. Here are just a few of the ways that young single people are boxed in, while those who become romantically coupled are given the equivalent of a clear and open path strewn with roses. As you read them, consider how they may contribute to single people feeling lonelier and less satisfied, not because they don’t have a romantic partner but because of how people are treated differently if they do or do not have a romantic partner.</p>

<ul>
<li>Other people are often happy for the young adults who become romantically coupled and feel sorry for the young adults who are living single.</li>
<li>Many of the newly coupled people will consider themselves members of an elite club, the Couples Club, that elevates them above their peers who are single.</li>
<li>Perhaps the newly coupled people once socialized with their single friends when they were single too; now they socialize with couples, and their single friends are neglected or demoted to lesser events, such as lunch instead of dinner.</li>
<li>In some families, the young adult who is coupled will be invited to bring their romantic partner to family outings; their single sibling will not be invited to bring their lifelong friend.</li>
<li>The coupled person will get to bring a plus-one invite to weddings and other such occasions. Again, the single person is less likely to be offered that option, no matter how close or longstanding any of their platonic relationships have been.</li>
<li>Coupled people, especially if they are married, get all sorts of breaks in the marketplace. For example, they pay less per person for insurance, memberships, cultural events, travel packages, and so much more. The single people who pay full price are subsidizing those couples.</li>
<li>In the workplace, the single employee may be asked to cover for their coupled coworker when the coupled person wants to leave early, get holidays off, or get their preferred time for when they take their vacation.</li>
<li>Romantically coupled workers (especially the married ones) may be able to take time off from work to care for their partner when their partner is ill, and their partner may be able to take time off to care for them. Single people typically cannot take time off to care for someone, such as a close friend or cherished relative, and no such person can take time off to care for them. They are not just shortchanged in their attempts to give or receive care; they also unfairly miss out on the deep bonding that can sometimes result from such experiences.</li>
<li>The coupled people read about studies in scientific journals claiming that they are superior; the single people learn that they are deficient.</li>
</ul>



  


<p>There is no end to this list. As you are reading it, you are probably thinking of other examples. Keep that in mind whenever you read about studies supposedly showing that single people are deficient and deprived.</p>
<p>Then ask yourself: Are single people lonelier and less satisfied with their lives (if they really are) because they are personally deficient and need psychological help? Or are they stereotyped, stigmatized, marginalized, and left out of social events (even by the people who once included them), while their coupled peers are admired, celebrated, routinely included, offered discounts (subsidized by their single peers), and benefited and protected by laws and practices?</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Perhaps it is the coupled people who could benefit from some help. Maybe they could be gently encouraged to consider whether becoming romantically coupled really has elevated them into an elite club, The Couples Club, that makes them superior to their single friends. And whether it is appropriate or dignified to treat their single friends as less valuable than their coupled friends.</p>

<p>Maybe a way forward is not to pathologize being single, but to work toward greater fairness for single people. The <a href="https://singlesequality.org/">Singles Bill of Rights</a>, for example, offers a path toward equality for single people.</p>
<h2><strong>Bottom line</strong></h2>
<p>Every time you read about a study purporting to claim that single people are deficient and romantically coupled people are superior, remember the boxes. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-single/202602/are-romantic-couples-really-the-winners" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-single/202602/are-romantic-couples-really-the-winners</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-single/202602/are-romantic-couples-really-the-winners</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Bella DePaulo Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/AI%20generated%202%20boxes_0.png.jpg?itok=L5lm5dnh" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Changing Your Mind Is a Critical Strength Not a Weakness]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Kyle-Killian.jpg?itok=XykK75mG" alt="Kyle D. Killian Ph.D., LMFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Identity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Changing Your Mind Is a Critical Strength Not a Weakness</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A willingness to change your mind, when evidence warrants it, is honorable.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A key component of critical thought is our willingness to reconsider our views and ways of doing things.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many folks are unwilling to change their minds for fear that it would indicate a personal failing.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">But being wrong is not a character flaw or something horrible from which one can never recover.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/marija-zaric-hmnHrLnoCj8-unsplash.jpg?itok=qGCEpuOg" width="320" height="268" data-insert-type="image" title="Marija Zaric/Unsplash" alt="Marija Zaric/Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Marija Zaric/Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Critical thinking includes motivational dispositions, such as inquisitiveness, open-mindedness, tolerance for ambiguity, thinking about thinking, honesty in assessing or evaluating biases, and <em>willingness to reconsider one’s own views and ways of doing things<strong> </strong></em>(see Killian, 2024, 2025). </p>
<p>This last part is crucial to our critical thinking capacity, and is represented in a negatively worded item of the Critical Thinking Dispositions Scale (Killian, 2024): “Changing one’s mind is a sign of weakness.” This item seems to be a mantra for many folks who refuse to honestly assess or evaluate their own biases, past and present, and are unwilling to change their minds for fear it indicates a personal failing.</p>

<p>But being wrong is not a character flaw or something horrible from which one can never recover. It need not be a source of embarrassment. It’s <em>insisting</em> on remaining wrong about something that becomes dicey. Many folks are afraid to face the truth (about their own sexist or racist views, about a political leader, or an unconstitutional government policy or act, etc.). They’re so afraid of the cognitive dissonance they might experience if they took the bold step of evaluating new information or facts that they may go so far as to claim that facts and truth no longer exist (a specific form of nihilism).</p>

<p>In addition to checking our own biases and updating our personal views, critical thinking helps us sustain the complexity of a phenomenon or problem and to avoid oversimplifying reality. Sure, when a political leader promises a simple fix to a complex problem, it can sound appealing, because of the reductionistic notion that an overly simplified problem can be remedied with overly simplified solutions. When government and private institutions tell us they have our interests at heart, that they are protecting us, we want to believe it’s true. But a complex problem rarely gets solved by reducing it to an overly simplistic form, and a leader’s promises during and following a campaign are often soon forgotten. Nonetheless, people “cling to the original story” because that’s what they know. It’s reassuring, familiar, and may have become a part of their identity, but it may not stand the test of time.</p>

<p>This week, Substack writer (and NBA All-Star Center) Kareem Abdul-Jabbar wrote about why folks cling to the original story: “It’s what they voted for, what they pledged allegiance to, what they were certain they learned, what they based their future on. It’s become a part of them.” People often double down or triple down on their original belief rather than making a courageous effort to reevaluate outdated beliefs and assumptions and relegate them to the dustbin of history.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Abdul-Jabbar continues, “Admitting you were fooled means admitting you trusted the wrong person, or believed the wrong headline, or followed the wrong crowd. I try to remind myself that changing my mind is a sign of strength, not weakness. The world is full of people who will lie to protect their power, money, and image.”</p>

<p>Who are the people who keep us mired in deceptions and lies? <em>Ourselves</em>. We choose what infotainment ecosystems we partake of. As adult, responsible citizens, we have a civic duty to assess what reliable, reputable sources for news and information are and choose multiple ones to gain and fully engage multiple perspectives. Open-minded, critically engaged persons exercise freedom when they work hard to let go of a promise or a story that fooled them. The next step is creating space to write a new and improved narrative for both themselves and others.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/intersections/202602/why-changing-your-mind-is-a-critical-strength-not-a-weakness" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/intersections/202602/why-changing-your-mind-is-a-critical-strength-not-a-weakness</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/intersections/202602/why-changing-your-mind-is-a-critical-strength-not-a-weakness</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kyle D. Killian Ph.D., LMFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/marija-zaric-hmnHrLnoCj8-unsplash.jpg?itok=rm0PwFsA" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Risks of Parasocial Relationships]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-09/3E18729B-F68D-4848-A756-5E63475BFC3F-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=HR7e6hh8" alt="Anna Rostomyan Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Loneliness</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Risks of Parasocial Relationships</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">In parasocial relationships, we may feel loved while feeling lonely.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>Parasocial relationships (PSRs) are one-sided emotional bonds where individuals invest their time, effort, energy, emotions, and feelings into a well-known media figure, such as a celebrity, influencer, or fictional character from a book or movie, who is not aware of their existence. </p>
<p>Often, teenagers feel secure in parasocial relationships when they admire an idol and become his/her fans, though they are separated from them by space and time. In this case, love, admiration, and devotion are directed from one party to the other, but the other does not receive it in a direct one-to-one manner. For example, I used to be a long-time Nick Carter fan (of the Backstreet Boys), while my cousin worried about my emotions being one-sided and going to waste. I always assured her that he was just an idol for me.</p>

<p>Parasocial relationships are often characterized by an "illusion of intimacy." The affection sender—that is, the admirer—feels love, admiration, and attraction, and feels they know, trust, and have a personal friendship with the persona, despite the lack of direct, reciprocal, or face-to-face interaction. For instance, dozens of followers may follow a well-known personality or influencer on Instagram, see their daily posts and stories, witness their daily life and activities, and feel a kind of "connection" with that person. But in reality, that influencer might be unaware of the followers' admiration or even their existence at all. </p>

<p>Sometimes, though, the energy exchanged between admirer and idol is reciprocal. The admirers gain energy from influencers, and the influencers may also gain energy from the love and affection of their fans, even if theit personalities are mostly unknown to them. For instance, Selena Gomez has said multiple times in interviews that her fans gave her strength in her difficult times, as has Britney Spears, who has attested to the significance of emotional support from her fans.</p>

<p>These experiences suggests that parasocial relationships are not necessarily something bad that we must avoid, but that we do need to be aware of their pros and cons. Nonetheless, too much one-sided affection from fans to their idols can lead to damage and disastrous effects on fans' psychological well-being when they do not get affection back from the other party.</p>

<p>Michelle Möri and Andreas Fahr (2024) state in their research paper that viewers of media content observe media characters and evaluate their behavior based on moral judgments, which results in affective dispositions toward the media characters. It is generally assumed that if characters behave morally, viewers develop positive feelings toward them, whereas if they behave immorally, viewers develop negative feelings toward them. </p>

<p>Influencers should be aware of this tendency and mindfully post their content, realizing that they have an impact on the mentality and worldview formation of a generation.</p>
<p>Partly because of the influence of media figures on their followers, French president Emmanuel Macron has pushed to ban social media for users under 15 and prohibit mobile phones in high schools starting in September 2026 to combat mental health risks, bullying, and screen addiction. The legislation, passed by lawmakers in January 2026, aims to deactivate non-compliant accounts by year-end, following similar bans in Australia. </p>

<p>It is also noteworthy that with the rise of AI, we are witnessing a global spread of parasocial relationships with various chatbots; in certain cases, even leading to tight and even romantic interrelations with AI agents. If humans do not realize that these tools do not possess human emotions the way we do, it can have a negative influence on their emotional well-being, even though it may provide short-term comfort to them to feel loved, even artificially.</p>


<p>With the development of new technology, new ways of connection and cross-media communication have become possible. To get the most of it, and not be negatively affected by it, we have to raise the awareness of the public. </p>
<p>In short, people should be aware of the fact that they are attracted to fictional characters or celebrities they don't really know and not fully base their emotional well-being on them as a source of emotional comfort and psychological well-being. If they can understand this, they will benefit from the beauty of parasocial relations, in terms of having the possibility of closely admiring their idols and digitally interacting with them.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/emotions-in-our-lives/202602/the-risks-of-parasocial-relationships" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/emotions-in-our-lives/202602/the-risks-of-parasocial-relationships</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/emotions-in-our-lives/202602/the-risks-of-parasocial-relationships</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Anna Rostomyan Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_2655327531.jpg?itok=2T_KRcID" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>