<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 15:38:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 15:38:46 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Executive Function Myths That Need to Go]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-08/Headshot_4-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=FiAh0fTm" alt="Sarah Kesty" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Executive Function</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Executive Function Myths That Need to Go</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Your beliefs about time management may be doing more harm than good.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many myths about executive function may be harmful to your growth.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Executive function and morality are not tied together, although society may connect the two.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Skills like time management are reflective of effective strategies but not necessarily effort.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Executive function grows best when we let go of the myths surrounding it.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">Somewhere, deep down, I know my level-eight reaction is a mismatch to the level-three problem: I’ve fallen behind on emails, and now I seem like a total flake. My inner voice chides me, “You’re an executive function expert, for goodness sake. You can’t make mistakes like these!” I time-travel in my head, forecasting that all of the families I work with will turn on me, my family will be shamed, and I will be seen as an irresponsible fraud.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Never mind that I’ve fallen behind because I just moved. My brain has soaked up the messaging that conflated my executive function with my character, and as such, I worry that any executive function struggle reflects poor morality. The tangling of who we are with our executive function is just one of the many myths that permeate our thinking and, unfortunately, really set us back. It’s time to dispel the executive function falsehoods:</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Being late means you don’t care</h2>
<p dir="ltr">We all have that friend who will be late to their own funeral. For a while, I was that friend: rushing, hustling, and always feeling like a letdown. I had more than a few people tell me how frustrating my tardiness was, asking if I genuinely cared about them or the activity for which we were meeting. If they only knew how much I cared and how, every time, I would think things would be different. I’d think I would be on time, maybe even early, only to find that I had misestimated the time I needed to get ready or got stuck in (admittedly predictable) traffic.</p>

<p dir="ltr">While I’m pleased to have strategies that help me show up consistently on time now, I also have a lot of compassion for my younger self. Being late never meant I didn’t care. It meant that I needed to improve in the time management skill set of executive function.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-ola-dapo-1754561-3521937.jpg?itok=RH7qJMqd" width="320" height="427" data-insert-type="image" alt="If you're struggling to start a task, you might need an executive function strategy." title="Ola Dapo / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">If you're struggling to start a task, you might need an executive function strategy.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Ola Dapo / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2 dir="ltr">Trying harder will solve your executive function struggles</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Every one of the people I coach has heard they need to “just try harder,” “study harder,” “work harder,” or any other combo of skill plus the assumption of low effort. Executive functions are not improved with more effort, and struggles do not reflect a lack of effort. Instead, executive functions improve with strategies, reflection, practice, and self-awareness, a slow but steady progression of small wins and the courage to stick with yourself through challenges.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Executive functions are often brain-based, meaning they are impacted by our neurology and vary across the day and different contexts. What takes little energy when you’re well rested, interested, and satiated may feel nearly impossible when your brain is distracted and exhausted. You may end up giving more effort to your executive function in tough moments, but have less to “show” for it. Executive function struggles are not related to how hard you try.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">If you’re smart enough, you’ll have good executive function</h2>
<p dir="ltr">It’s a frustratingly common misconception that being intelligent means you won’t struggle with executive function. In fact, teachers still share with me that they question whether students with executive function needs belong in advanced or gifted programs. Intelligence and executive function are entirely separate. In fact, a study in <em>Nature</em> found that the rate of thickening of the cerebral cortex is associated with both executive function and IQ, but not how you might think. The study found that the longer the child’s cortex is thinner, the more likely they are to have both a high IQ and slower executive function development, since executive function skills rely on cortical thickening. In short, struggling with executive function does not indicate that you’re not intelligent.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Taking initiative only takes willpower</h2>
<p dir="ltr">“Just do it” might be a catchy slogan, but that line of thinking often isn’t helpful where executive function is concerned. Many people who struggle to initiate a task will share that they are both highly motivated and know what to do, but it’s the crossing of the bridge between intention and action that is so challenging. Getting started on a task relies on executive function to plan, prioritize, manage attention, chunk the task into steps, and more. Having a tough time getting going doesn’t mean you’re lacking willpower, but likely reflects an executive function challenge that can be matched with a strategy.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Dispelling harmful misunderstandings matters. It helps us release some of the shame and guilt that occurs when we tie executive function struggles to morality. When we embrace that it is a wonderfully human thing to have executive function needs, we are able to normalize needing strategies and support. And that, my friends, will make us unstoppable.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/brain-tools-school/202602/executive-function-myths-that-need-to-go" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/brain-tools-school/202602/executive-function-myths-that-need-to-go</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/brain-tools-school/202602/executive-function-myths-that-need-to-go</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah Kesty]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-ola-dapo-1754561-3521937.jpg?itok=91fsuzKm" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Overhead-Free Strategy That Tripled Donations]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/petrocelli_photo-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=5RiDK0OQ" alt="John V. Petrocelli, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Behavioral Economics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Overhead-Free Strategy That Tripled Donations</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How charity: water cracked the code on donor psychology</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">An experiment with 40,000 donors found zero-overhead guarantees nearly tripled donations vs. standard appeals.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">71% chose a charity when overhead was pre-funded vs. 49% when donors paid it—same overhead, different framing.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Raising suggested donations from $20-30 to $60 kept participation stable but substantially increased amounts.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Matching programs don't attract new donors but cause existing supporters to increase gifts by about 30%.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Scott Harrison, founder and CEO of the nonprofit <em>charity: water</em> faced a brutal reality. His nonprofit was caught in the same exhausting cycle that torments every charitable organization: the annual donor exodus. Year after year, the vast majority of supporters would vanish, forcing the team to rebuild their entire funding base from scratch.</p>

<p>Harrison brought an unusual perspective. Before founding charity: water, he’d mastered persuasion psychology in Manhattan’s club scene. He suspected that traditional nonprofit thinking was missing something fundamental about human nature.</p>
<h2>The Fundraising Puzzle</h2>
<p>The fundraising playbook seemed carved in stone. For decades, nonprofits had relied on two primary strategies: showcasing early commitments from major backers and promising to multiply every gift through matching programs. Both approaches enjoyed robust academic support and widespread adoption.</p>

<p>The problem is that when you donate $100 to most charities, maybe $75 goes to programs (e.g., wells) and $25 goes to overhead (e.g., salaries, rent). Donors often view that $25 as “waste” even though it’s necessary to run the organization effectively.</p>
<p>So, charity: water’s solution was to get separate major donors to cover the $25 overhead entirely. The connection started when Scott Harrison cold-emailed tech leaders, including Mark Zuckerberg and MySpace’s Tom Anderson, seeking advice on using technology for fundraising. Michael Birch (Bebo founder) responded, coded charity: water’s website, donated $1 million, and crucially introduced Harrison to other tech entrepreneurs. Wealthy tech entrepreneurs and philanthropists who understood the value of operational infrastructure (Sean Parker, Facebook co-founder; Jack Dorsey, Twitter founder; Chris Sacca, investor; Kevin Rose, Digg founder; Daniel Ek, Spotify founder; Shakil Khan, early tech executive) got on board.</p>

<p>So public donors could give $100 knowing it <em>all </em>goes to wells. Same total budget, but donors feel their contribution has 100 percent direct impact. Donors don’t mind that overhead exists—they just don’t want their money paying for it. They want to feel their personal contribution creates direct change in the cause they care about.</p>

<h2>The Signal</h2>
<p>Researchers working with charity: water decided to challenge everything. Working with an education foundation, they orchestrated an experiment involving 40,000 potential donors. One experimental group received a fundamentally different proposition: complete assurance that administrative expenses had been pre-funded, guaranteeing that their entire contribution would flow directly toward program delivery, no overhead (i.e., administrative and operational costs that keep a nonprofit running, but don’t go directly to the cause itself).</p>

<p><strong>The results were seismic:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Standard solicitation: 3.36 percent response rate, $8,040 total</li>
<li>Early commitment messaging: 4.75 percent response rate, $13,220 total</li>
<li>Matching opportunity: 4.41 percent response rate, $12,210 total</li>
<li><strong>Zero-overhead guarantee: 8.55 percent response rate, $23,120 total</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>The administrative-cost-free approach nearly tripled donations. In fundraising, where marginal improvements are celebrated, these results represented a paradigm shift.</p>

<h2>The Second Discovery: Permission vs. Price</h2>
<p>charity: water’s own experiments revealed two additional breakthroughs that shattered conventional wisdom.</p>
<p><strong>The $60 Anchor:</strong> Their donation interface historically suggested modest amounts between $20-30, preloaded into the donation box online. When they elevated the baseline suggestion to $60, participation rates remained stable while contribution amounts substantially increased. Higher anchors didn’t deter donors—they authorized greater generosity.</p>

<p><strong>The Matching Paradox:</strong> When charity: water promoted “donation doubling,” the total number of contributors remained unchanged. But existing supporters dramatically altered their behavior—people prepared to give $50 elevated their gifts to $65, a 30 percent increase.</p>
<p>The pattern was clear: <em>Financial capacity rarely limits generosity—social uncertainty about appropriate giving levels does.</em></p>

<h2>The Revelation</h2>
<p>Researchers investigated the psychological mechanisms through a controlled study with 449 participants. The findings illuminated the truth: <em>Donors don’t object to organizational overhead—they simply prefer not funding it directly.</em></p>
<p>When participants learned that a charity allocated 50 percent of donations to administrative functions, only 49 percent selected it. However, when informed that identical overhead expenses were pre-covered by other sources, 71 percent chose that same organization.</p>



  


<p>This wasn’t about operational assessment. It concerned personal agency. Contributors wanted confidence that their specific investment created tangible progress on issues they valued.</p>
<h2>The Strategy</h2>
<p>charity: water’s discoveries reveal four transformative principles:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Prioritize individual agency over institutional performance.</strong> Contributors focus on how their personal investment generates change rather than organizational efficiency metrics.</li>
<li><strong>Distinguish acquisition from amplification tactics.</strong> Zero-overhead messaging attracts new supporters; elevated anchors and matching programs increase existing supporter generosity.</li>
<li><strong>Separate operational funding from impact funding.</strong> By securing administrative support independently, organizations enable supporters to experience direct-impact satisfaction.</li>
<li><strong>Question industry orthodoxy.</strong> The most effective strategies frequently contradict established practices.</li>
</ol>

<h2>The Actionable Framework</h2>
<p>For organizations seeking enhanced engagement:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diagnose permission barriers.</strong> What prevents your audience from maximizing their investment?</li>
<li><strong>Isolate “infrastructure” from “impact.”</strong> Can you restructure so that supporters feel their investment targets what matters most to them?</li>
<li><strong>Test counter-intuitive approaches.</strong> Which “proven” strategy might actually limit results?</li>
</ul>

<h2>The Experiment to Run</h2>
<p><strong>Hypothesis:</strong> Restructuring value propositions around individual agency will enhance engagement more than conventional approaches.</p>
<p><strong>Method:</strong> Create two versions of your primary value proposition. Version A maintains your current strategy. Version B eliminates operational efficiency language, focusing exclusively on direct impact.</p>

<p><strong>Success Metrics:</strong> Track response rates plus longer-term engagement (retention, repeat interactions, referrals).</p>
<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Allow 2-4 weeks for meaningful insights.</p>
<p><strong>The Bottom Line:</strong> charity: water’s breakthrough reveals that people don’t just give money—they purchase feelings. The most compelling proposition isn’t about your organization’s capabilities; it’s about the supporter’s personal agency. When individuals feel their investment creates direct, unmediated change, they don’t merely contribute more—they return consistently.</p>

<p><em>The insight isn’t about the dollar amount. It’s about inviting people to purchase something unavailable elsewhere: absolute certainty that their resources are transforming lives.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/toward-a-more-critically-discerning-world/202602/the-overhead-free-strategy-that-tripled" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/toward-a-more-critically-discerning-world/202602/the-overhead-free-strategy-that-tripled</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/toward-a-more-critically-discerning-world/202602/the-overhead-free-strategy-that-tripled</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[John V. Petrocelli, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Coins.jpg?h=bdbdce41&amp;itok=w8K8H5-v" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Ways to Be Nimble in a Rapidly Changing World]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/alice_boyes.jpg?itok=beWKdmMs" alt="Alice Boyes Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Cognition</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Ways to Be Nimble in a Rapidly Changing World</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How flexible thinkers can thrive when systems aren't perfect.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_gzt9fogzt9fogzt9%20(1).png.jpg?itok=CK_sqxEH" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="AI Generated Image" alt="AI Generated Image"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI Generated Image</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Let me start with a quick story: One of my <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202512/5-types-of-hobbies-that-can-build-self-discipline">hobbies</a> is collecting miles and points (e.g., airline miles and hotel points).</p>
<p>In this arena, opportunities open and disappear constantly. Programs devalue overnight (e.g., requiring far more points for the same flight), advantageous loopholes close, and new cards and promotions become available. It's a constant game of cat and mouse.</p>

<p>What was good advice or the best way to do something three months ago often isn't anymore.</p>
<p>Everything about the hobby is always in flux. For example, I was about to cancel a card because of a huge increase in the annual fee, and then the bank dropped an offer to receive a $359 health tracker for free, making me glad I hadn't yet.</p>

<p>Why am I telling this story? Because operating in that volatile environment is what has prepared me better than anything else in my life to deal with (a) corporations and (b) rapidly changing or fuzzy scenarios.</p>
<p>Thriving in a fast-changing world, characterized by imperfect (and sometimes unfair) systems requires being <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202601/how-to-cultivate-an-experimenters-mindset">flexible and nimble</a> in specific ways. Here are three that can help you navigate whatever volatile systems you’re operating within.</p>

<h2>1. Ability to Adapt to Flexible Rules</h2>
<p>When we're children, we think in black and white and believe rules are hard and fast. As adults, as life experience kicks in, we begin to understand there are different sorts of rules.</p>
<p>We understand that not stealing is a hard rule. We might also understand that "don't wear jeans to work" means don't wear ratty jeans, or don't wear jeans on days the corporate team are visiting.</p>

<p>The practical takeaway: When you're allowed to break an unimportant rule, go with it. When you're not, don't make a fuss. Don't say, "But I was allowed to break the rule last week." Read the room. If you've been allowed to break an unimportant rule before, but suddenly you're not, let some time pass and poke it again.</p>

<p>Understand what a rule is trying to prevent. If what you're doing doesn't undermine that, and won't get anyone in trouble, you've found a rule that might be flexible.</p>
<h2>2. Know When to "Hang Up and Call Again"</h2>
<p>In the miles and points world, there is an infamous saying that you should never ask a customer service agent a question you don't already know the answer to. Miles and points experts often know more about the intricacies of certain rewards programs than a lot of the customer service agents.</p>

<p>For example, if you need to book a complex flight award over the phone, only an agent who has done it before might know how to help you. The HUCA principle would tell you that if the first person you reach on the phone is struggling, rather than attempting to work with them, politely find a reason to end the call, then call back and try your luck with someone new.</p>

<p>This example might seem pretty specific, but the underlying principle is much broader than you'd expect. For example, with AI, when the AI agent is stuck, it's often better to clear the context and start from a blank slate than try to get it out of its loop of stuckness. Something in the existing context (the work you've done in the session) has essentially <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2602.11988">poisoned or hijacked their reasoning</a>. You don't have to know what it was. You can clear all the context and start fresh.</p>

<p>The general principle: if the capability you need exists in the system, but your current interaction can't access it, the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202601/7-ways-to-increase-your-resourcefulness">nimble move is resetting </a>the interaction. If prior context is poisoning an interaction, start fresh.</p>
<h2>3. Learn to Deal With Half-Baked Technology</h2>
<p>We build up expertise with tools by using them. The best tools are often developer versions or labeled as "labs" or "experiments." The companies making them are offering them to test but warning you they will have bugs and unexpected behavior.</p>



  


<p>AI is evolving so fast that if you're used to very polished, "dummy-proof" versions of tools, you might experience an expectations mismatch when using cutting-edge ones. If you only want the very safe versions where the company has put in all the guardrails for you, you're going to be limited in what you can use.</p>

<p>What being adaptable means here: Learn what's important to understand (e.g., security considerations) and what you can gloss over. Good metacognition is invaluable, like being aware of the Dunning-Kruger effect and also of how cleverly designed products have manipulated our attention and motivation throughout the internet era.</p>

<p>Don't delay your start on gaining expertise until tools are perfect. But don't allow yourself to be manipulated unawares either.</p>
<h2>Being Nimble Relies on Both Meta-Cognition and Psychological Flexibility</h2>
<p>You may have noticed that everything I've called being nimble requires metacognition and psychological flexibility. I knew the bank and the wearable manufacturer were manipulating me with the free health tracker (the bank to have me keep paying the huge annual fee, and the manufacturer to get me to try their product). I chose to let myself be the mouse caught by the cat in that specific situation, but I didn't do it blindly.</p>

<p>All three skills I've presented work the same way. They're about making good observations and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202512/5-tips-for-naturally-cautious-people">responding flexibly rather than rigidly</a>. They require you to anchor yourself in ethics and meet systems where they are rather than getting frustrated about the way things "should be."</p>
<p>A fast-moving world can feel anxiety-provoking. We can easily feel like successfully navigating it requires skills we don't yet have, or strengths that don't come naturally. However, what we need to expertly traverse volatile, imperfect systems can be broken down into some key fundamentals: meta-cognition and flexible thinking. When we see this, it can help us realize we already have the core building blocks of what's required to thrive.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/3-ways-to-be-nimble-in-a-rapidly-changing-world" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/3-ways-to-be-nimble-in-a-rapidly-changing-world</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/3-ways-to-be-nimble-in-a-rapidly-changing-world</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Alice Boyes Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_gzt9fogzt9fogzt9%20%281%29.png.jpg?itok=no9Ew3II" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>