<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 16:28:41 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 16:28:41 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Adaptability Advantage: How to Thrive in a Changing World]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/jamie_gruman.jpg?itok=hqETDOnP" alt="Jamie Gruman Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Positive Psychology</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Adaptability Advantage: How to Thrive in a Changing World</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Research suggests that specific tactics can help you be more adaptable.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The world seems to be changing at an accelerating pace.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Adaptability is key to success in a changing world.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Specific tactics can help make us more adaptable.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/geralt%20pixaby%20III.png.jpg?itok=n6UOYFx8" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Geralt/Pixabay" alt="Geralt/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Geralt/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The modern pace of change can be unnerving. Both <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/janesparrow/2024/03/18/the-acceleration-of-change-requires-a-special-set-of-leadership-skills/">practitioner</a> and academic sources suggest that the pace of change is accelerating. Today, advances in artificial intelligence (AI) force many employees to update their approach to work every few months and sometimes find new jobs. Modern crises, such as the COVID pandemic, forced people across the entire planet to adapt to new realities almost instantaneously. In such a dynamic world, a particularly useful resource is adaptability.</p>

<p>Adaptability is the ability to adjust oneself in order to function effectively in different or shifting situations. It has cognitive, emotional, and behavioral components, and can be <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2013-14504-001">measured</a> with items such as “I am able to think through a number of possible options to assist me in a new situation” and “When uncertainty arises, I am able to minimize frustration or irritation so I can deal with it best.” Research has shown that adaptability is associated with <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2013-14504-001">academic outcomes</a> such as school enjoyment and <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0001879116300604?via%3Dihub">career success</a>, and the flexibility associated with adaptability promotes <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272735810000413?via%3Dihub">psychological health</a>.</p>

<p>So, how do we promote adaptability so that we can thrive in a changing world? There is <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doiLanding?doi=10.1037%2Famp0000163">not a lot</a> of research on adaptability, but the research that does exist offers us some suggestions that allow us to produce an adaptability advantage.</p>
<p><strong>Acknowledge Your Emotions. </strong>When change unfolds,<strong> </strong>you are not expected to be an unemotional robot.<strong> </strong>A little bit of occasional change can feel exciting. A lot of constant change can feel overwhelming. Having to make changes because your job was overtaken by AI can make you angry and resentful. These reactions are normal. Accept them. In addition, try to develop an attitude of curiosity, which has been suggested as an <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0090261625000312?via%3Dihub">important part of adaptability</a> and also an <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jclp.20326">aspect of mindfulness</a>, which can help you cope with the stress and negative emotions associated with change, and consider how best to adapt. The ability to <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doiLanding?doi=10.1037%2F0021-9010.85.4.612">handle stress</a> is a key component of adaptability.</p>

<p><strong>Diversify.</strong> Don’t put all your eggs in one basket. The <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doiLanding?doi=10.1037%2Fa0040367">diversified portfolio model of adaptability</a> suggests that adaptability is enhanced by engaging in many activities, having a wide set of experiences, and occupying a variety of roles, such as parent, volunteer, and pickleball partner. This occurs because such a diversified set of life circumstances builds resilience, confidence, and a more complex self-concept that is protected from disruption when individual aspects of it are threatened by change. This makes you more adaptive. Varied experiences also foster a broad base of knowledge, which has been <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1540-5915.02375">shown</a> to be associated with adaptability in organizational contexts.</p>

<p><strong>Experiment and Be Willing to Fail. </strong>Adaptability requires that we creatively experiment with new mindsets, approaches, and behaviors. It is important to recognize that these experiments may not turn out well at first. But every failure generates valuable information that may redirect us to ultimate success. The willingness to try new things and potentially fail <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0894439320926087">has been shown</a> to be associated with the ability to adapt to novel technologies.</p>

<p><strong>Build and Leverage Relationships. </strong>Cultivating<strong> </strong>new relationships and leveraging old ones allows you to benefit from a network that offers interpersonal and problem-solving resources that can promote adaptability by expanding the assets you can draw on. Old and new relationships <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0090261625000312?via%3Dihub">can offer ideas, support, and advice</a> that support adaptability. This highlights that adaptability is influenced not only by personal resources but also by the external resources provided by the <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1534484319836315">context</a> in which people find themselves, which can help or hinder their ability to adapt.</p>

<p><strong>Have Fun.</strong> Negative emotions narrow our thinking, and positive emotions do the opposite. Positive emotions such as joy, contentment, and love <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doiLanding?doi=10.1037%2F0003-066X.56.3.218">broaden</a> our thinking and allow us to be <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272735810000413?via%3Dihub">more flexible</a> in the way we approach challenges. It is somewhat ironic, then, that when the challenges generated by the pace of change lead us to think that we should hunker down and brainstorm adaptive solutions, it may be just as valuable to relax, engage in enjoyable activities that foster positive emotions, and just let natural psychological processes do their thing.</p>


<p>The modern pace of change can be stressful, and there is no magic bullet that will make it pleasurable. There are, however, different ways of dealing with change that are more or less likely to help you adapt. Capitalizing on the former will promote the adaptability advantage.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dont-forget-the-basil/202602/the-adaptability-advantage-how-to-thrive-in-a-changing-world" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dont-forget-the-basil/202602/the-adaptability-advantage-how-to-thrive-in-a-changing-world</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dont-forget-the-basil/202602/the-adaptability-advantage-how-to-thrive-in-a-changing-world</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamie Gruman Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/geralt%20pixaby%20III.png.jpg?itok=UoVaTY9K" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Do I Worry?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/_Jaimie%20Lusk.png.jpg?itok=pk3Ao6Ph" alt="Jaimie L Lusk Psy.D., ABPP" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Anxiety</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Do I Worry?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Exploring the function of worry and finding new ways to work with it.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Worry is future-focused and often distracts from deeper emotions like sadness, guilt, anger, shame, or fear.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Chronic worry can harm emotional processing and physical health, and keep us from meeting core needs.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Worry persists because it feels protective, offers an illusion of control, and is reinforced by habit.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Compassionate awareness and boundary-setting are key to transforming worry into growth.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Worry is when your mind spins stories about what could go wrong, even when nothing is happening right now. Worry, a mental rehearsal of future dangers, is distinct from fear, which is a response to immediate threat (Barlow, 2002). Fear is your body’s alarm system, activating when you’re actually in danger. Worry, on the other hand, is like a smoke detector that keeps going off, even when there’s no fire.</p>

<p>Worry is a hallmark of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD), but it’s also a common experience for many people. While fear mobilizes us to act in the face of real danger, worry keeps us mentally busy, scanning for threats that may never materialize.</p>
<h2>The Hidden Costs of Worry</h2>
<p>Worry might seem helpful—maybe you believe it keeps you prepared, motivated, or safe. But what does it actually cost you?</p>

<p><strong>Worry Blocks Emotional Processing: </strong>Worry often acts as a distraction from deeper, more painful emotions. Instead of feeling sadness, shame, or loneliness, we stay agitated and hypervigilant. Borkovec and colleagues (2004) found that worry serves as a cognitive avoidance strategy, preventing processing of fearful imagery, which then serves to maintain emotional disorders like generalized anxiety disorder.</p>

<p><strong>Worry Masks Core Needs: </strong>When we worry, we may miss the messages our emotions are sending. For example, feeling shame might signal a need for validation; feeling lonely might signal a need for connection. Worry keeps us focused on hypothetical problems, rather than tuning into what we truly need (Greenberg, 2015).</p>

<p><strong>Worry Takes a Toll on Our Minds and Bodies: </strong>Chronic worry keeps the body in a state of fight or flight. Worry impairs problem-solving abilities and contributes to self-doubt and a diminished sense of agency (Sweeny &amp; Dooley, 2017). Physical symptoms can include restlessness, muscle tension, irritability, fatigue, and sleep disturbances. Over time, this can lead to chronic health problems.</p>

<p><strong>Worry Steals Joy and Purpose: </strong>Perhaps most insidiously, worry can keep us from doing things we value. When we’re preoccupied with what might go wrong, we miss out on meaningful experiences and relationships.</p>
<h2>Why Do We Worry? The (False) Promise of Protection</h2>
<p>If worry is so costly, why do we do it? </p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Worry as Motivation and Control: </strong>Many people believe that worrying helps them prepare for the worst, avoid mistakes, or solve problems. While excessive worry rarely leads to effective action, it creates an illusion of control over the uncontrollable. (Sweeny &amp; Dooley, 2017).</li>
<li><strong>Superstitious Thinking: </strong>Sometimes, people believe that worrying actually prevents bad things from happening. When someone worries excessively, then the feared event doesn’t occur, they may perceive that the worry “worked”—much like carrying a lucky charm (Wells, 1995).</li>
<li><strong>Distraction From Pain: </strong>Worry can distract from more distressing experiences, such as past traumas or painful relationships. It’s easier to worry about the future than to feel the ache of loss, traumas, and morally injurious events.</li>
<li><strong>Habit and Emotional Buffering: </strong>Worry becomes a habit, reinforced by repetition. For some, it can be a way to titrate trauma—serving as a buffer against emotional highs and lows. They may think it is better to stay in a constant state of mild anxiety than risk being blindsided by despair (Newman &amp; Llera, 2011).</li>
<li><strong>Defense Against Uncertainty: </strong>Ultimately, worry is a defense against the unpredictability of life. It’s a way to brace against the unknown, even if it keeps us stuck (Dugas et al., 1998). </li>
</ul>

<h2>Understanding and Working With Worry</h2>
<p>So how do you begin to shift your relationship with worry? Start by getting curious about what worry is really like for you:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>How do I worry?</strong> Notice your patterns—do you catastrophize, ruminate, replay scenarios?</li>
<li><strong>What drives my worries?</strong> Is it fear of loss, humiliation, disconnection, boredom, or danger? Is it something else?</li>
<li><strong>What is the impact?</strong> How does worry affect your mood, body, and ability to focus?</li>
</ul>


<p>Just noticing your worry and starting to understand it better can begin to break its hold on your life.</p>
<h2>Steps to Working Through Chronic Worry</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Stay With the Pain: </strong>Instead of avoiding uncomfortable feelings, gently notice the thoughts, sensations, and urges that come with worry. Mindfulness-based approaches have been shown to reduce worry and anxiety by increasing awareness and acceptance (Hoge et al., 2013).</li>
<li><strong>Explore Catastrophizing: </strong>Notice when your mind jumps to the worst-case scenario. Ask yourself: “Is this likely? What evidence do I have? How will I cope with it if the worst thing happens?”</li>
<li><strong>Articulate Unmet Needs: </strong>Go deeper—what is the worry protecting you from? Underneath the worry, there are other emotions. Perhaps sadness, fear, guilt, shame, or anger. Notice what unmet needs those emotions are pointing to. Perhaps the need for safety, comfort, reassurance, validation, joy, connection, provision, guidance, or protection. Naming these needs can help you address them directly.</li>
<li><strong>Express Compassion and Grieve: </strong>Allow yourself to feel compassion for the part of you that worries. Grieve what was missed or lost, and let in kindness. Say to your worried little self, “This is hard. I’m here for you. Let's get you some support.” Self-compassion practices have been linked to lower anxiety and greater resilience (Neff &amp; Germer, 2013).</li>
<li><strong>Find Protective Anger: </strong>Sometimes, worry covers up anger at being hurt or unprotected. Tapping into healthy anger can help you set boundaries.</li>
<li><strong>Set Boundaries With Your Worried Self: </strong>Imagine your worry as a separate voice—an overzealous protector. Thank it for trying to help, and then set a boundary: “I hear you, but I’m choosing to focus on what matters right now.”</li>
<li><strong>Do What You Can Do: </strong>Get to work, attempting to at least partially meet unmet needs.</li>
</ol>

<h2>Mindfulness Exercise</h2>
<p>Sit quietly and notice where worry shows up in your body. Is it a tightness in your chest, a flutter in your stomach, a buzzing in your mind? Place a gentle hand there. Breathe in whatever safety is available in the moment. Breathe out your worry, letting go of any extra vigilance that is not needed right now. Repeat for a few minutes, allowing this practice to soften the edges of your worry.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/threshold/202602/why-do-i-worry" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/threshold/202602/why-do-i-worry</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/threshold/202602/why-do-i-worry</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jaimie L Lusk Psy.D., ABPP]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-liza-summer-6382637.jpg?itok=DCx1CLBJ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Breaking Free From Childhood Patterns]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-06/Paul%20Dunion.png.jpg?itok=0M8shGnk" alt="Paul J. Dunion Ed.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Adverse Childhood Experiences</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Breaking Free From Childhood Patterns</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to move beyond reproducing and compensating for childhood patterns.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Childhood patterns deeply influence adult beliefs and behaviors.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It can be difficult to interrupt the tendency to either reproduce or compensate for these patterns.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Compensation behaviors may look positive but can be harmful.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Learning to detect and interrupt these behaviors can help you develop your own beliefs and unique qualities.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/javier-allegue-barros-55bVEzGVnzY-unsplash.jpeg.jpg?itok=Zh1JEfFO" width="215" height="321" data-insert-type="image" title="Javier Allegue Barros / Unsplash" alt="Javier Allegue Barros / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Javier Allegue Barros / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>A critical piece of information is understanding how we carry childhood patterns of beliefs, behaviors, and emotions into adulthood. These dynamics are easily introduced to our young, malleable psyches. Immediate family members, relatives, teachers, clergy, and coaches present us with prescribed ways to live. The beliefs we inherit describe convictions about religion, work, money, and relationships. These early templates include how to relate to emotions, with the options being suppression or expression. As we step into adulthood, we either reproduce what we learned or compensate for it.</p>

<h2>Reproducing</h2>
<p>Reproducing patterns of beliefs, behaviors, and emotions usually occurs unconsciously. We don’t typically choose to be like one of our parents. A reproduction might first come to our attention when a spouse boldly says, “You’re just like your father!”—a comment we don’t usually receive as favorable. Yet it is those around us who seem to see first how we are reproducing our pasts. </p>

<h2>Interrupting a Reproduction</h2>
<p>Let’s look at several ways we can interrupt a reproduction and let go of what doesn’t belong to us.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Accept that reproducing beliefs, behaviors, and emotional patterns is natural</em>. They were simply our earliest maps of how to be a person. And a reproduction may or may not be who we actually are.</li>
<li><em>Be mindful that it is commonly blind loyalty that binds us to reproduce these patterns</em>. We may need to decide whether a reproduction is simply an act of loyalty or a reflection of who we really are. It may be a question of loyalty to the clan vs. loyalty to yourself.</li>
<li><em>Get honest.</em> It may call for a rigorous examination of a particular belief in order to ascertain what you actually believe and how similar or different it is from your family’s belief.</li>
<li><em>Talk about your views with someone you trust</em>. This can be quite helpful, especially with someone familiar with the experience of wanting to interrupt early adaptive patterns.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Interrupting Compensations</h2>
<p>Compensating for early patterns is a bit more difficult to detect. These behaviors are often cloaked with the striving to bring a measure of excellence into our lives. Hence, they can not only seem harmless but also make us look good. Because compensation is driven by “I won’t be like my father or mother,” it’s difficult to know if you are choosing to be something or choosing not to be something. Compensation can spread. The father of a 10-year-old son felt abandoned by his own father when he was 10. He compensates by spending excessive time and energy fathering his son, trying to ensure his son doesn’t turn out like him and doesn't neglect him. He then unconsciously expects his son to also compensate by being happy, content, and responsible, allegedly demonstrating his success as a father.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Here are some steps for interrupting compensations.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Remain curious</em>. Because compensating often has us looking good, for instance, being exceptionally responsible or excessively attending to the needs of others, we may not notice compensation.</li>
<li><em>Look for opposites</em>. If a parent struggles to hold a job, look for compensatory workaholism. If a parent was extremely frugal, look for a tendency toward compulsive spending.</li>
<li><em>Decide upon the impact of the compensation on your life and the life of those close to you. </em>Then decide if you’re ready to let it go. If you are ready, decide if you need support. </li>
<li><em>Get help. </em>If you’re not sure about interrupting a compensation, get help from a friend or a professional counselor who has experience with compensations.</li>
</ul>

<p>The revelatory work of interrupting either reproductions of the past or compensations for it serves our individuation and the liberation of our uniqueness. Both dynamics can reflect the heavy weight of legacies created by generations. When reproduction or compensation appears on the back of a legacy, it may be advisable to seek professional support for an interruption. </p>

<p><em>To find a therapist, please visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a>.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-secular-mystic-path/202602/breaking-free-from-childhood-patterns" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-secular-mystic-path/202602/breaking-free-from-childhood-patterns</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-secular-mystic-path/202602/breaking-free-from-childhood-patterns</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Paul J Dunion Ed.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/javier-allegue-barros-55bVEzGVnzY-unsplash.jpeg.jpg?itok=j9uP9QnZ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>