<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 02:13:56 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 02:13:56 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gabapentin for Chronic Pain, a Safe Alternative to Opioids?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-03/Mager.jpg?itok=H7OKbwjp" alt="Dan Mager MSW, LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Chronic Pain</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Gabapentin for Chronic Pain, a Safe Alternative to Opioids?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">In the face of increased use, new research questions long-held assumptions.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Gabapentin is FDA approved to treat seizure disorders and the nerve pain syndrome often linked to shingles.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It is often prescribed off label for chronic pain conditions and viewed as a safer alternative to opioids.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Prescriptions for gabapentin in the U.S. per 1,000 people more than doubled from 2010 to 2024.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">New research links gabapentin prescriptions for chronic back pain with higher risks for dementia.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/geralt-dementia-595638_1920%20copy.jpeg.jpg?itok=xPZETKn5" width="320" height="453" data-insert-type="image" title="Gerd Altmann from Pixabay" alt="Gerd Altmann from Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Gerd Altmann from Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Gabapentin is an anticonvulsant medication that is FDA approved for the treatment of seizure disorders and postherpetic neuralgia—a chronic, often debilitating, nerve pain syndrome often linked to shingles. It is classified as an anticonvulsant and a GABA analogue, meaning it mimics the neurotransmitter gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA), which normally reduces nerve excitability. An extended-release version (gabapentin enacarbil) is approved for restless legs syndrome.</p>

<p>Gabapentin works by calming overactive nerve activity in the brain and nervous system, primarily through interactions with calcium channels. However, it is also frequently prescribed off label for a variety of chronic pain conditions and generally viewed as a safer alternative to opioids. As a result, over the last 15 years, prescriptions for gabapentin have increased dramatically. This coincides with burgeoning awareness of and concern about the opioid epidemic that began around this time, and subsequent to the significant relaxing of opioid prescribing standards to include chronic pain conditions.</p>

<p>A September 2025 report by CDC researchers in <em>Annals of Internal Medicine</em> documented gabapentin's rapid rise in the U.S. Prescriptions for gabapentin per 1,000 people more than doubled from 2010 to 2024, while the number of Americans taking this medication nearly tripled—from 5.8 million to 15.5 million. In 2024 gabapentin was the fifth most dispensed drug in U.S. retail pharmacies.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a></p>

<h2>More Prescriptions = Greater Risk</h2>
<p>But perhaps the most concerning recent finding about gabapentin came from a 2025 study that linked gabapentin prescriptions for chronic low back pain with increased risks for cognitive impairment and dementia, especially in younger people. Among more than 52,000 adults tracked over the course of 10 years through U.S. healthcare claims records, chronic pain patients with six or more gabapentin prescriptions had a higher incidence of mild cognitive impairment and dementia compared with those who were not prescribed gabapentin. The research, published in <em>Regional Anesthesia &amp; Pain Medicine</em>, found that dementia risk was more than double, while mild cognitive impairment risk was more than triple, among those ages 35 to 49. Results among those ages 50 to 64 years were similar.<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a></p>

<p>This research was based on a retrospective cohort study of more than 26,000 adults diagnosed with chronic low back pain using the TriNetX national database of de-identified patient records from 2004 to 2024. Importantly, those with prior gabapentin use, dementia, epilepsy, stroke, or cancer were excluded. Risks for both cognitive impairment and dementia increased further with prescription frequency: Patients with 12 or more prescriptions had a higher incidence of both conditions than those prescribed gabapentin 3-11 times.</p>

<p>Adding fuel to this unease, a recent analysis in <em>JAMA Network Open</em> questioned whether prescribing cascades—a pattern in which the adverse effects of one medication are treated with another—were tied to gabapentinoid-induced edema. A study of medical records of gabapentin-treated military veterans showed that clinicians almost never explicitly considered gabapentinoid effects when treating edema with diuretics, commonly attributing fluid build-up to congestive heart failure or venous stasis. Nearly one in four patients had potential harms from such a resulting prescribing cascade.<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a></p>

<p>Moreover, global research mirrors U.S. concerns. A 2025 review of qualitative studies in the <em>European Journal of Pain</em> indicated that uncertainty was a recurring theme, with clinicians worldwide saying there was lack of guidance for starting, monitoring, or tapering gabapentinoid use.<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a></p>
<h2>Gabapentin and Self-Harm</h2>


<p>Long-standing fears about gabapentin and self-harm also were re-examined in a U.K. self-controlled case series published in the <em>BMJ</em> in April 2025. It found that self-harm risk rose in the 90 days before gabapentin treatment, persisted during the early treatment period before dropping to a reference level, and rose again within 14 days after treatment stopped. While the findings didn’t support a direct effect of gabapentin related to self-harm, it demonstrates the importance of careful patient monitoring of self-harm throughout the process of treatment with gabapentin.<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a></p>

<p>Full disclosure: I began my personal recovery journey after being on prescription opioids for eight years for my own chronic pain in late 2006. Subsequently, I took gabapentin for approximately two years. I chose to discontinue it after being unable to identify any notable beneficial effects and in consultation with my prescribing physician.</p>



  


<p>The common side effects of gabapentin include drowsiness, dizziness, blurry or double vision, and difficulty with coordination and concentration. Chronic pain frequently causes tremendous and wearying distress for those afflicted with it. However, it’s essential for medical professionals to ensure (to the maximum extent possible) that the treatment doesn’t create more problems than it ameliorates.</p>

<p>Copyright 2026 Dan Mager, LCSW</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/some-assembly-required/202602/gabapentin-for-chronic-pain-a-safe-alternative-to-opioids" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/some-assembly-required/202602/gabapentin-for-chronic-pain-a-safe-alternative-to-opioids</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/some-assembly-required/202602/gabapentin-for-chronic-pain-a-safe-alternative-to-opioids</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Dan Mager MSW, LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/geralt-dementia-595638_1920%20copy.jpeg.jpg?itok=_mmOTu_0" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are You Creating Trust?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/nick_morgan_1.jpg?itok=2PVETKxz" alt="Nick Morgan Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Trust</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Are You Creating Trust?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">You might argue that nothing much happens in organizational life without trust.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>Trust. You might argue that nothing much happens in organizational life without it. Leaders need to trust their workers. Workers need to trust their leaders. Customers and companies need to trust each other, as well as suppliers and companies, and so on. When there’s a circle of trust, good things can happen. When trust is lacking, everything is hard – or stuck.</p>

<p>So, what can neuroscience teach us about trust? Most generally, we know that trust is something we decide unconsciously in areas where we make all our important decisions. That means that it happens fast – we decide, for example, that a face is the face of someone we can trust in less than half a second.</p>

<p>But what else happens in our brains that might surprise us as far as trust is concerned? Here are five recent insights from neuroscience about what builds trust.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Expressive faces are more trustworthy</strong> (<a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-62902-6">Kavanagh et al., 2024</a>). If we can see the emotions playing across your face, we’re more likely to trust you. That's probably because we feel like we know you, and we know what you might do under a variety of circumstances.</li>
<li><strong>Sharing secrets builds trust</strong>. (<a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1037/pspi0000441">Kardas et al., 2023</a>). We worry that people will judge us for our secrets, but the research shows that they like us better and trust us more. And we shed the burden of keeping secrets, which is a heavy one for most of us. So share away!</li>
<li><strong>Use the "Mona Lisa smile</strong>." (<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0146167215591495">Hehman et al., 2015</a>). This study has been around for a while, but it’s so simple that it’s a secret worth spreading: a slight smile (not a big grin) builds trust.</li>
<li><strong>Use the same language as me</strong>. (<a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1017/langcog.2024.27">Matzinger et al., 2024</a>). English is a polyglot language with many ways of expressing similar ideas. You say potato, I say po—tahhh-to. If we speak the same language sub-group, we’re more likely to trust each other, since we come from the same tribe.</li>
<li><strong>If all else fails, try humility</strong>. (<a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41562-024-02060-x">Koetke et al., 2024</a>). This study was particularly about scientists who display humility about their research, but it seems likely to apply to anyone who displays humility as well as expertise. We are more likely to trust you if you recognize your limits.</li>
</ol>

<p>Now we have a picture of someone we’d be likely to trust immediately: someone whose face is an open book, who is sharing personal stuff with us with a slight smile on their face, sending out a couple of tribal indicators in the language they use, and someone who admits that they don’t know everything.</p>

<p>Does that sound like anyone you know? Or is it a collection of traits you could pull off without too much of a stretch? Don’t try this if you score low on all of these measures; it’s likely that it would be too obvious and look like you were trying too hard – and that is not one of the trust indicators!</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/communications-that-matter/202602/are-you-creating-trust" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/communications-that-matter/202602/are-you-creating-trust</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/communications-that-matter/202602/are-you-creating-trust</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Nick Morgan Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Public-Words-Featured-Blog-Image-1200x800-1%20%281%29.jpg?itok=PlvO9_N2" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The One Question That Determines Your Good Death]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/Suzanne.png.jpg?itok=bQd6Xxrn" alt="Suzanne B. O’Brien RN" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Aging</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The One Question That Determines Your Good Death</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Quality of life defines care and shapes your good death.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When quality of life is undefined, medical care defaults to aggressive interventions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Early goals-of-care conversations reduce family anxiety and decisional regret.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Surrogate decision-makers face higher stress when wishes aren't discussed in advance.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Defining care preferences early aligns treatment and reduces unnecessary suffering.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>As a young oncology nurse, I cared for a woman in her late 80s whose cancer had overtaken her body.</p>
<p>She was scheduled for exploratory abdominal surgery.</p>
<p>When I entered her room to perform my assessment, I couldn't even find a place to place my stethoscope. Tumors were visibly protruding across her abdomen. Her disease was advanced beyond medical intervention.</p>

<p>Her family sat nearby, nervous and hopeful. I'm not a doctor, but even I knew that this surgery would be futile. The surgeon proceeded.</p>
<p>He opened her up-and closed her back up.</p>
<p>There was nothing medically that could be done.</p>
<p>I remember standing there asking myself: Why did this happen?</p>
<p>It wasn't because her family didn't love her.</p>

<p>It wasn't because the physician lacked skill.</p>
<p>It wasn't because anyone was indifferent.</p>
<p>It happened because this beautiful, sweet woman had not clearly defined what <em>quality of life meant to her.</em></p>
<p>When quality of life is undefined, medicine defaults to intervention.</p>
<h2>The Default Toward "Doing More"</h2>
<p>Modern medicine is structured to treat, extend, and attempt to fix. Doctors are trained to offer options. Families are told, "This is what we can do".</p>

<p>But "what we can do" is rarely defined. And neither is the clarity of how truly advanced the patient's disease process is.</p>
<p>In the absence of clearly stated goals, escalation often becomes the default path — particularly in moments of fear and crisis.</p>
<p>Psychologically, this is predictable. Under acute stress, the amygdala becomes more active, narrowing cognitive flexibility and increasing threat-based decision-making. Families and patients confronted with sudden decline often experience what researchers describe as "decision conflict", a state associated with heightened anxiety and impaired clarity.</p>

<p>Without a predetermined benchmark, <em>fear hijacks the situation.</em></p>
<h2>The Question That Changes Everything</h2>
<p>There is one question that shifts this trajectory.</p>
<p><strong>What does quality of life mean to you, and when would you consider it no longer acceptable?</strong></p>
<p>Quality of life is subjective. For some, it means being able to recognize loved ones. For others, it means independence, mobility, cognitive clarity, or freedom from pain.</p>

<p>There is no universally correct answer. This is a subjective one. But <em>there must be an answer.</em></p>
<p>Research on advance care planning consistently shows that when individuals clarify and communicate their wishes in advance, end-of-life care is more likely to align with their values. Patients and families experience less stress, anxiety, and depression when preferences are known ahead of time.</p>

<p>Once a person defines their quality of life threshold, it becomes a decision-making benchmark. When that benchmark is no longer attainable, care can pivot — from prolongation at all costs (and those costs are high ) to comfort, presence, and alignment.</p>
<p>Without that clarity, families are left to decide under pressure. Studies indicate that surrogate decision-makers often suffer long-term emotional consequences, including symptoms consistent with post-traumatic stress, when making high-stakes decisions without prior guidance. I have seen this many times in my career.</p>


<p>In my experience, serving over 1000 people at the end of life, most traumatic grief is not caused by death itself; it is caused by unplanned medical escalation that conflicts with what the person might have truly wanted—<em>had they shared this ahead of time.</em></p>
<h2>Why We Avoid the Conversation</h2>
<p>Culturally, we treat death as a medical failure rather than a natural, human experience. Conversations about decline are often postponed out of fear that discussing limits will diminish hope.</p>

<p>But evidence suggests the opposite.</p>
<p>Studies of patients with advanced illness have shown that early goals-of-care conversations are associated with improved quality of life and, in some cases, even longer survival compared to aggressive late-stage interventions.</p>
<p>Planning does not extinguish hope. It clarifies it.</p>



  


<p>It reframes hope from "cure at any cost" to "care aligned with my values and my choices."</p>
<p>Psychologically, anticipatory dialogue reduces uncertainty. Research in behavioral health consistently shows that perceived control — even when outcomes cannot be changed — reduces anxiety and increases emotional resilience. </p>

<p>Avoidance, on the other hand, transfers the burden forward to a future moment of crisis.</p>
<h2>Most People Want to Die at Home</h2>
<p>National surveys repeatedly show that most Americans would prefer to die at home. Yet the majority still die in hospitals or other institutional settings.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Christine.JPG.jpg?itok=3JPwrjkT" width="320" height="693" data-insert-type="image" alt="Suzanne and Doulagiver Client" title="Suzanne B. O'Brien RN"></div>
<div class="caption">Suzanne and Doulagiver Client</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Suzanne B. O'Brien RN</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Why the disconnect?</p>
<p>Preferences without planning are unlikely to be honored.</p>
<p>If someone wishes to remain at home, that requires logistical preparation, caregiver education, and medical coordination. Without that groundwork, hospitalization becomes the default during acute decline.</p>
<p>The system moves quickly. <em>Fear moves even faster.</em></p>

<h2>A Good Death Begins Earlier Than We Think</h2>
<p>A good death does not begin in the final days of life.</p>
<p>It begins the moment someone defines how they want to live.</p>
<p>Answering the quality of life question does not hasten death. It anchors care in clarity. It protects families from guessing. It provides doctors with instruction. </p>

<p>Most importantly, It restores subjective agency.</p>
<p>We cannot avoid death. But we <em>can reduce the amount of unnecessary suffering around it.</em></p>
<p>And often, that reduction begins with one conversation and one question:</p>
<p>What does quality of life mean to me?</p>
<p>And when would you not want extended measures to keep you alive, when that quality is no longer there.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-rebirth-of-death/202602/the-one-question-that-determines-your-good-death" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-rebirth-of-death/202602/the-one-question-that-determines-your-good-death</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-rebirth-of-death/202602/the-one-question-that-determines-your-good-death</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Suzanne B. O’Brien RN]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Christine.JPG.jpg?itok=yUGb-IWG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why We Love the Olympics and How Watching Uplifts Us]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/eva_ritvo.jpg?itok=JFvjoTw_" alt="Eva Ritvo M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sport and Competition</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why We Love the Olympics and How Watching Uplifts Us</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Witnessing human excellence inspires kindness, connection, and personal growth.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Witnessing courage and perseverance triggers moral elevation, boosting generosity and motivation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mirror neurons make athletes' triumphs and setbacks feel viscerally personal to viewers.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The Olympics' shared global focus reduces isolation and reinforces belonging.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Seeing elite athletes fail and recover helps viewers cultivate self-compassion.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">There's something profoundly moving about an athlete on the podium, tears streaming as their national anthem plays. Even thousands of miles away, we feel it; a lump in our own throat, a swell of emotion that surprises us. The Olympics aren't just a spectacular display of physical achievement; they're a cultural ritual that taps into deep psychological needs and offers real benefits for both individual mental health and our collective spirit.</p>

<p dir="ltr">At the heart of our response to the Olympics is moral elevation — that warm, inspirational feeling that arises when we witness acts of virtue, courage, or extraordinary human effort. When athletes demonstrate dedication, sportsmanship, and composure under immense pressure, they do far more than win medals. They model values we admire and want to embody.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Research on moral elevation shows that experiencing this emotion increases prosocial behavior, generosity, and motivation to improve ourselves. Watching an athlete help a fallen competitor or celebrate a seemingly impossible achievement can nudge us toward kinder actions, renewed commitment to personal goals, and a greater sense of purpose. Those fleeting moments of uplift ripple outward in ways that extend far beyond our viewing hours.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Part of what fuels moral elevation is our deep appreciation for beauty, symmetry, teamwork, and the aesthetic dimension of human excellence. The Olympics showcase these elements in their purest form: graceful movements executed with precision, synchronized teams moving as one, the striking balance between strength and elegance. Our brains are wired to find harmony inherently rewarding; witnessing physical artistry and coordinated effort triggers aesthetic pleasure that merges with moral awe.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Another powerful reason the Olympics inspire us is that they create a rare sense of shared attention on a massive scale. In daily life, our social world is fragmented. We inhabit different political camps, geographic regions, and cultural spheres. For about two weeks every two years, the Olympics interrupt that pattern. Millions watch the same performances, hold the same breath, celebrate the same triumphs. This collective focus fosters connection and belonging that nourishes us. Humans are social creatures; feeling part of something larger than ourselves supports mental well-being by reducing isolation and reinforcing shared meaning.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The universality of certain human experiences (failure, perseverance, grief, joy) makes Olympic stories especially potent. We recognize in athletes' journeys reflections of our own struggles and aspirations. Seeing elite performers confront setbacks or injuries reassures us that difficulty isn't a flaw but part of any meaningful path. That recognition cultivates self-compassion: We're less inclined to interpret our own stumbles as personal failures and more likely to view them as essential steps in growth.</p>

<p dir="ltr">We saw these dynamics play out vividly in this year's Games. Lindsey Vonn's crash and serious leg fracture could have ended only in bitterness, yet her public reflections emphasized "no regrets" and the acceptance that sometimes dreams end inches from where we hoped. Ilia Malinin's soaring expectations and painful meltdown on Olympic ice gave viewers a front-row seat to pressure, vulnerability, and the reality that even prodigies can falter. Piper Gilles' bronze medal in ice dance, achieved after surviving ovarian cancer and grieving the loss of her mother to brain cancer, transformed private suffering into shared beauty and joy. These stories teach empathy, normalize struggle, and offer living templates for how to keep going when life knocks us down.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Neuroscience helps explain why these stories strike so deep. Mirror neuron systems allow us to internally simulate others' actions and emotions, creating a visceral bridge between their experience and ours. When we see an athlete's triumph, our brains spark in ways similar to experiencing victory ourselves; when we see their tears, we often feel a corresponding pang. That empathy isn't a sentimental accident; it's an evolved capacity for group cohesion and cooperation, exactly what the Olympics celebrate.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The Games also honor slow mastery and discipline in a culture addicted to instant gratification. Athletes reveal that excellence is built in invisible increments, through repetition, patience, and quiet endurance. Witnessing their commitment can recalibrate our own sense of time and effort, renewing faith in gradual progress. For people struggling with motivation, seeing someone devote years to a single routine or race can act as a psychological nudge: it becomes easier to believe that small, consistent actions in our own lives might eventually add up to something meaningful.</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">But mindful viewing keeps that inspiration healthy. Excessive betting can evolve into problematic gambling behaviors; obsessive consumption at the expense of sleep and relationships leads to exhaustion and strained connections. Mindful viewing also means attending to the complexity behind the highlight reels (inequities in funding, access to training, and support structures that shape athletes' lives). Holding admiration for individual triumphs while recognizing these broader contexts deepens appreciation without simplifying reality, and opens avenues for constructive action: supporting community sports programs, advocating for athlete mental health resources, or promoting equitable access to training.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The collective ritual of watching the Olympics can be healing in times of global stress. The Games have periodically functioned as a balm when societies face crises, offering a vision of cooperation and excellence that counters despair. That symbolic power isn't merely sentimental; it can mobilize hope and remind us that human beings are capable of remarkable cooperation and creativity. Especially when public discourse is frayed, the shared experience of cheering for human potential can restore a sense of possibility and mutual regard.</p>

<p dir="ltr">And that brings us to what happens when the flame goes out. The closing ceremony doesn't have to mark the end of inspiration. The balance, beauty, and teamwork that move us during the Olympics aren't unique to sports; they're available in everyday life. The same joy we feel watching speed skaters or ice dancers can reappear when a family problem is solved collaboratively, when colleagues accomplish a shared goal, or when we bring grace and presence to our daily routines. The Games remind us not only of what humans can do, but of how beautiful it is when we move together toward a common good. In the arena of everyday life, courage, resilience, teamwork, and the pursuit of excellence are goals we can all strive toward.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/on-vitality/202602/why-we-love-the-olympics-and-how-watching-uplifts-us" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/on-vitality/202602/why-we-love-the-olympics-and-how-watching-uplifts-us</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/on-vitality/202602/why-we-love-the-olympics-and-how-watching-uplifts-us</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Eva Ritvo M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_27uj5l27uj5l27uj.jpg?itok=6g19ADY4" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>