<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 19:43:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 19:43:50 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Signs of Love]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-10/Larry_Carlat_FINALjpg-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=pHB0ghqE" alt="Larry Carlat" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Grief</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Signs of Love</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Your child is always with you because you carry them in your heart.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/SIGNS%20OF%20LOVE.jpeg.jpg?itok=namGNYOx" width="320" height="344" data-insert-type="image" title="Larry Carlat" alt="Larry Carlat"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Larry Carlat</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Your lost child is well onto their next journey, but they’re still here, there, and everywhere. All you have to do is look.</p>
<p>Your child is in the book you’re reading. Your child is on every other TV show you’re watching. Your child is in the bite of pizza you’re eating. Your child is in every song you listen to. Your child is in the marigolds sitting on your desk. Your child is staring back at you in the mirror.</p>

<p>Your child is always with you because <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202502/the-people-in-your-heart-will-make-you-cry">you carry your child in your heart</a>.</p>
<p>Sometimes these memories <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202504/one-from-the-heart-after-losing-a-child-keep-happy-memories-alive">make you smile,</a> <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202412/the-soul-knows-when-its-time-to-go">sometimes they make you cry,</a> sometimes they make you drunk with love, and sometimes they make you feel empty inside, but they keep you connected to your child, and that’s all that really matters.</p>

<p>Not a day goes by without something you do or watch or read or taste or smell reminding you of your child, and that’s in addition to all the signs they leave to show they’ve come to visit. Who knew that <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202508/me-and-him-after-loss-a-conversation-with-god">the powers that be </a>keep them so busy on the other side?</p>
<p>The signs are different for all of us, but one thing they have in common is that they’re all signs of love.</p>

<p>A psychic medium told me to look for feathers and for my ex-wife Caryn to keep an eye out for sunflowers. For the first year <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202411/forever-trying-to-rescue-you">after my son Rob died</a>, Caryn saw sunflowers wherever she looked, but I didn’t see a single feather. I remember joking, “What the heck! The lazy bum can only do one or the other?”</p>

<p>He finally got around to hitting me up with feathers, and every time I see one now, I point to it and say, “Hi Rob!” or “Dude!” The feathers are really a perfect choice. It feels like he’s tickling me <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202511/grieving-parents-are-desperate-for-comic-relief">to make me laugh</a>, which is just so Rob. I was happy to make his job easier last year, when I moved in with my girlfriend at the beach, where there’s plumage galore.</p>

<p>Our kids are also fond of visiting us in our dreams, and Rob is no exception, although he comes infrequently. At first, I thought that he was just occupied with his booming feather business, until my friend Sarah texted me about a dream she recently had in which Rob appeared.</p>
<p>Just like him to show up in somebody else’s dreams!</p>

<p>Whenever he deigns to drop in to one of mine, he appears only as <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202501/you-are-me">Little Robbie</a>, and I’m not sure why, other than that was when he was most adorable. I could barely remember any of these dreams, except for the following one that I had the wherewithal to write down:</p>
<p><em>I’m walking on Venice Beach right before sunset, and aside from a few rowdy homeless guys and the steady beat of the drum circle, it is beautiful and peaceful. I watch the waves gently breaking on the shore, and it feels hypnotic, so I close my eyes for a few seconds. When I open them, I see a small sailboat on the horizon.</em></p>


<p><em>As it comes into view, it looks like the one from </em>Where the Wild Things Are<em>, but instead of Max in his wolf costume, it’s Robbie in his G.I. Joe pajamas. He sails a little closer to shore and we both start frantically waving to each other, and he’s yelling something, but I can’t hear what it is because the drums are getting faster and louder.</em></p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p><em>And then the bow of the sailboat slowly turns around and heads out to the open sea, and that’s when my heart tells me what he was saying. Robbie is still waving and I’m standing on the shore waving back, and he keeps sailing farther and farther away until he is just a speck. Then, all of a sudden, he’s gone.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202602/signs-of-love" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202602/signs-of-love</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-space-in-the-heart/202602/signs-of-love</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Carlat]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/SIGNS%20OF%20LOVE.jpeg.jpg?itok=bAhdC9_3" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Science That Explains Why We All Love Alysa Liu]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/emma_seppala_larger.jpg?itok=vJ8hDXAN" alt="Emma Seppälä Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Authenticity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Science That Explains Why We All Love Alysa Liu</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What Alysa Liu's joy reflects back to us about our own unlived possibilities.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>By now, anyone who watched Alysa Liu skate her way to Olympic gold has felt it: Her irresistible likability has little to do with medals, technical scores, or podiums and everything to do with something far less measurable: the magnetic presence of a person wholly, unapologetically, and joyfully herself.</p>

<h2>From Prodigy to Sovereignty</h2>
<p>Liu first captured public attention as a prodigy, becoming the youngest U.S. champion at 13. Then, in a move almost unheard of in elite sport, she stepped away. She chose an ordinary teenage life. She chose space. She chose to discover who she was beyond the rink.</p>
<p>And when she returned, it didn’t feel like a comeback driven by unfinished ambition. It felt like a return anchored in self-trust.</p>

<p>We are not just watching a champion. We are witnessing someone who chose selfhood over expectation — and came back not hardened, but illuminated.</p>
<h2>So why can’t we stop watching her?</h2>
<p>Because the joy that radiates from Liu’s skating feels unrehearsed. After landing a difficult jump, she doesn’t simply compose herself for the judges; she beams. There is a flash of delight, almost disbelief, as if she’s still in love with the act itself.</p>

<p>To a sport known for exacting standards — tight hair buns, balletic lines, disciplined smiles — she has brought something disarming: ease. Her movements feel lived-in rather than manufactured. Even under immense global pressure, she projects a grounded exuberance that is electric.</p>
<p>Authenticity commands attention because it is rare. Most of us are not elite athletes, but we know the quiet pressure to conform — to smooth our edges, mute our instincts, and present the most acceptable version of ourselves. Over time, we trade aliveness for approval. Research in self-determination theory shows that autonomy and authenticity are core psychological needs; when honored, vitality rises.</p>

<p>What we see in Liu is the opposite of self-erasure. It is sovereignty. In my book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Sovereign-Reclaim-Freedom-Distraction-Uncertainty/dp/1401975062"><em>SOVEREIGN</em></a>, I describe sovereignty as the power that emerges when a person lives in alignment with their deepest truth. It unlocks a different quality of performance — one infused with profound and noticeable positive energy.</p>

<h2>A Mirror to Our Own Lives</h2>
<p>Authenticity does not guarantee Olympic gold. But it does allow for the fullest expression of one’s potential. Alysa Liu offers a counterpoint to the common end-of-life regret of not living true to oneself.</p>
<p>In Liu, we are not merely watching a skater; we are witnessing a mirror held up to our own unlived possibilities. In her joy, we glimpse what it feels like to move without apology. In her presence, we are reminded that life is not meant to be performed for approval but inhabited fully.</p>

<p>We love Alysa Liu not only for who she is, but for what she awakens in us: the courage to <em>claim our own sovereignty.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/feeling-it/202602/the-science-that-explains-why-we-all-love-alysa-liu" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/feeling-it/202602/the-science-that-explains-why-we-all-love-alysa-liu</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/feeling-it/202602/the-science-that-explains-why-we-all-love-alysa-liu</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Emma Seppälä Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Alysa_Liu_2026_Olympics_Women%E2%80%99s_Figure_Skating_Final.jpg?itok=r5iVKtPY" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>