<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 20:29:39 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 20:29:39 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Your Gut Reveals About Work Culture]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/mira_brancu.jpg?itok=hVd27tno" alt="Mira Brancu, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Career</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What Your Gut Reveals About Work Culture</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Emotions like guilt and resentment at work are data points.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Negative emotions in the absence of counterbalanced positive emotions can indicate unhealthy work cultures.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotions like guilt, shame, and fear can be a combination of our socialization and how we are treated at work.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Leaders can significantly improve trust, engagement, and performance by going beyond simply "managing" people.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Sometimes, an unhealthy work culture operates silently and beneath the surface. You might sense that something feels off, wrong, or just bad, but everything appears normal, or even high functioning, on the surface. There's no obvious villain, but you still feel on edge. This contrast can make it hard to articulate why something feels persistently and uncomfortably wrong.</p>

<p>This is one of the hardest workplace dynamics to navigate, precisely because it's so hard to name. When dysfunction is loud and visible, you can act on it, or at the very least complain about it ("That guy is such a bully!"). When it's quiet and disguised as business-as-usual, you start to question your own perception.</p>

<p>I've experienced enough of these situations and heard so many stories from clients that I've learned to recognize the signs, though it remains challenging. Over time, I've learned that the clearest signal often isn't what you can observe externally. It's what is felt internally, during and after the meeting ends.</p>

<p>Here's a recent example. I attended an initial leadership team meeting after joining an organization. On the surface, the team ran an efficient and effective meeting, moving quickly from topic to topic and making swift decisions without getting bogged down in details. When conflicts arose, team members provided additional information to resolve them promptly. I thought, "Wow! This team sure knows how to run a meeting!"</p>

<p>But what nagged away at me was what wasn't said. They moved a little too quickly to resolution. They were OK when the top executive dismissed concerns from multiple team members, instead offering a solution that allowed him to skirt his personal responsibility.</p>
<p>Later, that same executive ignored my request to step away from a project, instead using both policy and compliments to keep me doing it. On the surface, I thought: "Yeah, that policy makes sense, and given my strong sense of responsibility, I really should keep doing this. Plus, they clearly value me."</p>

<p>But deep down, I felt resentful, manipulated, obligated, and guilty.</p>
<p>When another executive later told me, "You don't need to do this. We will figure this out. You don't need to feel pressured if you've made your decision," I felt relieved, heard, and appreciative. I felt seen, not managed. The contrast between Executive #1 and Executive #2 was striking.</p>

<h2>Your Emotions Are Telling You Something</h2>
<p>In my work as a leadership advisor and team consulting psychologist, I've come to think of persistent negative emotions in the workplace as diagnostic signals, not character flaws or signs that you're being too sensitive.</p>
<p>When you consistently feel guilt, resentment, and obligation without any counterbalancing sense of excitement, hope, anticipation, or genuine choice, that's a sign the situation is not mutually beneficial. It may be structured to serve others at your expense.</p>


<p>This is meaningfully different from normal work stress. Stress can coexist with purpose, engagement, and trust. What I'm describing is a one-way drain, a pattern where you keep giving and the relational or organizational structure keeps taking, often while framing that extraction as reasonable, necessary, or even flattering.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<h2>Why This May Be Harder for Women</h2>
<p>For many women, this dynamic is often even more complicated. Many of us are socialized from a young age to feel guilty or obligated when we say no or set limits on our time or personal space, whether related to household chores, child-rearing, intimacy, emotional labor, or work expectations. These patterns don't just disappear when we walk into the workplace.</p>



  


<p>This means that when a leader uses policy, flattery, or subtle pressure to override a boundary you've tried to set, you might feel confusion, guilt, or shame, or begin to question whether you're being unreasonable. The hardest part of boundary-setting at work isn't necessarily knowing what you'd like to set a boundary around. It's dealing with the emotional noise surrounding it: the guilt, fear of disappointing others, or fear of being judged as "difficult," "not committed," or lacking integrity. These are real risks for women. But feelings of guilt, shame, or confusion don't mean you're doing something wrong. They signal that you're questioning expectations designed to keep you compliant and serving others instead of yourself.</p>

<h2>What the Two Executive Styles Reveal</h2>
<p>The contrast between Executive #1 and Executive #2 illustrates the difference between a leader who cultivates a thriving environment and one who simply manages people.</p>
<p>Executive #1 thought he was doing right by the organization and meeting his own needs by encouraging me to stay and framing it as a rational decision supported by policy. But all he would get if I stayed was a resentful person in a role they didn't really want.</p>

<p>Executive #2 understood that pressuring me would erode trust. By acknowledging the emotions behind my decision and leaving the choice genuinely up to me, he made me feel respected, seen, and validated. As a result, I felt more loyal, and even open to reconsidering.</p>
<p>The burden of managing these dynamics shouldn't fall entirely on individuals. Organizations have a responsibility to cultivate cultures where leaders don't just achieve results, but do so in ways that build trust and preserve dignity.</p>

<h2>What This Means for You</h2>
<p>If you have tried to be clear about your needs and yet consistently only feel the bad feelings, it's time to honestly assess the health of your work culture. That doesn't mean the answer is always to leave. But the pattern deserves attention. The greater clarity you gain from understanding it, the greater insight you'll have about what kind of support or protection you may need to seek.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>And if you're an organizational leader aiming to retain top talent, routinely ask yourself: How do supervisors actually treat their teams? What is the day-to-day experience of employees? Are your leaders more Machiavellian (operating on the logic that the ends justify the means) or more transformative (building trust and inspiring genuine engagement)?</p>

<p>More importantly, what kind of leader are you? How do you know? And what would it take to find out? </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-new-look-at-womens-leadership/202603/what-your-gut-reveals-about-work-culture" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-new-look-at-womens-leadership/202603/what-your-gut-reveals-about-work-culture</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-new-look-at-womens-leadership/202603/what-your-gut-reveals-about-work-culture</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mira Brancu, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/pexels-karola-g-6632379.jpg?itok=GBdmU9me" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Seeing Is Not Always Knowing: The Limits of Visual Authority]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-08/JPR_AMWASW-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=Cblm2bHd" alt="Jeffry Ricker Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Heuristics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Seeing Is Not Always Knowing: The Limits of Visual Authority</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Sighted people can be misled when mental shortcuts ignore blind expertise.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Humans have a strong impulse to help others because of biological, social, and cultural factors.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">This impulse can misfire when sighted people use mental shortcuts to decide how to help blind people.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">To offer more appropriate help, sighted people need to listen to the expert testimony of blind people.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/AdobeStock_141793500.jpeg.jpg?itok=s2bDUHDK" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="pahis / Adobe Stock" alt="pahis / Adobe Stock"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: pahis / Adobe Stock</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Many years ago, I was playing with my niece, who was only one year old at the time. She was happy and excited. In her enthusiasm, she threw an object that opened a small cut on my forehead. She immediately cried out in despair, “My friend is hurt!” She wanted someone to help me.</p>
<p>It is not much of an exaggeration to say that humans are born to help. In fact, helping behavior in humans evolved from the psychological processes that motivated mutual cooperation in ancestral hominids (Buss, 2016; Hepach et al., 2020).</p>

<p>The evolutionary origins of cooperative helping gave rise to social and cultural practices, norms, values, etc., that govern cooperative helping in humans today. The combined influence of biological, social, and cultural factors underlie the strong impulse to help that most of us experience when we see someone in need.</p>

<p>But this impulse can misfire, as it sometimes does in situations where nondisabled people try to help people with disabling impairments, such as blindness. Sighted people often feel confident that their vision provides more reliable knowledge about their surroundings than blind people get from their nonvisual senses. Blind people, on the other hand, claim that their training gives them the cognitive skills needed to gain reliable knowledge about their surroundings. The result is miscommunication and, often, highly stressful interactions, especially for blind people who frequently deal with these situations.</p>

<p>This post explores reasons for help-related miscommunication between sighted and blind people. My goal is to encourage sighted people, who obviously are concerned with the well-being of others, to offer more effective help to people who are blind.</p>
<h2>The Development of Instrumental Helping</h2>
<p>Instrumental help occurs frequently in blind-sighted interactions. “Instrumental help” is the provision of concrete, practical, direct assistance to another who is trying to achieve a goal (Brownelle et al., 2013; Svetlova et al., 2010).</p>

<p>As we saw with my niece, instrumental helping develops early in life. By about 18 months of age, children often try to help people without being asked or promised a reward (Warneken &amp; Tomasello, 2006). For example, toddlers will help others to get past physical obstacles or locate a dropped object.</p>
<p>At around three years of age, children realize that sometimes the best way to help is to do something other than what someone requests. Alia Martin &amp; Kristina Olson (2013) called this type of instrumental help “paternalistic helping.” They defined paternalistic help as: the substitution of a more effective method of help for an ineffective method, as judged by the child. For example, young children will substitute an undamaged tool for a requested tool that is damaged.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/AdobeStock_1068150750.jpg?itok=50M9V34S" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Angel Santana / Adobe Stock" alt="Angel Santana / Adobe Stock"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Angel Santana / Adobe Stock</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Instrumental Helping of Blind People</h2>
<p>Sighted onlookers often feel concerned about someone using a white cane to cross a busy intersection. They may offer paternalistic help, sometimes by running up to the person, grabbing their arm, and attempting to pull them to the other side. The blind person often claims that they are able to cross streets safely. But sighted people usually find that claim to be implausible.</p>

<p>The central question is, why do sighted people immediately dismiss that claim? One reason is that the lived experience of sighted people convinces them that vision is necessary for functioning in everyday life: They rely on vision more than any other sense. A second reason is the influence of cognitive structures called “epistemic schemas.”</p>

<p>An epistemic schema is a set of implicit (unconscious) assumptions and mental habits that actively focus our attention on certain kinds of information, while filtering out other kinds of information (Peña-Guzmán &amp; Reynolds, 2019). Thus, without our being aware of it, epistemic schemas set limits on what people consider to be valid knowledge and who they consider to be reliable knowers.</p>

<p>Ableism is an epistemic schema that guides the help-related actions of sighted people (Peña-Guzmán &amp; Reynolds, 2019). "Ableism" is a mostly implicit cultural ideology about the differences between disabled and nondisabled people. Some of the assumptions reflect negative cultural stereotypes about disability. These stereotypes include traits such as incompetence, dependence, helplessness, asexuality, and low intelligence (Nario-Redmond, 2010; Nario-Redmond, 2020).</p>



  


<p>Ableist assumptions often lead well-meaning people, without realizing it, to treat disabled people in ways that devalue or dehumanize them (Campbell, 2009; Hehir, 2002). For example, under certain circumstances, ableism motivates nondisabled people to help even when disabled people insist that their help is unneeded. Such paternalistic help occurs when helpers feel they need to act quickly or are not motivated to think carefully about the situation (see Devine, 1989 for a general discussion of implicit processing). In those circumstances, their decision-making is guided by fast-acting mental shortcuts (heuristics) that implicitly assume the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Disabled and nondisabled bodies experience the world in different ways</li>
<li>These different experiences produce differences in knowledge</li>
<li>The knowledge gained from nondisabled bodies is more accurate than the knowledge gained from disabled bodies</li>
</ul>
<p>In other words, the ableist schema leads people to infer that nondisabled “ways of knowing” produce knowledge that is more valid, reliable, and objective than disabled ways of knowing. This inference allows nondisabled people to, first, disregard disabled people’s claims about their abilities and, second, conclude that they know best how to help the disabled person (Klyve, 2019; also see Fricker, 2003).</p>

<h2>How Can Sighted People Help More Effectively?</h2>
<p>Sighted people who frequently interact with people who are blind can learn to bypass the rapid-acting mental shortcuts triggered by the ableist schema. The key is to give themselves time to think carefully about what is happening during help-related situations. For example, sighted people can mentally rehearse how they would respond more appropriately if they see a blind person crossing a street.</p>

<p><em>I would like to thank Kiera Feng for her editorial assistance.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/blindness-visible/202603/seeing-is-not-always-knowing-the-limits-of-visual-authority" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/blindness-visible/202603/seeing-is-not-always-knowing-the-limits-of-visual-authority</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/blindness-visible/202603/seeing-is-not-always-knowing-the-limits-of-visual-authority</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeffry Ricker Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/AdobeStock_176310645.jpg?itok=BtwhCbRy" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Virginia Woolf and the Reclaiming of Attention]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/screen_shot_2020-11-11_at_8.18.17_am.jpg?itok=cvv1yaCG" alt="Jason Tougaw" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Attention</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Virginia Woolf and the Reclaiming of Attention</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The novelist was a master in the art of attention—and connection.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Attention is necessary for connection.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Virginia Woolf's stream of consciousness style is a lesson in the art of attention.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A preponderance of writing on distraction in the digital age suggests a yearning for attention.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-03/Woolf%20Mrs%20Dalloway%201925%20Hogarth%20Press%20Cover.jpg?itok=GzfgmIAA" width="320" height="348" data-insert-type="image" alt="Mrs. Dalloway, 1925 Hogarth Press edition. Art by Vanessa Bell. " title="Public Domain"></div>
<div class="caption">Mrs. Dalloway, 1925 Hogarth Press edition. Art by Vanessa Bell.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Public Domain</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Reading Virginia Woolf in 2026 feels like an answer to a widespread cultural yearning to reclaim our fleeting attention spans. </p>
<p>Virginia Woolf is famous her stream-of-consciousness technique. As she describes it in her essay “Modern Fiction,” Woolf sought to “record the atoms as they fall upon the mind” and “trace the pattern, however disconnected and incoherent in appearance, which each site or incident scores upon the consciousness.” Woolf's atoms and “scores” are fundamental to her narrative techniques—revolutionary during her time and newly relevant today. How we pay attention, she is arguing, changes us. </p>

<p>Woolf anticipates a book like Jenny Odell's <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/600671/how-to-do-nothing-by-jenny-odell/"><em>How to Do Nothing: Resisting the Attention Economy</em></a>. Odell's book reads like a manifesto, decrying "the invasive logic of <em>commercial</em> social media to keep us in a profitable state of anxiety, envy, and distraction." Like all good manifestos, it focuses more on solutions—new ways of being—than critique. Odell advocates for what she calls bioregionalism, "an awareness not only of the many life-forms of each place, but how they are interrelated." Later, discussing David Hockney's paintings, John Cage's experiments with the musicality of ambient sound, and William Blake's poetry, she makes the point that "Practices of attention and curiosity are inherently open-ended, oriented toward something outside ourselves."</p>

<p>A stream of consciousness is inherently open-ended. That much seems obvious. Woolf is attuned to the attention's unpredictable non-linearity. She would not have used a term like <em>bioregional</em>, but her portrayals of her characters' mental experience is "oriented" to the interrelationships of the many somethings—objects, people, feelings—outside ourselves. In her fiction, Woolf portrays consciousness as a roving, transmittable process. </p>

<p>In <em>Mrs. Dalloway</em>, for example, Woolf's characters' absorb the bustle of London streets and the grandeur of Bourton Hall. Their surroundings become part of them. “The throb of the motor engines sounded like a pulse irregularly drumming through an entire body,” she writes in the famous passage in which Clarissa Dalloway and Septimus Smith witness the chaos of traffic created by a stopped car purportedly occupied by the Prime Minister. As the passage continues, the effects of this car reverberate from the sun through popping parasols, the sweet peas in Clarissa’s pursed face, finally “scoring” Septimus’s combustible psyche:</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<blockquote><p>The sun became extraordinarily hot because the motor car had stopped outside Mulberry’s shop window; old ladies on the tops of omnibuses spread their black parasols; here a green, here a red parasol opened with a little pop. Mrs. Dalloway, coming to the window with her arms full of sweet peas, looked out with her little pink face pursed in enquiry. Every one looked at the motor car. Septimus looked. Boys on bicycles sprang off. Traffic accumulated. And there the motor car stood, with drawn blinds, and upon them a curious pattern like a tree, Septimus thought, and this gradual drawing together of <a> </a>everything to one centre before his eyes, as if some horror had come almost to the surface and was about to burst into flames, terrified him. The world wavered and quivered and threatened to burst into flames. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>In Woolf's fiction, moments when one character's stream of consciounsess pours into another are all-important. Woolf blends her characters’ interior monologues by mingling their responses to the environmental stimulus they share. We feel the “throb of the motor engines” through the lens of two filters. Clarissa has been watching Septimus, imagining what life feels like for him. Now they both feel the traffic as they watch the car come to a halt. As the passage progresses, Septimus’s fragile psyche dominates, his shell-shock the catalyst that makes the world waver and quiver. But Woolf makes it clear that Septimus’s symptoms are an exaggerated form of a sensitivity to environment shared by Clarissa—and, presumably, “every one” of the people on that street looking at that motor car. </p>

<p>Throughout the novel, the mental experience of characters is interactive, rather than strictly internal. In fact, Woolf goes so far as to suggest that consciousness may be shared. “They went in and out of each other’s minds without any effort,” Clarissa reminisces about the passionate friendship she once shared with Peter Walsh:</p>


<blockquote><p>They sat on the ground and talked—he and Clarissa. They went in and out of each other’s minds without any effort. He said to himself as they were getting into the boat, “She will marry that man,” dully, without any resentment; but it was an obvious thing, Dalloway would marry Clarissa. And then in a second it was over.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>In her book <em>Why We Read Fiction: Theory of Mind and the Novel</em>, Lisa Zunshine argues that Woolf engages in forms of "mind reading" that mirror the experience of her characters. Woolf, she observes, trains readers in the art of "cognitive embedment." Our mental experience is embedded in the narrator's, which is embedded in Peter's, which is embedded in Clarissa's. And so on. Through the puzzle of these interrelated mental experiences, we discern the waning of Peter and Clarissa's intimacy. In the process, we are primed to feel their re-connection after many years more fully. </p>



  


<p>Literary critics borrowed the term <em>stream of consciousness</em> from William James's 1892 work of that name. Crucially, for James, consciousness is persona, continuously changing and focused on objects outside ourselves. Our screens—specifically, per Odell's point, the platforms that commercialize them—are dispersing the streams of our attention to such a degree that it feels like they no longer belong to us. In Woolf's terms, they "score" our consciousness in ways we are increasingly unsatisfied with. In the process, we feel isolated. We feel disconnected from our immediate environments and from each other. </p>

<p>As it is for Odell, attention is a close cousin of connection in Woolf's writing. This may account for the yearning quality of so much writing about attention in the digital age. (Some key titles listed in the sources below.) Connection, of course, is a central theme for any number of novelists. Zunshine argues that the act of reading any fiction exercises our capacity for so-called mind reading—attending to the thoughts and feelings of others. When it comes to the art of attention, though, Woolf is masterful. </p>

<p>If you're tired of the way your phone is "scoring" your brain, try spending some time with Virginia Woolf.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-elusive-brain/202602/virginia-woolf-and-the-reclaiming-of-attention" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-elusive-brain/202602/virginia-woolf-and-the-reclaiming-of-attention</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-elusive-brain/202602/virginia-woolf-and-the-reclaiming-of-attention</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Tougaw]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Roger_Fry_-_Virginia_Woolf-1.jpg?itok=38v3VEFg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Understanding How Medication and Psychotherapy Work Together]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/Busch.png.jpg?itok=d2pFK2_0" alt="Busch" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychopharmacology</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Understanding How Medication and Psychotherapy Work Together</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How Combined Treatment Eases Symptoms and Helps Build Coping Skills</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Combined treatment often works better than medication or therapy alone.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Medication reduces pervasive symptoms so therapy can work more effectively.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychotherapy helps change patterns that contribute to anxiety and depression.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p><em>While the primary focus of this blog will be skills training and targeting problems with psychodynamic psychotherapy (Busch, 2022), I thought it would be useful to begin with a discussion about how medication and psychotherapy work together. </em></p>
<p>Many studies and wide-ranging clinical experiences have found that a combination of medication and psychotherapy is often more effective than either treatment alone for depressive and anxiety disorders (Cuijpers et al., 2019; Cuijpers et al., 2024). Recent guidelines have recommended that combination treatment is particularly valuable for depression that is moderate to severe or recurrent (American Psychiatric Association, 2023; National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE), 2022), and similarly useful for anxiety that is severe, persistent, or recurrent (National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE), 2011). It is also common for patients to start either medication or psychotherapy alone and then have the other treatment added if symptoms persist (Guidi et al, 2021). </p>

<p>Explanations for the combined effectiveness include that medication leads to a reduction of pervasive mood and anxiety symptoms, improving energy, sleep, and concentration, while psychotherapy enables modification of maladaptive expectations and relational patterns that trigger negative mood states and improve psychological skills that reduce recurrence of symptoms (Breedvelt et al., 2023). Psychotherapy can also aid medication treatment, in understanding and addressing why patients sometimes skip or even stop their medication (Busch and Sandberg, 2007).</p>

<p>Not all psychopharmacologists or psychotherapists accept that treatment combinations are most effective, and it is sometimes up to patients to seek them out. Some psychopharmacologists see anxiety and depression as biological and do not believe therapy adds much of value. Some therapists believe that anxiety or down mood are useful in therapy as signals to identify the source of these symptoms. This is sometimes true, but if you are always anxious and depressed, it’s hard to use it as a signal. Proper medication treatment (often antidepressants) will help to ease pervasive anxiety and depression. At that point occasional anxiety or down mood may be more useful signals of problems that need to be addressed from a psychotherapeutic standpoint. Let’s say you’re worried all the time about several issues in your life (finances, health, your relationship) and after you improve with medication you just get worried when you separate from your partner. This anxiety is now a signal for you to explore in therapy: What psychologically is causing you to get anxious when you separate from your partner? Are there particular problems with your partner? Has separation from important people in your life always been scary for you?</p>

<p>I’ve often been asked by patients (and sometimes therapists) to explain how medication and psychotherapy could be understood to work together. In addition to providing evidence from the literature and the clinical explanations described above, I’ve found certain metaphors to be particularly useful.</p>
<p>One way I describe the combined effectiveness of medication and psychotherapy is using the metaphor of a river. The river overflowing represents an anxiety or depressive disorder. Three streams flow into the river: a biological stream, a psychological stream, and an environmental stream. The environmental stream would refer to various stresses in your life: financial, health, tensions in your relationship, etc. In this model, when there is too much flow from the tributaries it leads to anxiety or depressive disorders. Medication helps diminish the flow from the biological tributary and therapy helps reduce the psychological tributary, causing the river to recede, leading to the relief of symptoms.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>This model is helpful but is simplified in a number of ways. Medication can have placebo effects that are essentially a psychological change. Psychotherapy can sometimes by itself relieve anxious and depressive disorders, affecting the biological tributary without medication. And relief of anxiety and depression can sometimes help to reduce your perception of environmental stresses. For instance, anxiety and depression can lead you to be much more worried about money than you need to be. And when your symptoms are better you often are better able to manage the stress in your life, e.g. budget more carefully. So the model should probably include channels that connect the tributaries, but that starts to make it more complex than helpful.</p>

<p>Another metaphor for explaining the impact of and need for medication is a blood pressure model. Some peoples’ blood pressure increases from stress alone. If they can reduce their life stresses (not always so easy) their blood pressure goes down. But they would still need medication as long as their stress remains high. Another group may reduce their stress but still need medication: They have more of a “biological” blood pressure problem. What works best for most people? Stress reduction and medication. This can be seen as similar to whether you need medication for anxiety and depression: Some people require it for improvement, whereas others may only need psychotherapy (another means of stress reduction).</p>

<p>This metaphor is also useful in answering the question people often ask of whether they will continue to need medication after they improve. And as with blood pressure, some will and some won’t. That is, some people have a biological component to their anxiety and depression that requires medication in an ongoing way. Patients may assume that as they learn coping strategies in treatment they will no longer need medication, but this isn’t necessarily true. The blood pressure model may help them understand that they may still require it in spite of their improved psychological skills.</p>


<p>Additionally, people often want to understand why their anxiety or depression could recur or did in fact come back after they had treatment. The metaphors described above can help. Perhaps their environmental pressures increased (e.g., a new baby or more pressure at their job). Or for some reason there may have just been a shift in their biology. For example, when some people go in for their yearly checkup they find their blood pressure has increased for no apparent reason; there has been a shift in their biology that requires an increase in their medication dose or perhaps another medication.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Finally, back problems can be used as another metaphor, particularly for people who have suffered from them. Like anxiety and depression, once you have back problems you are vulnerable to getting them again. Sometimes there is a clear trigger (you twist your back) and sometimes there isn’t. Life stress can also trigger back problems. Ibuprofen may be needed (medication) and physical therapy (therapy) can be used to strengthen your muscles to reduce risks, but the right combination of factors can still cause a recurrence of pain.</p>



  


<p>In most cases of depression and anxiety, therapy plus medication can help diminish the intensity and length of time you experience symptoms. The metaphors I described provide a better understanding and some additional relief for people who are suddenly beset with these symptoms.</p>
<p><strong>To find a therapist, </strong><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><strong>visit the Psychology Today Therapy Directory</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/skills-training-in-psychodynamic-psychotherapy/202603/understanding-how-medication-and" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/skills-training-in-psychodynamic-psychotherapy/202603/understanding-how-medication-and</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/skills-training-in-psychodynamic-psychotherapy/202603/understanding-how-medication-and</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Fredric N. Busch, MD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/shutterstock_1483265618.jpg?itok=MEW52mWv" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Giving Away Our Mental Health]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-03/bertin_headshot_2024-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=3rQr-qy5" alt="Mark Bertin M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Happiness</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Giving Away Our Mental Health</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">It's not clickbait, but what keeps us sane remains old school and mundane.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The chaos and intensity of modern life actively undermine our mental health.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Resilience and happiness stem from simple, old-fashioned habits more than quick fixes or trendy solutions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Strong face-to-face relationships are crucial for emotional health; screen time can erode these connections.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Intentionally defending what builds our health helps us stay strong.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-roman-odintsov-6898861.jpg?itok=4P_NvXK7" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="ROMAN ODINTSOV Pexels" alt="ROMAN ODINTSOV Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: ROMAN ODINTSOV Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Just about everything that improves mental health is free and available to all of us, apart from the right to therapy and medical treatment when required. It’s an utterly frustrating, unexciting, unsellable, and unlikely-to-go-viral message. It also isn't judgmental, since none of us control our emotional state or the state of the world. Our likelihood of feeling good heavily relies on each of us staying intentional in a world that pushes us toward unproductive habits instead.</p>

<p><em>Simple but not easy</em> summarizes the research on resilience and happiness. Beyond the bedrock rights everyone has to basic sustenance and safety, there are no quick fixes and nothing extra to buy. It takes effort and planning but isn't found in cutting-edge medical research. This is the modern science of getting back to the basics.</p>

<p>The unrelenting stress and anxiety of the modern world keep us off balance and reactive. We're up against powerful forces intentionally influencing how we live. Social media companies are being sued for their methods. <a href="https://www.apa.org/monitor/2026/03/nutrition-food-mental-health">Nutrition influences our mental health</a>, and yet our food is designed and marketed to keep us eating badly. Individually, we don't control everything that happens, but we do retain the ability to choose a lifestyle that makes resilience more likely.</p>

<p>As individuals and as parents, we can practice pausing, settling, and aiming to make intentional choices. And then stay kind and patient with ourselves when we notice we're off track again, because change is hard. Separate from responsibilities and problems to solve and all the rest of life, we can steer our families toward strength, resilience, and joy.</p>

<h2>The Effort of Staying Intentional</h2>
<p>So what does living that way actually look like? It starts with the people around us. Having others in our lives who are emotionally consistent and present is one of the strongest predictors of resilience. Smartphones and social media erode that experience in ways we're only beginning to understand. Prioritizing face-to-face time with those who make us feel stronger, while emphasizing being genuinely present for our children when we're with them, isn't sentimental. It's protective.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.sleepfoundation.org/mental-health">Sleep matters more</a> than most of us want to admit. Our bodies and minds require rest, and technology makes the already common challenge of sleep worse. A consistent sleep routine, for ourselves and our kids, is less glamorous than almost any other intervention and more effective than most. </p>
<p>Exercise works the same way. <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/humans-evolved-to-exercise/">Humans evolved to move</a>. The research linking physical activity <a href="https://theconversation.com/exercise-can-be-as-effective-as-medication-for-depression-and-anxiety-new-study-272243">to better mood and lower anxiety</a> is about as settled as it gets. It doesn't require a gym plan or competition. It requires prioritizing and pushing through the inertia. Studies show that even minutes a day of intense, heart rate-raising activity matters, which isn’t all that much to steal away from our typical average screentime.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>What we eat shapes how we feel, in ways that are easy to dismiss and hard to ignore. <a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/nutritional-psychiatry-your-brain-on-food-201511168626">Traditional diets built</a> around whole foods, shared meals, and minimal processed foods support a more stable mood. The typical Western diet does the opposite. Changing how a family eats is emotionally loaded yet worth doing anyway, one realistic step at a time.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most exhausting aspect of modern family life is carving out time for what screens have quietly replaced. Reading. Free play. Being outside. Unplugged hobbies. These aren't nostalgic indulgences; they settle the mind and build the kind of focused attention that doomscrolling, gaming and similar activities actively dismantle. Technology today is engineered to be hard to put down. Treating unplugged time as something to actively defend, rather than something that will happen naturally, is fundamental for modern mental health.</p>

<h2>An Effortful Return to the Basics</h2>
<p>All of this runs into the same wall: Habits are hard to build and easy to lose. The antidote isn't self-criticism or willpower but the same patient advice you'd offer a child: Take small realistic steps. Emphasize scheduled routines. Set alarms. And when you lose the thread, which you will, return to your intentions without self-judgment rather than abandoning them entirely. Adjust the plan, and start again. That new habit hasn’t stuck around – yet.</p>



  


<p>We are giving away our mental health when we forget these basics. Awful and upsetting things keep happening. Staying strong means returning to what has worked for generations: rest, movement, real food, real people, and time that isn't optimized for anyone else's profit.</p>
<p>None of this is exciting. All of it is hard to maintain. And on any given day, if you've managed to move toward even one of these, whether getting outside, eating a meal together, or putting phones away for an hour, you've done something that matters, even if it doesn't look like much from the outside.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Start right now. Consider your typical family schedule. Consider what you’d like to prioritize. Schedule a specific time for that intention, set up a reminder, and take a first step toward healthier, more resilient living. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/child-development-central/202602/giving-away-our-mental-health" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/child-development-central/202602/giving-away-our-mental-health</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/child-development-central/202602/giving-away-our-mental-health</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Bertin M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-roman-odintsov-6898861.jpg?h=a6451d3a&amp;itok=MvBJf6av" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>