<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 21:24:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 21:24:50 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Perfectionist's Quest for a Love Without Limits]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-05/Leon-Garber.jpg?itok=SCVGgFWd" alt="Leon Garber LMHC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Perfectionist's Quest for a Love Without Limits</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why love in perfectionism is conflicting and impossible.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perfectionists yearn for a love that resolves all of the basic conflicts inherent in experience.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Fundamentally, perfectionists strive to acquire endless options.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">To challenge perfectionism, one is required to challenge the pull toward fantasy.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p><em>Blue Moon</em>, a film chronicling a day in the last week of the life of legendary songwriter Lorenz Hart, features a notable aphorism about love. In the scene, Hart recounts a favorite book of his and says it taught him a valuable lesson: In love, one adores and the other allows themself to be adored. While this is a somewhat cynical take, it speaks to a significant truth, if discovered: Love can’t exist completely on our terms. We can’t own it. (But, if we did, we wouldn’t know how to manage it.)</p>

<p>This is especially true in perfectionism, in its absolute form to be specific. Here, all contradictions are magically made whole in one’s imagination. The perfectionist aspires to be perfect everywhere, all the time, and to everyone, embodying a plethora of seemingly incompatible traits, whose manifestations depend on the context—in essence, the perfectionist is a chameleon. This sort of thinking bleeds into one’s understanding of love, too. What is love to the perfectionist? Is it having to accept some limitation, like the one described above? No. Love is everything at once. Love is the thrill of chasing aloofness while bathing in admiration. It’s adrenaline but with security. It’s comfort without vulnerability. It’s the valley of an idyllic future but with the peaks of a tempestuous beginning. It’s equality but with an implied hierarchy, wherein one simultaneously is reaching but feels out of reach. And it’s the juxtaposition of “I need you but don’t love you” and “I love you but can’t have you.”</p>

<p>To even say that a perfectionist wants immature love fails to capture this reality. For in reality, it isn’t love at all. Love, like every other perfectionistic fantasy, is some nonsensical hodgepodge revealing the perfectionist’s true desire: limitlessness. If we consider perfectionism as sourced in a deep desire for control and an even deeper-seated fear of uncertainty, then love begins to feel impossible. But, again, it isn’t love that’s desired. When Lorenz remarks that love entails an adorer and an adored, he essentially tells his friend that all of us have to settle. With grandiose dreams, however, the idea feels personal, like an indictment of one’s core self. “Why should <em>I</em> have to settle?”</p>

<p>All of this is associated with limerence (the fixation on a love object that seems both attainable and unattainable, which often becomes all-consuming), maladaptive daydreaming (the preoccupation with an imagined world where all of one’s needs are met, yet the conflicts of each are somehow resolved or erased), and obsessive striving (always wanting more). The perfectionist is, thus, stuck climbing a ladder leading nowhere. There is no sense of what one wants or needs, what or whom they should pursue, or even what’s meaningful. Yet, all of that is hidden by the blinding light of hope, which invariably seems benign or even good. Unbeknownst to the obsessive seeker, happiness may be out of reach when your only goal is endless options. But, maybe that’s what you want, at least in part.</p>

<p>Accepting that your standard is one of the main reasons you’ll never fully be content can be a catalyst to making better, and more measured, choices. While this aspect of perfectionism, the inability to feel fully satiated, can feel suffocating, it can, counter-intuitively, also be liberating. Maybe complete satisfaction shouldn’t be the aim. Perfectionists, despite these conflicting pulls, can still cultivate good lives. But, several things need to happen. They need to understand how their sense of self-worth is tied up with absurd expectations of love and success. They need to see how their penchant for black and white thinking renders any realistic assessment of what’s meaningful impossible. They would have to reframe how to perceive ‘settling’ and why they consider themselves to be above it. Their partners would need to, if they want to stick around, de-emphasize the perfectionist’s fixations—to accept that perfectionists want what they can’t have merely because it represents some ridiculous ideal, which, like a vampire, is always burned by the flame of life. The perfectionist would have to commit to finding gratitude in what they have and what they’ve done.</p>

<p>The fantasy, and even its pursuit, is easy. So, lastly, the perfectionist is implored to acknowledge an intolerable weakness—their preference for ease. I used to tell people that I pursued success because it was easy, despite the apparent diligence involved. It wasn’t complicated, or was at least less so than the rest of life. My ambitions prevented me from thinking much and they liberated me from choosing, affording me the freedom from love, too. Limitlessness might be freeing and its pursuit, in all fairness, might be noble; there’s something really beautiful about man striving to overcome his limits. And while some degree of that is warranted, I stress that it can’t be your life’s overarching goal because then, there won’t be a life lived; it would be as though you never even existed. Whatever meaning is, it must be wrapped up in your choices, and if it’s associated with others (which I can’t imagine it not to be), then they have to feel that you chose them—with your time, space, patience, and humility. They need to know that you gave them some part of your actual existence, all the better if you sacrificed your fantasy.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202603/the-perfectionists-quest-for-a-love-without-limits" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202603/the-perfectionists-quest-for-a-love-without-limits</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202603/the-perfectionists-quest-for-a-love-without-limits</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Leon Garber LMHC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/cuilei2016-arang-2521591_1920.jpg?itok=U3GJ_2RC" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Surprising Way to Reduce Hunger—Without Weight Loss Drugs]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/image0_1_-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=9LsLSHnF" alt="Jeffrey Bernstein Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Appetite</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">A Surprising Way to Reduce Hunger—Without Weight Loss Drugs</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A counterintuitive shift that helps many people feel less hungry.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Intermittent fasting can reduce the spikes and crashes that can intensify appetite.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Containment occurs naturally because you keep your eating time within a reliable window.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The benefit is not just about eating less; it is about thinking less about eating.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>As a psychologist who has spent over 30 years breaking free from anxiety and overthinking, what fascinates me most about intermittent fasting isn't just the metabolic research, but what happens with the mind. </p>
<p>Most people discover something unexpected: they are much less hungry. This is not because they are using more willpower. It's not that they are distracting themselves. Rather, and this is huge, the mental noise about food gets much quieter.</p>

<h2>Quieting the "I Must Eat Now" Loop</h2>
<p>In a culture that encourages us to eat all day long, hunger has become a near-constant signal, along with the internal dialogue that precedes it. "Hmm, should I just eat now?" "I guess I can eat this and I will just eat less later." "Well, I already blew it for today, and I deserve a treat anyway." </p>

<p>That maddening mental loop pattern is identical to the overthinking loops I describe in my book, <em>Freeing Your Child From Overthinking.</em> The brain keeps scanning, correcting, and trying to create certainty (e.g., "This food will certainly hit the spot now!"). The result is exhaustion and a "feed me now" response that makes certain we eat because we think we "need" to have that food right then and there.</p>

<h2>The Little Talked About Magic of Intermittent Fasting</h2>
<p>When our eating is confined to a fixed time window, powerful things happen. There are obviously fewer decisions about when we will eat. There are fewer back-and-forth internal debates about food. And, there are fewer faulty "self-corrections" driven by emotional eating drivers such as boredom, frustration, and let's not forget that big one—<em>anxiety</em>. </p>

<p>The magic part of these intermittent fasting time windows is that they lead us to fewer food-related decisions, less internal, emotionally driven, civil war over eating or not, and fewer "self-corrections" in favor of the "certainty" of getting to eat when it is not in our best health interests. In plain English, "hunger" becomes less urgent and more predictable. </p>

<h2>The Magic Behind Reduced Overall Appetite From Intermittent Fasting</h2>
<p>We are in an age where many people are thrilled with prescribed GLP-1 meds that reduce hunger. I am not advising anyone to forgo prescribed meds in favor of intermittent fasting. Always check with your health care provider about what is best for you. </p>

<p>With that said, biologically speaking, intermittent fasting also leads to a steadier eating rhythm that can reduce the spikes and crashes that can intensify appetite. But just as important as the psychological shift, the brain gets retrained to perceive that hunger is not an emergency. Intermittent fasting has a beginning, a middle, and an end. This eating predictability lowers threat, and that lower perceived threat reduces rumination about food.</p>


<h2>PACE Your Way to Quieting Those Hunger Madness Loops</h2>
<p>In my counseling work, I teach the PACE model from my book, <em>Freeing Your Child From Overthinking. </em>I have seen this model greatly promote impulse control for children, teens, and adults when it comes to challenging behaviors, runaway thoughts, and overpowering emotions. PACE stands for pause, acknowledge, contain, and engage. A flexible, non-rigid approach to intermittent fasting mirrors that process:</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<ul>
<li><strong>P</strong>ause and gently remind yourself that you are on an intermittent fasting plan when you feel hunger outside your eating window (common fasting plans are 14, 15, or 16 hours). </li>
<li><strong>A</strong>cknowledge<strong> </strong>your hunger in a nonjudgmental way. "I am hungry, but I have a plan that helps me stay in control of my hunger instead of it continuing to control me."</li>
<li><strong>C</strong>ontainment is naturally occurring because you keep your eating time within a reliable window.</li>
<li><strong>E</strong>ngage with food more intentionally and with less urgency as you reflect on the predictability your intermittent fasting program offers. </li>
</ul>



  


<h2>Final Caveat</h2>
<p>Intermittent fasting is not appropriate for children, teens, people with certain health conditions, or those with a history of disordered eating. It works best when there is some cognitive flexibility around it rather than rigidity; otherwise, it can precipitate even more overthinking. Yet, for many adults, the benefit is not just about eating less; it is about thinking less about eating. </p>

<p>Again, intermittent fasting is not for everyone, so please consult your health care provider about the options that are best for you for managing food cravings, nutritional requirements, weight control, and overall health. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/liking-the-child-you-love/202602/a-surprising-way-to-reduce-hunger-without-weight-loss-drugs" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/liking-the-child-you-love/202602/a-surprising-way-to-reduce-hunger-without-weight-loss-drugs</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/liking-the-child-you-love/202602/a-surprising-way-to-reduce-hunger-without-weight-loss-drugs</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeffrey Bernstein Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-03/louis-hansel-woman%20eating%20unsplash.jpg?itok=zEkZ0bay" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>