<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 14:25:36 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 14:25:36 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Do So Many Gay Men Hate Their Bodies?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-02/Chris%20Tompkins%20%281%29.png.jpg?itok=yiWElR_3" alt="Chris Tompkins LMFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Body Image</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Do So Many Gay Men Hate Their Bodies?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The "male gayzed" is a lens gay men don't realize they're looking through.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Gay men experience eating disorder rates 42 to 49 percent higher than heterosexual men.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Gay men face unique body image challenges driven by minority stress, internalized shame, and pornography.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research suggests that fostering body positivity is crucial for improving mental health in gay men.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/julee-juu-zndWqyDWkD4-unsplash.jpg?itok=eONJk7fj" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Julee Juu / Unsplash" alt="Julee Juu / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Julee Juu / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Earlier this year, Olympic gold medalist Tom Daley opened up about his struggles with an eating disorder and the shame he's carried about being gay in a documentary, <em>Tom Daley: 1.6 Seconds</em>.</p>
<p>His willingness to speak openly about his experience points to something many of us already know but don't always say out loud. Even with visibility, success, and legal progress, the internal wounds of growing up in a world that tells us we're wrong still linger, and for many gay men, they can appear most painfully in our relationship with our bodies.</p>

<p>The term "male gaze" was coined by feminist film critic Laura Mulvey in 1975 to describe how visual media is structured from a masculine, heterosexual perspective, depicting women as objects of desire while positioning men as the ones doing the looking. Women learn to see themselves through this lens, internalizing how they're perceived rather than how they actually are.</p>

<p>For gay men, something similar happens, but with its own distinct texture. We don't just internalize the broader culture's judgments about masculinity and femininity. We also absorb the specific beauty standards, body ideals, and hierarchies of desirability within our own community.</p>
<p>I call this the <em>male gayzed</em>, the lens through which gay men learn to view themselves and each other, measuring worth by how closely we match narrow standards of attractiveness, masculinity, and physical perfection.</p>

<p>For most gay men, the male gayzed begins long before we come out or set foot in a gay bar. Most gay youth learn about sex through pornography, often before they've had any real sexual experience of their own. The bodies in mainstream gay porn are almost uniformly muscular, young, and manicured. Before a gay man has had the chance to develop his own sense of desire or understand what he likes, porn has already told him what gay men are "supposed" to look like and introduced him to a standard of desirability he'll spend years measuring himself against without ever knowing where it came from.</p>

<p>Studies show gay men report significantly lower body esteem, higher body dissatisfaction, and eating disorder rates that are between 42 and 49 percent higher than those of heterosexual men. Gay men are also more likely to engage in self-objectification, viewing our bodies from an observer's perspective rather than from the inside out, which leads to greater body shame over time.</p>

<p>Gay men who are feminine-presenting, larger-bodied, or lower-income tend to face an even greater burden, and community labels like twink, bear, and daddy, while sometimes worn with pride, can also reinforce hierarchies of desirability that leave a lot of men feeling like they don't quite belong, even within a community where they’re supposed to feel safe.</p>

<p>Gay bars have long been a cornerstone of gay culture, but they're also where the male gayzed moves from the private world of a screen into public life. For 11 years, I worked at a gay bar in West Hollywood, and one of the things I noticed early on was how pervasive body standards were in every aspect of the environment. Every piece of marketing featured shirtless men with abs. Go-go dancers, a fixture of gay bar culture, almost always fit a very specific physical ideal. Even bartenders were hired based heavily on appearance. The message, whether intentional or not, was clear about what kind of body had value.</p>


<p>I remember when I first started serving, taking over another server's section on a busy Sunday afternoon. When I walked up to introduce myself to a large group of attractive and physically fit gay men, they looked me up and down. One of them yelled, "Oh no honey, bring back the hot server!" I turned around and walked away. I felt defeated and gave the table to another server.</p>

<p>After working at a popular gay bar for as long as I did, I heard many similar stories from coworkers. The strain of trying to meet a certain standard was exhausting, and the feeling of inadequacy was pervasive. I wore a jacket when I worked, not because I was cold, but because it protected me from feeling judged. I also used substances to get through my shifts, which was a way to anesthetize my shame.</p>



  


<p>The <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lgbtq-affirmative-psychology/202210/the-clinical-implications-internalized-queerphobia">clinical consequences</a> of the male gayzed are real. Depression, eating disorders, substance use disorders, and low self-esteem are all significantly more prevalent among gay men, and body image is often at the center of it. A colleague once shared a tribute she wrote for a young gay man who died by suicide. She wrote, "The pressure he felt living amongst all those hard bodies in West Hollywood got to him like a poison in his brain. I wish he'd known he was beautiful. I wish he'd known his worth.”</p>

<p>I recently came across a photo of myself from my time working at the bar during Pride. I was in great shape, but I can vividly remember almost leaving my shift rather than put on the tight tank top we were required to wear. When I look at the photo now, I feel sadness for the version of myself who couldn't see what was actually there, so consumed by the male gayzed that I missed out on feeling good in my own body and being present with people I really loved.</p>

<p>One practical way we can start to heal from the male gayzed is to intentionally seek out spaces where bodies of all kinds are visible and normalized. For some people that might mean spending time at a Korean spa or bathhouse where nudity is ordinary and non-sexual, and where bodies are varied. For others, it might mean following accounts on social media with different body types, or simply noticing and challenging the internal reaction we have when we see a body that doesn't match the narrow standard we've been conditioned to see as ideal.</p>

<p>The goal is gradual exposure to the reality that there is no single standard of beauty, even if the male gayzed has spent years convincing us otherwise.</p>
<p>Anything we were taught, we can learn to unlearn.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lgbtq-affirmative-psychology/202602/why-do-so-many-gay-men-hate-their-bodies" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lgbtq-affirmative-psychology/202602/why-do-so-many-gay-men-hate-their-bodies</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lgbtq-affirmative-psychology/202602/why-do-so-many-gay-men-hate-their-bodies</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris Tompkins LMFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/vince-fleming-Vmr8bGURExo-unsplash.jpg?itok=Pw21WBz2" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Drs. Dunning and Kruger and 300 Million More Health Experts]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-06/Miller.png.jpg?itok=dzR6E7c1" alt="Miller" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Dunning-Kruger Effect</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Drs. Dunning and Kruger and 300 Million More Health Experts</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Public figures' health misinformation statements are making people sick.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People who don’t know much often think they know more than they know.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Misinformation can start when minimally informed people mistake associations with evidence of causation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People exhibiting the Dunning-Kruger Effect often reject information that conflicts with their beliefs.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cognitive dissonance can help unwind belief in misinformation.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/hhs-hero-make-america-great-again-2-15-26.jpg?itok=GD0xbvUm" width="320" height="178" data-insert-type="image" title="HHS.Gov" alt="HHS.Gov"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: HHS.Gov</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>In a class I recently taught about U.S. Health Care Policy &amp; Politics, I asked the students how many health policy experts there are in the United States. Amidst a field of befuddled faces, one student said "300 million." That is basically the right answer because virtually everyone who has been ill or seen a clinician for a checkup or physical believes they understand the U.S. health care system’s problems and know how to fix them.<a href="#_edn1">[i]</a></p>

<p>This illustrates what is sometimes called the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/dunning-kruger-effect%20">Dunning-Kruger Effect</a> (DKE)<a href="#_edn2">[ii]</a>, in which, for example, someone with some knowledge of a subject believes they know more than people who’ve studied (or worked in) a field for many decades.</p>
<h2>Drs. Dunning and Kruger</h2>
<p>We are now in situation where health misinformation is being promoted by people who have significant public platforms for spreading fallacies, which could be dangerous to the health of individuals, communities, and countries. For example, during and since the COVID-19 pandemic, public figures have repeatedly asserted substantial knowledge and understanding of vaccines while criticizing many actual experts. This resulted in lower vaccine confidence and reinforced many people’s belief in misinformation. Interestingly, in the fall of 2025, many people who had (incorrectly) come to believe that vaccines were a primary cause of autism were confounded (if not distraught) when the U.S. government announced that acetaminophen was a cause of autism without also mentioning vaccines.<a href="#_edn3">[iii]</a></p>

<p>People exhibiting the Dunning-Kruger Effect also often do not understand (or appreciate, or recognize) the difference between associations (or correlations) and causations. An extreme example of that fallacy would be that using sunscreen causes shark attacks. (Both increase during warmer weather, but it does not mean that sunscreens attract sharks.) In contrast, an actual cause-and-effect relationship is that decreased rates of children receiving MMR vaccinations caused an <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/measles/data-research/index.html">increased number of measles infections</a>.</p>

<h2>Identifying False Experts</h2>
<p>As individuals and society strive to reduce the ill effects of health misinformation, one key for assessing someone’s actual expertise is to determine if they have a background that would actually give them deep knowledge of the topic. A second key – or clue – that may identify someone who is a "Dr. DKE" is if they also denigrate and dismiss others who do have deep subject-matter backgrounds, for example by calling them “so-called experts.”</p>

<p>When you look at many misinformation spreaders who believe they are experts, they are usually highly selective in choosing the information they share about a complex situation. Importantly, they reject information contrary to what they already believe, which is known as <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/science-of-choice/201504/what-is-confirmation-bias">confirmation bias</a>.</p>
<p>Thus, two other clues for assessing the validity of health information from people who profess to be experts are: Do they describe something as evidence of causation when it is only an association or a correlation? And do they dismiss information that conflicts with their stated “expert” insights?<a href="#_edn4">[iv]</a></p>

<h2>What to Do About Drs. Dunning and Kruger?</h2>
<p>The first step in defusing false information<a href="#_edn5">[v]</a> is to recognize it – as discussed above. The next step is to create some cognitive dissonance so that a misinformed person questions their belief in the falsehood. <br><br>Clinicians are likely too busy to have extended conversations with misinformed patients, but one shortcut they can try with someone resistant to get a recommended vaccine is to ask “Who would you get vaccinated for?” This direct question might create cognitive dissonance since it challenges the patient to ask themselves who they love enough to question their belief in vaccine misinformation. (A similar question could be asked of a patient who is refusing to take a medicine for a chronic illness like diabetes or high blood pressure. The difference being that with a vaccine the patient might be indirectly protecting a loved one from getting sick, but with those conditions they would be primarily trying to avoid their own death or disability which could burden their child, spouse, or parent.)</p>

<p>As for reducing the influence of misinformation in the public sphere, whether it be on social media or elsewhere, that requires different approaches. One option is to vote with your media choices, since many of those outlets and platforms make their money based upon their numbers of viewers, readers and listeners, or clicks, like and shares. Another avenue is to become more involved with your neighbors and community since it seems that communities with stronger interpersonal ties are more immune to misinformation.<a href="#_edn6">[vi]</a></p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>
<p>People who believe they are experts in a field even though they only know a small amount about the topic are exhibiting the Dunning-Kruger Effect. Those people may resist considering any information that conflicts with their belief in their own expertise. Such people can spread false information about important health matters, such as vaccines, which can lead to health problems for individuals, communities, and countries.</p>

<p>There are four clues to identifying such false experts:</p>
<ol>
<li>They don’t have the background or experience to be an expert.</li>
<li>They denigrate people who do have extensive experience as “so-called experts."</li>
<li>Their explanations of complex matters relies on cherry-picking data points, and to "identify" associations or correlations, which they may incorrectly describe as evidence of causation.</li>
<li>They dismiss any information that is contrary to their false beliefs, sometimes with dismissive statements such as “you’re just trying to confuse things.”</li>
</ol>



  


<p>Reducing the influence of misinformation requires generating cognitive dissonance. Doing this with individuals can be complicated, as I’ve written <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/misinformation-in-life-and-society/202512/3-keys-to-reversing-misinformation-with-cognitive">elsewhere</a>, and in my book <a href="https://www.healthpolcom.com/reversing-misinformation-book/"><em>Reversing Misinformation</em></a>, but it can be done. Resistance to misinformation can also be increased with stronger community connections so that falsehoods that come from the outside (e.g., from social media) are less likely to find a susceptible host.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/misinformation-in-life-and-society/202602/drs-dunning-and-kruger-and-300-million-more-health" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/misinformation-in-life-and-society/202602/drs-dunning-and-kruger-and-300-million-more-health</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/misinformation-in-life-and-society/202602/drs-dunning-and-kruger-and-300-million-more-health</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Miller, MD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/hhs-hero-make-america-great-again-2-15-26.jpg?itok=ETksViaV" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>