<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 16:42:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 16:42:50 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Your Rage Serving You or Hijacking You?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2022-09/Leigh_PT-removebg-preview%281%29.jpg?itok=nQQ84Y6c" alt="Leigh W. Jerome Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Anger</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Is Your Rage Serving You or Hijacking You?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Reactive, righteous, and chronic rage: How to manage angry emotions.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Anger is not a singular emotion, but regardless of the form it takes, anger always feels justified.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Rage activates the sympathetic nervous system and floods the body with stress hormones.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">If your anger feels constant, rumination may be fueling it.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Rage2.png.jpg?itok=dZwLi69U" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Rage1" title="Image L.W. Jerome / Dalle"></div>
<div class="caption">Rage1</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Image L.W. Jerome / Dalle</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>We all face irritations and injustices that produce feelings of hostility, indignation, and frustration. Long meetings, traffic, rude people, disappointments, and betrayals, we all get triggered, and sometimes anger can grow into a sweeping rage. While it’s not always possible to prevent the circumstances that make us angry, we can learn how to manage our reactions when rage overtakes us.</p>

<p>Anger is a basic human emotion, observable even in infancy. Anger ranges from mild irritation to extreme furor, tending to evoke defensiveness or attack (Januszewski, 2016). It has evolved as a means for preparing an organism for a challenge. While anger is a normal emotion, it is not without physiological consequences. Anger activates the sympathetic nervous system, raising heart rate and blood pressure in ways similar to the body’s fight-or-flight response. Anger generates an immediate stress response and floods the body with adrenaline and cortisol that can weaken the immune system for hours after the actual event, reducing the body's ability to defend against infections (Alotiby, 2024). Intense rage or chronic anger elevates these hormones in the long term, decreasing immunity for a prolonged period and increasing risks of inflammation and heart disease.</p>

<p>Anger affects one psychologically as well. As a self-defense mechanism, anger is <em>always</em> experienced as a justified response, a protection against antagonism, injustices, and perceived wrongdoing (Alotiby, 2024). Anger activates our brain in a way that suppresses fear, pain, and shame, so it can override inhibitory controls on aggressive behavior. Anger lowers the threshold for responding reactively to a perceived provocation. It narrows the focus of the aggrieved person, moving them toward either retaliation or restoration of their loss of power, and it heightens the likelihood of impulsive and risk-taking behavior (Pop and colleagues, 2025). Further, when there is rumination about the triggers of the anger, the anger reaction lengthens and amplifies. Over time, holding onto, overreacting, or centering anger can damage relationships, interfere with job performance, and reduce well-being (Karppinen, King, and Russell, 2023; Umbra and Fasbender, 2025).</p>

<p>Whether or not an experience of anger is problematic depends on context, frequency, latency, intensity, duration, and mode of expression (Alotiby, 2024). Anger is not a singular emotion. It can reflect a physiological state, a set of appraisals, an action tendency, a personality trait, and sometimes a moral posture (Spielberger, Reheiser, and Sydeman, 1995). All anger starts as a constructive emotion, a defensive response to some kind of threat (Sznycer and Cohen, 2021). Whether anger leads to constructive or destructive expression depends not on the emotion itself, but on how an individual regulates and directs their response (Januszewski, 2016). People who tend to avoid problems, dwell on them repeatedly, or push their feelings down are likely to experience more intense and longer-lasting anger. People suppress anger to avoid conflict or out of fear of harm, rejection, or abandonment. When anger is not expressed outwardly, but rather turned inward and redirected toward oneself, it can lead to depression, anxiety, and self-loathing (Sahu, Gupta, and Chatterjee, 2014). People who can accept what they are feeling and rethink a situation in a broader way (i.e., cognitive reappraisal) tend to experience less anger and recover from it more quickly (Pop and colleagues, 2025). Anger is not only about what happened. It is also about what you do with what happened.</p>

<p>Reactive anger is an immediate, intense, and unregulated anger response. Aggressiveness, such as yelling, withdrawing, name-calling, and physical aggression are characteristic of reactive behavior. While all emotions are valid, reactivity is an expression of anger without reflection. It is frequently impulsive and overreactive, and it is more likely to impair judgment. Another form of destructive anger is passive aggressiveness, where, rather than open defiance, an expression of anger is sugar-coated or indirect. When a stinging comment is made with a smile or a back-handed compliment is dropped, the intent is still hostile and can lead to significant relational difficulties, where trust erodes, and resentments build. Righteous anger is a more delayed and sustained kind of anger related to one’s identity, beliefs, and moral compass. Moral conviction without agency can harden into frustration and helplessness.</p>

<p>For some people, anger becomes chronic, where irritability, contempt, or resentment are present all the time rather than temporarily, in response to a specific trigger. Rumination is the most common way anger becomes chronic. Rumination can feel like moral vigilance, as if replaying the evidence is necessary to remain on guard for possible attacks. But rumination is a fuel source. It keeps your body and mind in prosecutorial mode. Over time, the cost is not only distress; it is a narrowing of attention, where impressions crystalize and the capacity for empathy and nuance diminish (Januszewski, 2016; Pop and colleagues, 2025).</p>

<p>Constructive expressions of anger issues act as a catalyst for positive change or personal growth. To channel anger constructively means not to run, freeze, or fight but to respond to the emotion in a way that is reflective, regulated, and respectful. Shift your focus away from the source of the rage. A time out can help you process rage, as can physical exercise. Take a short walk or step into a quiet, darkened space for a little deep breathing. Honor your anger by naming it. Notice your impulses. Your feelings are valid. You are only accountable for your actions and the consequences of your response. Scan your body and notice where you are experiencing the emotion. Breathe. These steps will help to regulate your nervous system to become calmer and more balanced, so you can think clearly and decide on an intentional, positive response. At its core, your anger is telling you there is a problem. Anger that is anchored in threat perception alone, without reflective appraisal or a framework for constructive action, results in escalation and negative outcomes. Anger, when interpreted as information, can mobilize psychological resources and motivate behaviors that serve to correct the situation (Novaco, 2016). Anger, well managed, can be energizing and empowering. When anger is understood as aligned with values and tethered to thoughtful action, it can be a source of clarity and momentum.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-stories-we-tell/202602/is-your-rage-serving-you-or-hijacking-you" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-stories-we-tell/202602/is-your-rage-serving-you-or-hijacking-you</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-stories-we-tell/202602/is-your-rage-serving-you-or-hijacking-you</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Leigh W. Jerome Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Rage1.png.jpg?itok=PZE9-9Mx" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Reasons You Feel Guilty for Wanting More]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/photoofmarktravers.png.jpg?itok=4rcV_Py2" alt="Mark Travers Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Guilt</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Reasons You Feel Guilty for Wanting More</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Three ways guilt holds you back from finding the happiness you deserve.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/getty-images-E9hznwnaRCg-unsplash.jpg?itok=pTpNDQLC" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Getty Images / Unsplash" alt="Getty Images / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Getty Images / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>You might feel like your life looks good “on paper,” or maybe it even feels objectively good. You might even have stability, relationships, or opportunities others might envy. And yet, you might feel a quiet sense of restlessness. A sense that you want more growth, more meaning, and more alignment in your life. But instead of excitement, that desire comes with guilt.</p>

<p>Many people feel ashamed for wanting more when their life already meets the criteria for “good enough.” Psychology suggests this guilt is not a sign of ingratitude or entitlement. It is the product of how self-worth, social comparison, and early learning shape our relationship to desire. Research shows that wanting more and feeling guilty about it often come from the same psychological roots.</p>

<p>Humans are wired for growth. <a href="https://link.springer.com/rwe/10.1007/978-3-031-17299-1_2630">Self-determination theory</a> shows that well-being depends on three core needs: autonomy, competence, and relatedness. Interestingly, meeting external markers of success does not guarantee these needs are met internally.</p>
<p>You can have stability without autonomy, comfort without meaning, or connection without authenticity. When one of these needs is undernourished, the brain generates dissatisfaction as a signal to recalibrate. And that signal often shows up as restlessness or longing.</p>

<p>The problem is that many people interpret this signal through a moral lens rather than a psychological one. Instead of seeing desire as information, they see it as evidence that something is wrong with them. Here are three reasons that your guilt is forcing you to shrink down, even though you want to expand.</p>

<h2>1. You Feel Guilty Because You Don’t Want to Seem ‘Ungrateful’</h2>
<p>One of the strongest predictors of guilt around desire is early emotional socialization. Research on moral emotions shows that guilt develops when people believe they are violating an internalized standard. For many, that standard is the belief that appreciation and ambition cannot coexist.</p>

<p>This belief often forms early in life. Children who were praised for being easy, compliant, or low maintenance may have learned that wanting more attention, support, or stimulation created tension or disappointment. Over time, the nervous system links desire with relational risk.</p>
<p>As adults, this link can manifest as intrusive thoughts that may sound like:</p>

<ul>
<li>“I should just be grateful.”</li>
<li>“Other people have it worse.”</li>
<li>“I do not deserve to want more.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Self-silencing, particularly in close relationships, leads to suppressing needs to maintain harmony, which has been associated with increased anxiety and depressive symptoms over time. Gratitude becomes a tool for minimizing the self rather than appreciating reality.</p>


<h2>2. You Feel Guilty Because You Feel Obliged to Be Content</h2>
<p>Modern life intensifies guilt through constant comparison. Social comparison theory shows that people evaluate their worth and success relative to others. When upward comparison dominates, it creates a sense of inadequacy. In other words, when we compare ourselves to those who have it better than us, we feel worse. But downward comparison creates a different problem.</p>

<p>When you compare yourself to those who have less, wanting more can feel morally suspect. <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2017.01554/">Research</a> shows that people often engage in what psychologists call comparative guilt. This happens when personal desire conflicts with perceived social fairness. The internal dialogue becomes, “If I already have more than average, who am I to want more?”</p>



  


<p>This mindset frames fulfillment as a zero-sum resource. But psychological research does not support the idea that personal growth deprives others.</p>
<p>In fact, <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/259043450_The_power_of_one_Benefits_of_individual_self-expansion">studies</a> on self-expansion show that pursuing growth-oriented goals often increases empathy, creativity, and contribution rather than selfishness. The guilt is not evidence that your desire is wrong. It is evidence that you are measuring your inner life using external comparisons.</p>

<h2>3. You Feel Guilty Because You Think You Owe People Stability</h2>
<p>Another reason wanting more feels uncomfortable is that many people are rewarded for stability rather than authenticity. Adults often remain attached to roles and life structures that once ensured safety, even after they stop being psychologically nourishing.</p>

<p>Outgrowing a version of your life does not mean it was a mistake; it might simply mean that it worked for who you were, not who you are becoming.</p>
<p>But change threatens identity continuity. In other words, people experience distress when growth challenges their existing narrative of who they are. And in the scenario, guilt acts as the emergency brake system and keeps you loyal to an outdated self-story by framing change as betrayal.</p>

<p>This is especially common in high-functioning individuals who are praised for being responsible, or for having an extraordinary level of resilience, or for being “the most reliable person” someone knows. In short, wanting more feels like destabilizing an identity that others depend on.</p>
<h2>Why Gratitude and Guilt Shouldn’t Cancel Each Other Out</h2>

<p>Psychological health does not require choosing between gratitude and growth. You can hold appreciation for what you have and curiosity about what else is possible. These states activate different neural systems and are not mutually exclusive.</p>
<p>Here’s how you can reframe things in a more helpful way: Gratitude acknowledges what has supported you, and desire listens to what is emerging. Most importantly, ignoring either creates an imbalance.</p>

<p>People experience less guilt and more meaning when they pursue goals aligned with intrinsic values rather than external validation or comparison. So, the question is not whether you are allowed to want more. The real question is whether you are listening to what your desire is trying to tell you.</p>
<p>Feeling guilty for wanting more in a good life is a learned emotional response shaped by social norms, early experiences, and misunderstanding desire. Psychology shows that longing often signals growth, not dissatisfaction. And guilt often signals internalized rules that no longer fit.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-reasons-you-feel-guilty-for-wanting-more" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-reasons-you-feel-guilty-for-wanting-more</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-reasons-you-feel-guilty-for-wanting-more</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Travers Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/getty-images-E9hznwnaRCg-unsplash.jpg?itok=jiwRjsTd" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Is Life?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/trverny_0.png.jpg?itok=2BAhleY0" alt="Thomas R. Verny M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Evolutionary Psychology</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What Is Life?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The long ascent from matter to mind</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">What constitutes life, and how did it originate?</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Life likely emerged from nonliving matter aided by asteroids striking a turbulent, chaotic Earth.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Natural selection may not be the primary driver of adaptive evolution.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Self-organizing molecules slowly acquired memory, agency, and, eventually, consciousness.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>I watch Rufus, a friend’s dog, chew enthusiastically on a rubber bone. I know the dog is alive, and his toy is not. I know that intuitively. But can I prove it scientifically? Can science parse the distinction between life and inert matter? </p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Asteroid%20impact:ChatGPT.png.jpg?itok=HqlpKa11" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" alt="Asteroid impacts Earth" title="Generated with AI / ChatGPT"></div>
<div class="caption">Asteroid impacts Earth</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Generated with AI / ChatGPT</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>To be considered alive, does something have to be able to reproduce, move, grow, and process energy? Any definition along these lines is riddled with exceptions. For instance, is a virus alive? While viruses do evolve, they don’t replicate on their own. They use the host’s tissues to make copies of themselves.</p>

<p>In <em>Star Trek: The Next Generation,</em> the definition of life as something that “absorbs compounds from its environment,” “excretes waste,” and “grows” is famously challenged by characters like Data to show its limitations. Fire or crystals, for example, also consume nutrients, which are energy, “excrete” waste, and grow, yet are not considered alive. Throughout <em>Star Trek</em>, the ultimate definition of life, particularly when discussing androids or artificial intelligence, often centers on sentience, consciousness, and self-awareness rather than just biological or metabolic functions. However, these are abstract concepts that are difficult if not impossible to define scientifically.</p>

<p>One of science’s most enduring riddles is what constitutes life and how cells that metabolize, replicate, and adapt emerged from matter that was once inert. Many scientists speculate that the early bombardment of Earth by asteroids set in motion a cascade of chemical and environmental changes, culminating in the appearance of the “last universal common ancestor,” endearingly called LUCA.</p>

<p>After impacting Earth, materials from asteroids may have undergone further transformation in hydrothermal settings before being transferred to surface environments where cycles of drying, re-wetting, and ultraviolet exposure concentrated them, packaged them into primitive membranes, and allowed rudimentary selection to occur. Evolutionary biologists believe that organisms with cellular nuclei appeared around 1.8 billion to 2.7 billion years ago. Then there was the transition to multicellular organisms around 1.6 billion to 2 billion years ago, the abrupt diversification of body forms in the Cambrian explosion 540 million years ago, and the appearance of central nervous systems around 520 million years ago.</p>

<p>In the last few decades, major scientific breakthroughs across disciplines, from chemistry and biology to astrobiology, geology, and even philosophy, have shed new light on the evolution and definition of life. Several recent international meetings have addressed these issues.</p>
<p>A few months ago, in Kyoto, Japan, the ALIFE 2025, Artificial Life Conference, was held. The theme was “Ciphers of Life,” exploring information, computation, emergence, and what counts as life in artificial and natural systems. Mike Levin of Tufts University was one of the many distinguished speakers. In his talk, he emphasized the importance of acknowledging and, in fact, utilizing the goal-directedness of life as a critical step in the maturation of the life sciences. His focus on agency in living systems seems to me closely related to the dominant theories about life on <em>Star Trek</em>. Kudos, <em>Star Trek.</em></p>

<p>At the Oxford 2026 Evolution Conference last month, Raju Pookottil gave a presentation called “BEEM: Biological Emergence-based Evolutionary Mechanism: How Species Direct Their Own Evolution.” Pookottil, an engineer and a self-taught evolutionary scientist, advanced the heretical idea that natural selection may not be the primary driver of adaptive evolution. Rather, he said, “Organisms may direct their own evolutionary trajectories.”</p>

<p>In this view, organisms assess challenges, devise solutions, and transmit them across generations. Ants act as agents within colonies; complex protein networks perform analogous roles within cells. Genes, he argues, are tools rather than tyrants. Organisms can regulate gene expression and repair many accidental changes.</p>

<p>Mutations, Pookottil suggests, are often not random, and when they are, they are frequently corrected within a few generations. Many studies show that mutations are uncommon, and in medicine, the mutations we most often notice are often harmful (disease and cancer).</p>
<p>A substantial amount of ink and lately, electricity, has been spent by scholars in efforts to pin life down with a tidy definition. Following a suggestion by Carl Sagan, NASA adopted a definition of life as “a self-sustaining chemical system capable of Darwinian evolution.” The word “system” was chosen deliberately, acknowledging that components of living systems—cells, viruses, even organisms—may not individually exemplify life in isolation. “Self-sustaining” was meant to exclude entities that require constant external intervention to exist. “Darwinian evolution” served as shorthand for replication with heritable variation and differential fitness.</p>

<p>From the outset, this process required mechanisms that allowed molecules to change adaptively over time. As Pookottil suggested, there are many other processes besides Darwinian evolution responsible for the long ascent from matter to <em>Homo sapiens.</em></p>
<p>The transition from non-life to life was a gradual process involving planetary habitability, prebiotic chemistry, molecular self-replication, self-assembly, and the emergence of membranes aided by asteroids striking a turbulent, chaotic Earth. What began as self-organizing molecules slowly acquired memory, agency, and, eventually, consciousness.</p>



  


<p>From the cacophony of the voiceless early Earth, over vast stretches of time and space, a few notes gradually arose, forming a melody played on various instruments in various combinations until it triumphed in a symphony: life.</p>
<p><strong>This article also appears on </strong><a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/article-what-is-life-the-long-ascent-from-matter-to-mind/"><em><strong>The Globe and Mail</strong></em><strong>.</strong></a></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/explorations-of-the-mind/202602/what-is-life" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/explorations-of-the-mind/202602/what-is-life</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/explorations-of-the-mind/202602/what-is-life</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Thomas R. Verny M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Asteroid%20impact%3AChatGPT.png.jpg?itok=9G4FTaQ9" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jimmy Sotos on Catching Up and Going Viral Overnight]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-08/DB-PT-image-removebg-preview%20%281%29.jpg?itok=Ykm4vE3S" alt="Duygu Balan LPCC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Social Media</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Jimmy Sotos on Catching Up and Going Viral Overnight</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Male body image, identity, and the hidden mental health cost of content creation</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">How a late-blooming athlete internalized performance as identity and carried that wiring into digital fame.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">There's a psychological impact of turning your physique into a monetized product.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Diversification of identity roles can function as psychological protection.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_3429%202.JPG.jpg?itok=G64YEVts" width="320" height="469" data-insert-type="image" alt="Jimmy Sotos" title="Joe Gemma, used with permission"></div>
<div class="caption">Jimmy Sotos</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Joe Gemma, used with permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>I had the pleasure of speaking with Jimmy Sotos about overnight visibility and the mental strain of living inside the algorithm.</p>
<p>Sotos grew up the youngest of four boys in a basketball family. His father played professionally in Greece, and his brothers played as well. He describes his brothers taking him to the gym, investing in him, rooting for him, love and expectation intertwined with the pressure to be good. He knew early on that time and energy were being poured into him, and he wanted to make it worth their while.</p>

<p>“I was maturing late in life,” he reflects. “So in order to keep up with my peers, I had to really train hard and work on my craft.” He remembers being 5’2” as a freshman in high school and thinking, “They don’t know what’s gonna hit them. Once I catch up to them physically, I’m gonna be way more skilled,” he says. “I would bank on this idea and keep training.”</p>

<p>At 15, he made a deal with his father: If he earned a scholarship, he would not need a job. Basketball would be his job.</p>
<p>“I convinced my dad that if I got a scholarship, I could put the hours I would have spent working a job into my game.”</p>
<p>The scholarship came. Along with it came a self-imposed standard that followed him into every chapter of his life.</p>

<h2>From Athlete to Algorithm</h2>
<p>Sotos’ identity was organized around sport. His father’s motto was: “If you’re the best player in the gym, you’re in the wrong gym.” That ethos of seeking harder competition and never plateauing became his internalized narrative.</p>
<p>“I was always Jimmy the basketball player,” he says. “And then overnight, it was Jimmy the TikToker.”</p>

<p>His rise was abrupt. “I went from a couple thousand followers to hundreds of thousands in a week, and then from there to over a million in less than a month.”</p>
<p>“All of a sudden, no one seems to care if I’m not playing well. They just care if I post a video.”</p>
<p>In performance-based industries, the body becomes currency. In digital culture, that currency is tracked in real time.</p>

<p>“They really like the videos with my shirt off,” Sotos says. “So now I’m getting comfortable objectifying and kind of sexualizing myself on the internet.”</p>
<p>He describes a perfect storm: monetization, virality, modeling contracts in New York, and constant scrutiny of his appearance.</p>
<p>“We weren’t supposed to know how all these people think about us,” he says. “You have 100 people tell you they love you, that one person that says you’re a loser… that one just sticks.”</p>

<h2>“Prepare to Hate Your Body”</h2>
<p>In Los Angeles, a well-known model told him, “Prepare to hate your body.”</p>
<p>He brushed it off. “Don’t project your stuff onto me.”</p>
<p>Then he started modeling in New York.</p>
<p>“I remember being as thin as I’ve ever been, and they were asking if I could get even thinner. I was like, damn, bro, even thinner?”</p>

<p>Male body image concerns often look different from female presentations. The goal is often lean and muscular at the same time. That can mean restriction, overtraining, obsessive food tracking, and strategic dehydration. These behaviors can turn into disordered eating symptoms but are often dismissed as discipline or optimization (Pope, Phillips, &amp; Olivardia, 2000).</p>

<p>For Sotos, the pressures of being a Division I basketball player, a model, and an online personality converged. He was studying anatomy, nutrition, food science, and recovery while navigating an industry where aesthetics were prioritized over health or skill.</p>
<p>Coffee, which later became a business venture and passion, initially functioned as an appetite suppressant. “I realized I could just drink coffee all day and not eat till later,” he explains. Before shoots, he would manipulate his hydration levels. “I would drink coffee to dehydrate myself, so my veins would pop, so I’d be more vascular.”</p>



  


<p>Sotos compares food intake and the effort to stick to a healthy diet to the effort of abstinence from alcohol.</p>
<p>“You can go your whole life and not have alcohol, and you’d be good. But you can’t stop eating. You have to eat.”</p>
<p>Eating becomes a constant mental struggle in which each meal involves calculation and rationalization, and each social event includes negotiation. “Should I be eating this? How much of it? Can I afford this cheat meal right now?”</p>

<p>In male athletes, disordered eating and body dysmorphia can hide behind performance goals and be reinforced by coaches and peers. In male models and content creators, the algorithm becomes the judge, resulting in a constant feedback loop: post, monitor, adjust, repeat. The body transforms from being experienced to being managed (Wolfers &amp; Utz, 2022).</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/JS%20coffee%20pic.JPEG.jpg?itok=QUMi1RFa" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Jimmy Sotos" title="Daniel Tran, used with permission"></div>
<div class="caption">Jimmy Sotos</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Daniel Tran, used with permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>The Myth of “Real Problems”</h2>
<p>Sotos hesitates when discussing mental health advocacy.</p>
<p>“My problems are so first-world… I have friends that have real problems.”</p>
<p>Many high-functioning men minimize their distress. Because they are financially stable or socially privileged, they disqualify their own distress. But suffering is not a competition.</p>

<p>Achievement has no real measurement in content creation. Virality replaces victory and becomes something that is constantly chased. Metrics replace medals. There is no final buzzer. When posts go viral, the focus shifts to the next post. The constant question becomes, “Am I enough?”</p>
<p>“It’s easy to celebrate sports… You win, or you lose. Content creation is different. You can always do more.”</p>

<p>When a partner sent him an edible arrangement for reaching a digital milestone, he recalls finding it hard to celebrate: “Huh, this is an accomplishment, I guess?”</p>
<h2>Multifaceted as Protection</h2>
<p>“I’ve just learned that I’m very multifaceted… I’m not just the basketball player, I’m not just the model, I’m not just the guy that yaps about coffee.”</p>

<p>For him, role diversification became resilience. Instead of overidentifying with his persona as a basketball player, basketball became “a vehicle for self-expression.” Content creation, modeling, coffee entrepreneurship, music interests, and family roles each contributed to his sense of self.</p>
<h2>The Necessary Delusion</h2>

<p>“You need a healthy dose of confidence… You need a little bit of delusion,” he says.</p>
<p>“As a realist, it’s like, who the f--- do you think you are to think you can make it amongst seven billion people? But you kinda have to believe it, you know.”</p>
<p>Ambition requires imagined possibility. In performance-based cultures, self-belief carries individuals through developmental gaps, public scrutiny, and industry pressure. Sotos’ early internal dialogue about catching up physically evolved into a broader sense of self, one that is not up for public vote.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/un-numb/202602/jimmy-sotos-on-catching-up-and-going-viral-overnight" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/un-numb/202602/jimmy-sotos-on-catching-up-and-going-viral-overnight</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/un-numb/202602/jimmy-sotos-on-catching-up-and-going-viral-overnight</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Duygu Balan LPCC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_3429%202.JPG.jpg?itok=fHcxbhAD" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why We Fall for Scams]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-09/moya_picture_2-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=_wCgDs9i" alt="Lindsay Weisner Psy.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Persuasion</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why We Fall for Scams</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Research on personality traits helps explain why some of us fall for scams.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A scam is a false promise of something or someone that doesn't exist.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Peer pressure, need for consistency, and lack of self-control make certain people vulnerable to scams.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Recently scams have begun to prey more on those who respect authority.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-tara-winstead-7111608.jpg?itok=Iax_hJfg" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Sometimes it's tough to see what's right in front of you." title="Tara Winstead / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">Sometimes it's tough to see what's right in front of you.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Tara Winstead / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">“Sorry, I’m running late for lunch, I’ll see you soon,” the text reads.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Confused, you write back, “I’m sorry, you have the wrong number.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">“Oh, no! I was supposed to meet my friend for lunch. I must have messed up her phone number. I apologize, I’m Mary.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">But Mary isn’t texting the wrong number. She is trying to attract potential fraud victims. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Mary will soon tell you about her family, her personal issues, and her financial woes as she struggles to make a living. You become fast friends, or more than friends if Mary has struck gold and found a willing romantic partner to dupe with this scam.</p>
<h2>What is a scam?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">A scam is an exchange whose purpose is to gain your trust and inspire a sense of urgency by offering the promise of something that doesn’t exist, whether that something is money, love, or power. </p>

<h2>What makes people fall for a scam?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">According to a 2013 study by David Modic and Stephen E.G. Lea, some individuals are more likely to comply with scams than others. To answer the question of who is more likely to fall for a scam, the authors created a Susceptibility to Persuasion Scale, which was tested and normed on 250 undergraduate students. This scale determines your likelihood of falling for a scam as opposed to the general likelihood of the population at large. What makes someone more likely to fall for a scam?</p>

<ol>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Authority or respect for those in power. </strong>For example, listening to the advice of your parents, following the rules of a teacher, or – in the case of scams – heeding the warning of a (purported) representative of your bank or financial institution who tells you they need to protect your savings account but requires your password to do so.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Social influence.</strong> We are all swayed by peer pressure, both overt peer pressure (imagine a teenager verbally pressuring someone to have a drink because “everyone else is doing it”) and covert peer pressure (think of adults attending an after-work happy hour where the assumption is that everyone will order an alcoholic drink). When we are unsure of how to react we often look to others for guidance. An example of social influence in a scam would be fake testimonials from people who have purportedly profited from investing in a business.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Need for consistency. </strong>Often, it takes time to realize that an investment is too good to be true, and someone who has a strong need for consistency may not want to appear like a flip-flopper when it comes to making decisions. Once we say yes to something (or someone), we often feel pressure to stick with the plan (and therefore to fall for a scam) even after red flags start to arise. People who stick to the plan despite their reservations have a stronger need for consistency in their words and actions than others who may be more flexible with evaluating new information. </li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Lack of self-control.</strong> Our greatest weakness in falling for scams is often our lack of emotional regulation. Scammers can prey on our emotional responses by making us fearful that our finances are in danger of being harmed or encouraging us to feel like we could be the hero in a situation where someone needs us. Investigating the truth behind a scam doesn’t take long, but it does take a willingness to exercise self-control.</li>
</ol>

<h2>Who falls for a scam more?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Modic and Lea conducted two studies to answer the question of who was more likely to fall for a scam. In Study #1, participants were asked to respond to whether someone was likely to get involved in 14 different situations, including a pyramid scheme, purchasing fake concert tickets, and an online romantic relationship scam. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Participants were also asked three other questions: whether they had ever found a scam plausible, whether they had provided information in this type of situation, and whether they had ever given money to someone.</p>
<p dir="ltr">A whopping 74% of the college students surveyed responded that they had complied with at least one scam in terms of finding the scenario plausible, giving personal information, or losing money. The majority of participants had fallen for at least one scam at some level by finding a scam plausible or giving away some personal information. They found that social influence (peer pressure), a need for consistency, and low self-control contributed to lifetime scam compliance. </p>

<p dir="ltr">In Study #2, a new sample of participants was asked to complete the same Susceptibility to Persuasion Scale but was only asked about what had occurred in the last three years. In this study, all four factors—adherence to authority figures; social influence (peer pressure); a need for consistency; and low self-control—all predicted falling for a scam in the last three years. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Why did adherence to authority predict scam compliance only in the past three years as opposed to across a lifetime? One theory is that modern scams increasingly impersonate banks, large corporations, and fraud departments, whereas older scams did not do so as often.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p dir="ltr">If a too-good-to-be-true offer comes your way and makes you feel a sense of urgency, fear, or flattery, take a minute to pause. Keep in mind that there are certain personality traits that make people more likely to fall for a scam, specifically peer pressure through social influence, a need for consistency in words and actions, adherence to authority figures, and low self-control. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-venn-diagram-life/202602/why-we-fall-for-scams" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-venn-diagram-life/202602/why-we-fall-for-scams</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-venn-diagram-life/202602/why-we-fall-for-scams</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Lindsay Weisner Psy.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-tara-winstead-7111608.jpg?itok=K25kg5TC" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Your Life Is Positively Impacted by Black History Month]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/untitled_4_1.jpg?itok=_6MAmcza" alt="Vernita Perkins, PhD and Leonard A. Jason, PhD" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Race and Ethnicity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Your Life Is Positively Impacted by Black History Month</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The important thing you don't know about February’s Annual Black History Month.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Black American history Is U.S. history.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Black American history significantly shapes U.S. popular culture, which influences world history.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Unlearning and learning the truth about U.S. American history is a pathway to psychological well-being.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>This February has been the 100th anniversary of acknowledging U.S. Black American history and the 50th anniversary of the official recognition of Black History Month.</p>
<p>What explains why so many people overlook this significant month? This absence of acknowledgment raises questions about our collective memory and the values we prioritize. It’s important to consider the consequences of ignoring events that shape our history and identity, diminishing their significance in our shared cultural narrative.</p>

<p>Black History Month, celebrated each February in the United States, traces its roots back to <em>Negro History Week</em>, which was established in 1926 by historian Carter G. Woodson. Officially recognized in 1976, this month-long observance highlights the significant contributions and historic dehumanization of Black Americans. For over 400 years, considerable resistance to acknowledging the full scope of the Black American experience has remained a critical issue.</p>

<h2>Willingness to Unlearn and Learn</h2>
<p>This resistance to and denial of Black American lived experiences is counterproductive, as understanding the history of Black Americans can illuminate many of the challenges currently facing this nation. The origins of <strong>Anti-Blackness </strong>and <strong>Anti-Black Racism</strong>, the systemic dehumanization of Black individuals, and the long-standing inequities in all aspects of life—including leadership, the professional workforce, housing, economic wealth, traffic stops, politics, social connections, neighborhoods, and romantic partnerships—would become clearer if all Americans engaged with and understood this history. Embracing this knowledge is essential for developing a more informed and equitable society.</p>

<p>While many Americans are familiar with Civil Rights icons like Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Rosa Parks, it is essential to acknowledge the thousands of Black Americans who played vital roles in shaping U.S. history. There are inventors, innovators, scientists, educators, business leaders, activists, critical thinkers, and advocates whose contributions have been pivotal in the fight for justice and equality. Recognizing their stories is crucial for a comprehensive understanding of America’s past, the political divisiveness, economic wealth, and the ongoing struggle for <strong>equal living</strong> and <strong>equal justice</strong>.</p>

<p>The mere mention of the term “equal” can evoke discomfort and even anger among those who dehumanize Black Americans. This reaction underscores the deep-seated resistance to acknowledging the fundamental rights and dignity that should be afforded to all individuals equally, regardless of skin color. Such a visceral response highlights the ongoing resistance to admitting systemic Anti-Black racism exists and the urgent need for societal change and transformation.</p>

<h2>Triaging Inequities</h2>
<p>The same Americans who avoid and go silent during Black History Month are more than happy to fill the rest of the calendar year with heritage months in competition with Black History Month. Where does this competition and jealousy come from? When researchers and practitioners with Black American lived experience and expertise are trained to triage inequities, they realize Black people are still the most dehumanized and worst-treated people on Earth. Research reveals that because of this systemic dehumanization, Black Americans endure notable health indicators and a higher mortality rate. A direct relation to depriving Black Americans of social services equal to the benefits white people receive. Many white Americans are offended and complain when Black Americans receive any social support, while they regularly access the same and better social benefits which they don’t see as unfair. </p>

<p>The genocides, erasure, terrorism, human trafficking, violence, and disregard for human and animal life find their direct origins in the globally and legally sanctioned dehumanization of Black Americans and Black people worldwide. Many of the worst atrocities in modern human history used the dehumanization of Black Americans and their enslaved ancestors as a framework for those atrocities. The denial of this context and attempts at erasure of this historical fact to elevate whiteness and other racialized groups prove the depth of social conditioning practiced to keep Black people dehumanized in the U.S. and around the world.</p>

<h2>Historical Context and Psychological Well-Being</h2>
<p>A deeper understanding of these resistances and denial enables U.S. Americans to grasp the intricate complexities and stark inequalities that Black Americans endure. When analyzing societal issues in the U.S. and globally, it is imperative to acknowledge the dehumanization of Black Americans as a fundamental cause of the horrific violence that plagues the world.</p>

<p>Understanding the significance of Black American historical narratives is crucial for your personal well-being, economic stability, and mental health. Throughout your life, gaps in your knowledge about American history have often been filled with myths and deliberate misinformation, resulting in a distorted narrative. This distortion has allowed harmful justifications for the mistreatment of Black Americans to take root, shaping societal views that perpetuate a sense of superiority among those who are not Black, even when these individuals and groups possess marginalized social identities. Recognizing Black American history is essential for developing a more equitable understanding of our shared past and its ongoing impact on the present.</p>



  


<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/lawrence-crayton-hOiDpAZ8Pok-unsplash_0.jpg?itok=xLFYE8rp" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" alt="Studies reveal Black dads are more involved than dads from other groups." title="Lawrence Crayton / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption">Studies reveal Black dads are more involved than dads from other groups.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Lawrence Crayton / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>President Obama became the first to enact universal healthcare in the U.S., despite facing significant backlash, but he was not the first to advocate for such a system. The mere mention of Obama’s achievement can provoke anger among those harboring Anti-Blackness, prompting them to strategize their counterarguments. Both Presidents Roosevelt and Truman attempted to introduce universal healthcare for all citizens. Roosevelt incorporated healthcare into broader social insurance proposals, while Truman presented a national health insurance plan in 1945. However, these efforts encountered fierce opposition from white populations fearing that equal access to healthcare for Black Americans might increase their population, threatening white demographic dominance instead of minimizing Black Americans. Had those policies been adopted, the U.S. could have enjoyed nearly 100 years of universal healthcare, significantly improving American lives.</p>

<p>The point of learning and understanding history is <strong>not</strong> to repeat the mistakes and harms of the past. When facing challenges in your life or observing issues in your communities and workplaces, reflect on the vibrant history of Black Americans. This reflection can provide valuable context for understanding current challenges. This historical approach can empower you to tackle obstacles with greater insight, psychological well-being, and a renewed sense of purpose.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-mental-health-revolution/202602/why-your-life-is-positively-impacted-by-black-history" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-mental-health-revolution/202602/why-your-life-is-positively-impacted-by-black-history</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-mental-health-revolution/202602/why-your-life-is-positively-impacted-by-black-history</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Vernita Perkins, PhD and Leonard A. Jason, PhD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/national-cancer-institute-VJVsEnR_vNE-unsplash.jpg?itok=pZkEGZcW" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>