<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 19:17:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 19:17:07 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Punch the Monkey Tells Us About Parent Abandonment]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-10/image1__2___1_-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=m2bkKpzh" alt="Kaytee Gillis, LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Adverse Childhood Experiences</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What Punch the Monkey Tells Us About Parent Abandonment</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A baby macaque’s story sheds light on the lasting impact of family rejection.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Early family rejection can disrupt a child’s sense of safety and attachment.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In the absence of parental comfort and belonging, many look for other sources of support.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Substitute sources of comfort can help repair the effects of early rejection on attachment and safety.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <h2>Punch: The Abandoned Baby Macaque</h2>
<p>From the moment he was born at Ichikawa City Zoo, Punch, a baby Japanese macaque, was rejected by the one being evolution designed to protect him: his mother. For reasons not fully understood, she refused to nurse or hold him. The tiny infant reached for her, clung to her fur, and desperately sought contact, but his mother showed no signs of bonding. Whether due to stress, inexperience, or instinct, she pushed him away. In the wild, this would have been a death sentence.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/froos3msvullings-reclining-monkey-3484185_1280.jpg?itok=ibqfd026" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="froos3msvullings / Pixabay" alt="froos3msvullings / Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: froos3msvullings / Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Instead, zookeepers intervened. They provided bottle feedings and round-the-clock care to keep him alive, stepping in to take the place of his mother. </p>
<p>These types of things likely happen more often than we know. But, for some reason, this baby monkey captured the hearts of visitors, who followed Punch’s progress. Social media updates showed him gaining strength: We watched him learning to grip with his fingers, and videos showed him exploring his enclosure and learning to climb. But one image in particular captured public attention: Punch curled around a stuffed toy, clinging to it for comfort. It was a heartbreaking image that evoked many emotions, especially for those who have experienced their own parental rejection.</p>

<h2>When Family Becomes Unsafe</h2>
<p>For living things, attachment is a biological necessity. It helps growing babies (and primates) learn to explore their surroundings safely, and helps them develop a sense of identity in the world.<sup>1</sup> </p>
<p>But Punch and his primate family are no strangers to learning about attachment. Decades ago, psychologist Harry Harlow conducted groundbreaking (and controversial) studies with infant rhesus macaques. In his experiments, baby monkeys were given two surrogate “mothers”: one made of wire that provided milk, and one covered in soft cloth that provided no food.<sup>2</sup> The infants overwhelmingly chose the cloth surrogate. They clung to it for comfort and security, leaving it only briefly to feed from the wire figure when necessary. When frightened, they ran back to their soft cloth mother. The results were clear: In times of stress, they wanted comfort. </p>

<p>Harlow’s research reshaped our understanding of attachment. Safety, comfort, and emotional availability are foundational to development. Food alone is not enough. Survival requires connection and comfort, especially from those who are meant to protect us and care for us. And when we don’t have that, it can feel scary. And understandably so. </p>

<p>Punch’s instinct to cuddle a stuffed toy mirrors what Harlow observed decades earlier. In the absence of maternal contact, he sought something—anything—that approximated safety.</p>
<p>Family rejection, whether through abandonment, emotional neglect, or other forms of rejection, destabilizes a child’s internal sense of safety. When caregivers are unwilling or unable to provide consistent comfort, the world can feel unpredictable and frightening. </p>

<p>Children who experience rejection often internalize it. Rather than concluding, <em>“My caregiver couldn’t show up for me,”</em> they conclude, <em>“There must be something wrong with me.”</em></p>
<p>From an evolutionary perspective, this makes painful sense. Maintaining attachment to caregivers is essential for survival. If the bond fractures, the child’s nervous system responds with alarm, such as the example of Punch clinging to a stuffed toy. </p>

<h2>The Need for Connection and Safety Is Biological</h2>
<p>This drive for comfort is biological. To a frightened infant like Punch, left without maternal contact, clinging to a soft stuffed animal is adaptive. In the absence of a regulating caregiver, he reaches for something that approximates warmth and safety.</p>


<p>The behavior reflects the same attachment system that operates in human children: When comfort is uncertain, we grasp for whatever form of connection we can find. Punch showed us something that many of us have seen in ourselves and our clients: a need for support and belonging.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/invisible-bruises/202602/what-punch-the-monkey-tells-us-about-parent-abandonment" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/invisible-bruises/202602/what-punch-the-monkey-tells-us-about-parent-abandonment</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/invisible-bruises/202602/what-punch-the-monkey-tells-us-about-parent-abandonment</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kaytee Gillis, LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/froos3msvullings-reclining-monkey-3484185_1280.jpg?itok=rk5VzaQ4" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Five Strategies to Make Yourself More Lovable]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/douglas_kenrick.jpg?itok=bpSO8cDO" alt="Douglas T. Kenrick Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Five Strategies to Make Yourself More Lovable</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Review of Sonja Lyubomirsky and Harry Reis's book 'How to Feel Loved'</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 25, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">'How to Feel Loved' is a fine example of a scientifically based book full of good advice.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It begins by pointing out that to feel more loved, you need to first make others feel more loved.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The authors suggest five mindsets to make your relationships more mutually affectionate.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>I used to be embarrassed to walk into the “Psychology” section of the local bookstore. Most of the titles on offer there were variations of “pop psychology” that met the criterion for “pop” but not for “psychology.” Psychology is, after all, the discipline that uses <em>scientific methods</em> to analyze human thoughts, feelings, and behavior. But a shockingly large portion of pop-psych books have little or no scientific evidence underlying their confidently stated nuggets of advice about how to improve your relationships, your moods, or bad habits. Many could as easily have been featured in the bookstore section on religion, perhaps in a subsection titled “Untested but Pleasant-Sounding Ideas Related to Pastoral Counseling.”</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/HowToFeelLoved_.jpg?itok=KVMfdWE-" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Harper Collins" alt="Harper Collins"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Harper Collins</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The recently released book <em>How to Feel Loved</em> by Sonja Lyubomirsky and Harry Reis is a shining example of an advice book that really does belong in the psychology section. Sonja Lyubomirsky is a distinguished professor at the University of California, Riverside, who has conducted many years of rigorous research on the causes of happiness and psychological well-being. I have given her book <em>The How of Happiness</em> to several friends and relatives, and recommended it to many others as a great example of useful science-based advice (see my post “<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-murder-and-the-meaning-of-life/202109/7-proven-steps-to-happiness">7 Proven Steps to Happiness”</a>). Harry Reis is a Dean’s professor of psychology at the University of Rochester who has conducted rigorous research on relationships for several decades. I have assigned his papers in my graduate seminars as good examples of thorough and clear scientific writing. Both authors have won awards for their research, based on published findings in the field’s most prestigious journals. I was delighted to learn about their collaboration, and even more delighted after reading the book.</p>

<p>Their collaboration started with a casual conversation about why relationship researchers and happiness researchers don’t talk to one another more. After all, good relationships are a central part of what makes for a happy and fulfilling life.</p>
<p>The book’s title suggests a focus on tactics for you to boost your own feelings of being loved. But in reality, it is mostly about ways you can behave toward others so that they feel loved. The argument is that if you make those other people feel loved, they will, in turn, make you feel loved. As the Beatles put it: “And in the end, the love you take is equal to the love you make.”</p>

<p>Of course, it’s easy to say you should make the other people around you feel loved, but it’s not so easy to pull that off. Some of our default conversational styles, such as talking about ourselves and trying to look cool, get in the way. So does the tendency to fear that our attentions and affectionate feelings will not be reciprocated.</p>

<p>The book is quite nuanced in spelling out various suggestions that stem from their own research, and that of their colleagues, and I was impressed that whenever I had a reservation about a particular suggestion (such as the encouragement to self-disclose intimate details to others), the authors acknowledged that very reservation in the next page or two, pointing out, in this example, that self-disclosure has to be done in small-steps with the right person at the right time. You should read the book to get those nuanced and devilishly important details, but I’ll summarize the central points:</p>

<p>To make yourself feel more loved (by being more loving towards others), you should:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Be willing to share intimate details about yourself.</strong> Go first in taking a chance that the other person will respond favorably. As just noted, they observe that self-disclosure has to be selective, incremental, and thoughtful, and to be done in the right way with the right partner. They detail suggestions for how to make those judgments in a chapter called the <em>“sharing mindset.”</em></li>
<li><strong>Listen carefully when your partner reciprocates with details about their thoughts, feelings, and experiences.</strong> The authors call this the <em>“listening to learn mindset,”</em> and one simple tactic for exercising this capacity is to give yourself the assignment to just listen to your conversational partner the next time, and assume you’ll later be quizzed on the details.</li>
<li><strong>Be truly curious and enthusiastic</strong> <strong>about what your friend, lover, coworker, or even the person sitting next to you on a train ride, is like.</strong> Dig deep and try to understand what the other person is actually like, as part of the <em>“radical curiosity mindset.”</em></li>
<li><strong>Let yourself feel genuine care about and concern for the other person.</strong> And let them see it, in what Lyubormirsky and Reis call the <em>“open-heart mindset.” </em>They talk about an idea developed by Caryl Rusbult and Stephen Drigotas called the “Michelangelo phenomenon,” in which close partners bring out the best in one another, in the way that Michelangelo “released” the beautiful sculpture of David from what was originally a big chunk of marble.</li>
<li><strong>Finally, it is important to accept that, when you hear about another person’s inner thoughts and feelings, and they confess their past misdeeds or failings,</strong> <strong>you might not approve of everything they say, feel, and do.</strong> But just as you do better in life if you accept that you yourself will always have strengths and weaknesses (what they call having <em>self-compassion),</em> you will have better relationships if you develop what they call a <em>“multiplicity mindset,”</em> compassionately accepting the fact that those close to you are always complex individuals, who will never, and should not be expected to, reach your criterion for perfect.</li>
</ol>

<p>As mentioned earlier, the authors describe research relevant to each suggestion and include very thoughtful qualifications. They point to the danger of using the list above to judge your current partners’ failings when you have not yourself shown sufficient openness, curiosity, caring, and acceptance to get the ball rolling. And they note repeatedly that none of these strategies is guaranteed to work with everyone you might hope will feel love for you, so when others close to you don’t reciprocate your openness, curiosity, attention, and caring, it might make sense to invest your efforts in another relationship. </p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-murder-and-the-meaning-of-life/202602/five-strategies-to-make-yourself-more-lovable" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-murder-and-the-meaning-of-life/202602/five-strategies-to-make-yourself-more-lovable</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-murder-and-the-meaning-of-life/202602/five-strategies-to-make-yourself-more-lovable</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Douglas T. Kenrick Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-pixabay-34761.jpg?itok=Tgrg6G6e" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>