<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 22:35:44 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 22:35:44 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI in HR? Yes—but Humans Should Hire Humans]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/kovach.jpg?itok=ibIfJDzr" alt="Robert Kovach Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">AI in HR? Yes—but Humans Should Hire Humans</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">AI is only as good as the humans who run it.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">AI can be incredibly helpful in HR, including identifying skill sets and creating job descriptions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Ultimately, however, the job of assessing talent requires understanding the complexity of people.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Hiring great teams with strong judgment is the best guardrail against the biases of AI.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>If you’re old enough to remember the early 2000s, as the internet really began to take hold and dot coms were still in the bubble and not the bust phase, then the fascination with AI might be a bit familiar. (If you are too young, find a YouTube clip of <em>Today</em> show hosts Katie Couric and Bryant Gumbel trying to understand email. The @ sign was particularly perplexing for them.) One thing that may have faded from memory now is that this was a relatively slow adoption from analog life. Yes, by the 1990s, Amazon was an online bookstore. However, B. Dalton, a huge bookseller with hundreds of stores, remained relatively competitive well into the first decade of this century.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/redd-francisco-5U_28ojjgms-unsplash.jpg?itok=F-_uhurd" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title=" Redd Francisco/Unsplash" alt=" Redd Francisco/Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Redd Francisco/Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>In other words, while excitement ran wild about the internet, email, online shopping and early chat rooms, actual use ran alongside our analog ways. We kept putting stamps on envelopes, going to the mall, and talking on the telephone (or in person!). We used email for low-risk activity or sent a confirmation by post. Online commerce for purchases of books was a low-investment, low-risk foray into the new world long before we managed our stock portfolios via touch screens.</p>

<p><strong>It's been a fast 25 years into the digital era. But full adoption was slower than you might remember.</strong></p>
<p>AI deserves the same excitement (check – we are there.). But it also requires a similar second-tier implementation into our lives until it’s stabilized enough for first-line decision making. When I hear people discuss hiring and AI, it feels as risky as letting Couric and Gumbel manage the Today Show inbox 25 years ago. Human resources is exactly that – it’s the understanding and assessment of people as assets. In most cases the most valuable assets. And often amongst the most expensive. And the most impactful.</p>

<p>Hiring is part science, part art. It requires both deep experience and a leap of faith. Humans are irrational and the choices about which ones we invite into our boardrooms, our showrooms, our factory floors require a species-specific level of insight. We need to both be able to connect with our colleagues in order to be productive, collaborate and reinforce our shared corporate culture and values. Yet we also must fight the biases and tribalism inherent in human decision-making.</p>

<p>Hiring always requires a compromise. Across skill set and experience, personality and budget, timelines and circumstances, something has to give. Even if AI were to help you strike that balance, it needs an enormous understanding of the consequences of each choice. Nearly every hire will have some small question marks. Or some gaps we intend to accommodate or train up. That is a heck of a prompt for ChatGPT. (Truth be told, it’s a heck of an ask for a human.)</p>

<p><strong>AI is only as good as the prompts we give it. And the prompts are only as good as the humans who write them.</strong></p>
<p>Most importantly, perhaps, is that humans are, for now, the most reliable guardrails on AI that we have. We are the only check on each other when it comes to hiring decisions. Someone vets resumes, another does a first-round interview. Others weigh in on the shortlist. But the more we let AI influence the humans we choose, the more we have outsourced our ability to anticipate the decisions that person will make (including how they use AI).</p>

<p>How many times has someone had a great resume and been utterly disappointing in an interview? Or we take an informational interview with someone who is “clearly not the right hire” and they blow us away with other competencies we didn’t know we needed. AI cannot see potential or opportunity that isn’t written down. It rarely questions itself when sent down a path (and most of us are still learning to stop it from giving us perfectly worded renditions of bad ideas).</p>

<p><strong>AI can help us with large amounts of data. But it shouldn’t drive the large decisions.</strong></p>
<p>That doesn’t mean AI has no place in hiring. It can help us write job descriptions, it can cull existing job postings for skill sets and industry terms. It can certainly help with compensation baselines and compliance protocols. As long as the people who oversee its decisions are found, vetted and hired by… other people. Our deeply flawed, change-resistant, consistently inconsistent, emotionally-driven selves are a terrible burden of human <em>being</em>, literally. But, at this stage anyway, only we can manage those same qualities in others. Takes one to know one.</p>

<p>What drives people at work is as much about our own dreams and identities and personal narratives, as it is our skill sets and titles. Hiring and managing and developing people is far more art than science. Sometimes the less rational decision is the right one. Context is everything. Someday, maybe, we will be in awe that humans used to hire using their brains the way that humans used to build bridges with their hands.</p>



  


<p>But let’s keep our heads in the game, for now. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-work/202602/ai-in-hr-yes-but-humans-should-hire-humans" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-work/202602/ai-in-hr-yes-but-humans-should-hire-humans</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-psychology-of-work/202602/ai-in-hr-yes-but-humans-should-hire-humans</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert Kovach Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/redd-francisco-5U_28ojjgms-unsplash.jpg?itok=ADY8Lu_A" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Black Women Face Burnout and the Path to Self-Care]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-05/Leno.png.jpg?itok=b1kF29-r" alt="Leno" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Burnout</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Black Women Face Burnout and the Path to Self-Care</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Understanding the weight of expectation and the quiet shift to choosing yourself.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cultural expectations of strength contribute to burnout in Black women.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Caregiving roles can lead to self-neglect when personal needs are ignored.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">To implement self-care, it's important to reframe it so it's not considered a luxury, but a daily necessity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-vlada-karpovich-6802968.jpeg.jpg?itok=GubAIOpr" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Vlada Karpovich / Pexels " alt="Vlada Karpovich / Pexels "></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Vlada Karpovich / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Black women have long been expected to carry more than most, not just in what they do but in who they are allowed to be. Black women are expected to show strength and resilience. And more than anything, they are expected to always care as if it’s second nature. </p>
<p dir="ltr">From an early age, many Black women are forcibly socialized into roles that prioritize nurturing (daughter, sister, mother, caregiver, etc.). These roles are not inherently burdensome, but when they’re simply expected without recognition or support, they can suddenly feel burdensome. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Over time, what begins as genuine care quickly turns into a chore, then burnout. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Burnout, in this context, does not always look like collapse. It often looks like showing up anyway. It looks like meeting everyone’s needs while quietly setting your own aside. It looks like being dependable, capable, and strong, even when you are tired. But there is that invisible, underlying hate for a task that should bring joy because you care for everyone around you.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">The cost of being 'built for it'</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Black women are constantly told that they are <a href="https://blackwomensstudies.org/blog/2025/5/30/the-burden-of-strength-exploring-the-impact-of-the-strong-black-woman-schema-on-aging-black-womens-health">somehow built to handle more</a>. As “natural” caregivers and having “natural” strength, they can handle more responsibility, more stress, and more emotional labor. </p>
<p dir="ltr">While often framed as a compliment, it’s actually incredibly harmful and demeaning. And when strength and “natural” capability are assumed, struggles are often overlooked. </p>

<p dir="ltr">When Black women face challenges, they’re often minimized or, worse, normalized. The expectation isn’t simply to endure it, but to do so without requiring rest. And when rest is needed but not supported, it can feel uncomfortable when a woman finally admits to needing a break. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Taking a break can carry guilt. And slowing down can feel like letting someone else down.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">When care for others becomes self-neglect</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Studies show that <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9064901/#:~:text=The%20SBW%20is%20a%20%E2%80%9Ccultural,%2C%20and%20able%2Dism).">Black women often feel uncomfortable</a> when they try to step back from these imposed societal roles, even when they know they need to. There is often a fear of neglecting others or not being present enough, as if they can’t fulfill their roles as they’ve always done. </p>

<p dir="ltr">When you consistently place yourself last, your needs do not disappear. In fact, they accumulate. The physical and emotional toll of caring for others grows heavier and heavier until resentment builds. </p>
<p dir="ltr">What once felt like purpose can now feel like unwanted pressure, and this is often the turning point. Not because something dramatic happens, but because the quiet realization sets in that something has to shift.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Self-care is a recalibration, not a luxury</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Self-care is often misunderstood as indulgence or escape. In reality, it requires maintenance. It is the intentional act of tending to your own well-being so that you can remain grounded, present, and whole. </p>
<p dir="ltr">For Black women, embracing self-care can feel unfamiliar at first because it requires unlearning the belief that your worth is tied to how much you do for others, and asks you to consider that your needs are not secondary. It’s like how a car that needs routine maintenance, or your body needs fuel before going for a run. </p>


<p dir="ltr">These things seem obvious, but because of the societal pressure placed on Black women, it is not expected of them to keep the level of care they’ve held for decades or generations. But once that shift, that realization, starts to blossom, everything changes. </p>
<p dir="ltr">When a woman starts to prioritize self-care, it starts to slowly feel like a necessity rather than an option. When rest is no longer earned but required, everything else starts to feel slightly easier. </p>

<p dir="ltr">But more importantly, once a Black woman understands that caring for herself is not taking away from others, she can show up fully for others. The pressure that has been weighing her down starts to lift, and there’s joy in caring for others again.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">Choosing yourself without apology</h2>
<p dir="ltr">There is an irony to all of this. When Black women begin to focus more on themselves (not less), their capacity to care for others actually improves. They are more present, more patient, and more connected. Not because they are doing more, but because they are no longer running on empty. </p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Developing a self-care mindset does not have to be complicated or grandiose. It can begin with something small and daily that is entirely yours. It can be as simple as enjoying a cup of coffee for 15 minutes in the morning. It can be a quiet walk around the neighborhood. It can also be a boundary set to help people understand you’re not available 24/7. It can even just be the allowance to pause without backlash. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Over time, those moments build into something more sustainable. And suddenly, self-care becomes easier for both you and everyone else. </p>
<h2 dir="ltr">And just like that, the shift begins</h2>
<p dir="ltr">You do not have to earn rest. Nor do you have to reach a breaking point to justify taking care of yourself, or have to continue carrying everything in the same way you always have. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Caring for yourself is not an option. Period.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Caring for yourself is an act of love for you and others.</p>
<p dir="ltr">So, the next time you feel the pull to keep going, just to push through and put yourself last, pause. Ask yourself: “What would it look like to care for me at this moment?”</p>
<p dir="ltr">Because when you begin to answer that question honestly, you are not stepping away from who you are and from caring for others. You are finally making space for yourself, and therefore, creating more space for others.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mind-matters/202602/why-black-women-face-burnout-and-the-path-to-self-care" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mind-matters/202602/why-black-women-face-burnout-and-the-path-to-self-care</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mind-matters/202602/why-black-women-face-burnout-and-the-path-to-self-care</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Michele Leno Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-vlada-karpovich-6802968.jpeg.jpg?itok=xGaD-lB6" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>