<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 19:58:43 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 19:58:43 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When You Don’t Remember What Happened During Psychotic Breaks]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-09/Sarah_Merritt_Ryan-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=t8r3gmUY" alt="Sarah Merritt Ryan" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychosis</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">When You Don’t Remember What Happened During Psychotic Breaks</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Insights from Alison MacComber about bipolar schizoaffective disorder.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychosis is not spiritual warfare; it requires medicine just like any other health condition.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Not remembering can be scary because of not knowing how your actions have impacted others.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Not knowing what happened can weigh on you and cause undo shame. You are better off finding out.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Personal development and working hard on yourself is one way to trust and believe in yourself again.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Psychology%20Today%20photo.jpg?itok=DlODMvmM" width="320" height="427" data-insert-type="image" alt="Alison MacComber Choosing Positivity" title="Photo Courtesy of Alison MacComber"></div>
<div class="caption">Alison MacComber Choosing Positivity</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo Courtesy of Alison MacComber</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>I had the honor of interviewing Alison MacComber, a peer of mine I have known for years. She is a wife, business owner, and meaningful member of her family and community. She in fact is the first person I’ve ever met who has openly shared a similar diagnosis to mine (schizophrenia), and I am forever thankful. Even though I remember everything that happened during my breaks and hospitalizations, Alison has shared that she does not remember everything. She has previously explained to me the emotional challenges of not knowing what happened, and I realize she has important insights and wisdom to share with <em>Psychology Today</em> readers about when you don’t remember what happened.</p>

<p><strong>Sarah Merritt Ryan: Tell us a bit about your journey with bipolar schizoaffective.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Alison MacComber:</strong> I was diagnosed with bipolar in 1998 after an arduous mission trip to Mexico, where I got overheated and didn’t sleep for eight days. At the end of those eight days, I was hospitalized and diagnosed. My family did not believe I had a mental illness, so a few years later, my dad encouraged me to stop taking my meds. I then wound up in the hospital again in 2001. That was the worst depression and psychosis of my life. I was hospitalized again in 2004. I had seven hospitalizations in my 20s, three in my 30s, and two in my 40s. With bipolar schizoaffective, you have the mood swings, and then when the mania gets out of hand, it can become psychosis.</p>

<p><strong>SMR: What emotions have you felt, and what have been your challenges to overcome?</strong></p>
<p><strong>AM:</strong> I have felt a lot of shame and guilt about my diagnosis. The main challenge was not just seeing it as some sort of spiritual warfare, but as a brain that was different from others and that needed medicine, just as a diabetic would need insulin. </p>

<p><strong>SMR: Explain what it means to not remember your breaks and black out.</strong></p>
<p><strong>AM:</strong> Some of the days up to my hospitalization I don't remember. The scary part about not remembering is that you don't know how it hurts the people you love, and that's not something I'm proud of. That’s the reason why I never want to be psychotic again, ever.</p>

<p>Finding out can be emotional too. For example, during a hospitalization in my 30s, I found out later I had tried to kill myself by strangling myself with a necklace around my neck. A nurse saw me and stopped me, but I have no memory of that.</p>
<p><strong>SMR: You speak of this desire to know what happened, that you are not comfortable with not knowing, but also being afraid of knowing. How have you confronted these feelings?</strong></p>

<p><strong>AM:</strong> A good friend from college and I have been back in contact the last year and a half, and I told her this week about my <em>Psychology Today</em> interview. I asked if she could shed some light on some things I don't remember. I asked, “Was anyone killed because of me in our senior year of college? She said, “No Alison, nobody died.” I then thought to myself, <em>Oh my gosh. All this time I thought that people had been killed because of me, because I thought I was the Antichrist.</em> I carried the weight and the shame and the guilt of that fear for all this time, so that was really freeing for me. I also asked, “Was I ever in the news? Was I ever famous?” She assured me I was never famous. So that was really freeing for me, because obviously, I don't want to be famous for something bad. It is such a huge relief to finally confront my fears and find out information. I just felt like a weight had been lifted off my shoulders. It was huge.</p>

<p><strong>SMR: What is your advice for others who don't remember what happened during their psychotic breaks?</strong></p>
<p><strong>AM:</strong> Don't wait years and years to find out what happened, because I carried that weight and shame and guilt for years, thinking that people had died because of me. It's literally just been this week that I was able to have that conversation. I would say, don't wait for a long time.</p>


<p><strong>SMR: Where are you at currently with trusting and believing in yourself again after your psychotic breaks?</strong></p>
<p><strong>AM:</strong> The more I do with personal development, the more I trust and believe in myself. For me personally, I want to work hard. I want to say at the end of the day that I did the best I could. I know that if I don't respect myself, then other people won't respect me. If I'm not putting in the hard work, then people won't respect me.</p>

<p><strong>SMR: What is your advice on emotional recovery from psychosis?</strong></p>
<p><strong>AM:</strong> You have to make an effort to come out of your depression, come out of your shame, come out of your lethargy, and work hard. Do the basic stuff, do the hard stuff; it's going to be worth it in the end if you focus on the positive parts of the world, the positive parts of your life, because a sure fire way to end up really depressed laying on the couch all day long is if you don't do the hard work necessary to recover.</p>



  


<p>Do little things, like go for a jog or journal about your experience. Get up and do the dishes, like something simple, to help yourself each day. Just take it one day at a time, one step at a time, and don't expect too much from yourself too quickly, because it's going to take time to overcome that. I would say anytime I've been in the hospital with psychosis, it's taken me a good solid year to sort things out and get over it.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/healing-mind/202602/when-you-dont-remember-what-happened-during-psychotic-breaks" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/healing-mind/202602/when-you-dont-remember-what-happened-during-psychotic-breaks</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/healing-mind/202602/when-you-dont-remember-what-happened-during-psychotic-breaks</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah Merritt Ryan M.S., CPSS]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Psychology%20Today%20photo.jpg?itok=Ej6mtnZp" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Science-Backed Secret to Long-Term Passion]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/justin-j-lehmiller.jpg?itok=yASRMr1j" alt="Justin J. Lehmiller Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sex</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Science-Backed Secret to Long-Term Passion</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">To keep the spark alive, focus on shared growth.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sexual desire often declines as relationships become routine and predictable.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Self-expansion involves growing through new, shared experiences that alter how you see one another.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research links self-expansion to greater sexual desire and satisfaction.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Seeing your partner as distinct and evolving supports attraction.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/divaris-shirichena-LEDcMe8dBPs-unsplash.jpg?itok=2v0V9Pef" width="320" height="400" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Divaris Shirichena on Unsplash." alt="Photo by Divaris Shirichena on Unsplash."></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Divaris Shirichena on Unsplash.</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Romantic relationships often begin with intense passion before settling into something that feels more predictable and routine. However, this doesn’t mean the partners have fallen out of love. It’s just that the intense spark that initially drew a couple together has faded.</p>
<p>Part of the reason for this is because of a decline in novelty. Research shows that we tend to experience a decrease in arousal to the same sexual stimulus over time, but that introducing something new brings it roaring back. This is precisely why sex therapists often encourage couples to try new activities together: novelty is an easy thing you can do to spice things up.</p>

<p>However, a powerful way to augment the effects of novelty is to incorporate it in a manner that also promotes self-expansion.</p>
<h2>What Is Self-Expansion?</h2>
<p>The basic idea behind the concept of self-expansion is that human beings are wired for growth. We have a fundamental drive to expand our sense of who we are, including our skills, identities, experiences, and perspectives. One of the main ways we accomplish this is through our relationships with others.</p>

<p>When we enter a new relationship, we gain far more than just a partner, because our partner may introduce us to all kinds of new things. For example, they might expose you to new music, books, hobbies, friends, ideas, or ways of thinking. Every single one of these things can expand your sense of self.</p>

<p>When this happens, it feels exciting. It’s part of what fuels that passion in the very beginning. However, it's often the case that couples experience a decline in self-expansion over time as they settle into roles and routines. And when expansion slows or even stops entirely, sexual desire typically declines.</p>

<h2>Why Self-Expansion Fuels Sexual Desire</h2>
<p>Self-expansion is about more than mere novelty. It’s about seeing yourself and your partner in new and different ways. This can affect passion and desire for multiple reasons:</p>
<p><strong>1. It Disrupts Predictability</strong></p>
<p>The stability and security of a long-term relationship may lead us to feel very safe with our partners, but it can paradoxically put a damper on eroticism. As therapist Esther Perel argues in <em>Mating in Captivity</em>, familiarity breeds comfort. But when we get too comfortable, we lose the sense of mystery that stimulates desire.</p>

<p>When you and your partner engage in new activities that are challenging or push your boundaries, you introduce uncertainty, surprise, and novelty. While that can feel exciting in and of itself, it can also change perception.</p>
<p>For example, let’s say you and your partner took a dance class together and you witnessed a side of them that you’ve never seen before. Maybe you didn’t know they could move so sensually or confidently. A newfound perspective like this can easily reignite attraction.</p>

<p><strong>2. It Strengthens Commitment</strong></p>
<p>Research has shown that people who create space for growth and expansion within their relationship tend to be more committed to one another, which makes sense. It creates a relationship context that feels enriching instead of confining.</p>
<p>When being with your partner makes you feel more capable, curious, or alive, you’ll be more motivated to invest in and work on the relationship, which can strengthen your connection.</p>


<p><strong>3. It Boosts Sexual Desire</strong></p>
<p>Studies also show that couples who engage in self-expanding activities together report higher sexual desire. That increased desire, in turn, is linked to greater relationship satisfaction.</p>
<p>But how could engaging in non-sexual activities together (e.g., going on an adventure walk, taking a cooking class) affect your sex life? It’s because excitement is transferable. When we engage in novel or challenging experiences with a partner, this creates physiological arousal that can spill over into sexual arousal. </p>

<p>This is the classic “misattribution of arousal” effect: your racing heart during a new experience can potentially amplify how attractive your partner seems because you're attributing some of your excitement to the other person instead of the situation. In this way, you can think of adventure as a unique kind of foreplay.</p>



  


<p><strong>4. It Deepens Emotional Intimacy</strong></p>
<p>Self-expansion isn’t just about the activities we're engaging in. It’s also about vulnerability, because trying new things together can prompt self-disclosure. For example, it might lead one of you to disclose an unspoken desire or hidden fear.</p>
<p>As you explore new ground together and incorporate these new perspectives and experiences into your sense of self, that creates the kind of conditions under which intimacy grows, which may also lead to more desire.</p>

<h2>How to Harness the Power of Self-Expansion</h2>
<p>Incorporating self-expansion doesn't mean you have to completely change your life. It can be done in relatively small ways that ultimately make a big difference. </p>
<p><strong>Try Something Slightly Uncomfortable</strong></p>
<p>Keep in mind that the key to self-expansion isn’t just novelty, it’s growth. This means that it's important to choose activities that push your limits a little. For instance, this could potentially include taking a class neither of you has ever tried before, traveling to a new or unfamiliar place, sharing or acting on a sexual fantasy, or initiating sex in a completely different way. Regardless of the activity, the goal is to try something new where there's the opportunity to see each other in a new light.</p>

<p><strong>Work Toward a Shared Goal</strong></p>
<p>Self-expansion doesn't just have to involve one-and-done kinds of things, like taking a class or a trip. For example, you might train for a mini marathon together, learn a language together, or work on some type of art project together. A larger, recurring activity that involves shared effort can help to create shared identity.</p>

<p><strong>Support Individual Growth</strong></p>
<p>I know this might sound counterintuitive because we just spent a lot of time talking about the importance of doing things together, but it’s also important to support one another’s individuality. Having a little bit of distance and some space to be yourself is also really important for desire.</p>

<p>When your partner develops interests, passions, or hobbies outside the relationship, it creates the opportunity to see them as a distinct person, not just an extension of you. Support each other's individual pursuits because having that little bit of mystery or otherness can spark desire.</p>
<p><strong>Communicate Along the Way</strong></p>

<p>As you continue your journey of self-expansion, it's also important to talk about your experiences, as well as how each of you are changing. For example, what are you curious about exploring in the bedroom these days? Do you want something new or different than you used to?</p>
<p>You might discover that what turns you (or your partner) on now isn’t the same as it was a few years ago. Our desires evolve, which is why sharing them should be an ongoing thing.</p>

<h2>Takeaways</h2>
<p>In long-term relationships, it's common for desire to fade. The culprit isn't necessarily lost lust, but stalled growth. Self-expansion is one of the keys to preventing our relationships from stagnating. It keeps partners curious about one another, it creates opportunities for surprise, and it offers a way to continuously renew attraction and deepen connection.</p>

<p>To keep the spark alive, focus on growth. Try new things, reveal vulnerabilities, and don’t be afraid to rewrite the script. When self-expansion happens, desire often follows.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-myths-of-sex/202602/the-science-backed-secret-to-long-term-passion" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-myths-of-sex/202602/the-science-backed-secret-to-long-term-passion</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-myths-of-sex/202602/the-science-backed-secret-to-long-term-passion</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin J. Lehmiller Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/divaris-shirichena-LEDcMe8dBPs-unsplash.jpg?itok=umw1B9Pn" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Our Fears and Hopes for AI Medicine]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/191.png.jpg?itok=6A9meQ8h" alt="Justin C. Key M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Our Fears and Hopes for AI Medicine</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">We've been speculating about AI in medicine for decades.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Advances in AI are rapidly changing our social and technological landscapes.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Large language models can present false information in satisfying ways that can easily deceive.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Early case studies are showing concerning side effects, including AI-associated psychosis.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Technology has always been and will continue to be best utilized as a tool, with humans at the helm.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>After decades of flourishing in science fiction, AI is having its moment. It’s quickly maturing into a mix of our deepest hopes and wildest fears with some truly head-scratching surprises. Both OpenAI and Anthropic are growing at incredible speeds and are set to usher in a new wave of trillion-dollar companies. Whether or not AI will disrupt industries is no longer speculation: It has, it is, and it will.</p>

<p>As a practicing physician, I have to stay current and adapt. Some changes can be slow, and others happen overnight. When the pandemic hit, I immediately became a non-consenting telehealth psychiatrist. More insidiously, my smartphone has become essential for my practice. From two-factor authorization in prescribing controlled medications to HIPAA-compliant document scanning to communicating with staff and patients on the go, the tech in my pocket has simultaneously made me more productive and more distracted. A 2018 study in adolescents showed a correlation with high digital media use and subsequent symptoms of ADHD. That was eight years ago! The technology is even more ingrained in our day-to-day. And then there’s the potential impact on one of a physician and therapist’s greatest assets: Critical thinking. I already know this from years of GPS making me geographically incompetent, but the studies showing our cognitive offloading to technology can impair critical thinking are sobering.</p>

<p>Like it or not, though, the technology is here. Even if I’m resistant to, or wary about, AI—which I am—if I ignore it, I will be left behind. And my patients will suffer for it.</p>
<p>Anything that becomes ubiquitous so rapidly brings with it unforeseen problems. For AI and large language models, problems like hallucinations are well-known. I asked AI not too long ago about myself. The result: “Justin C. Key is a practicing psychiatrist and author (so far, so good) who wrote the movie <em>Get Out” </em>(I didn’t write <em>Get Out</em>)<em>. </em>For low-risk asks, like ‘how should I populate my raised garden’, a little fantasy will not do much. But for complicated medical issues? You can see where I’m going. Large language models are also sycophants. Like a good social media algorithm, they’re designed to keep you engaged, and that means appealing to your ego. We’re seeing the implications of this in real time. Some results are funny. Others are tragic.</p>

<p>An emergent consequence of AI that this psychiatrist and sci-fi author did <em>not </em>see coming is induced psychosis. Dr. Joseph Pierre, whom I trained under at UCLA, has been researching and writing extensively about this. I would expect prolonged use of LLMs to steer concerning thoughts in those with previously diagnosed psychotic disorders; however, we’re seeing patients with no previous psych history needing multiple hospital stays to come out of their AI-induced delusions.</p>

<p>If this can happen, what other downstream effects might emerge? What will we know relatively quickly, and what might it take generations to realize? Much like Covid, another global change that hit hard and quick, I suspect AI’s long-term effects on our society won’t be fully understood until it’s time to write our chapter in the history books.</p>

<p>But we can all hope, right? Mine is that society continues with the model of medicine that saw us through from bloodletting patients to transplanting organs: human-led with technology as an ever-evolving tool. As a psychiatrist and therapist, bridging a patient’s past to their present is key in extracting important insights from the hard-earned therapeutic relationship and in making sound medical decisions. The idea of an LLM counseling my patient through their suicidal ideation is scary, but the thought of one reminding me of patterns from a patient’s history, interventions that worked versus those that made things worse, and insights into what the thought of dying meant to this person historically, fed to me in real-time, to inform one human trying to save another, is intriguing. Physician burn-out is real, and a 2018 review identified charting and ‘treating the data and not the patient’ as major contributors. </p>

<p>I don’t want AI driving the car, but whether I like it or not, it’s going to be in the passenger seat, yapping away. It’s my job to learn how to listen.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/holding-on-to-humanity/202602/our-fears-and-hopes-for-ai-medicine" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/holding-on-to-humanity/202602/our-fears-and-hopes-for-ai-medicine</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/holding-on-to-humanity/202602/our-fears-and-hopes-for-ai-medicine</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin C. Key M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/iStock-2207625508.jpg?itok=Q_lEl1ZE" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Downsides to Remote Work?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-10/JBallard.jpeg.jpg?itok=G8r4Kaq9" alt="John Ballard Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Career</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Downsides to Remote Work?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">For some, losing the social interaction of working in the office has its downside.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Approximately 25% of U.S. employees work remotely, either all the time or part of the time.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Leaders and employees may see benefits and costs of remote work differently.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Face-to-face interactions may contribute to personal and organizational success.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/remote%20work.jpg?itok=PiiGGlM4" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="kreatikar/Pixabay" alt="kreatikar/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: kreatikar/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The COVID pandemic (2020-2023) changed the world of work, especially for those who work in offices. In 2019 in the U.S., fewer than 6% of employees were working remotely. During the peak of the pandemic, surveys suggested remote workers, including those who worked at home part of the time, increased to over 50%. Today, surveys find about 25% of employees work remotely at least part of the time. Of these, about 10% work away from the office, mostly at home, all the time.</p>

<p>Attitudes toward remote work vary. In 2020 <em>The Wall Street Journal</em> published remarks about remote work from 19 CEOs in different industries: 9 remarks were negative; 3, positive; 7, undecided. Two concerns were the quality of work and productivity. Studies have found that usually these have remained the same or improved. But the CEOs expressed other concerns: the lack of social interaction could affect personal growth and professional development, and also affect innovation and creativity. Research has found these concerns to be valid.</p>

<p>On the other hand, most employees are very positive about working remotely. Remote work is more convenient for managing work and other activities, such as home tasks or childcare. Autonomy allows for more flexibility. Hybrid schedules are compromises between home and office. These require employees to be physically in the office a certain number of days each week or in the office on specific weekdays.</p>

<p>But there can be downsides to not working at the office. Peter Cappelli (Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania) and Jasmine Wu (now at the University of Texas at Austin) conducted group interviews about remote work with over 750 employees of a multinational company. Among their findings:</p>
<ul>
<li>People working remotely focused more on individual tasks.</li>
<li>They focused less on collective tasks involving others.</li>
<li>Cooperation was more difficult.</li>
<li>Social relationships eroded affecting organizational culture.</li>
<li>For new employees, learning the ropes was challenging.</li>
</ul>

<p>Cappelli and Wu concluded that face-to-face interactions are important in building social relationships essential to making office work successful.</p>
<p>Years ago, my office was one of several that had to relocate to a building 10 miles from the rest of our organization. Daily face-to-face interactions with others in the organization no longer happened. Communication became more difficult. The conversations and useful information we obtained interacting informally were gone. It was harder to stay in the loop. It took effort to make sure we did not become “out of sight, out of mind.”</p>

<p>In 2021 in <em>The Wall Street Journal,</em> Cappelli suggested we may be heading toward a two-tier workplace. Employees in the office have better access to managers, receive more attention, have more face time, and are more likely to be promoted. Cappelli’s comments are consistent with our knowledge of the workplace. We are more likely to interact with others who are nearby than with people who are farther away or not physically present. All things being equal, in most organizations managers will be more inclined to favor the on-site worker they see every day over the remote worker with whom they interact virtually. As Cappelli suggests, a two-tier system may naturally develop.</p>

<p>Organizations take different approaches to remote work based on many factors. There are jobs where there are no issues with working remotely, and others where it would be difficult. Depending on the organization, one policy for all may not be the best approach. Organizations are still at the experimental stage regarding remote work and some of us are part of that experiment. For organizations, and for each individual, remote work is a matter of costs, benefits, and preferences. </p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/expanding-our-potential/202602/downsides-to-remote-work" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/expanding-our-potential/202602/downsides-to-remote-work</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/expanding-our-potential/202602/downsides-to-remote-work</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[John Ballard Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/remote%20work.jpg?itok=DwrNhAZ1" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are We Cruising Toward Cognitive Capitulation?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/IMG_1313-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=ObbAdNW8" alt="Cornelia C. Walther Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Are We Cruising Toward Cognitive Capitulation?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">AI is reshaping what we think, and if. We can still do something about that.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">We are entering a stage in which we are letting AI think instead of us.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Beyond cognitive surrender, we enter the murky space of belief offloading—and it's arguably more troubling.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">We need is a practiced commitment to keeping our cognitive agency intact.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2022,%202026,%2002_46_53%20PM.png.jpg?itok=akACNRWi" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" alt="Are our reasoning abilities gradually withering inside the warm, frictionless embrace of artificial intelligence?" title="Walther, ChatGPT, 2026 / OpenAI"></div>
<div class="caption">Are our reasoning abilities gradually withering inside the warm, frictionless embrace of artificial intelligence?</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Walther, ChatGPT, 2026 / OpenAI</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">There's a particular kind of exhaustion that comes not from overwork, but from underuse. Muscles atrophy in casts. Your sense of direction dissolves the moment GPS becomes a habit. Are our reasoning abilities gradually withering inside the warm, frictionless embrace of artificial intelligence (AI)?</p>
<p dir="ltr">An emerging body of research suggests the answer is yes. And the most alarming part? It feels like progress.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">A Third Way of Thinking</h2>
<p dir="ltr">You may have heard of the two-system model of the mind—popularized by psychologist Daniel Kahneman in<a href="https://dn790002.ca.archive.org/0/items/DanielKahnemanThinkingFastAndSlow/Daniel%20Kahneman-Thinking%2C%20Fast%20and%20Slow%20%20.pdf"> <em>Thinking, Fast and Slow</em></a>. System 1 is fast and instinctive: the snap judgment, the gut feeling. System 2 is slow and deliberate: the part of you that actually sits down and works something out. Together, they've given us a remarkably useful map of how humans think.</p>

<p dir="ltr">That map may need updating. Some researchers now argue we need a<a href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=6097646"> Tri-System Theory</a>—because AI has become a System 3: an external cognitive process so deeply woven into our daily thinking that it functions almost like a third mode of mind. Except this one lives outside your skull, runs on servers, and never gets tired.</p>

<p dir="ltr">That might sound like pure gain. The research suggests otherwise.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">What "Cognitive Surrender" Actually Looks Like</h2>
<p dir="ltr">In three pre-registered experiments involving more than 1,300 participants, something striking showed: When people had access to an AI assistant, they consulted it on more than half of all tasks—and their accuracy mirrored the AI's almost perfectly. When the AI was right, they were right. When it was wrong, so were they. Most crucially, they weren't checking. They were simply adopting the AI's answers, bypassing both instinct and analysis entirely.</p>

<p dir="ltr">This is cognitive surrender in motion. We use AI to help us think, and we adopt the outputs, no questions asked, no effort invested. Past the stage of thinking with AI, we are entering a stage in which we are letting AI think instead of us.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That dynamic sits at the far end of the scale of <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202506/the-risk-of-agency-decay-amid-ai-use">agency decay</a>. It is a troubling continuum that starts with cognitive offloading—normal enough; that's why we write shopping lists and register phone numbers. From here, it moves to cognitive outsourcing, where we delegate not just memory but judgment. And it ends with cognitive surrender: the near-total abdication of independent reasoning and judgment. The dial moves gradually. Most of us never notice we've turned it.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">We're Outsourcing Tasks and Beliefs</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Here's where it gets philosophically vertiginous. Beyond cognitive surrender, we enter the murky space of <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4698/15/1/6">belief offloading</a>—and it's arguably more troubling still.</p>
<p dir="ltr">When we ask AI to help us draft an email, we're using a tool. When we ask what we should think about a political issue, a moral dilemma, or a major life decision—and then accept the answer—we're doing far more than utilizing an external asset. We're ceding a fragment of our identity.</p>

<p dir="ltr">A survey of 666 people across age groups and educational backgrounds found a direct correlation between frequent AI use and reduced critical thinking, with habitual offloading as the key mechanism. Younger users were most vulnerable, showing both greater dependence and lower critical thinking scores. The brain really is like a muscle. When the crutch is always there, we never build the strength to walk without it.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">The Uncomfortable Irony</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Here is the part that should give us (even more) reason to pause. While humans risk losing their capacity for self-reflection and deliberate analysis, AI systems are being specifically engineered to gain it. Researchers have begun to build<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44387-025-00027-5"> AI architectures</a> that mirror healthy human reasoning—systems with a fast mode, a slow mode, and a metacognitive layer that monitors which one to deploy and when.</p>

<p dir="ltr">These machines are learning to check themselves, while we are gradually losing the appetite, and ability, to do so. That has consequences. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Across virtually every major psychological framework—from <a href="https://selfdeterminationtheory.org/theory/">Self-Determination Theory </a>to <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/social-sciences/cognitive-behavioral-model">cognitive-behavioral models</a>—autonomy is central to well-being. The felt sense that you are the author of your own thoughts and choices is not a luxury; it is quintessential to being who we are. When that authorship is transferred to an algorithm, something essential erodes—slowly, and in ways that are genuinely hard to reverse.</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Will AI make us stupid? Maybe. The immediate risk is subtler: AI makes the effort of thinking feel unnecessary—and we gradually lose the taste for it.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">The ABCD Framework: Staying the Author of Your Own Mind</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Awareness alone isn't enough. What's needed is a practiced commitment to keeping your cognitive agency intact—an ABCD of AI agency:</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Aspire:</strong> Before opening an AI tool, pause. What do you actually think about this? Treat your own reasoning as something worth developing, not just a stopgap before the real answer arrives.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Believe:</strong> Trust that effortful thinking builds something the AI's polished output cannot replace. The process of working something out changes you. The product of a prompt does not.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Choose: </strong>Make conscious, deliberate decisions about when to use AI and when to resist it. Cognitive surrender happens when AI use becomes automatic. Resistance begins the moment you make it intentional.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Do: </strong>Write the first draft. Form the opinion. Make the call. Then use AI to challenge, refine, or expand what you've already built. Begin with yourself.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">AI is going to be part of our cognitive lives, at scale. It is something we need to reckon with. The question is whether we remain the authors of those lives, or simply their hosts.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Cognitive surrender isn't inevitable. But avoiding it requires something no algorithm can supply: the choice to live life from the inside out, not vice versa.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202602/are-we-cruising-toward-cognitive-capitulation" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202602/are-we-cruising-toward-cognitive-capitulation</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202602/are-we-cruising-toward-cognitive-capitulation</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Cornelia C. Walther Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2022%2C%202026%2C%2002_46_53%20PM.png.jpg?itok=7jBEwTao" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>