<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 23:31:47 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 23:31:47 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Time Increasingly Matters in Adolescence]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/img_3807.jpg?itok=I4ijgknr" alt="Carl E Pickhardt Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Adolescence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Time Increasingly Matters in Adolescence</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Between adolescents and parents, time becomes a growing source of contention.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Time becomes an emotional issue for teenagers in many powerful ways.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Adolescents often address time in two ways that frustrate parents: impatience and delay.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Parents must be both more patient and persistent in getting teenage cooperation.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" alt="Carl Pickhardt" data-insert-type="image" height="414" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2024-11/20220811115658_00018.jpg?itok=B7RcJVZA" title="Carl Pickhardt" width="320"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Carl Pickhardt</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Time matters to us because we depend upon it in several essential ways, over which parent and teenager can increasingly conflict.</p>
<ul>
<li>To <em>measure</em> our life experience: how much there is, how long it lasts, how to keep up, scheduling what needs to happen when. About measured time, the adolescent can become more <em>impatient</em> and <em>resistant</em>: “I need this now!” “I’ll do that later!”</li>
<li>To <em>evaluate </em>our life experience: how it felt, how relaxed or hurried, easy or hard, pleasurable or painful. About evaluated time, the adolescent can become more <em>critical</em> and <em>dissatisfied:</em> “This is a bad time!” “Stop giving me a hard time!”</li>
<li>To <em>communicate </em>our life experience: how much to be known, how much to share, how much to conceal. About communicated time, the adolescent can become more <em>private</em> and <em>secretive</em>: “I don’t want to talk about it!” “It’s my business!” </li>
</ul>

<p>As more diversity, distance, and disagreement grow between adolescent and parent, conflicts over time increase.</p>
<h2>Adolescence and time</h2>
<p>For parents, an adolescent's sense of time can be frustrating in two contrasting ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>On the one hand, there is more <em>youthful impatience.</em> “Whenever she badly wants something, she has to have it ‘now’, treating it like an emergency!”</li>
<li>On the other hand, there is more <em>youthful delay.</em> “Whenever we request something, he puts us off until ‘later,’ which feels like it will last forever!”</li>
</ul>

<p>On both counts, there can be an increase in time conflicts with parents. Expressed in each is the growing desire for more control over what needs to happen when. Time is life-time, and increasingly young adolescents want to determine how their lives are personally spent. The outcome for parents is that they can feel rushed by youthful demands, while it can take more time for them to get what they requested.</p>

<h2>What to do? <strong> </strong></h2>
<p><em>In response to youthful impatience</em>, parents often want to take sufficient time to thoughtfully consider risks that an urgent request may bring. “Before we decide if this can happen, we need to discuss possible difficulties.”</p>
<p><em>In response to youthful delay</em>, parents often need to mount a more steadfast pursuit to gain the cooperation and consent they want. “To make sure what we asked for is accomplished, we will keep after you until it gets done.”</p>

<h2>Controlling time </h2>
<p>Come the onset of their child’s coming of age passage and the push for more individuality and independence, usually between the ages of 9 and 13, parents must deal with more <em>time conflicts</em>—more passive resistance (delay), and active resistance (disagreement) when wanting to get what they require and desire.</p>

<p>Thus, now, they need to be more consistent with their rules, more persistent with their requests, and more patient with the increased time it can take to get youthful compliance and cooperation.</p>
<p>Why more resistance? With the adolescent awakening, four growing drives for autonomy make control over personal time more important to the teenager.</p>

<ol>
<li>Individual expression and independent action</li>
<li>Personal privacy and social separation from family</li>
<li>Worldly curiosity and experimenting with acting older</li>
<li>Social belonging and fitting in with one’s group of peers</li>
</ol>
<p>In each case, time must be invested to pursue personal growth. So, consider some complexities of managing time.</p>


<h2>Time and emotion</h2>
<p>Time is complicated because it can easily become an emotional issue. Telling phrases describe how this felt connection to time comes to be so. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>When we have plenty of time, we can feel <em>relaxed</em>.</li>
<li>When we wonder about the best time, we can feel <em>curious</em>.</li>
<li>When we look forward to a good time, we can feel <em>enthusiastic.</em></li>
<li>When we don’t know what to do with our time, we can feel <em>bored</em>.</li>
<li>When we are rushed or short of available time, we can feel <em>anxious.</em></li>
<li>When we miss a good time that is now over, we can feel <em>sad</em>.</li>
<li>When we fall behind some scheduled time, we can feel <em>rushed</em>.</li>
<li>When we feel the necessity of being on time, we can feel <em>obligated</em>.</li>
<li>When we feel the opportunity of time has passed us by, we can feel <em>regret.</em></li>
<li>When we are told or tell ourselves to take our time, we can be <em>careful</em>.</li>
<li>When we can’t wait for a good time to arrive, we can feel <em>impatient.</em></li>
<li>When we undergo a dangerous or threatening time, we can feel <em>anxious.</em></li>
<li>When we are mistreated at the time or all the time, we can feel <em>angry</em>.</li>
<li>When we can’t get our needs met at the time, we can feel <em>frustrated</em>.</li>
<li>When we don’t want to waste time, we can concentrate and be <em>productive</em>.</li>
<li>When we have too much to do in too little time, we can feel <em>stressed</em>.</li>
<li>When we are having a good time, we can feel pleasure and <em>enjoyment.</em></li>
<li>When we are going through a taxing time, we can feel <em>fatigued</em>.</li>
<li>When we are going through a downtime, we can feel <em>discouraged</em>.</li>
<li>When we wish we had acted differently at the time, we can feel <em>regretful</em>.</li>
<li>When we appreciate the time we have been given, we can feel <em>grateful</em>.</li>
<li>When we suspend our sense of time, in the limitless moment, we can feel <em>free</em>. </li>
</ul>

<p>And then of course there is that <em>time-threat</em>: the deadline. Now, a scheduled line in time has been drawn after which some possibility is "dead"—a person feeling pressed or anxious on that account.</p>
<h2>Frustration with time</h2>
<p><em>Timing conflicts </em>between parents and teenagers are more common during adolescence, as needs for immediacy and intolerance for delay can become more wearing on them both. Now or later? That is often the question. Enter <em>delay</em>. For parents and teenagers, <em>tolerating and managing impatience</em> can feel harder to do.</p>



  


<ul>
<li>Parent: “I need this right away!” vs. Teenager: “I’ll do it in a minute!”</li>
<li>Teenager: “I need permission now!” vs. Parent: “We need time to think.”</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s easier for each to feel frustrated by the other’s disagreement and delay—argument and putting off now until later, in each case having to wait for what one wants. From denial of desires and intolerance of delay, impatience grows. And from prolonged impatience, feelings of frustration, irritation, and anger can follow, hence the shared complaints: “Now cooperation takes longer than it should!” “Now it takes more talk to reach an agreement.” “Now it’s harder to get each other to understand.”</p>

<p>Compared to the simpler days of childhood, come adolescence, between parent and teenager, there will be more growing tensions over time.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/surviving-your-childs-adolescence/202411/why-time-increasingly-matters-in-adolescence" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/surviving-your-childs-adolescence/202411/why-time-increasingly-matters-in-adolescence</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/surviving-your-childs-adolescence/202411/why-time-increasingly-matters-in-adolescence</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Carl E Pickhardt Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2024-11/20220811115658_00018.jpg?itok=3n5-tQED" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>