<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:15:26 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:15:26 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rewired: How the Digital World Reshapes the Human Brain]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/shirleymueller_3_-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=784PxvrR" alt="Shirley M. Mueller M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Neuroscience</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Rewired: How the Digital World Reshapes the Human Brain</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The role of technology in molding the brain.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The excessive use of digital technology especially affects young people.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Attention and emotional and social intelligence can be altered by excessive digital technology use.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Later in life, technology can be associated with enhanced decision-making, reasoning, and visual processing.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>This happened to me a few days ago. I am talking to a Gen Z (born between 1997 and 2012) on the phone about a trip we were planning. She seemed fragmented, texting her parents while speaking with me, and crafting decorations for a party for 20 people that she was giving in a few hours.</p>
<p>My gosh! How could she keep it going? The answer apparently is that she is young, a Gen Z. Her brain can’t do anything else. </p>

<p>This is why. Frequent use of digital technologies (smartphones, computers, video games, and ubiquitous online interfaces) can have profound effects on the human brain (Small et. al., 2020). From this perspective, the relevance of technology lies in how it engages neural circuits, exhausts or enhances cognitive systems, and potentially restructures brain development across the lifespan.</p>

<h2>Attention and Technology Use</h2>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/0f7587d2-2dc1-4dc3-aa12-50c99a72f885.png%202.png.jpg?itok=rou7ayfG" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" alt="Young girl intently using her iphone." title="AI-generated with ChatGPT / OpenAI"></div>
<div class="caption">Young girl intently using her iphone.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI-generated with ChatGPT / OpenAI</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>One of the most striking neuropsychological issues raised in this article relates to the <em>relationship between screen time and attentional control</em>. The authors summarize evidence that extensive digital media use correlates with heightened symptoms akin to attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), including distractibility and impaired sustained attention. This finding aligns with what we know about the executive control network (a constellation of frontal and parietal regions) responsible for attentional control, task switching, and cognitive inhibition.</p>

<p>To explain, when individuals constantly shift attention among apps, notifications, and multimedia stimuli, they effectively train the brain to fragment attention. Over time, this can reinforce neural pathways that favor rapid switching over sustained attention.</p>
<p>Cognitive neuroscience indicates that the brain adapts to environmental demands, and in this case, it may be adjusting in ways that favor rapid reactivity over sustained<em> focus</em>. From a neuropsychological standpoint, such revisions have implications for learning, problem-solving, and emotional regulation.</p>

<h2><strong>E</strong>motional Intelligence, Social Cognition, and Digital Engagement</h2>
<p>Beyond attention, the article highlights potential declines in <em>emotional and social intelligence</em>, particularly in young screen users. Neuropsychologists study constructs like theory of mind, facial emotion recognition, and social cue processing as emergent properties of complex neural circuits (the amygdala, prefrontal cortex, and temporo-parietal junction).</p>

<p>When children and adolescents spend disproportionate time in the digital world at the expense of face-to-face interactions, they lose crucial experiences that support specific circuits. Research cited by the article indicates that reduced screen exposure improved children’s ability to interpret emotional and social cues—a <em>neurobehavioral outcome</em> with real-world implications.</p>

<p>From a neuropsychological view, this suggests that <em>early experience shapes development </em>not only structurally but functionally. If social processing networks are understimulated in early childhood due to the digital replacement of in-person interaction, the consequences may include altered neural trajectories that persist into adulthood.</p>

<h2>Compulsive Use, Neural Reward Pathways, and Technology</h2>
<p>The review also tackles <em>problematic technology use</em>, framing it within the concept of addiction. Neuropsychology has extensively documented how repeated engagement with rewarding stimuli, whether substances or behaviors, modulates the brain’s reward circuitry, principally through dopaminergic pathways between the ventral tegmental area (a midbrain structure associated with pleasure and dopaminergic neurons) and the nucleus accumbens (a pleasure center).</p>

<p>While “internet addiction” is not yet codified in the <em>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</em>, the authors describe characteristics that align with addictive behaviors: preoccupation, tolerance, withdrawal, and functional impairment. This points to <em>altered reward sensitivity and impulse control</em>, two domains critical to adaptive decision-making and self-regulation.</p>



  


<p>The potential for technology to hijack reward systems through likes, notifications, and endless novelty suggests a reconfiguration of neural motivation networks that resemble other compulsive behaviors. Here, neuropsychology helps frame technology not just as a tool but as a <em>stimulus environment</em> that interacts with brain systems governing reinforcement and habit formation.</p>

<h2>Cognitive Enhancement</h2>
<p>Not all findings point to harm. Notably, the authors cite neuroimaging research indicating that internet searching activates brain regions associated with decision-making, reasoning, and visual processing, particularly in older adults. This implies that digital engagement can serve as a form of <em>mental exercise</em>, increasing neural activity and potentially strengthening integrative cognitive functions.</p>

<p>This aligns with <em>cognitive reserve</em>, the idea that engaging stimulating tasks can build resilience against age-related cognitive decline. Skills such as problem-solving, multitasking, and memory are not static; they are products of ongoing engagement with complex environments. Thus, certain kinds of digital use may strengthen neural networks rather than weaken them.</p>

<p>What’s neuropsychologically compelling here is the <em>bidirectionality</em> of technology’s effects: The same digital tools that can undermine attention and social cognition might also fortify other cognitive domains through intentional practice, especially later in life.</p>
<h2>Sleep, Brain Health, and Means of Intervention</h2>

<p>Another important dimension the article discusses is <em>sleep disruption </em>caused by screen exposure, particularly by blue light and circadian interference. Sleep is fundamental to memory consolidation, emotional regulation, and neural homeostasis, all of which are of intense interest in neuropsychology. Disrupted sleep impairs prefrontal function, weakens executive control, and degrades memory performance, which can create a vicious cycle when combined with heavy technology use.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Reading “Brain health consequences of digital technology use” through the lens of neuropsychology reinforces that digital engagement is neither inherently benign nor uniformly harmful. Instead, its impact depends on a<em> </em>multitude of subtleties, including how attentional systems adapt, social cognition develops (or degrades), reward pathways are modulated, and, finally, how sleep and cognition are affected.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-mind-of-a-collector/202602/rewired-how-the-digital-world-reshapes-the-human-brain" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-mind-of-a-collector/202602/rewired-how-the-digital-world-reshapes-the-human-brain</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-mind-of-a-collector/202602/rewired-how-the-digital-world-reshapes-the-human-brain</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Shirley M. Mueller M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/3ef278ba-e228-43c1-9028-bae091e88194.jpg%201.jpg?itok=ScpKLOXJ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stepping Off the Achievement Treadmill]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/Susanna%20Newsonen.png.jpg?itok=dm_DuXxc" alt="Susanna Newsonen" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Hedonic Treadmill</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Stepping Off the Achievement Treadmill</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The quiet courage of redefining enough.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">When achievement becomes your identity, nothing is enough.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Success can be reenvisioned by how you live your days, not what you produce in them.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">You don't need to abandon your goals, but you can redefine how you approach them.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/stepping%20off%20the%20achievement%20treadmill.jpg?itok=Rmuqm-zX" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Brett Jordan on Unsplash" alt="Photo by Brett Jordan on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Brett Jordan on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>For as long as I can remember, I was an achiever. At school, I aimed high and measured success in grades. At university, praise became a powerful motivator, and I committed to being one of the top students in my year. This pattern followed me into adulthood as I built a meaningful career, set ambitious goals, and learned to keep going no matter how tired I felt. I was productive, driven, and deeply invested in doing my best at work, in relationships, and in sport.</p>

<p>From the outside, my life looked successful. And in many ways, it was. But beneath the momentum sat a quieter truth I hadn’t yet admitted to myself: the goalposts never stopped moving. No achievement felt satisfying for long. There was always another target waiting. Over time, striving became more than ambition. It became the way I felt safe. The way I felt valuable. The way I reassured myself I was enough.</p>

<p>There’s a psychological explanation for this: something called hedonic adaptation. As humans, we adapt quickly to success and to improvements in circumstances. A success that once felt extraordinary soon becomes normal. Satisfaction rises briefly, then settles back to baseline. It explains why achievement can feel both rewarding and strangely empty at the same time. The relief is real, but short-lived. And so the striving resumes.</p>

<p>I didn’t realise how tightly achievement had wrapped itself around my identity until my life began to change. I moved from the pace of London to the quiet of the French countryside. I stepped back from my coaching business and focused more fully on writing. I slowed down and found myself unexpectedly uncomfortable. Restlessness surfaced. Guilt followed. The urge to prove myself returned quickly, as though slowing down might undo everything I had built. Instead of rushing to fill the discomfort, I stayed with it.</p>

<p>With fewer external pressures, I began to notice how often I evaluated my days by output alone. How uneasy it felt to be present without turning the moment into something productive or useful. How quickly my mind leapt to the next milestone, even in moments meant to be enjoyed. Gradually, I loosened the grip. Not because achievement became unimportant, but because I no longer wanted it to organise my life. Something in me sensed there was another way to live, even if I couldn’t yet name it.</p>

<p>Psychological research supports what many people discover for themselves: long-term well-being depends less on what we achieve and more on how we live. A sense of autonomy, connection, and meaning predicts long-term fulfilment far more reliably than external markers of success. Yet culturally, we continue to reward busyness, optimisation, and visible wins.</p>

<p>At the end of life, this imbalance becomes especially clear. Palliative care nurse Bronnie Ware observed a recurring regret among those in their final days: not that they hadn’t achieved more, but that they had worked too much and missed the life they were living.</p>
<p>Achievement itself isn’t the problem. Humans are wired to grow, learn, and create. Purposeful effort can be deeply fulfilling. But the difficulty arises when achievement becomes compulsive and the thing you rely on to feel worthy, calm, or secure. In that state, success brings temporary relief rather than lasting satisfaction. Each milestone briefly soothes the nervous system, only to raise the bar again.</p>

<p>Many people recognise this pattern not through burnout, but through subtler signs: feeling anxious when not being productive, struggling to enjoy success once it arrives, measuring self-worth by what has been accomplished that day, or finding stillness vaguely threatening. If this feels familiar, you’re not broken. You’re likely very good at what you do. But you may also be tired in a way that rest alone doesn’t resolve.</p>

<p>Loosening the grip the achievement treadmill has on you doesn’t require abandoning your goals. It begins internally, by separating who you are from what you produce. In practice, this can look small: allowing something to be good enough, resisting the urge to optimise every moment, and noticing when the mind jumps to the next goal — and gently choosing not to follow it. At first, this can feel unsettling. When achievement has long acted as a stabiliser, loosening it may bring guilt, fear, or the unnerving question: <em>If I’m not striving, who am I?</em></p>



  


<p>That discomfort isn’t a sign that something is wrong. Often, it’s a sign that something new is emerging.</p>
<p>Over time, something begins to shift. Presence replaces pressure. Depth replaces speed. Work becomes more intentional; not less ambitious, but less frantic. Creativity flows more freely when it isn’t constantly being asked to prove itself.</p>

<p>One of the hardest parts of this shift is learning to tolerate “enough.” Enough effort. Enough success. Enough for today. Our culture trains us to believe that more is always better, but psychologically, growth doesn’t disappear when striving softens. It simply becomes less about constant expansion and more about depth. It shows up in quieter ways: learning for curiosity rather than advantage, improving without urgency, and allowing progress to unfold without needing to prove its worth.</p>

<p>I still work, write, and care deeply about what I do. But I no longer organise my life around achievement. I focus more on the process than the outcome. Alignment matters more than productivity alone. My life is quieter now, but not smaller. Achievement still exists; it’s just no longer in charge.</p>
<p>And perhaps that’s the quiet courage of stepping off the treadmill: not abandoning ambition, but redefining success as whether you were present and aligned in your days, not simply productive in them.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-path-to-passionate-happiness/202602/stepping-off-the-achievement-treadmill" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-path-to-passionate-happiness/202602/stepping-off-the-achievement-treadmill</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-path-to-passionate-happiness/202602/stepping-off-the-achievement-treadmill</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Susanna Newsonen]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/stepping%20off%20the%20achievement%20treadmill.jpg?itok=XJv5AQLE" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Reasons Behind Compulsive Financial Giving]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/photoofmarktravers.png.jpg?itok=4rcV_Py2" alt="Mark Travers Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Altruism</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Reasons Behind Compulsive Financial Giving</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Compulsive generosity is very different from generosity that grows out of choice.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">For some people, money is a salve they might use compulsively to ease an internal discomfort.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perceived balance in give-and-take predicts better relationship outcomes than absolute equality.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Continual self-sacrifice increases the risk of emotional exhaustion, resentment, and loss of self-clarity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/alexander-grey--8a5eJ1-mmQ-unsplash.jpg?itok=_U56kVEJ" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Alexander Grey / Unsplash" alt="Alexander Grey / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Alexander Grey / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Most people have met or known a compulsive giver in their lifetime. They always pick up the bill without hesitation, often send unsolicited gifts when someone’s in a tight spot, or even quietly bankroll group plans so no one has to miss out. On the surface, it reads as kindness and an unusually robust sense of generosity. Up close, however, it often reveals itself to be part of a complex and obsessive pattern that reinforces their identity and repairs invisible childhood wounds.</p>

<p>Here are the psychological roots of compulsive financial giving, the toll it takes, and what it means for the friendships built around it.</p>
<h2>1. Compulsive Giving as Emotion Regulation (Not Just a Love Language)</h2>
<p>Gift-giving features in pop psychology most often as one of the “<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202505/2-signs-you-arent-speaking-your-partners-love-language">love languages</a>.” And insofar as it brings the person and the receiver happiness, it feels wrong to nit-pick the habit. For some people, however, money is a salve they might use compulsively to ease an internal discomfort. This discomfort can take many forms: guilt about having more, worry about abandonment, or the acute distress of social friction.</p>

<p>When buying someone dinner or covering a friend’s rent reduces anxiety, the act often fuels a reinforcement loop. As soon as you engage in it, your anxiety drops, you feel relief, and your urge to repeat the behavior becomes even stronger.</p>
<p>Experimental work on prosocial spending finds predictable emotional returns, especially when the giver perceives impact or connection, but the benefit shrinks when giving is compelled by fear or obligation rather than freely chosen. In other words, giving can soothe, but it can also mask deeper anxieties.</p>

<h2>2. Conditional Belonging Leads to Compulsive Giving</h2>
<p>A 2019 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2018.02.009">study</a> on attachment and development points to a common origin story for this compulsion. If a child learns that love or safety is contingent on usefulness, caretaking, or sacrifice, they internalize that message.</p>
<p>The resulting belief might sound something like, “I am valuable when I provide.” And that belief can calcify into adult patterns where money becomes a reliable currency of belonging.</p>

<p>This is how early caregiving environments shape adult strategies for securing closeness and managing threat. Those who learned to earn approval by giving or fixing are more likely to overfunction in relationships, sometimes with money as the medium.</p>
<h2>3. Compulsive Giving Creates a Social Asymmetry</h2>
<p>There’s an uncomfortable social dynamic baked into financial provision that creates asymmetry. Social-exchange theorists and anthropologists have long argued that gifts carry implicit expectations. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003572350">Mauss’s classic insight</a> that giving creates a three-part obligation to give, receive, and reciprocate still shapes modern thinking about social debt.</p>

<p>When one friend is habitually the payer, others may feel grateful, indebted, infantilized, or even relieved. Over time, the pattern can, intentionally or unintentionally, produce moral leverage. The giver might quietly start expecting gratitude, loyalty, or deference in return, whether consciously or not.</p>

<p>Notably, this isn’t to cast generous friends as manipulators. For many, the impulse to provide is genuinely an expression of care. But the relational outcome can sometimes look like access rather than intimacy; people might just stay for the comfort of provision, not necessarily for mutual vulnerability.</p>

<p>Relationships need a currency of exchange, but they thrive on <em>reciprocity</em>, not dependence. Social-psychological studies show that perceived balance in give-and-take predicts better relationship outcomes than absolute equality.</p>
<p>When one person repeatedly covers costs, the balance shifts: Reciprocity becomes symbolic rather than practical, and friends may unconsciously fall into roles—“the provider” and “the provided for.” That may limit the depth of connection: Other forms of care (emotional availability, shared labor, presence) can atrophy if money is always the substitute.</p>

<h2>The Emotional and Financial Toll on the Compulsive Giver</h2>
<p>The long-term costs of chronic over-giving are measurable. Clinical and social <a href="https://psychologyinrussia.com/volumes/index.php?article=9865">research</a> on caregiving and burnout, typically studied in family or professional caregiver contexts, applies here. </p>
<p>Continual self-sacrifice increases the risk of emotional exhaustion, resentment, and loss of self-clarity. People who repeatedly put others’ needs ahead of their own report feeling invisible unless they are providing, and ashamed when they notice the resentment building inside them.</p>



  


<p>Financially, the consequences are obvious, too. Compulsive giving can lead to eroded savings, postponed goals, and vulnerability when the giver hits an unexpected personal crisis. Psychologically, the consequences are subtler, but not any less damaging: The giver’s identity becomes wrapped in provision, making it hard for them to ask for help without guilt.</p>

<p>Here’s a list of signals that can help you determine if someone’s “giving habit” has moved from healthy to harmful:</p>
<ul>
<li>Repeated financial sacrifice that undermines the giver’s well-being or goals</li>
<li>Giving that primarily reduces the giver’s anxiety, rather than meeting a clear need</li>
<li>Resentment that follows giving, especially if the giver tells themselves they “shouldn’t feel that way.”</li>
<li>Relationships that feel transactional—people attend events, stay close, or call mostly when money or logistics are involved.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you spotted any of these patterns in your daily life or relationships, here’s another list of practical pivots that can help you preserve generosity without self-erasure:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Name the motive.</strong> Givers who reflect, “Am I helping because I want to, or because I’m afraid of being rejected?” gain critical insight. Therapy and journaling can uncover these motives.</li>
<li><strong>Set breathable boundaries.</strong> Decide in advance what you can afford emotionally and financially, and communicate it. Boundaries reduce moral leverage and make reciprocity clearer.</li>
<li><strong>Share emotional labor.</strong> Ask for nonfinancial ways friends can show up, such as time, listening, or practical help, so money isn’t the sole proof of care.</li>
<li><strong>Create structured generosity.</strong> Allocating a fixed “gift budget” or charity fund satisfies giving impulses without eroding stability.</li>
<li><strong>Practice asking.</strong> Letting others contribute, even when you could pay, creates mutuality and reduces one-way indebtedness.</li>
</ol>

<p>Money talks in every relationship, but we rarely treat it as psychology. Exploring why some people feel compelled to financially show up exposes how identity, insecurity, and care intersect in modern social life. It reframes generosity away from moral tidy-ups toward a human story about how we seek safety, recognition, and belonging, and what we risk when the price of those needs is our own well-being.</p>

<p><em>A version of this post also appears on Forbes.com.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-reasons-behind-compulsive-financial-giving" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-reasons-behind-compulsive-financial-giving</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-reasons-behind-compulsive-financial-giving</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Travers Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/alexander-grey--8a5eJ1-mmQ-unsplash.jpg?itok=cTqDQiED" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Emotional Impact of American Misogyny]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/bender.jpg?itok=7Et4Vms2" alt="Suzanne Bender M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Media</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Emotional Impact of American Misogyny</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Recognizing and coping with the mental health effects of the Epstein files.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Trust yourself: If the news is upsetting you, it is because the news is upsetting.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In large doses, media exposure can be overwhelming, so pace yourself.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Recognize that you are not alone, and it may help to note the allies fighting for accountability.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/iStock-145995617.jpg?itok=Ct8mrcr8" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="HannamariaH/istockphoto " alt="HannamariaH/istockphoto "></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: HannamariaH/istockphoto</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Inside and outside of my psychotherapy office, there is undiluted fury. Panic attacks after reading social media posts. Disgust. A deep sadness, followed by rage.</p>
<p>The Epstein files detail correspondence of powerful, mostly white, rich men discussing and joking about their abuse of children, their pedophilia, and worse. There is a disconcerting feeling, familiar from the uncovering of abuses by pedophilic priests, as we recognize that the public persona and the private actions don’t sync. Readers of the files feel shaken to the core as they read emails detailing decades of molestation, even murder. We have entered a horror movie without our consent.</p>

<p>Part of being a psychotherapist is recognizing and validating pain. The role becomes especially important when society at large has been dismissive. As we learn more about Epstein and his colleagues, the daunting depth of American misogyny becomes clear. While there were male victims, it seemed much easier to find girls to exploit and harm. The female body was considered a disposable toy. A child’s bodily integrity was not of concern. It makes sense that you are feeling half -sick as you learn more about the flagrant child abuse of the Epstein clan.</p>

<p>And the lack of concern for the victims’ well-being is not just in the past. At a recent Congressional hearing, Pam Bondi refused to turn around and look at the Epstein survivors. One doesn’t need to be male to dismiss female suffering — internalized misogyny exists.</p>
<p>We note what officials in power didn’t do. The government has had this information for years, during Democratic and Republican administrations. They have files so disturbing that they can’t even release them to the public. So many powerful men with egregious, immoral behavior considered themselves untouchable. Wouldn’t the FBI or DOJ have the resources and staff protections to investigate a case like this? Women and their allies ask: In concerning emails, why is the name of the perpetrator redacted? Why are some victims identified? Why haven’t any of Epstein’s clients been prosecuted? Where is law “without fear or favor”?</p>

<p>The decision to ignore front-row misogyny has been normalized. President Trump responded to reporter Kaitlan Collins’ question about the Epstein files by berating her because she wasn’t smiling. He reprimanded another female journalist with the phrase “Quiet piggy”. In each case, note what happens next. The other reporters pivoted to ask their own questions and moved on. They ignored the despicable treatment of their female colleague to obtain the information they wanted. In an alternate universe: What if each reporter had repeated their colleagues’ questions so Trump was unable to dodge them so easily? What if they all left the press conference to send a message that it is unacceptable to treat a fellow female reporter in this manner?</p>

<h2>How to Cope</h2>
<p>In my conversations inside the office, this is what I have been saying:</p>
<p>There are two parts of this story that are immensely troubling — the abuse by seemingly normal public figures and the lack of adequate reaction to the abuse.</p>
<p>The reaction by some in power, the minimizing or flat-out denial of any wrongdoing, can make you doubt your own perception. Know your observations are accurate; those in need of protection have not been protected. </p>

<p>It makes sense to be upset when flooded with dismissal. Gender injustice is real. Yearning for accountability and consequences makes sense.</p>
<p>Your anguish reflects your humanity. Talk to others and bear the weight together. If you feel distressed, it is because you have empathy. That is a good thing.</p>
<h2>Media Onslaught Has the Potential to Traumatize</h2>

<p>While we need to be aware of what happened, it is also important to protect oneself. Research has shown an association between media exposure of traumatic events and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) symptoms, such as fear, increased anxiety, and dysphoria. One study showed that those with higher sympathetic reactivity (reacting to a negative image with a higher heart rate/having a heightened startle response) have an increased risk of PTSD symptoms in response to low levels of media coverage of a traumatic event. Of note, with high media exposure, individuals with BOTH low and high sympathetic reactivity may develop significant PTSD symptoms.</p>

<p>Information about the latest horrific finding may be popping up on one’s daily social media feed, bathing the consumer in information they may not be in a state to see. The take-home: Take care of yourself and your exposure to this information. I’m not saying that you hole yourself off from the world. It is important to consider the emotional impact of what you are learning and pace yourself accordingly. </p>

<h2>Find the Allies</h2>
<p>There aren’t as many allies as there should be or should have been — but they exist. Note the individuals in Congress who are pushing for transparency and accountability and support them. While there aren’t as many as one might like, the list is growing every day. Tune into those who are speaking out. A couple: Julie K. Brown’s fierce investigative reporting has been doggedly uncovering Epstein abuses for years and providing a voice for victims. Molly Jong-Fast’s recent posts and editorials put words to the rage, organizing the emotional experience. When facing a bully (or in this case, bullies) power is found when people band together. Slowly but surely, this may be happening.</p>



  


<h2>Find Each Other</h2>
<p>Don’t suffer alone if the information you are learning is turning your stomach and affecting your sleep. Talk to trusted friends and family. Talk to your therapist if you have one; if the news is causing sustained emotional distress, consider finding a therapist to help you process what is happening. If it would feel cathartic to use your platform to speak out, do so. Speak truth to power. Use your voice. We are not moving on. American women will not take this sitting down. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lets-talk/202602/the-emotional-impact-of-american-misogyny" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lets-talk/202602/the-emotional-impact-of-american-misogyny</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lets-talk/202602/the-emotional-impact-of-american-misogyny</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Suzanne Bender M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/iStock-145995617.jpg?itok=xw0h7ucS" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New Voices on Social Media Empower Alienated Parents]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/fern_schumer_chapman.jpg?itok=skRm55mE" alt="Fern Schumer Chapman" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Family Dynamics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">New Voices on Social Media Empower Alienated Parents</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Parents on social media find they aren't alone: "It's a pain you can't describe!"</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Parents may be accused of neglect or abuse when a child cuts them off, but that's often a one-sided narrative.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Alienated parents and therapists are claiming social media space to argue parents are not always to blame.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">One therapist suggests that parents not "chase" children or make them the center of their emotional universe.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-shvets-production-6984609.jpg?itok=w5zfCKxC" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="shvets-production/pexels" alt="shvets-production/pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: shvets-production/pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">When adult children go no contact, parents feel misunderstood or manipulated, and often have no opportunity to share their side of the story. They are rendered voiceless.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The societal perspective frequently assumes that if a child has cut off from a mother or father, the parent must be at fault: guilty of abuse, neglect or other failings. This skewed view is widespread because social media tends to be the territory of young people, who are generally more adept than their elders at using those platforms to make themselves heard.</p>

<p dir="ltr">But the experience is much more complicated. Estrangement can arise from many factors, including manipulation by third parties, unresolved trauma, and even simple misunderstandings. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Parental alienation is emotionally fraught, as parents feel guilt, shame, and helplessness at having seemingly failed in this crucial, primary relationship. Making matters worse, alienated parents are marginalized and powerless, and stigma and shame shroud their experience. Their ostracism and isolation is compounded by a lack of understanding from friends, family, and society at large. </p>

<p dir="ltr">In recent years, however, some parents whose adult children have cut them off—as well as therapists who recognize the unfairness of the “parents are always at fault” narrative—are pushing back. Turning to social media platforms, they are sharing stories, connecting with others who are struggling, challenging the prevailing assumptions, and offering insights and guidance.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Two such voices, <em>Doormat Mom</em> and <em>makeitmakesense_kat</em>, have emerged as prominent examples, using platforms like TikTok and Instagram to bring visibility to the pain and complexity of parental alienation.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">Doormat Mom No More</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Laura Wellington, aka “Doormat Mom,” launched her social media platform in response to her own experience. In July 2024, Wellington, the mother of five, learned that she would not be invited to her daughter’s wedding in Australia after suggesting compromise on her daughter’s request that Wellington host a second wedding in the United States to accommodate family and friends who could not travel to Australia. Wellington, noting that the actual wedding would have already been held, offered to host a celebratory gathering rather than another wedding. Displeased, her daughter went no contact.</p>

<p dir="ltr">"I was literally just completely blindsided by this," Wellington says. Widowed at the age of 35, she raised her children as a single parent and says she put her heart and soul into the role.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“When you give birth to a child, you fall in love with that child," she explains, "and you want to give that child an easier road than you had. I was not a perfect parent. There is no perfect parent. But I was a really good parent."</p>

<p dir="ltr">Wellington says there are no words that capture the pain of being cut off. “It’s a pain you can’t describe unless you feel it,” she said. “Parents who do feel it often consider suicide because it’s that painful.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">When Wellington experienced the devastating cutoff, she realized that she couldn’t be the only one suffering this loss. She wanted to do something about it. Driven by the need for connection and understanding among parents facing alienation, she decided to establish a safe space where people could share their stories, find support, and empower each other.</p>

<p dir="ltr">“I wanted to create a place where parents like me could feel heard, understood, and supported,” she says. “No one should have to go through this alone.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">Wellington has posted heart-wrenching stories about missed birthdays, unanswered messages, empty holidays. She has captured small victories in court, unexpected reconnections, or simply moments of peace and self-acceptance. </p>


<p dir="ltr">Consequently, her social media platforms have ballooned, especially after articles appeared in national and international publications such as People, Fox Media, and the Wall Street Journal. KK Magazine of Norway recently featured Wellington to shed light on that country's parental alienation crisis. Since posting her first video in August 2024, Wellington has built a vibrant community of nearly 150,000 on TikTok and Instagram which includes parents in similar situations, as well as some critics. </p>

<p dir="ltr">“I thought I was all alone,” Wellington says. “But when I spoke up, they woke up. Social media has given me the power to connect with thousands of parents who were experiencing the same pain and confusion.” Wellington believes that the platform “brings hope and healing to families who feel lost.”</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">Make It Make Sense</h2>



  


<p dir="ltr">"makeitmakesense_katt," a clinical social worker who says she is not alienated from her children, has created a platform that helps devastated parents shift their perspective from ravaged victim to empowered survivor. With a no-nonsense approach, Katt offers education, advocacy and healing, and often advises parents to take steps that may seem counterintuitive:</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p dir="ltr">She admonishes her 60,000 followers on Instagram and TikTok not to panic or chase: “Chasing does not prove love, it proves panic. And panic makes you look unstable, like you are the crazy person – which only feeds the story that you are the problem.”</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr">She says parents should stop defending themselves. “You cannot reason with a verdict that has already been handed down before you’ve even walked into the courtroom. Every paragraph you send trying to defend yourself only confirms that you think you are on trial....stop acting like you are the defendant.”</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr">She recommends that alienated parents rebuild their lives: “Go to the gym. Take the trip. Build the business. Deepen your faith. Laugh with friends. Stop orbiting their rejection like it’s the sun. Your child is not the center of your emotional universe.”</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p>Social media, with its capacity for connection and advocacy, is providing a megaphone that enables the voices of parents and therapists to contribute to a pivotal, cultural shift that could lead to a more balanced and compassionate approach to family estrangement. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/brothers-sisters-strangers/202602/new-voices-on-social-media-empower-alienated-parents" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/brothers-sisters-strangers/202602/new-voices-on-social-media-empower-alienated-parents</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/brothers-sisters-strangers/202602/new-voices-on-social-media-empower-alienated-parents</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Fern Schumer Chapman]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-shvets-production-6984609.jpg?itok=rNo1TY-a" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>