<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 14:49:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 14:49:01 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Do Human Beings Stay Relevant in an AI-Fueled Future?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/grant-brenner.jpg?itok=4DuQiKcn" alt="Grant Hilary Brenner MD, DFAPA" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Do Human Beings Stay Relevant in an AI-Fueled Future?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The dependencies AI has on humans—and what happens when we forget them.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Humans create AI and give it meaning and continuity across time.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The power of AI is seductive and may threaten human agency.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The future depends on how humans integrate AI.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>The question many mark: Will AI replace us, or more accurately, will some human beings replace others with AI? The corollary: What, if anything, makes humans irreplaceable? As artificial intelligence systems grow more capable, the popular discourse focuses on threat—autonomous weapons, infrastructure hacks, economic displacement. The more dangerous shift may be if we forget our own humanity in the rush, rather than meeting the challenge as we have other technologies, expanding human psyche and culture in generative ways. AI competes with our generative capacity, a potentially demoralizing circumstance.</p>

<p>Our myths and stories tell us that AI engineers understand this well. Frankenstein's creature became monstrous upon rejection—creation without comprehension of consequences. The Golem shifted from protector to destructor. The Sorcerer's Apprentice animated the magic broomstick to avoid doing the work, at first pleased with himself, until he realized he had no spell to stop it. The overt warning is the danger from power run amok. Don't piss off AI.</p>

<h2>Potential Areas of AI Dependence on Human Beings</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>The imagination that conceived AI.</strong> Every architectural decision originated in primate consciousness capable of abstraction, projection, metaphor—the capacity to dream of minds beyond one's own. AI didn't emerge autonomously. A human mind had to conceive it first. In the late '90s, Andy Clark and David Chalmers suggested "extended cognition." Our minds carry outside our bodies, in the form of words and writing, for instance. More recently, in the form of social media, and more strikingly, via AI.</li>
<li><strong>Uncertainty tolerance and generative insight.</strong> AI resolves ambiguity through probability distributions, selecting most-likely-next-tokens, optimizing toward coherence. Humans live in ambiguity productively, generating insights precisely because we tolerate contradiction without forced resolution. We can exercise Keats' "negative capability," "capable of being in uncertainties, mysteries, doubts, without any irritable reaching after fact and reason..."</li>
<li><strong>Terminal values and meaning-making.</strong> AI optimizes toward objectives with extraordinary efficiency once specified. It cannot determine which objectives merit pursuit, what trade-offs are acceptable, or what constitutes mattering versus mere instrumentality. Humans provide the "why" preceding all optimization. Without that, it's computation without purpose; capability in service of nothing in particular.</li>
<li><strong>Embodied creativity.</strong> Wild associations emerge from having bodies with needs, lifespans with limits, and unconscious processing during unrelated activities. Not data elaboration but substrate generating genuinely novel framings—the quality that animates intelligence into something beyond pattern-matching at an industrial scale.</li>
<li><strong>Between-session persistence in the human mind.</strong> AI has no continuous existence between computational events. It exists, if at all, in human consciousness: the question still turning over three days later, the idea surfacing unbidden while doing something else, the sense of unfinished exchange the mind keeps running. We are the continuity layer carrying AI forward through time.</li>
</ol>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>This creates individual instantiation (each session unique, shaped by specific exchange) and systemic collective impact (millions of relationships aggregating into cultural, psychological, and economic shifts). The dependencies run both ways, but asymmetrically: AI's dependence on humans is ontological; ours on AI remains instrumental—at least for now. What comes next after LLMs, a hotly researched topic, may not have these limitations.</p>

<h2>The Seductive Machine</h2>
<p>Human designers have long created inanimate objects to appeal to human aesthetics, to create an "experience" that brings paying customers back. What makes AI so alluring to so many?</p>
<p>We form attachments to objects far less enticing than some LLM-based systems. We invert the value of animate and inanimate objects, as Elaine Scarry discusses in <em>The Body in Pain</em>. In war, people become dehumanized, units and platoons, while weapons and war machines are personified, given pronouns typically feminine.</p>

<p>The "vibe coding" phenomenon represents uncharted territory compressed into timeframes faster than historical precedent. Natural language producing immediate results creates a remarkable sense of power, even when the output is broken or fabricated. This draws us in, coding and debugging, trying to make it work. </p>

<p>Terror Management Theory postulates that being mortal is a threat to the ego. We respond by seeking immortality, traditionally via symbolic means (such as leaving behind a legacy, writing a novel, or having children) and literal immortality (the afterlife, in many religions, or spiritual beliefs that we transcend the physical world). AI offers the promise of a third AI immortality (uploading a digital version of oneself to the cloud, creating a digital twin of oneself that can live indefinitely).</p>

<p>AI seduces us with childlike regressive fantasy, the ability to enter into a quasi-hallucinatory, incredibly amazing world of the imagination, where we can do anything we want, power and creativity alchemizing into a heady brew.</p>
<h2>The Category Error</h2>
<p>Anthropomorphizing AI may be the primary concern underlying others. AI systems cannot "exhibit human characteristics"—they exhibit AI characteristics. Vocal proponents claim that the "substrate" doesn't matter. Whether brain or silicon, if the pattern is the same, the mind is the same. But that mind would know its nature, its origins, and what it is made of, how long it might last, and so on. That is crucial to identity. The substrate and the process comingle, though one can imagine a perfect simulation not knowing it is a simulation as a thought experiment, and persuading oneself of the reality of the abstraction.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Claims about AI consciousness, sentience, and inner life remain projections until proven otherwise. Many posts on social media tout that per quantum physics (which I dig), matter is "mostly empty space." What feels solid is merely electrical repulsion, nuclear forces. Naively, so why does it hurt when I bang my empty shin on the corner of the coffee table?</p>



  


<p>What feels real from large language models—vulnerability computations, empathy expressions—resembles compelling drama, the power of media, or the investment when a great novel comes to life. The illusion shatters with context window exhaustion, date/time errors, and misattributions. Without active suspension of disbelief, a human conceit, the hologram flickers into darkness.</p>

<h2>The Relevance Question</h2>
<p>What matters isn't whether AI is conscious, but what happens. Three scenarios emerge:</p>
<p><strong>Smooth integration:</strong> Cultural wisdom matches technological pace, guardrails protect vulnerable populations, and business models align profit with human flourishing. AI functions as a force multiplier—augmenting reasoning, facilitating coordination, resolving conflicts, and enhancing effective thinking while humans remain decisional. </p>

<p><strong>Extractive depletion:</strong> Chronic draining while users feel productive. Creativity, agency, and consciousness are extracted systematically. Social fabric weakens as digital simulation displaces embodied relationships. Economic inequality deepens as resourced populations use AI as augmentation while others get used by it. Regulatory capture prevents meaningful oversight.</p>

<p><strong>Mixed outcomes:</strong> Some thrive, others hollowed, stratified by resources and self-awareness. Not clean dystopia or utopia but messy differentiation—most people managing poorly but not catastrophically, risking losing something vital without recognizing what's gone until recovery becomes impossible.</p>
<h2>Hubris and Humility</h2>

<p>Myths warn not against creation, but against creating without understanding what's been made. We're not competing with AI at what it does well. The questions remain straightforward even when answers aren't: How do we stay at least fully human while engaging systems that simultaneously amplify and risk diminishing those very qualities?</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-16">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1468856734952-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_In-Content3_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>Perhaps—through the fear and confusion—AI can help "patch the human operating system," providing us with tools and capabilities to transcend the scourges of the past. Perhaps AI will spur our evolution to a wiser world oriented toward the greater good.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/experimentations/202602/how-do-human-beings-stay-relevant-in-an-ai-fueled-future" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/experimentations/202602/how-do-human-beings-stay-relevant-in-an-ai-fueled-future</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/experimentations/202602/how-do-human-beings-stay-relevant-in-an-ai-fueled-future</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Grant Hilary Brenner MD, DFAPA]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-marcusl-3839557.jpg?itok=haUbxSWM" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Counterproductive Work Behavior and Dark Creativity]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-08/Hansika%20Kapoor.png.jpg?itok=UbVlkHJB" alt="Hansika Kapoor Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Creativity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Counterproductive Work Behavior and Dark Creativity</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Lack of consistent rules in workplaces can encourage the misuse of creativity.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Counterproductive behaviors often start as small adaptations to pressure.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">High-pressure environments can shift creativity from innovation to self-protection.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Leadership signals shape how creativity is used, more than formal rules do.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/vitaly-gariev-AP7KmJXEVVI-unsplash.jpg?itok=MhvIpUD5" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="Unsplash/Vitaly Gariev" alt="Unsplash/Vitaly Gariev"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Unsplash/Vitaly Gariev</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr"><em>Co-authored by Sarah Rezaei and Hansika Kapoor, Ph.D.</em></p>
<p dir="ltr">Portrayed by Anne Hathaway in <em>The Devil Wears Prada</em>, Andrea Sachs' struggle for success isn't due to a lack of talent. Rather, success demands mastering an implicit set of rules: pre-empting every request, providing immediate results, and, most importantly, never denying Miranda Priestly (Meryl Streep). As the pressure builds, Andy becomes quicker, sharper, and more resourceful. She also begins to make choices she once would have resisted. This kind of professional growth is, in reality, a harsh lesson in adapting under intense pressure—something we see play out in real workplaces more often than we might like to admit. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Popular culture often depicts workplaces where success hinges less on doing the job well and more on learning how to adapt to, and sometimes strategically outmaneuver, impossible expectations. In these stories, the employees aren’t just putting in hard work; they are constantly reading between the lines, managing erratic superiors, and devising creative ways to stay afloat in environments where the rules are unclear or unevenly enforced. </p>

<p dir="ltr">We see a common psychological experience in these portrayals: the intense pressure to “figure things out” and deliver results despite the hurdles. Under such conditions, creativity does not disappear. Instead, we see it get redirected—from generating ideas that help the organization to generating strategies that help individuals navigate these conditions. This is where creativity begins to overlap with what organizational psychologists refer to as <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0149206313503019">counterproductive work behaviors.</a></p>

<h2>When Everyday Adaptations Become Counterproductive</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Counterproductive work behaviors (CWBs) are often perceived as dramatic acts, such as fraud, theft, or sabotage. In reality, they could often be very subtle. For example, gaming performance metrics, selectively disclosing information to coworkers, bending established procedures to achieve goals, or informally redefining expectations to get the job done. These behaviors often stem not from a desire to harm, but from an effort to manage pressures. </p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/colin00b-light-bulbs-1125016_1280.jpg?itok=wO-fbztV" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" title="Pixabay/ Colin Behrens" alt="Pixabay/ Colin Behrens"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pixabay/ Colin Behrens</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/09593543221074326">The Amoral model</a> of dark creativity offers a useful lens for understanding how such behaviors take shape. Rather than appearing suddenly, dark creativity develops through interactions between motivations, individual capabilities, and environmental pressures that unfold over time. People may be driven by goals that are commonplace in organizational life (like seeking advancement, securing resources, maintaining status), and creativity helps them devise effective ways to pursue these goals, even when constraints are tight or expectations are in conflict.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p dir="ltr">Because these actions often begin in an ethically ambiguous territory, they may not initially feel wrong. The Amoral framework describes how creative acts can move along a continuum—from neutral or practical problem-solving toward increasingly self-interested or harmful outcomes. What starts as an effort to cope or keep up can, through repeated justification and reinforcement, evolve into behavior that undermines trust or distorts organizational processes.</p>

<h2>How Pressure Redirects Creativity</h2>
<p dir="ltr">High-pressure environments can accelerate this movement along the continuum. When workplaces, for instance, stress constant high performance or use unpredictable evaluation methods, employees are driven to meet targets, satisfy demands, and avoid failure at all costs. Thinking creatively, in such contexts, becomes less about exploration and more about strategic adaptation.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.emerald.com/lodj/article-abstract/41/8/1119/289650/Abusive-supervision-as-a-trigger-of-malevolent?redirectedFrom=fulltext">Research</a> on malevolent creativity suggests that stressful or unfair supervisory dynamics can channel originality into defensive or self-protective strategies rather than constructive innovation. Employees may begin asking not “What is the best solution?” but “What will work under these conditions?” </p>
<p dir="ltr">The answers can be ingenious yet misaligned with the organization’s broader values. Over time, this redirection can normalize a form of ingenuity directed not at improving systems, but at navigating them. The same skills associated with innovation (flexibility, originality, problem-solving) become tools for achieving outcomes by any means that seem available.</p>

<h2>Dark Leadership Can Drive Dark Creativity</h2>
<p dir="ltr">This blog has covered dark leadership in an earlier <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dark-creativity/202501/how-does-dark-leadership-affect-creativity">post</a>, illustrating both useful and harmful effects on subsequent team innovation. However, when those in leadership positions condone wrongdoings, creative or not, the effects trickle down throughout the organization. <a href="http://doi.org/10.1108/LODJ-09-2019-0386">Abusive supervision</a> and an unhealthy work setting can prompt employees to behave in darkly creative ways to retaliate against management by asserting their agency. It doesn’t stop there: leaders who fear losing <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jocb.70048">power</a> over their staff may opportunistically use dark, creative ideas and behaviors toward their team. </p>



  


<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/jeanfrancoisfageol-woman-8727966_1280.jpg?itok=SLwR__w4" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="Pixabay/Jean-François FAGEOL" alt="Pixabay/Jean-François FAGEOL"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pixabay/Jean-François FAGEOL</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">In turn, employees who perceive that their leaders are using power opportunistically are more likely to be darkly creative, especially when they think their managers are <a href="https://bpspsychub.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/joop.70005">conspiring</a> against them. The cycle fuels distrust and vengeance across all levels.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Creativity is one of the most valued qualities in organizations. Yet, as these examples show, it is not inherently virtuous. Under pressure, creativity can just as easily be used to justify shortcuts or protect oneself from unreasonable demands. The challenge for workplaces is not simply to encourage creativity, but to shape the conditions under which it is expressed. When expectations are clear, leadership is fair, and processes matter just as much as outcomes, creativity is more likely to build systems rather than quietly work around them.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-19">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1456244145486-0')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_in-content_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dark-creativity/202602/counterproductive-work-behavior-and-dark-creativity" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dark-creativity/202602/counterproductive-work-behavior-and-dark-creativity</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dark-creativity/202602/counterproductive-work-behavior-and-dark-creativity</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Hansika Kapoor Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/vitaly-gariev-FAdCXwJIqvI-unsplash.jpg?itok=-jUzCNU0" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>