<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 17:01:12 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 17:01:12 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Global Glut in Cocaine Shocks the World]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-01/Mark%20Gold%20.png.jpg?itok=nPE4DpHC" alt="Mark Gold M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Addiction</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">A Global Glut in Cocaine Shocks the World</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Cocaine's back—and now it's the fastest-growing Illegal drug worldwide.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Global cocaine production has hit an all-time high, along with record seizures, consequences, and deaths.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cocaine accounts for nearly one-third of U.S. overdose deaths.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Cocaine enforcement has intensified, targeting maritime routes and cartel leadership to reduce access and use.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Dr%20Mark%20Gold,%20Nataga,%20Colombia%20Cocaine%20Andes%202021.jpg?itok=QBRwIKvC" width="320" height="427" data-insert-type="image" alt="Mark Gold, MD, in Nataga, the Andes, Colombia, observing indigenous use and coca production" title="Mark Gold, MD"></div>
<div class="caption">Mark Gold, MD, in Nataga, the Andes, Colombia, observing indigenous use and coca production</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Mark Gold, MD</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>With cocaine, the overdose bedside reflects decisions made thousands of miles away. Cocaine is clearly a major threat worldwide. </p>
<p>A decade ago, it would have seemed highly implausible that cocaine would account for nearly one-third (28%) of U.S. overdose deaths. Yet by 2023, approximately 30,000 overdose deaths in the U.S. involved cocaine. Synthetic opioids, particularly fentanyl, remain the principal driver of death, followed by cocaine. </p>

<p>Acute cocaine toxicity may cause arrhythmia, seizure, ischemic and hemorrhagic stroke, and sudden cardiac death. Chronic use contributes to cardiomyopathy, accelerated atherosclerosis, neurocognitive impairment, mood disorders, and psychosis. The drug’s effects generate immediate and cumulative cardiovascular risks.</p>

<p>The question is not just <em>why</em> an excessive flow of cocaine is happening, but <em>how</em> we react to this threat.</p>
<h2>Looking at Colombia</h2>
<p>To understand the cocaine resurgence, let’s start with Colombia, where coca is grown. I have visited indigenous people and coca farmers, most recently in 2021 (see picture). Up to 92% of cocaine seized on the streets of the U.S. originates in Colombia.</p>

<p>Beginning in 2016 and accelerating between 2020 and 2023, record amounts of coca were cultivated and record amounts of cocaine were produced, as documented by the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime. By 2022, the estimated potential production in Colombia had more than tripled from 2015. </p>
<p>Improved, more resilient coca plant varieties, combined with better techniques, led to exploding production, with potential yields increasing by more than 50% in the last reported period. Colombia produced an estimated 3,000 metric tons of cocaine in 2024. In fiscal 2025, <a href="https://english.elpais.com/international/2025-09-19/cocaine-trafficking-in-colombia-moves-as-much-money-as-the-construction-industry.html">the U.S. Coast Guard</a> reported a record-setting seizure of nearly 510,000 pounds of cocaine in the eastern Pacific and Caribbean.</p>

<p>Expanded cocaine production in Colombia has translated into greater availability in North America and Europe and more deaths. The Drug Abuse Warning Network (DAWN) estimates that roughly 354,000 cocaine-related emergency department visits occurred in the U.S. in 2023 and 393,000 in 2024. As with most items, greater supply brought lower prices—and lowered barriers to first use. Cocaine’s addictive pharmacology itself sustains repeated use. Stimulant co-involvement is present in most fentanyl-related overdoses.</p>

<p>As drug historian David T. Courtwright of the University of North Florida told me recently, “the late twentieth-century cocaine boom pushed up cocaine consumption in North America. The European market is now huge. Use is growing in East Asia and Australia. Cocaine smuggling is an international enterprise, with transshipment points in Africa and the Middle East. </p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/David%20T.%20Courtwright%20,%20PhD%20Emeritus%20Professor%20UNF.jpg?itok=ZJTWDCny" width="320" height="448" data-insert-type="image" alt="David E. Courtwright, PhD. Emeritus Professor and Author" title="University of North Florida/Used with permission "></div>
<div class="caption">David E. Courtwright, PhD. Emeritus Professor and Author</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: University of North Florida/Used with permission </div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>"The history of important psychoactive drugs is mostly a history of regionally traded goods like coffee and wine that became, with enterprise, bihemispheric commodities. Cocaine did it twice, first as a novel licit drug in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries and then as a popular illicit drug in the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries.”</p>


<p>Cocaine, and methamphetamine, can be lethal when either is taken alone. But the modern speedball, a combination of fentanyl with cocaine or methamphetamine, significantly amps up medical risks. Stimulants can mask sedation and delay recognition of respiratory depression, increasing fatal overdose risk. Patients may present with mixed sympathomimetic and opioid features, complicating rapid assessment and management.</p>

<h2>A Worldwide Threat</h2>
<p>Cocaine is today a hot global commodity. The Colombian market is in a massive boom, with the industry generating an estimated $15.3 billion in annual revenue, roughly 4.2% of the country's GDP. </p>
<p>While the U.S. is the primary destination, there are recent shifts. The European cocaine market has expanded dramatically. Use is increasing in East Asia and Australia. Smuggling routes now traverse Africa and the Middle East.</p>



  


<h2>The Expanding Stimulant Market: Methamphetamine</h2>
<p>In Mexico, after 2014–2015, methamphetamine production increased sharply, with falling prices and rising purity. Methamphetamine use dominates many Western states; cocaine retains strength from Miami throughout the East. </p>
<p>Consequently, a new trend in the U.S. is taking multiple stimulants. Toxicology data have been demonstrating increasing use of cocaine and methamphetamine together. Overdose risk is increasingly driven by fentanyl co-use, by smoking or injection, or inadvertent co-use due to fentanyl contamination.</p>

<h2>'Pink Cocaine" and Other Combinations</h2>
<p>A further complication of the stimulant drug problem is so-called “pink cocaine” (often called 2C, <em>tusi</em>, <em>tucibi</em>, or <em>tuci</em>). Pink cocaine is frequently marketed as cocaine or a premium "new" drug as a way to increase sales and cater to, or deceive, users in the club and rave scene. It typically contains little or no cocaine but is comprised of mixtures of ketamine, MDMA, methamphetamine, caffeine, novel psychoactive substances, and occasionally, fentanyl, dyed pink for branding. </p>

<p>There is no uniformity across batches, leading to increased toxicologic unpredictability. Emergency presentations of pink cocaine may involve dissociation; sympathomimetic toxicity (severe tachycardia, hypertension, profuse sweating); serotonergic excess or opioid effects, depending on the types and numbers of adulterants. </p>

<p>Unlike consuming a slice of bread, a new user has to experience cocaine to understand its quality, intensity, and effects. As a result, initial demand may be low, but low-cost access and a sampling build the cocaine user base. </p>
<h2>Enforcement</h2>
<p>Illicit drug markets obey the same economic principles as legal markets: When supply expands substantially at the source, prices fall (or purity increases at a stable price), barriers to experimentation decline, and downstream morbidity and mortality rise. </p>

<p>In addition to innovations in Colombian cocaine cultivation,<strong> </strong>the current market differs from prior cocaine waves because it exploits the U.S. polysubstance user market and delivery infrastructure. Cocaine distribution currently piggybacks on fentanyl and methamphetamine trafficking networks, creating vertically integrated supply chains managed by sophisticated transnational drug organizations. <strong> </strong>From an economic standpoint, the cocaine production expansion has translated into greater cross-selling of a variety of speedballing substances to consumer markets in the U.S., Europe, and globally. </p>

<p>Enforcement has intensified with the re-emergence of Colombia's cocaine production and processing, including attacks on maritime trafficking routes and high-value cartel targets. The recent designation by the U.S. of major cartels as terrorist organizations represents a conceptual shift from a law-enforcement-centered “war on drugs” toward a more literal war framework. </p>

<p>Such designation expands authority and coordination. But if history is any guide, targeted offensives only<em> temporarily</em> disrupt logistics, as illicit markets adapt. Short-term supply shocks may reduce access and increase prices and use, leading to changes in purity, adulteration, and substitution—paradoxically elevating overdose risk.</p>

<p>Major offensives such as capturing or killing cartel leaders temporarily disrupt supply chains, but they rarely produce sustained scarcity or durable price increases. Trafficking networks adapt. New leaders emerge. Routes shift. New actors enter profitable markets. </p>
<p>Consequently, for supply-reduction-related enforcement efforts to reduce harm, they must continuously adapt, focusing on increasing the cost of cocaine, decreasing cocaine use and deaths, and interrupting the drug supply in new and varied ways. As long as consumer demand remains strong and cocaine profit margins remain high, supply chains and drug smugglers remain tough, resilient, and innovative.</p>

<p>Cocaine is back—not because its pharmacology changed but because its market did. As we learned in the 1980s, cocaine epidemics do not end in isolation; they are shaped by lived experiences, public perception, enforcement intensity, price, competing substances, treatment accessibility, early intervention, and prevention. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/addiction-outlook/202602/a-global-glut-in-cocaine-shocks-the-world" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/addiction-outlook/202602/a-global-glut-in-cocaine-shocks-the-world</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/addiction-outlook/202602/a-global-glut-in-cocaine-shocks-the-world</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark S. Gold M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/cerro_photography%20iStock-1184035121.jpg?itok=ydxmXI4p" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Our Natural Intelligence Nexus Is at Risk]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/IMG_1313-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=ObbAdNW8" alt="Cornelia C. Walther Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Our Natural Intelligence Nexus Is at Risk</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How AI could lead to an implosion of inspiration, intuition, and interrogation.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Inspiration, intuition, and interrogation create a feedback loop that sustains natural intelligence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Frequent AI usage may weaken inspiration, intuition, and interrogation through cognitive offloading.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The implosion of human thinking is not destiny, but rather a systems failure that can be reversed.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2026,%202026,%2003_45_18%20PM.png.jpg?itok=OZbbTypi" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Walther. ChatGPT. 2026" alt="Walther. ChatGPT. 2026"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Walther. ChatGPT. 2026</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr"><em>What happens when a sophisticated cognitive system quietly stops being exercised?</em></p>
<p dir="ltr">There is a peculiar irony at the heart of the AI moment. We have built machines that mimic thought so fluently that we are beginning, almost imperceptibly, to stop thinking as deeply ourselves. We talk endlessly about artificial intelligence—its architecture, its possibilities, its dangers—while giving barely a passing glance to the natural intelligence it is gradually reshaping. This post is about that natural intelligence, and specifically about three of its most extraordinary features. </p>

<h2>The NI Nexus: A Systems Map</h2>
<p dir="ltr">From a systemic perspective, the ability to inspire and be inspired, to perceive and decide before you know, and the capacity to critically reflect on something are interconnected. They form an organically evolving feedback loop. Differently put, inspiration, intuition, and interrogation are nodes in a living network, each one feeding and refining the others, generating a sort of generative consciousness: the capacity not just to respond to the world, but to reimagine it.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Inspiration is the system's ignition</strong> — The moment a pattern breaks open and a new configuration becomes visible. It sits at the intersection of perception and possibility, when the mind makes a lateral leap that deliberate reasoning alone would never have permitted. It is the reward signal of a brain that has been doing the slow work of learning, absorbing, and wondering.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Intuition is the system's inner current.</strong> Recent research frames<a href="https://academic.oup.com/nc/article/2025/1/niae040/7942876"> intuition as nonconscious cognition</a> that co-arises with action — we know what to do and are already doing it by the time we realize that we know. Far from mystical,<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/feeling-it/202406/your-intuition-is-real-and-research-shows-how-to-access-it"> intuition is a finely tuned cognitive skill</a> — a natural compression algorithm for accumulated experience. A 2024 <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1336363/full">study</a> in <em>Frontiers in Psychology</em> argues that social intuition depends on social-affective implicit learning — the unconscious mapping of others' emotional states that only accumulates through real-world relational contact. This is not something that can be outsourced to a chatbot.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Interrogation is the system's quality-control mechanism</strong> — The capacity to question one's own assumptions, to sit with productive uncertainty, and to push past the first good-enough answer. It requires cognitive stamina, tolerance for ambiguity, and the metacognitive honesty to distinguish between what one actually knows and what one merely finds plausible.</p>

<p dir="ltr">These three nodes form a self-amplifying loop: Interrogation creates the tension that primes inspiration; inspiration generates raw material that intuition refines; sharpened intuition raises more sophisticated questions that feed back into deeper interrogation. When the system is healthy, it compounds.</p>

<h2>The Implosion Risk</h2>
<p dir="ltr">What happens when an external entity begins performing these functions on our behalf?</p>
<p dir="ltr">It is still early days in the latest wave of artificial intelligence’s grip on society, but the incoming data is not promising. A 2025 <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4698/15/1/6">study</a> found a significant negative correlation between frequent AI tool usage and critical thinking scores, with cognitive offloading as the primary mediating mechanism. Younger participants showed the steepest declines. A parallel <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0001691825010388">study </a>examining AI dependence in university students found that cognitive fatigue mediated the relationship between AI reliance and diminished critical thinking. Sadly, the very ease of AI-assisted thought is <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202602/are-we-cruising-toward-cognitive-capitulation">exhausting</a> the meta-skills needed to evaluate it.</p>

<p dir="ltr">This is the feedback loop running in reverse. When AI generates answers, interrogation loses its exercise stimulus. When algorithms deliver elegant solutions, the productive tension that sparks inspiration is preempted. And when social intuition is replaced by AI-mediated interaction, the implicit learning that builds it simply doesn't occur. </p>

<p dir="ltr">There is no dramatic collapse.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The result is something more insidious: a gradual implosion of the NI Nexus from the inside, as each node quietly atrophies from disuse. The brain operates on use-dependent plasticity. What we consistently stop doing, we eventually stop being able to do well. At a population level, across a generation, this is far beyond being a minor concern.</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Inspiration depends on the exploratory mental activity that generates unexpected cross-domain connections — boredom, open-ended wandering, unresolved questions. If we are consistently receiving polished AI outputs, we may be crowding out the very conditions that are the actual preconditions for creative insight. Are we doomed to live in a world in which thoughts, ideas, and eventually reality are a second-hand watered-down shadow of raw creativity?</p>

<h2>Implosion or Inversion? We Can (Still) Choose</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The picture is not uniformly grim, and the tool is not the problem per se. Intentional AI use <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC12255134/">can free </a>cognitive bandwidth for higher-order thinking. The challenge is the relationship that we cultivate with the tool. The same dynamic that erodes critical thinking in passive consumers can support it in proactive, reflective users who deliberately use AI to challenge their own reasoning.</p>

<p dir="ltr">This distinction — AI as amplifier versus AI as 24/7 assistant — is the defining psychological challenge of our era. The conundrum we have to crack is if, and how consciously, we inhabit our own minds. </p>
<h2>Practical Takeaway: The A-Frame</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The following four steps may help to build that consciousness over time: </p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Awareness</strong> — Notice when you reach for an AI tool before attempting the cognitive work yourself. Sit with the discomfort of not-yet-knowing. That discomfort is not a problem to solve; it is precisely the neurological condition in which inspiration incubates. Try a pre-AI log: Write your own first thoughts before querying the machine. This single habit begins to restore the interrogation loop.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Appreciation </strong>— Cultivate genuine reverence for the sophistication of your own cognition. The intuitive signal in a difficult conversation, the creative leap in the shower, the sense of knowing-before-knowing — these are the output of a system refined across millions of years of evolutionary pressure and decades of personal experience. Intuition can be trained and strengthened through mindfulness, reflective practice, and deliberate exposure to complexity. Treat it accordingly.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Acceptance </strong>— Accept that human cognition is slow, nonlinear, emotionally entangled, and frequently uncertain — and that this is not a deficiency to be corrected by AI efficiency. The features that seem like cognitive weaknesses (ambiguity tolerance, affective loading, somatic signals) are often exactly the features that generate insight optimization algorithms cannot reach. Accept, too, that interrogation requires friction. Easy answers are cognitively cheap; they are not always cognitively nourishing.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Accountability</strong> — Take personal and professional responsibility for the cognitive habits you are cultivating in yourself, your clients, your students, and your teams. Build deliberate AI-free zones into intellectual practice: undistracted inquiry, Socratic dialogue, unassisted problem-solving. And ask, regularly, the one accountability question that matters most: is my engagement with AI sharpening or stalling my own thinking?</p>

<p dir="ltr">The NI Nexus — inspiration, intuition, interrogation — is the living core of what human cognition offers that artificial intelligence cannot replicate: the capacity to be genuinely surprised by one's own mind, to know through the body, and to question even the questions. The implosion risk is real. But implosion is not destiny — it is a systems failure that awareness, appreciation, acceptance, and accountability can, together, prevent.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The most sophisticated intelligence on this planet is still the one asking the question. Not the one providing the answer.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202602/our-natural-intelligence-nexus-is-at-risk" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202602/our-natural-intelligence-nexus-is-at-risk</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/harnessing-hybrid-intelligence/202602/our-natural-intelligence-nexus-is-at-risk</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Cornelia C. Walther Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2026%2C%202026%2C%2003_45_18%20PM.png.jpg?itok=tbAPJVl9" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don’t Manifest More Pleasure. Do This Instead]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-04/C6F37350-7928-4982-9035-4ED750779569_1_201_a-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=dxkWxPu0" alt="Amy Campbell MClinPsych" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sex</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Don’t Manifest More Pleasure. Do This Instead</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why visualising desire can backfire.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In sexual wellbeing, the obstacles we face are largely internal, not external.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Feeling good is not the same as creating change.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Rather than abandoning visualisation altogether, the evidence suggests refining it.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-4980380.jpg?itok=ZOeluD3h" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Pexels/CottonBro Studios" alt="Pexels/CottonBro Studios"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pexels/CottonBro Studios</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">I remember seeing Jim Carrey talk about how his life was built by the belief that he could create his own reality. When he’s on a screen, he’s pretty hard not to watch, so naturally I was intrigued. At the time, I was mid-studies and deeply embedded in learning the scientific method. I had questions, but like most things consumed quickly online, the clip faded and I didn’t think much more about it.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Until recently. Manifesting has become a daily theme in my social feeds and in the online sexual wellness space. I am regularly seeing advice encouraging people to visualise the sex life they want—to imagine themselves confident, turned on, and deeply connected until that vision becomes their reality. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Armed with more evidence this time, I can tell you that there are decades of research showing that imagining a desired future can generate positive emotional states. This is true. Visualising “your best life” can boost mood and create a sense of hopefulness. That good feeling you get, and the boost in your mood, are nothing to sneeze at, <em>but—</em>and there is a <em>but</em>—feeling good is not the same as creating change. And this is where it can get tricky when you are applying it to a sex life that you actively want to change. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Here's the thing: Not only is it not the same thing as creating change, but it could actively decrease the likelihood that things will change. Research by psychologist Gabriele Oettingen and colleagues shows that when positive fantasy is used on its own, it can actually reduce follow-through (Oettingen, 2014). When we vividly imagine success, that emotional reward we get can unconsciously substitute for the effort required to make the change. In other words, your mind gets a win, feels good, and is no longer activated to motivate you to make effortful change. </p>

<p dir="ltr">And making an effort when it comes to your sex life is actually a pretty big deal. In one of the largest interview-based studies exploring what makes sex great (Muise et al., 2016), people who reported having great sex didn’t put it down to one simple action or effortless spontaneity. They described consistent prioritisation, significant effort, and engagement. They described investing attention and care in their sexual relationship. The great sex they reported wasn’t accidental or simply because they found great partners. It wasn't that they were some sort of sex god or goddess. It was attained through deliberate action and effort. </p>

<h2>So if we aren't manifesting our way to great sex, what does work?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Rather than abandoning visualisation altogether, the evidence suggests refining it. This idea comes from research on mental contrasting (Oettingen, 2014). Mental contrasting is the concept that instead of stopping at a desired future, you deliberately hold two things in mind when you visualise your desired outcome:</p>

<ol>
<li dir="ltr">The future you want.</li>
<li dir="ltr">The internal obstacle in your current reality that stands in the way.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">This contrast creates productive tension. And when the desired future feels attainable, that tension increases commitment and effort rather than replacing it.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Because in sexual wellbeing, the obstacles we face are largely internal, not external:</p>


<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Avoidance of vulnerable conversations</li>
<li dir="ltr">Fear of rejection</li>
<li dir="ltr">Negative body views</li>
<li dir="ltr">Fatigue and resentment</li>
<li dir="ltr">Emotional disconnection</li>
<li dir="ltr">Anxiety about performance</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr">Visualisation alone just bypasses these, whereas mental contrasting invites you to face them directly.</p>
<p dir="ltr">What does this shift actually look like? Instead of imagining yourself relaxed and connected during sex and stopping there, try this:</p>

<ol>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Imagine the desired future clearly. </strong>Perhaps you see yourself feeling present, responsive, and comfortable initiating touch.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Identify the internal obstacle. </strong>What usually gets in the way: Is it that you avoid initiating because you fear being rejected? Do you scroll on your phone instead of moving toward your partner? Do you disconnect from your body because of self-criticism?</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Commit to one concrete behavioural shift that supports you to overcome this obstacle. </strong>Consider initiating a cuddle or other non-goal-oriented touch; saying one honest sentence; or turning toward rather than away.</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Imagine what it will feel like to complete that change and, conversely, what it will feel like not to. </strong>How will it feel after doing that one action instead? What does it look like in the future if you dont take that action? </li>
</ol>



  


<p dir="ltr">Now the image you are creating of the future isn’t replacing effort; it is actively fuelling it. This change means you are no longer manifesting your ideal sexual self. Instead, you’re practising actually becoming it. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psyched-about-sex/202602/dont-manifest-more-pleasure-do-this-instead" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psyched-about-sex/202602/dont-manifest-more-pleasure-do-this-instead</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psyched-about-sex/202602/dont-manifest-more-pleasure-do-this-instead</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Amy Campbell MClinPsych]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-4980380.jpg?itok=au6ykcas" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Plato Would Have Seen at the Olympics]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-10/Sunde.png.jpg?itok=Hbip3dgr" alt="Sunde" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Philosophy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What Plato Would Have Seen at the Olympics</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Ancient self-governance played out on Olympic ice.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Alysa Liu won gold by becoming a friend to herself first, not by learning new jumps.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mikaela Shiffrin used reason as governance, not control, to end an eight-year drought.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Ilia Malinin's struggle was constitutional, not technical: governance overwhelmed by extraordinary stress.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The same three patterns show up in clinical practice, far from any Olympic ice.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">Plato was a wrestler. The name itself means "broad"; a nickname, though whether it referred to his build, his forehead, or his wrestling stance is debated. For the Greeks, athletic competition was never separate from training in self-governance. </p>
<p dir="ltr">I watched the Milan Cortina Games this month and saw three patterns of constitutional psychology that I’ve also seen in some of the people I’ve worked with.</p>

<h2>Constitutional Renovation: Turning the Whole Psyche</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Alysa Liu became the youngest national champion in American figure skating at 13. She made the 2022 Olympic team at 16. And she hated it. After Beijing, she retired, threw her skates in a closet, enrolled at UCLA, and spent 18 months figuring out who she was when nobody was giving her a score. Then she walked into a rink, landed a triple like she had never left, and called her coaches. She put it all on her terms: she would choose the music, the choreography, the costumes. They did not set a goal of winning gold.</p>

<p dir="ltr">On February 19th, she skated to Donna Summer and won: the first American woman to take individual figure skating gold in 24 years. Aly Raisman, the Olympic gymnast who now speaks on sports psychology, called the moment “healing” and said it proved that when an athlete loves something and also loves herself, anything becomes possible.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Raisman just articulated Republic 443d. Socrates defines justice for the individual psyche: a person should dispose well of what is properly his own, and “having first attained to self-mastery and beautiful order, become a friend to himself”: philon genomenon heauto (friend to himself). Liu did not learn new jumps during her time away. She turned her whole psyche, which is exactly how Socrates describes real education: not putting knowledge into people who lack it, but “turning the whole body” from darkness toward light (518c-d).</p>

<p dir="ltr">She did what I call constitutional renovation. She dismantled an organizing principle that had made skating into something she endured and rebuilt it until it became an expression of who she actually was. The technical excellence was there the whole time, waiting for governance worthy of it. I’ve seen this in my practice: The client who has mastered a context that is destroying them. The career they are brilliant at, but which leaves them empty. The relationship where they have become expert at managing someone else’s chaos. In these cases, the therapeutic work is not adding skills. It is a constitutional renovation.</p>

<h2>The Logistikon at Work: Governance Before Performance</h2>
<p>Mikaela Shiffrin tells a different version of the same story. One hundred and eight World Cup wins. Olympic gold in 2014 at 18. Then, eight years without an Olympic medal: Beijing was six events entered, three not finished, zero medals. Her father died. She dealt with PTSD from racing crashes. In Milan, she placed fifteenth in one event, eleventh in another. The slalom was her last chance.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Three days before that race, she wrote what amounted to a journal entry: fear, adrenaline, “the potential for criticism and backlash.” Then: “Still, when the countdown started, I pushed.” She won by 1.5 seconds. “The wonderful thing about this day,” she said, “was that I felt proud before it happened.”</p>

<p dir="ltr">That sentence is clinically precise. The constitutional order preceded the performance. She used what Plato calls the logistikon (reasoning faculty) not to suppress the fear, but to govern it: name the competing forces, organize them under a principle, carry that order down the mountain. This is what I watch for in my office: the moment a client moves from being overwhelmed by competing internal demands to being able to say what is happening and choose to act from an integrated position.</p>

<h2>When the Politeia Fractures</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Then there is Ilia Malinin. Twenty-one years old, the only person to land a quadruple axel in competition. He led after the short program. In the free skate, he landed one quad, and then everything collapsed: He bailed on his signature jump, doubled a planned quad, and fell twice. His skill did not disappear between programs. What gave way was his auto politeia (self-governance): the internal ordering that holds competing psychological forces together under pressure. </p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Plato describes something like this in the democratic psyche of Books VIII and IX: too many forces vying for the throne without a stable governing principle. In Malinin's case, it may have been anxiety and the sheer urgency of the moment overwhelming his concentration rather than competing desires. But the pattern is the same. Under ordinary conditions, the governance holds. Raise the stakes high enough, and every fault line opens.</p>

<p dir="ltr">I’ve seen this often. The high-functioning person whose coping works until it does not. The executive who manages enormous complexity at the office and falls apart when a relationship ends. The veteran who holds it together for years and comes undone over something that looks like nothing. This is not a skill failure. It is a constitutional vulnerability, and recognizing that changes the intervention: You build governance, relationship with self, not techniques.</p>

<h2>Choosing the Middle Life First</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Team USA had its best Winter Games in 76 years: 33 medals, 12 gold, including both hockey teams. But the numbers are not the point. In the Myth of Er, Plato describes the wise psyche choosing “the middle life” and fleeing “the excesses in either direction” (619a). Liu and Shiffrin did not choose gold medals. Liu said she did not need one to validate her decisions. They chose constitutional health first. The medals followed.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The question Plato would ask each one of us is the same one these Games answered: Who are you when the whole world is watching? The answer depends on whether you have become a friend to yourself first.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/platonic-psychology/202602/what-plato-would-have-seen-at-the-olympics" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/platonic-psychology/202602/what-plato-would-have-seen-at-the-olympics</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/platonic-psychology/202602/what-plato-would-have-seen-at-the-olympics</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Chester H. Sunde, Psy.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-pavel-danilyuk-6539359.jpg?itok=caGtjhNM" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Does Positive Body Image Alone Improve One’s Sex Life?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/SariCooper.png.jpg?itok=JDrttdSO" alt="Sari Cooper, CST, LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sex</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Does Positive Body Image Alone Improve One’s Sex Life?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How body positivity influences sexual confidence, communication, and intimacy.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 26, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Positive body image strengthens sexual assertiveness and relationship satisfaction.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Body image impacts sexual functioning more than BMI or body size.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Assertive expression of desire predicts greater relational and sexual fulfillment.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/huha-inc-OfVESgqrbJc-unsplash.jpg?itok=Wd5CubPo" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="HuhaInc / Pexels" alt="HuhaInc / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: HuhaInc / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>New research provides key insights into what partners need when it comes to more pleasurable sex. </p>
<p dir="ltr">General couples/relationship therapists observe common relational and systemic dynamics that affect most romantic relationships, such as: </p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Communication patterns</li>
<li dir="ltr">Attachment styles of each partner</li>
<li dir="ltr">Past traumas (including sexual trauma, childhood trauma, and domestic violence) </li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">However, another critical factor shows up frequently in individual and partner therapy with certified sex therapists, which can be frequently overlooked by general couples therapists and/or a romantic partner: <em>negative body image. </em></p>
<p dir="ltr">Many people who struggle with sexual connection, low desire, or relationship satisfaction may not be struggling with the love they feel for a partner or the level of commitment they have to their romantic relationship(s). What they may secretly be challenged by is the lack of comfort and safety they have in their own skin. </p>

<p dir="ltr">A negative body image can come with a host of symptoms, including avoidance of:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Initiating sex</li>
<li dir="ltr">Expressing desire to a partner, and/or</li>
<li dir="ltr">Communicating boundaries</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr">In a recent 2025 study in<em> </em><a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-328X/15/12/1730"><em>Behavioral Sciences</em></a>, Rizzo et al. examined how body appreciation, sexual esteem, and sexual assertiveness influence relationship satisfaction.<strong> </strong>They found that the way people feel about their bodies and whether this impacts their communication contributes to how they show up in their sex lives, which in turn can affect their romantic relationship(s) as a whole. These findings align with what the Sex Esteem® framework aims to improve in somatic sex therapy sessions.</p>

<h2>The Study: Who Was Included and What Was Measured?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Rizzo and colleagues recruited 473 Italian adults (50.1 percent men, 49.7 percent women; ages 18–49) who were currently in heterosexual romantic relationships. </p>
<p dir="ltr">The participants completed four self-report assessments on: </p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Body appreciation</strong> (Body Appreciation Scale-2)</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Sexual esteem</strong> (Sexual Esteem subscale of the Multidimensional Sexuality Scale)</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Sexual assertiveness</strong> (Sexual Assertiveness Questionnaire, focusing on initiating sex and refusing unwanted sex)</li>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Relationship satisfaction</strong> (Dyadic-Familiar Relationship Satisfaction Scale)</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">The researchers then used structural equation modeling (SEM) to test how these key pieces were connected in those relationships. </p>
<h2>Sexual Confidence Is Not Enough Without Clear Communication Skills</h2>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Screenshot%202026-02-25%20at%209.32.16%E2%80%AFPM.png.jpg?itok=YKdvZ0ZD" width="320" height="447" data-insert-type="image" title="Pexels/RobertoHund" alt="Pexels/RobertoHund"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pexels/RobertoHund</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Rizzo et al. discovered that when individuals felt more accepting and positive toward their bodies, they also were more confident sexual partners. However, the correlation the authors reported was: “Sexual assertiveness, but not sexual esteem, was positively associated with relationship satisfaction." In other words, a person having body positivity on its own isn’t enough to improve one’s sex life. It was only when the subjects felt more confident enough to take actions like initiating sexual activity, communicating their desires, and clearly accepting only the sex they wanted that the subjects reported improvement in their sexual and romantic relationships.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The difference between sexual esteem on its own versus when it is combined with sexual assertiveness is shown to be critical in this study and in clinical sex therapy. </p>
<p>Internal confidence is great, but alone, it doesn’t equal relational happiness.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In a somatic sex therapy clinical framework, two key cornerstones are <em>confidence</em> and <em>communication skills</em>. As confirmed in this study, what matters most to adults in a sexual relationship is how their sexual esteem is enacted through clear, confident communication skills followed by actions. Without clarity on what is wanted in a sexual scenario and the limits of what will be a consensual shared sexual encounter, partners frequently find themselves falling into patterns of: </p>

<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Avoidance (experienced as personal rejection by a partner)</li>
<li dir="ltr">Compliance (resulting in duty sex)</li>
<li dir="ltr">Unspoken (or passive-aggressive or aggressive) resentment over time</li>
<li dir="ltr">Potential non-consensual and/or coercive sexual encounters </li>
</ul>
<h2 dir="ltr">Further Research Results on Body Image and Sexual Function</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The previous study results are consistent with prior research on negative body image/low self-esteem. A 2023 study in the <a href="https://annals.edu.sg/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Annals_V52N4_April2023.pdf#page=28">Annals of the Academy of Medicine, Singapore</a>, found that poorer body appreciation was significantly associated with female sexual dysfunction in a questionnaire given to 514 sexually active young women (21-35) (Husain et al., 2023).</p>


<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/alexander-krivitskiy-DHPDsHOnTpg-unsplash.jpg?itok=DS_CSjf4" width="320" height="413" data-insert-type="image" title="Pexels/AlexanderKrivitskiy" alt="Pexels/AlexanderKrivitskiy"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pexels/AlexanderKrivitskiy</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">In past studies, researchers focused on how being overweight or underweight as a physical factor can impact people’s sex lives. However, similar to the previously cited study by Rizzo et al, Husain et al. found that<strong> </strong>a negative body image had a strong impact and relation to sexual dysfunction, unlike BMI (body mass index). </p>

<p dir="ltr">Specifically, lower body image and lower self-esteem were linked with poorer scores on the Female Sexual Function Index, whereas BMI categories (e.g., overweight) did not show a strong association with sexual dysfunction outcomes. This suggests that how a person perceives their body matters more than people may think.</p>



  


<h2>How Negative Body Image Intersects With Sex Therapy Skill-Building</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Both of these studies, along with sex therapy clinical experience, illustrate that when a partner feels disconnected or negative about their own body image, it is usually combined with less-than-optimal communication skills. Sexual avoidance, difficulty initiating, or the lack of communicating preferences can slowly destroy intimacy over time. </p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-ketut-subiyanto-4746698.jpg?itok=qpWKyX2F" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Pexels/KetutSubiyanto" alt="Pexels/KetutSubiyanto"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pexels/KetutSubiyanto</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Rizzo et al. (2025) remind us that relationship satisfaction is not built on sexual self-esteem alone, although it is helpful. It is the combination of the ability to use that internal security for authentic relational clarity in communication with a sexual partner. Having the courage to say “I want you,” “I don’t like that type of touch,” or “This stimulation feels good” requires a Sex Esteem® confidence-communication skill, and trust in one’s partner to listen without defensiveness, minimizing, or gaslighting. Therefore, improving intimacy may not only include improving or maintaining one’s positive body image but also gaining verbal and non-verbal techniques to express the nuances of what one truly desires and listening to a partner’s needs and wants without feeling pressure to immediately consent, people-please, or enact a sexual scenario. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Positive sexual self-esteem is one cornerstone of gaining authentic Sex Esteem®. It is the development of one’s sexual voice along with improved communication techniques, as the research above suggests, that helps to build improved relational and sexual satisfaction in relationships.</p>
<p><em>To find a therapist, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-esteem/202602/does-positive-body-image-alone-improve-ones-sex-life" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-esteem/202602/does-positive-body-image-alone-improve-ones-sex-life</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/sex-esteem/202602/does-positive-body-image-alone-improve-ones-sex-life</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sari Cooper, CST, LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/huha-inc-OfVESgqrbJc-unsplash.jpg?itok=32_-lvhT" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>