<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 20:29:59 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 20:29:59 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are Women Less Sexually Satisfied Than Men?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/Rob-Burriss.jpg?itok=IeQ6v0wE" alt="Robert P. Burriss Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sex</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Are Women Less Sexually Satisfied Than Men?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Psychologists pooled data from 37 studies for an answer. Here's what they found.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Women report being slightly more sexually satisfied than men, revealing a surprising gender trend.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Relationship satisfaction doesn't fully explain why women are more sexually satisfied than men.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Women's tendency to report higher satisfaction might be influenced by socialization and disclosure norms.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/couple_kissing_under_an_umbrella.jpg?itok=VhOt5-81" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Couple kissing" title="Joanna Malinowska / Freestocks"></div>
<div class="caption">Couple kissing</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Joanna Malinowska / Freestocks</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Who is more satisfied with their sex lives: men or women?</p>
<p>Ask ten of your friends that question, and most—perhaps all—will answer "women." But would they be correct? Or is this one of the many instances where our lay assumptions about psychology clash with the findings of scientific research?</p>
<p>As the authors of a new article published in <em>Archives of Sexual Behavior</em> acknowledge, research on this topic has yielded inconsistent results. Some studies suggest that men are more sexually satisfied than women, while others suggest the opposite. Others still suggest that there is little to no difference between the genders.</p>

<p>Ashlyn Brady of Sweet Briar College in Virginia and her large team of collaborators from across the U.S., Canada, and Europe decided to pool their resources in an attempt to answer the question. They combined data from 37 studies of sexual satisfaction in romantic couples—data representing 7,520 men and women. This was worthwhile because more data imbues an analysis with greater power to detect real effects. To take a metaphor from astronomy, think ditching your pocket binoculars for the James Webb Space Telescope.</p>

<p>What did Brady and co. find with this potent method? Contrary to lay assumptions, partnered women were slightly more sexually satisfied than partnered men. When asked to rate their enjoyment of sex and their satisfaction with their sex life, women, compared with men, tended to give higher scores. Men, meanwhile, reported greater sexual arousal as well as greater sexual inhibition.</p>

<p>The next step was to investigate <em>why</em> women were more sexually satisfied. The scientists recognised that prior research has shown that sexual satisfaction is not only a measure of physical pleasure but of a person’s feelings about how their sex life benefits their relationship in general. Because of this, and because women are known to place greater value than men on the relational benefits of sex, a plausible explanation for these new findings is that they are being driven by relationship satisfaction. Fortunately, the participants in the 37 studies were also asked about their relationship satisfaction. Statistically controlling for relationship satisfaction did not affect the results of the analysis: women were still slightly more sexually satisfied than men, regardless of whether they were more or less satisfied with their relationships.</p>

<p>The scientists also controlled for partners’ sexual satisfaction, because it has been previously shown that women tend to take into account their partner’s sexual satisfaction when estimating their own (to put it another way, women care more than men about whether their partner is having a good time in bed). Again, controlling for partner’s sexual satisfaction left the main result intact: women were slightly more sexually satisfied than men, no matter how satisfied their partners were.</p>

<p>One possible explanation for the results is that men, on average, value sexual novelty more than women do. This could mean that men’s sexual satisfaction decreases during a relationship at a greater speed or to a greater degree than does women’s. This possibility is supported by a further analysis of the mammoth dataset, which revealed that the gender difference was present in couples who had been together for a longer rather than a shorter time, although the authors caution that the effect is small.</p>

<p>Brady and colleagues also observe that, even though the participants in the studies responded to questions about their sex life in confidence, “it is possible that women may… simply be less willing to disclose a lack of sexual satisfaction than men due to being socialized to avoid discussing sexual problems.” </p>


<p>That is, women and men may be equally sexually satisfied, but women are more motivated than men to exaggerate their satisfaction.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/attraction-evolved/202602/are-women-less-sexually-satisfied-than-men" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/attraction-evolved/202602/are-women-less-sexually-satisfied-than-men</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/attraction-evolved/202602/are-women-less-sexually-satisfied-than-men</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert P. Burriss Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/couple_kissing_under_an_umbrella.jpg?itok=CLf_oj7F" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When Self-Care Becomes Another Thing to Be Good At]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/leah_marone.jpg?itok=F6-nepHD" alt="Leah Marone LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Self-Help</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">When Self-Care Becomes Another Thing to Be Good At</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The differences between performative and real self-care and why it matters.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 27, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-sound-on-3756791.jpg?itok=OxbF7kLf" width="320" height="216" data-insert-type="image" title="Sound-On/Pexels" alt="Sound-On/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Sound-On/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">She finished her workout, grabbed her water bottle, and before her heart rate had even come down, she was already scrolling through her camera roll looking for the right shot. She spent more time on the caption than she did stretching. By the time she posted, the endorphins had faded and so had most of the benefit.</p>

<p dir="ltr">We are living in the golden age of self-care content. Wellness routines are aestheticized, morning rituals are monetized, and the pressure to not only take care of yourself but to do it visibly has never been greater. Somewhere between the matching sets and the perfectly lit smoothie bowls, something got lost. For many people, self-care has quietly become one more thing to perform, optimize, and be good at, and that performance is actively canceling out the very benefits they're chasing.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-ivan-s-7161986.jpg?itok=F7ykevUf" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Ivan-S/Pexels" alt="Ivan-S/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Ivan-S/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>The Problem With Performative Self-Care </h2>
<p dir="ltr">Performative self-care isn't exclusively a social media problem, though that's where it shows up most visibly. It's any act of self-care where your attention is somewhere other than the moment you're in. It's the walk where you're mentally composing a caption before you've reached the end of the block. It's the meditation session you screenshot to show you showed up, while your mind was three tasks ahead the entire time. It's the yoga class you attended physically while being completely absent mentally.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The issue isn't the walk or the workout or even the post. The issue is what happens when we multitask our own restoration. The neurological benefits of exercise, the emotional reset of a quiet morning, the genuine recentering that comes from a real break — all of these require presence. When we split our attention between the experience and the promotion of the experience, we shortchange ourselves of the very thing we showed up for. We get the optics of self-care without the substance of it.</p>

<p dir="ltr">There's also a deeper psychological pattern worth naming. For high achievers especially, performative self-care can serve a particular function: it allows us to signal that we're okay to ourselves and to others without requiring us to do the harder internal work of actually becoming okay. It's self-care as reputation management. And when wellness becomes content, it becomes competitive. When it becomes competitive, it becomes another arena where we measure ourselves and another place we can quietly fall short.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-6963171.jpg?itok=zSJrm3ZA" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Cottonbro/Pexels" alt="Cottonbro/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Cottonbro/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>What Real Self-Care Actually Looks Like</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Real self-care is largely invisible. It doesn't photograph well. It often isn't comfortable in the moment, and it rarely gets likes.</p>
<p dir="ltr">It looks like saying no to something you genuinely don't have the capacity for and sitting with the discomfort of disappointing someone without immediately trying to smooth it over. It looks like stepping away from your phone during dinner, not because you announced a digital detox, but because you made a quiet decision that your presence mattered more than your feed. It looks like noticing the dozens of small transitions you already have throughout your day, the walk to your car, the two minutes before a meeting begins, the quiet commute, and choosing not to fill every open space with something your brain has learned to associate with productivity.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Real self-care is deliberate, consistent, and often uncomfortable. It requires the one thing that high achievers and over-functioners tend to resist most: doing less. It requires boundaries — real ones; not the kind announced in a caption, but the kind quietly held in your daily decisions. It means protecting your sleep even when there's more to do, ending the workday when you said you would, and choosing a genuine reset over an impressive one.</p>


<p dir="ltr">And real self-care is something you simply keep for yourself. Not everything that restores you needs to be shared, documented, or validated. In fact, there's something worth examining in the impulse to share it at all. When the act of caring for ourselves becomes something we perform for an audience, even a small one, we've already stepped a little outside of it.</p>

<h2>A Different Standard </h2>
<p dir="ltr">I'm not suggesting we stop posting our workouts or sharing our wellness wins. Connection and community have real value, and there's nothing inherently wrong with celebrating a healthy habit. But it's worth asking honestly: am I present for this, or am I producing it? Am I resetting, or am I performing a reset?</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">The goal of self-care was never to look well. It was to become well, steadily, privately, consistently, in the small and unglamorous choices that nobody else sees. Self-care is that walk where you left your phone at home, that boundary you held without explaining yourself, and that moment where you actually sat still long enough to find out how you were doing.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Nobody has to know, and, actually, that might be the point.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/gaining-and-sustaining/202602/when-self-care-becomes-another-thing-to-be-good-at" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/gaining-and-sustaining/202602/when-self-care-becomes-another-thing-to-be-good-at</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/gaining-and-sustaining/202602/when-self-care-becomes-another-thing-to-be-good-at</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Leah Marone LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-sound-on-3756791.jpg?itok=7sGL7fTa" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>