<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 15:25:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 15:25:33 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Become the Astute Thinker This Era Demands]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/alice_boyes.jpg?itok=beWKdmMs" alt="Alice Boyes Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Become the Astute Thinker This Era Demands</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Your most durable skills in a changing world are reflective, not technical.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_jrf5ejrf5ejrf5ej-med.png.jpg?itok=lM5DTg4p" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="AI Generated Image" alt="AI Generated Image"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI Generated Image</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The pace of change right now is dizzying. Many people are worried about whether their skills will continue to be rewarded as technology rapidly advances. People are anxious that skills they've built up over decades will be replaced by AI. They're afraid they won't be able to keep up, adapt, and meet mental challenges they haven't faced before.</p>

<p>I don't want to dismiss these fears; that would be inauthentic. I can't offer reassurance or tell you that you shouldn't feel under threat, but I can try to give you tools to meet the moment and help you understand that your most durable skills are cognitive, not technical.</p>
<p>We'll cover five reflective practices you can use to become a sharper, more <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/3-ways-to-be-nimble-in-a-rapidly-changing-world">nimble</a>, and more astute thinker in any external environment. They're all advanced metacognition — the ability to examine your own thinking, recognize your biases, adapt your mental models, and understand how your tools influence your mind and how your mindset influences the way you use tools.</p>

<h2>Adaptability Is a Cognitive Skill, Not a Technical One</h2>
<p><strong>1. Audit Your Own "Cognitive Lag." </strong>When AI tools are advancing rapidly, your intuitive approaches are going to lag behind. Don't let your brain be stuck six months ago. The best way to do any knowledge-related task six months ago probably no longer is.</p>

<p>You'll need to consciously and perpetually re-<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202512/how-to-excel-at-intuitive-problem-solving">calibrate</a> by asking, "Is this still the best way to do this?"</p>
<p><strong>2. Regulate Your Ego to Maintain a "Beginner's Mindset." </strong>When things are changing fast and fundamentally, the authority of past experience carries less weight. Strong, rigid opinions are more likely to be wrong. <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/how-to-reach-a-superior-level-of-curiosity">Keep your mind open</a> to rapid iteration in your methods and your ideas. Try assuming that you're probably wrong half the time and that half your ideas are bad. Get more comfortable with this level of fallibility.</p>

<p>The mental shift is not viewing this as threatening.</p>
<p><strong>3. Decouple Your Current Experience From Your Strategy. </strong>Imagine you're frustrated because your toddler takes a long time to dress themselves. If all you care about is your current experience, the "smart" move now is to jump in and do it for them. But that solution will quickly become irrelevant. In six months, they're not going to need that help. Another approach might be to create a lot of <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/the-engineering-method-that-helps-reduce-cognitive-overload">scaffolding</a> to enable them to get themselves dressed without it being such a clunky process.</p>

<p>The key insight here is that the child is going to mature and improve. Lightweight scaffolding makes sense. You get the best of both worlds — an easier life for you now, without undermining their developing capacity to endure frustration and persist.</p>
<p>Heavyweight scaffolding that takes a lot of effort doesn't make sense because the child's developmental process is going to take its natural course.</p>

<p>What's the point behind this extended analogy? You shouldn't try to adapt to the current reality. Trying to optimize for right now is bad strategy because it's going to be out of date very fast.</p>
<p>Solve permanent problems; don't build complex solutions for anything that's going to change in ways that make those solutions irrelevant.</p>

<p><strong>4. Only Outsource to Technology Skills You Don't Want to Retain. </strong>A good rule is to only outsource to technology the skills you don't need to maintain. For example, I don't care that Google Maps feels like it has worsened my sense of direction. I don't care to maintain the skill of documenting a process after I've done it so I remember for next time. On the other hand, I do care about being able to extract the most interesting insights from material I read or listen to. I'll go to AI for a different perspective or anything I've missed, but not to replace my own process of extracting insights and connecting dots across topics I'm interested in.</p>

<p><strong>5. Notice How New-Era Tools Are Changing You in Negative and Positive Ways. </strong>Don't rely on anyone else to warn you about negative effects technology might have on you. Be observant. Notice its impact on your skills, communication, perceptions, mood, and motivation.</p>
<p>Just as social media uses lots of hooks to keep us scrolling, AI tools will continue to build hooks to keep us chatting and working (whether that's an easy sense of productivity, asking us "would you like me to..." after giving an answer, or ways to remote into our files from anywhere). </p>



  


<p>AI companies aren't different from any other internet-era company in grooming their users to be sticky. We've all been through this before. Collectively, it's not our first rodeo. That pattern recognition is your advantage. Adjust your behavior when you notice expected or unexpected ways new-era tools are influencing you negatively.</p>

<p>Excellent metacognition isn't just about guarding against negatives, though. It's also about allowing yourself to notice delightful surprises.</p>
<p>Noticing the positive effects of new tools is just as important as noticing the negatives. This is a huge topic, so I can only touch on it, but I could easily rattle off a list of ways AI has made me a sharper thinker and learner, not a lazier or shallower one. And these aren't just quick wins that'll be replaced by long-term degradation. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>Thinking through how I could use AI and AI-written code to accomplish some of my workflows has improved my processes because it's forced me to be explicit about all the steps.</li>
<li>I've noticed that engineering skills I've learned for working with <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/how-to-use-ai-to-work-around-poor-concentration">AI</a> are resulting in an engineering mindset I apply to almost everything in my life.</li>
<li>Articulating my standards clearly enough for AI to follow them has made me sharper about what those standards actually are.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Meta-Cognitive Skills Will Never Be Obsolete</h2>
<p>The solution to anxiety about rapidly advancing technology isn't scrambling to keep up, even if hustle culture might feed you that message. Instead, recognize that your most important assets for meeting this moment are your enduring skills for observation and reflection. They'll never be obsolete.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/become-the-astute-thinker-this-era-demands" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/become-the-astute-thinker-this-era-demands</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/become-the-astute-thinker-this-era-demands</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Alice Boyes Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_jrf5ejrf5ejrf5ej-med.png.jpg?itok=FmMff2YT" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Reasons Men May Struggle With Their Mental Health]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/altman_img_1_1_-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=JZW7cTCD" alt="Donald Altman" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Emotions</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Reasons Men May Struggle With Their Mental Health</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">When a man is experiencing emotional issues, there are ways to help.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research shows that men seek help for mental health only half as often as women.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many men lack an understanding of their emotions.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mindfulness increases one's awareness of emotions and reduces reactivity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>According to a national health <a href="https://www.betterhelp.com/advice/therapy/who-goes-to-therapy-statistics-and-research-about-who-is-seeking-support/">survey</a>, approximately twice as many women seek help for mental health issues as compared to men. In addition, women are twice as likely to take a prescribed medication for their mental wellness as are men. </p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Moose-photos:pexels.jpg?itok=W6XNtnZv" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Emotional health is better for you than yelling." title="Moose Photos/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">Emotional health is better for you than yelling.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Moose Photos/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Other <a href="https://journalofethics.ama-assn.org/article/depressions-problem-men/2021-07">research</a> shows that twice as many women are diagnosed with depression. <em>Despite this, men commit suicide almost four times as frequently. </em></p>
<p>Obviously, something is keeping men from getting the help they need. What's up, guys? </p>
<p>Let's look at what I believe are three key reasons for diminished mental health in men, and then see how they can be remedied. These reasons are: </p>

<p><strong>1. Societal norms about being male.</strong> In this norm, men are supposed to "suck it up," "man up," and so on. In other words, to be a good man means stuffing your feelings and emotions. Of course, looking at the suicide rate as mentioned above, there's a steep price to pay for this strategy. </p>
<p><strong>2. A lack of understanding their emotions.</strong> In therapy, women often seek to work with their emotions. For example, I once asked someone how he felt about a recent accomplishment. His reply was, "I feel productive." That's nice, but "productive" is not an emotion. This is a big problem for many men (and many women too). For all humans, regardless of how rational we believe ourselves to be, our emotions are mixed into everything. We cannot escape the fact that we are deeply emotional beings.</p>

<p><strong>3. The belief that asking for help is a form of weakness</strong>. This stigma attached to asking for help may be one of the biggest reasons men are often reluctant to seek therapy. In my practice, I saw signs of this changing as I saw a range of men who came to my clinic. They ranged from software developers and truck drivers to doctors and teachers.</p>

<p>Before we look at a mindfulness remedy, let's point out some risk factors for men. </p>
<ul>
<li>Divorced men are more at risk for severe depression.</li>
<li>Alcohol abuse or substance abuse—1 in 5 men develop alcohol dependency during their lifetime. Three times more men die from alcohol-related causes than women.</li>
</ul>
<p>Also, men tend to experience depression differently. Instead of feeling sad or worthless, they often report feeling angry and irritable. They can lose interest in their hobbies, feel bored, report fatigue, and may be apathetic. If you or someone you care about has these warning signs, talk to them about this or seek professional help.</p>

<h2>The Truth About Emotions</h2>
<p>First, it's important to recognize that emotions are normal and natural. You don't need to push them away or avoid them. Isn't that a relief?</p>
<p>Feelings are another kind of information. They help us get our needs met. If you can’t identify at least five emotions, that could be a sign that you can improve your emotional understanding and vocabulary. (If you're interested, try naming five emotions right now.)</p>

<p>Did you ever hear the expression, <em>If all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a nail</em>? Here are some primary emotions that you've probably experienced: <strong>anger, sadness, fear, joy, interest, surprise, disgust, and shame.</strong></p>
<p>With a lot of emotions, we need to dig deeper to see if there's really <em>another emotion lurking beneath the surface</em>. For example, if a good friend forgets your birthday or doesn't show up for a scheduled lunch, are you <em>only</em> angry? Or, maybe you’re really frustrated, disappointed, exasperated, or hurt. </p>

<p>Likewise, let's suppose that something good happens to you, such as getting a promotion or reaching another goal. But instead of just feeling happy, maybe you are also astonished, surprised, shocked, amazed, awed, or thrilled.</p>
<h2>Mindfulness Remedy for Making Friends With Emotions</h2>
<p>Mindfulness helps you slow down and notice your emotions. This won't change the emotion or make it go away. But it can change your <em>relationship</em> to the emotion. </p>

<p>With mindfulness, you pay attention to the following: Where in the body am I experiencing this emotion or feeling? How strongly am I feeling this? What is a safe and positive way for me to respond to this emotion? If I gave this feeling a name, what would I call it? </p>
<p>Brain science tells us that <em>if you can name the emotion, you can tame the emotion.</em> That's because when you name your emotion, you are actually engaging the executive, thinking part of the brain. This distances you from being in the grip of the brain's fear and flight system. This shift lets you decide how to respond in the moment, rather than just react.</p>

<p>Naming emotions takes time, but it can give you a sense of control over an emotion, and that is the key to emotional regulation. With emotional regulation, you can notice emotions as they arise in the moment. </p>
<p>A final aspect of men's mental health is paying attention to self-care. Are you getting enough sleep, the right nutrition, supportive social connections, and so on? </p>



  


<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>It takes courage to look at your emotions and not just stuff them. By applying some of the ideas here, you are taking a first step to regulating emotions and improving your mental health. </p>
<p>Don't give up. It takes time and effort to practice emotional awareness. And, if you should need assistance (professional or otherwise) in doing this, know that you are acting in a wise and loving way to yourself and those around you.</p>

<p><em>To find a therapist, please visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>. </em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/practical-mindfulness/202602/3-reasons-men-may-struggle-with-their-mental-health" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/practical-mindfulness/202602/3-reasons-men-may-struggle-with-their-mental-health</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/practical-mindfulness/202602/3-reasons-men-may-struggle-with-their-mental-health</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Donald Altman]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/jack-lucas-smith-unsplash.jpg?itok=BB4c-djX" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Highly Sensitive People Overgive]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-03/SharonMartinLCSW-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=BfuHsaAz" alt="Sharon Martin, LCSW" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">People-Pleasing</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Highly Sensitive People Overgive</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Family dynamics can turn caring into overfunctioning.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted March 1, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-keira-burton-6624293.jpg?itok=Nk1u1noF" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Pexels / Keira Burton" alt="Pexels / Keira Burton"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pexels / Keira Burton</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Do you often feel responsible for other people’s feelings and problems? Do you give more than you have to give, then feel guilty when you try to pull back? Are you the one who steps in, fixes, soothes, and holds everything together?</p>
<p><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/highly-sensitive-person">Highly sensitive people</a> (HSPs) tend to be more attuned to emotions, subtle cues, and the needs of others. This heightened awareness can make you deeply compassionate—but also more prone to overgiving and overfunctioning, especially if you grew up in a difficult or dysfunctional family.</p>

<p><em>Overgiving</em> means consistently giving more time, energy, and emotional support than you can comfortably afford. You give because you feel obligated, not because you want to. You say yes to avoid conflict. You sacrifice your needs and wants because you think other people's needs and wants are more important. </p>

<p><em>Overfunctioning</em> is taking on too much responsibility in relationships, making them <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/conquering-codependency/202209/lopsided-relationships-when-your-needs-always-come-last">lopsided</a>. You step in quickly, fix problems, manage emotions, and carry more than your share of the load. You see it as your job to keep things from falling apart.</p>
<p>Both patterns are common among HSPs who grew up in emotionally unsafe or unstable homes.</p>

<h2>Why Highly Sensitive Children Learn to Do Too Much</h2>
<p>When you grow up with a parent who is unpredictable, volatile, emotionally immature, or impossible to please, your nervous system adapts. You become watchful and alert. You scan for changes in mood, tone, and energy. This is protective; it’s your system trying to keep you safe.</p>

<p>Highly sensitive children are especially attuned to subtle emotional shifts. They notice changes in tone of voice, body language, and the energy in the room, and adjust quickly to keep things calm.</p>
<p>This is often where overgiving and overfunctioning begin. You soothe, accommodate, and help. You become the responsible one, the emotional helper, the peacemaker. You may try to manage your parent’s moods, protect siblings, or carry emotional burdens that were never yours to hold.</p>

<h2>When Love Feels Conditional, Giving Becomes a Coping Strategy</h2>
<p>If your parent was hard to please or emotionally unavailable, you likely didn’t feel accepted just as you were. Many sensitive children in these families come to believe, “I’m not good enough,” or “I have to earn love.”</p>
<p>Overgiving becomes a way to feel worthy. Overfunctioning becomes a way to stay connected and avoid rejection. You try harder. You give more. You become extra helpful and accommodating. You minimize your needs and feelings. Being useful feels safer than being authentic.</p>

<p>With repetition, these responses become automatic and follow you into adulthood.</p>
<h2>The Difference Between Caring and Overgiving</h2>
<p>Because overgiving is familiar and often praised, it’s easy to mistake it for healthy caring. But they’re different. You can spot the difference by checking your motivation, your body, and the after-effects:</p>


<p><strong>Motivation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Healthy giving is something you want to do; it feels good.</li>
<li>Overgiving is an obligation; it’s driven by guilt and fear.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Body cues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Healthy caring feels open, calm, and steady.</li>
<li>Overgiving feels tense, urgent, or pressured.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>After-effects</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Healthy caring may be tiring, but it feels okay.</li>
<li>Overgiving often leads to resentment or depletion.</li>
</ul>

<h2>How to Change Patterns of Overgiving and Overfunctioning</h2>
<p>These patterns can become deeply ingrained, so you’re not likely to change them all at once. You can begin by interrupting the automatic pull to people-please or smooth things over, and practice new responses that honor your needs.</p>
<p>Try these strategies:</p>



  


<ul>
<li><strong>Pause before you answer.</strong> Most situations don’t require an immediate response, so give yourself time to determine what’s best for you. You can say something like, “Let me think about that and get back to you.”</li>
<li><strong>Check your capacity and responsibility. </strong>Ask yourself, <em>Do I actually have the energy for this? Do I want to do this?</em> or <em>Is this actually my problem or responsibility?</em></li>
<li><strong>Let other adults do their share.</strong> Resist the urge to step in too quickly and give others a chance to solve their own problems and develop competence.</li>
<li><strong>Set small, manageable limits</strong> with people who are likely to accept them. Start with <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/conquering-codependency/202306/how-to-set-compassionate-boundaries">simple boundaries that feel realistic</a>, like saying no to one small request or delegating a minor task. This will help you build your confidence and skills so you can set stronger boundaries with more difficult people in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Practice self-validation.</strong> Acknowledging your feelings and worth is a way to reclaim your power and start feeling better about yourself. From there, it’s easier to set limits and say no because you’re no longer depending on others to validate your worth or choices.</li>
</ul>

<p>Making these changes can be uncomfortable. However, remember that there are also benefits. Your relationships become more balanced and satisfying, you’re not as tired and resentful, you have time and energy for things that matter to you, and you feel stronger and more capable because you’re looking out for yourself.</p>

<p>These changes will help bring your caring into balance. You can be compassionate and still have limits. You can support others without taking on too much. Start with small changes and build from there.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/conquering-codependency/202602/why-highly-sensitive-people-overgive" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/conquering-codependency/202602/why-highly-sensitive-people-overgive</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/conquering-codependency/202602/why-highly-sensitive-people-overgive</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sharon Martin, DSW, LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-keira-burton-6624293.jpg?itok=rldSXI10" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>