<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 04:55:15 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2026 04:55:15 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Texts, Tracking, and the First Year of College]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-11/D7070BFA-0FFA-4E00-9560-C6EEFAF246D2-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=_1ZR_8aM" alt="America Edwards and Hannah Jones" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Family Dynamics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Texts, Tracking, and the First Year of College</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How mothers and daughters maintain closeness across distance.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mothers and daughters recalibrate communication when distance becomes routine.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Everyday digital contact often sustains relational continuity across distance.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Location sharing was commonly framed as reassurance rather than surveillance.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many dyads reported feeling closer during the first year apart.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>There is a lot of conversation about whether technology is good or bad for relationships.</p>
<p>That question has never felt especially useful to me.</p>
<p>As a scholar of family and interpersonal communication, I aim to study relationships as they are actually lived. Most close relationships today are performed across multiple modalities. A daughter who still lives at home may text her mother throughout the day about how school is going. A couple sitting on the same couch may send each other links to funny videos. Digital communication is not separate from “real” life; it is often an inherent part of the relational landscape.</p>

<p>But when a daughter leaves for college, something shifts.</p>
<p>Mediated communication is no longer just one channel among many. Between visits home, it becomes the primary way the relationship is enacted.</p>
<p>That shift is what led me to this study.</p>
<p>At the time, I was in graduate school in California, 2,234 miles from my hometown. Face-to-face conversations with my mom became rare. Texting, phone calls, and FaceTime were no longer supplemental; they were the relationship between visits.</p>

<p>My advisor’s daughter had just moved out to attend college in a different city. We were suddenly both navigating long-distance mother-daughter relationships from different roles—one as a daughter, one as a mother. Our conversations kept circling the same questions: How much contact feels supportive? When does it feel intrusive? What changes when proximity disappears?</p>

<p>Rather than debating whether technology was helping or hurting, we became curious about something more basic: How are mothers and daughters actually using it when distance becomes part of the relationship?</p>
<h2>Listening to Mothers and Daughters Talk to Each Other</h2>
<p>As part of my dissertation research, I analyzed Zoom conversations with 126 mother-daughter pairs during the daughter’s first year of college. The daughters were current college students living away from their mothers.</p>

<p>Pairs were asked to talk directly to each other about how they were using technology to stay connected—and what had changed since the move. The data showed a recalibration in the relationship, but the value of everyday contact remained central.</p>
<h2>Everyday Talk as Relational Continuity</h2>
<p>When daughters move away, families lose shared physical space.</p>

<p>What many dyads tried to recreate was not constant emotional intensity, but a sense of steady continuity.</p>
<p>Mothers and daughters repeatedly described brief, ordinary exchanges: photos, memes, “good morning” texts, quick updates about grades or social stressors. These small messages allowed them to remain embedded in one another’s daily lives.</p>

<p>Texting was central because it is sustainable. Pairs could connect alongside work, classes, and shifting schedules without having to be available at the same time.</p>
<p>In many of these conversations, closeness was less about depth in any single interaction and more about rhythm across time.</p>
<h2>When Presence Feels Important</h2>


<p>Video chat played a different role.</p>
<p>Many dyads described FaceTime as the closest approximation to being physically together. Seeing facial expressions and hearing tone offered reassurance and nuance that text could not.</p>
<p>At the same time, richer forms of communication sometimes intensified emotion. Some daughters described feeling more homesick after video calls. Some mothers described feeling the distance more acutely.</p>

<p>Families were not choosing one modality over another. They were moving between them depending on what the relationship needed in that moment.</p>
<h2>Ambient Awareness and Reassurance</h2>
<p>Some maintenance practices were passive: Location tracking apps were often framed as reassurance rather than surveillance. Mothers described checking a location late at night and feeling relief without initiating a conversation. Daughters, for the most part, expressed understanding of their mothers’ desire for that reassurance.</p>



  


<p>Social media viewership functioned similarly. Scrolling through posts allowed mothers and daughters to feel informed without requiring direct disclosure.</p>
<p>These practices complicate simple narratives about control or detachment. In these conversations, they were described as ways of managing uncertainty during a developmental transition.</p>

<h2>Development and Distance</h2>
<p>One of the most interesting findings had less to do with technology itself. Many mothers and daughters described feeling closer during the first year of college than they had previously.</p>
<p>Some attributed that to technology’s ability to sustain regular contact. Others attributed it to maturity and shifting relational roles. Daughters described being less reactive. Mothers described stepping back in ways that supported autonomy.</p>

<p>Often, it was both. Physical distance created space. Communication became more intentional. The relationship felt more adult.</p>
<p>Technology did not create that developmental change, but it provided the infrastructure through which it was negotiated.</p>
<h2>Beyond “Good” or “Bad”</h2>
<p>If there is one thing this study underscores, it is that the question is not whether technology is good or bad for families; it is already woven into how families relate.</p>

<p>The more useful question is how people are using it—and how those uses align with their relational needs, boundaries, and stage of life.</p>
<p>When mediated communication becomes the primary bridge between visits home, families enact closeness in the ways that are accessible to them at that moment.</p>
<p>And what these 126 conversations suggest is that, for many mother-daughter pairs, staying close during the college transition depends on whether they can recreate the everyday sense of being in each other’s lives.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-ties-that-connect-us/202602/texts-tracking-and-the-first-year-of-college" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-ties-that-connect-us/202602/texts-tracking-and-the-first-year-of-college</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-ties-that-connect-us/202602/texts-tracking-and-the-first-year-of-college</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[America Edwards, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_2655338093.jpg?itok=tbVJAAsr" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Pressure of Pre-Med]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-02/Marcia%20Morris.png.jpg?itok=lyueOB2l" alt="Marcia Morris M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Education</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Pressure of Pre-Med</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How you can help your college student through the pre-med journey.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The many academic and extracurricular requirements to get into medical school create pressure for pre-meds.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Most medical students now do a gap year between college and medical school to complete these requirements.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Parents can be critical in teaching students healthy habits around sleep, exercise, and social connection.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Healthy habits will reduce the pressures inherent in a medical career.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Early in my sophomore year of college, I was taking an organic chemistry test. Halfway through the exam, a classmate a few rows behind me stood up and started shouting in an agitated state. He was escorted from the class. I found out later he had consumed a large amount of caffeine during the last few days while studying around the clock. Fortunately, he went on to become a doctor, and we all learned a lesson about the dangers of excessive caffeine use and lack of sleep. That memory stays with me as a reminder of the intense pressure we pre-meds were under to perform, particularly in organic chemistry, which was considered the “weed out” class.</p>

<p>Having worked as a psychiatrist providing care to university students for several years, I have witnessed pre-med pressure rise. Medical school admissions in the US are highly competitive, and to make matters more challenging, schools have added requirements on top of outstanding grades and high MCAT scores. According to the AAMC (Association of American Medical Colleges), <a href="https://students-residents.aamc.org/medical-school-admission-requirements/admission-requirements">medical school requirements</a> may include many hours of extracurricular activities such as volunteering, shadowing, working, and doing research in a health-related field. Medical school applications request documentation of the hours worked and the experiences around these activities.</p>

<h2>Gap Year Before Medical School</h2>
<p>I’ve seen many pre-med students in my office overwhelmed by the pressure to “do it all” in four years. But it’s extremely challenging to complete those pre-med requirements. The cost of trying to do it all in college without sufficient sleep can be a sense of burnout as well as depression and anxiety. When I see pre-med students struggling in their classes and sleeping minimally as they study, participate in extracurricular activities, and work a job to help them pay for school, I encourage them to consider a gap year. In fact a recent <a href="https://www.amjmed.com/article/S0002-9343(25)00812-5/fulltext">article</a> in the American Journal of Medicine states that 75% of medical students are taking at least one gap year after college, up from 58% in 2014. </p>

<p>During that year, students can complete their requirements and perhaps work in a doctor’s office or hospital as a scribe or medical assistant, learning about healthcare and solidifying their wish to pursue medicine. They can take the MCAT and complete their applications. A gap year can be especially beneficial for someone with a weak science background from high school. It gives the students time to spread out their pre-med classes over the four years of college rather than taking them all in the first two years. They will have the time to study and obtain the tutoring they need to enhance their success. </p>

<h2>When It’s Time to Explore Other Careers</h2>
<p>Pre-med classes require an aptitude for science and a great deal of discipline. Some college students are not ready to take on the challenge. It is possible to come back to pre-med classes later, even after college. But if your student has failed chemistry three times and wants to take it again for pre-med requirements, they might want to explore other options instead.</p>

<p>I’ve seen pre-med students pursue wonderful careers in public health. I’ve also seen students shift into non-health careers such as journalism and advertising. Many schools have a career resource center that offers an interests assessment to help students understand which careers best suit them. Schools can also help students obtain job and volunteer experiences to hone their interests. Ask your children about what classes and activities they like at school and guide them in that direction.</p>

<h2>What Parents Can Do to Take the Pressure Off</h2>
<p>Being pre-med is a major life commitment, and becoming a doctor requires a great deal of time and energy. I love what I do; learning new ways to help people as medical knowledge evolves is exciting. However, the pressure continues in a variety of ways including providing top-level care while satisfying licensing, insurance, and specialty board requirements. Finding the right practice that provides for a good work-life balance can be a challenge.</p>


<p>You are essential in teaching your child healthy habits now that can reduce pressure for a lifetime. Here are some methods that will allow for a happier medical career:</p>
<ol>
<li><em>Get adequate sleep</em>. Maintain a regular sleep schedule that includes 7-8 hours of sleep a night. While some parts of medical training may not allow for sufficient sleep, training programs have set limits on the number of hours trainees can be awake and on total number of hours worked per week</li>
<li><em>Exercise</em>. A <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7641255/#:~:text=of%20these%20results.-,Results,lower%20on%20mean%20mood%20scores">survey</a> of doctors and medical students shows exercise is their top choice for stress relief. Exercise can elevate levels of feel-good neurotransmitters like <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4061837/">serotonin, norepinephrine, dopamine</a> and the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36768332/#:~:text=Physical%20exercise%20(PE)%20is%20considered,runner&amp;apos;s%20high;%20the%20endocannabinoid%20system">endocannabinoids</a>.</li>
<li><em>Make time for friends</em>. Numerous studies have demonstrated that <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC3874845/">social connection</a> decreases risk for depression, anxiety, and suicide. Social connections both at work and at home are good for our general health.</li>
<li><em>Keep alcohol use to a minimum</em>. Some <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10011852/">studies</a> suggest doctors, particularly surgeons, consume more alcohol than the general population. This can be problematic, as drinking is not a good long-term coping strategy for stress. Alcohol is a brain depressant, and there can be rebound anxiety the day after consumption.</li>
</ol>

<p><em>“Drink lots of water.”</em> This is the first bit of advice I received at my internship orientation right after medical school. I think the message was: take care of yourself as much as possible during this difficult year. And I would advise all pre-meds, medical students, and physicians to use self-care as a tool to enhance your journey through an exciting and challenging career. </p>



  


<p><em>©2026 Marcia Morris</em></p>
<p><em>Details have been altered to protect patient privacy.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/college-wellness/202602/the-pressure-of-pre-med" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/college-wellness/202602/the-pressure-of-pre-med</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/college-wellness/202602/the-pressure-of-pre-med</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Marcia Morris M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-anntarazevich-7904483.jpg?h=23011712&amp;itok=hCpoIzoe" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>