<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 16:00:34 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 16:00:34 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fortune Holds the Rudder—Take the Helm]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-10/Sunde.png.jpg?itok=Hbip3dgr" alt="Sunde" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Philosophy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Fortune Holds the Rudder—Take the Helm</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What two ancient texts reveal about governing what you can.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Ecclesiastes 9:11 names five forms of excellence and declares none of them sovereign over fortune.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Plato's Laws ranks three forces governing life: God, chance and occasion, and skill, in that order.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The therapeutic task is not controlling circumstances but governing the mind that meets them.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Last week, a veteran told me something I have heard in various forms over the years: "I did everything I was supposed to do. And it still went sideways." He was not complaining. He was genuinely bewildered. The contract he had been operating under his entire adult life: Work hard, train hard, follow the rules, and the outcomes will track your effort. That contract had been broken, but not by him.</p>

<p>I have written previously about the convergence between Ecclesiastes and Plato. Here I want to dig deeper into the two passages that speak most directly to the man sitting across from me.</p>
<h2>The Verse</h2>
<p>Ecclesiastes 9:11: "The race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all."</p>

<p>Five forms of human excellence. Not one of them rules over fortune. The Hebrew is worth pausing on. The word for "time" is <em>et</em>: not clock time but the appointed moment, the season that arrives unbidden. The word for "chance" is <em>pega</em>, from a root meaning to meet, to fall upon. <em>Pega</em> is what meets you on the road: the encounter you did not plan for and cannot prepare against.</p>

<p>These are not two separate forces. <em>Et</em> and <em>pega</em> are two faces of the same reality: fortune's timing and fortune's content. What falls upon you and when it falls. Time folds into chance. The seasons change, and you do not get to pick which one you are in.</p>
<p>Anyone who has sat in my chair long enough recognizes this. The veteran who deployed four times and came home intact, only to have his marriage collapse six months later. The woman who ate right and exercised and still got the diagnosis. Excellence does not insulate you. Ecclesiastes is not cynical but honest.</p>

<p>The colloquial version is two words: "Sh*t happens." It captures the diagnosis perfectly. What it leaves out is the response. Both Ecclesiastes and Plato supply one.</p>
<h2>The Philosopher</h2>
<p>Plato's response to fortune runs throughout the <em>Republic</em>: the dice and deliberation, <em>tyche</em> and <em>psyche</em>, the rough versus the smooth road. I have built my clinical framework around that material. What was new to me was a passage in the <em>Laws</em> where the Athenian Stranger states the same case in compressed form. No man ever makes laws, he says: Chances and accidents of all kinds make all our laws for us (709a). War, poverty, pestilence: These create the conditions that compel humans to legislate. The point is not that we are helpless but that the occasions that demand our response are not of our choosing (709b).</p>

<p>Then he names what does govern. Three forces, in descending order. First: <em>theos</em>, God: the ordering principle beyond human reach. Second: <em>tyche kai kairos</em>, chance and occasion: what happens and when it happens, arriving as an inseparable pair. Third, and explicitly the least: <em>techne</em>, art or skill.</p>
<p>His analogy: The pilot's art should cooperate with occasion (709c). The Greek word for pilot is <em>kubernetes</em>: helmsman, governor, the root of "cybernetics." The <em>kubernetes</em> does not control the storm or its timing. He governs the ship within it.</p>

<h2>The Coin</h2>
<p>On ancient coins, Tyche, the goddess of fortune, is regularly depicted holding a rudder. Fortune herself grips the mechanism that steers.</p>
<p>On ancient vessels, the rudder and the helm were the same object (a large oar). Modern usage has split them. The rudder is the blade in the water, the force that turns the ship. The helm is the wheel on deck: the point of command, where governance happens. That split gives us something both teachers understood but neither had a single phrase for:</p>

<blockquote><p>Fortune holds the rudder. Take the helm.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is not theory for me. On January 5, 2023, I woke up to my house on fire. I fought it until the fire department could take over and paid the price in severe burns. Weeks later, I woke up in a burn center facing a second and third skin graft surgery. I had gone to sleep in a life I had built over decades and woken up inside Ecclesiastes 9:11. What I had was Plato: the psychology of <em>auto politeia</em> I had been studying for years. Each morning, the choice was concrete: Stay in bed as a victim of <em>tyche</em> or get up and govern what I could govern. I got up. When I heard a podcast about Ecclesiastes recently, the connection between these two traditions was easy to recognize.</p>

<p>This is the clinical insight I keep returning to. The people who struggle most in my office are not those facing the worst circumstances. They are the ones who staked everything on controlling the rudder: on making the world yield to their merit and effort. When it does not yield, the problem is not the emotion that follows. Anger, sadness: Those are real and appropriate feelings. The anxiety that accompanies them is a survival response, fight or flight. The problem is the expectation that preceded them: the assumption that fortune owed them something in exchange for their excellence. That assumption is the contract, and it was never valid.</p>



  


<p>Ecclesiastes broke that contract 24 centuries ago. Plato's Athenian did the same. The therapeutic task is not to rebuild the contract. It is to help the person find the helm.</p>
<p>The helm is <em>auto politeia</em>: constitutional self-governance. On a ship, the helm turns the rudder. They are connected: The helmsman does influence the direction. But the sea, the wind, and the current have their hands on the rudder, too, and they are stronger than any pilot. You are not pretending your wheel overrides the sea, and you are not resigning yourself to drift. Sometimes you have to tack: You cannot sail directly into the wind, but a skilled pilot knows how to work with it, adjusting course to make progress through conditions he did not choose. You are governing what you can, adjusting to what you cannot, so that when <em>pega</em> falls upon you—and it will—you engage with your full might from a well-ordered constitution rather than from the wreckage of a broken expectation.</p>

<p>Ecclesiastes puts it directly: "Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might" (9:10). Not because doing it with your might controls the outcome. Ecclesiastes has just demolished that illusion. Because the engagement itself—full, governed, present—is the only thing that was ever actually yours.</p>

<p>Fortune holds the rudder. Take the helm. That is still the most useful thing I can tell the person sitting across from me.</p>
<p><em>This article is a companion to </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/platonic-psychology/202602/the-ancient-cure-for-is-this-really-it"><em>"The Ancient Cure for 'Is This Really It?'"</em></a></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/platonic-psychology/202602/fortune-holds-the-rudder-take-the-helm" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/platonic-psychology/202602/fortune-holds-the-rudder-take-the-helm</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/platonic-psychology/202602/fortune-holds-the-rudder-take-the-helm</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Chester H. Sunde, Psy.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-brenoanp-442535-1136576.jpg?itok=9XCTpi5a" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why 'Good Job!' Is Overused—What to Say Instead]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-11/image001-removebg-preview.png.jpg?itok=gdpLvMOO" alt="Joel Wong Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Gratitude</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why 'Good Job!' Is Overused—What to Say Instead</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Praise, encourage, celebrate, thank: Four ways to offer meaningful affirmations.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Praise, encouragement, celebration, and gratitude are different ways to communicate verbal affirmation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Compared to praise, gratitude is more intimate, more vulnerable, and more humble.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Praise says: You did something good. Gratitude says: You did something good for me.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Imagine this: You’ve just attended a talk by a co-worker at your organization. Her presentation blows you away. In fact, it’s a game-changer for you—her talk ignites a paradigm shift in the way you think. You’re inspired. Afterward, you walk up to her and say, “Good job! That was an amazing presentation.”</p>

<p>You’ve just praised her. And that’s fine—praise is positive. But you’ve also missed an opportunity to say something <em>even more meaningful</em>. Humans don’t just want to feel competent—we want to feel that we <em>matter</em>. We want to know that our work, words, or effort made a difference to someone.</p>
<p>So instead of “good job,” try this:</p>

<ul>
<li>“I learned so much from you.”</li>
<li>“You changed the way I think.”</li>
<li>“You inspired me.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Now you’ve done something powerful—you’ve communicated that she <em>added value to your life.</em> You’re saying, you matter to me. In essence, you’ve just expressed gratitude—even without saying “Thank you.” Because here’s the difference: Praise expresses your role as an evaluator. Gratitude signals that you’re a learner.</p>

<h2>The Four Affirmations: Praise, Encourage, Celebrate, Thank</h2>
<p>I want to introduce you to a family of language-based affirmations that uplift, connect, and empower. I call them PECT: praise, encourage, celebrate, and thank. Each one communicates appreciation differently—and when used thoughtfully, they transform everyday interactions into meaningful exchanges.</p>

<p>Of course, you can express any of these four affirmations without words, too. But for this piece, I’m focusing on the verbal kind—the things we say or write to others.</p>
<h2>Praise</h2>
<p><a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2002-15487-005">Praise</a> communicates a <em>positive evaluation</em> of another person’s performance (<em>Good job!</em>) or attributes (<em>You’re so talented!</em>).</p>
<p>In American society, praise is so common it’s practically a reflex. We use it as a form of greeting, like saying “Hello.” It keeps things pleasant but often lacks depth. Praise also functions as a <em>reinforcer</em>—we use it to increase desirable behavior.</p>

<p>But praise is most useful when it serves an <em>informational </em>function. Praise, when appropriately expressed, communicates meaning, telling a person <em>what </em>is valued and <em>why </em>they were successful. For instance, you could draw attention to a person’s skill or strategy that helps them succeed.</p>
<p>Psychologist Carol Dweck’s theory on the <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1999-05027-021">growth mindset</a>—and the type of praise that fosters this mindset—is now widely known among American educators. Drawing on Dweck’s research showing that <em>process praise</em> (“You worked hard on this!”) is better at motivating kids than <em>person praise</em> (“You’re so smart!”), some educators misapply her theory by blindly praising kids for their hard work, even when they fail.</p>

<p>But sometimes, failure isn’t due to a lack of hard work but perhaps a poor strategy that needs to change. So simply praising someone for their hard work can be <a href="https://srcd.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/cdev.12955?casa_token=yQRAYYVfmuAAAAAA%3A9Rv_kAZt2MVfoK74oFCFtKbUjjW6Bsdjh-rWDgkDuMsmFZ24Qi0LY4iNN2Y_eJW5hwN9V_P9bZU20VGV">disingenuous</a>—or even worse, reinforce a strategy that isn’t working.</p>
<p>The takeaway? When using praise, think about the type of information we’re communicating and whether it’s actually meaningful to the recipient.</p>


<p>Instead of saying “Great talk!”, try: “The stories you shared really brought your ideas to life.” That’s meaningful praise—it tells the person what you valued and what specifically contributed to their success.</p>
<h2>Encouragement</h2>
<p>Encouragement and praise are sometimes used interchangeably, but encouragement has a stronger focus on <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0011000014545091?casa_token=hmxXrPGZ3KQAAAAA%3Aq2D1cqCCDBNZQBDijHVkH0Jj5fTlxPuqMFAEx7F1-b8CKqnwSnF1xnfkhpZqe-6xJQgCZXKBgs2C0w">enhancing another person’s motivation</a>—whether that’s instilling hope, inspiration, confidence, perseverance, or courage.</p>

<p>Encouragement is often used as a form of social support for people who are struggling—a positive message to boost their spirits when they’re feeling down.</p>
<p>But encouragement can also focus on <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0011000014545091?casa_token=hmxXrPGZ3KQAAAAA%3Aq2D1cqCCDBNZQBDijHVkH0Jj5fTlxPuqMFAEx7F1-b8CKqnwSnF1xnfkhpZqe-6xJQgCZXKBgs2C0w">realizing potential</a>—even when there isn’t an existing problem. This type of encouragement is <em>future-oriented.</em> You’re helping someone imagine a bigger version of themselves—sometimes before they can see it.</p>



  


<p>Here’s an example: “Have you thought of pursuing a Ph.D.? You have a great grasp of research, and I know you’d be successful.”</p>
<p>In fact, encouragement stands out from the other three affirmations as the only one with a <em>future orientation.</em> After all, it’s odd to praise, thank, or celebrate someone for their <em>future</em> actions—but we can certainly encourage them to pursue future opportunities.</p>

<p>This type of encouragement can be incredibly powerful. You’re broadening and building someone’s dreams. Many people would never have pursued an opportunity—or even imagined it—without the encouragement of someone who believed in them. You can be that person.</p>
<h2>Celebration</h2>
<p>Celebration recognizes and honors others’ achievements or milestones. It includes a <em>reactive</em> component—responding positively when someone shares good news (“I’m so happy you won that award!”)—and a <em>proactive</em> component, when we take the initiative to honor someone’s milestone (like a birthday or promotion) through rituals, ceremonies, or public acknowledgment.</p>

<p>Celebration communicates to others that we value them—that we didn’t forget their birthday or that we think their promotion is a big deal.</p>
<p>How you celebrate someone may be just as important as what you say. Research shows that responding with <a href="https://compass.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/spc3.12407?casa_token=0XsYAzAuwD8AAAAA:M6yOLup8X24knV9T7tJPa86f1J7Jm4v3jVMAEoTiarWPdaXxGtL85VqgieUadehYPQxisGKmGKaJwUJI">genuine enthusiasm and curiosity</a> (for example, by asking questions) when someone shares good news not only boosts their mood but also strengthens your relationship with them.</p>

<h2>Actionable Gratitude (Thank)</h2>
<p>Gratitude can be a feeling—but it can also be an action. I call this actionable gratitude: expressing your thanks directly to your benefactor.</p>
<p>Praise and gratitude both acknowledge someone, but they differ in tone and depth.</p>
<ul>
<li>Praise says: <em>You did something good.</em></li>
<li>Gratitude says: <em>You did something good for me.</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Gratitude is more intimate, more vulnerable, more humble. It acknowledges that someone has made a positive difference in your life—and that you’re, in some way, indebted.</p>
<p>If you find yourself defaulting to praise instead of thanks, ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
<li>Am I hiding behind the safety of evaluation?</li>
<li>Does admitting I learned something from someone feel uncomfortable?</li>
</ul>

<p>Because gratitude isn’t just polite—it’s connective. It says, <em>You changed me. </em></p>
<p>And according to research by my former student Alexis Pandelios, gratitude feels most sincere when it’s specific. Don’t just say, “Thank you!” Tell the person <em>what</em> they did and <em>how</em> it helped you. “Thank you for taking the time to review my draft. Your feedback helped me clarify my argument—and I learned so much from it.” That’s being specific. That’s actionable gratitude in motion.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article_inline_full">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_full_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_full_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/praise%20vs.%20gratitude.jpg?itok=EA_c06yL" width="639" height="639" data-insert-type="image" alt="Praise vs. Gratitude" title="AI-generated with ChatGPT / OpenAI"></div>
<div class="caption">Praise vs. Gratitude</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI-generated with ChatGPT / OpenAI</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>So there you have it: Praise. Encourage. Celebrate. Thank. Each one speaks a slightly different dialect of affirmation.</p>
<ul>
<li>Someone’s performing well but doesn’t know <em>why</em>—use <strong>praise </strong>to show them.</li>
<li>Someone’s got untapped potential—<strong>encourage</strong> them.</li>
<li>Someone feels unseen—<strong>celebrate</strong> them.</li>
<li>Someone’s made a difference in your life—<strong>thank </strong>them.</li>
</ul>

<p>Give someone a PECT today. Watch how it changes them—and how it changes you.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/gratefully/202602/why-good-job-is-overused-what-to-say-instead" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/gratefully/202602/why-good-job-is-overused-what-to-say-instead</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/gratefully/202602/why-good-job-is-overused-what-to-say-instead</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Joel Wong Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/celebration.jpg?itok=t446XexO" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Radical Honesty Isn’t Emotional Intimacy]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/jill-weber.jpg?itok=zpYi1X2b" alt="Jill P. Weber Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Radical Honesty Isn’t Emotional Intimacy</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why saying everything you feel doesn’t bring you closer.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Radical honesty may come from good intentions but can be a shortcut around the work of intimacy development.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">There can be anxiety when we have difficult things to say to loved ones.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The art of intimacy is learning to manage negative feelings in way that keeps your relationship the priority.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>In a recent "Love Is Blind" episode, a couple, Chris and Jess, seem to have it all. They share a sense of humor, worldview, and goals for the future; are authentic; and share a physical closeness with one another. Suddenly, in a dramatic shift, Chris tells Jess, in not-so-many words, that he is not sexually attracted to her because she is not physically fit enough for his liking, although he wants to “work on it.”</p>

<p>Although radical honesty can come from a place of good intentions, not wanting to hide or mislead another person, it can also be so destabilizing that there really is nothing left to work on.</p>
<p>We exist in a culture where being radically authentic is touted and can become a kind of virtue signaling. It means you are honest and have integrity—better to hurt people’s feelings than to lead them on.</p>

<p>On the other hand, authenticity, to such an extent, takes the hard work out of the art of relationship development. Instead of sitting with one’s feelings, understanding another person and how they might interpret your feelings, or starting a dialogue vs. a declarative statement, you skip all that and just drop the bomb.</p>

<p>When we have difficult things to say to loved ones, it can create a kind of internal anxiety. Most people don’t want to hurt others, but holding onto upset hurts us. This tension is uncomfortable and can make one either suppress their emotions entirely or, in other cases, just unleash the beast and let the cards fall where they may. Sadly, the cards typically fall in a way that the other person is left feeling emotionally exposed and unsafe.</p>

<h2>Here are 5 ways to be yourself with warmth:</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Develop an emotional container for your thoughts and feelings:</strong> When upset regarding your loved one runs through your mind, take a pause. Try journaling or sit with your feelings a bit. Instead of sticking with a narrative blaming your partner, try to label what you’re feeling and what the issue brings up for you from your past. If you can sit with your feelings and understand them first, when you do communicate, they may not feel as intrusive and exposing to your partner.</li>
<li><strong>Tolerate the anxiety:</strong> It is normal to have ambivalence or even uncomfortable thoughts about close others in your life. Sure, in the moment, it may feel relieving to just <em>get it out,</em> but in the long term, this bluntness may make others feel emotionally unsafe with you. Some of what you feel will naturally get worked out through conversations over time. See if, when something comes up, you can take a breath and remind yourself that there is time to work on things and that everything doesn’t have to be perfect at all moments.</li>
<li><strong>Attune to your partner:</strong> It is a given that you need to be honest with others in your life. The hard part of relationships is that to be intimate and close, you have to (1) know what you are feeling and (2) share it in a way that prioritizes the relationship. To do this, make sure you have regulated your anxiety (#2) so as not to overwhelm the other person, and lead with empathy. Imagine how the other will feel, what it might bring up for them, and find a way to communicate with this in mind.</li>
<li><strong>Share what helps in understanding each other:</strong> Every thought or feeling you have doesn’t deserve a release. And what feels like an emotional release to you may feel aggressive to others. Be thoughtful about what you bring up, particularly when it could hurt the other person. Ask yourself, “How can I bring this up in a way that not only helps my partner understand me but also helps deepen my understanding of them?”</li>
<li><strong>Learn to be vulnerable:</strong> Research shows that how a difficult conversation starts is predictive of how it will end. A “soft startup<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>” means beginning with your feelings and owning them as opposed to drawing conclusions about your partner. So instead of: “You are not physically fit enough for me to be sexually attracted to you.” Consider: “I care about us feeling strong and healthy for the long term, and I am holding in some anxiety about these feelings. Would you be open to talking about this some?”</li>
</ol>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/radical-honesty-isnt-emotional-intimacy" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/radical-honesty-isnt-emotional-intimacy</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/having-sex-wanting-intimacy/202602/radical-honesty-isnt-emotional-intimacy</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jill P. Weber Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/vecteezy_the-wife-shouted-at-her-husband-after-knowing-that-her_19050448.jpg?itok=RRpyBuR7" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We’re Measuring AI on the Wrong Ruler]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-02/John%20Nosta.png.jpg?itok=MdOqub5o" alt="John Nosta" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">We’re Measuring AI on the Wrong Ruler</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The relentless urge to compare AI and human intelligence may be a mistake.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 24, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">We assume artificial intelligence (AI) and humans share the same scale of intelligence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Human thought carries lived consequence while AI computation does not.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">One ruler may not be able measure two different kinds of thinking.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AIRuler.png.jpg?itok=hbaOUiZU" width="320" height="226" data-insert-type="image" title="ChatGPT /OpenAI, modified by NostaLab" alt="ChatGPT /OpenAI, modified by NostaLab"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: ChatGPT /OpenAI, modified by NostaLab</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Every debate about artificial intelligence (AI) seems to revolve around the same question: Is it smarter than we are?</p>
<p>The subtitles of the questions might change, and the endpoints might be argued, but behind the cacophony of authoritative brilliance is a shared assumption—that intelligence lives on a single line. More of it on one end, less on the other. Humans are somewhere along that spectrum, and machines are moving toward us.</p>

<p>But with all the discussion and debate, we rarely stop to examine the ruler itself. And the moment we ask whether AI is ahead of us, we have already accepted that we are measuring the same thing.</p>
<h2>The Illusion of a Shared Scale</h2>
<p>It’s understandable why we default to this handy ruler. Large language models create the very stuff of our humanity, from words to images. And this output clearly looks like thinking, and it is commonly better than what we humans produce. But let's be careful not to get our hand slapped by that ruler in the process. Here's what we need to consider: When surface outputs converge, we assume structure also does. Thought for thought and concept for concept seem to arrive along a continuum where a "cognitive assessment" can be placed alongside them.</p>

<p>But human cognition is not just output quality; it's consequence-bearing. When you make a decision, you carry the aftermath forward. And when you change your mind, that revision becomes part of your biographical narrative. It unfolds through time and alters who you are.</p>
<p>AI computation does none of this. It generates responses without any biography. It doesn't carry yesterday into tomorrow in any lived sense. Its fluency is extraordinary, but it's reversible, consequence-free, and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202508/the-fragile-mind-of-artificial-intelligence">precariously fragile</a> in its understanding.</p>

<p>To measure both along a single axis of “smart” flattens the difference and misses key opportunities.</p>
<h2>Optimization Is Not Superiority</h2>
<p>So, let's start with some basic assumptions. A calculator outperforms you at arithmetic. A navigation system like Waze outperforms you at route planning. Yet we certainly don't conclude that either possesses deeper intelligence. What we recognize is the optimization for a specific task.</p>

<p>The confusion (and trouble) begins when AI’s optimization extends into domains that are traditionally human, such as writing and creativity. And because that terrain feels familiar, we assume we are witnessing a better version of ourselves. But resemblance is not equivalence.</p>
<p>If we insist on placing human thought and machine computation on the same ruler, we will misread both. The machine appears superhuman because it excels at measurable outputs. The human appears inefficient because we hesitate, revise, doubt, and sometimes contradict ourselves.</p>

<p>Those very “inefficiencies” are inseparable from what makes human cognition distinct.</p>
<h2>A Different Kind of Comparison</h2>
<p>What if the real mistake is not overestimating AI or underestimating ourselves, but misclassifying what we are comparing?</p>
<p>Human thought is embodied and autobiographical. It's shaped by lived experience and future consequence. AI, to the contrary, operates through statistical inference across vast datasets. It identifies patterns with astonishing scale and speed. Both generate language, and both can solve problems. But the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202507/ai-and-the-architecture-of-anti-intelligence">architectures</a> that define the "thinking" are not interchangeable. And when we collapse them into a single metric of intelligence, we distort the conversation. We fuel hype on one side and anxiety on the other.</p>

<p>If we step off that single “axis of smart,” the debate shifts. The question is no longer whether AI is ahead of us. It becomes more precise: What kind of cognitive system is this, and how does it intersect with ours? That shift does not minimize AI’s power; it helps clarify it. It also preserves space for a more honest account of the multifaceted complexity of human thinking—from fear to flow.</p>

<h2>Rethinking the Frame</h2>
<p>The language we use shapes the future we imagine. If we continue to treat intelligence as a single measurable quantity along a single axis, we'll keep asking whether machines are catching up or surpassing us. If instead, we recognize that we may be dealing with different dimensions of cognition, we open a different and more nuanced path. </p>

<p>And to this point, the age of AI may not hinge on who is smarter but on whether we can abandon a model of intelligence that was too narrow to begin with.</p>
<p>The first step is simple. Question the ruler.</p>
<p>Explore these ideas and more in my new book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0GMJ77QSP"><em>The Borrowed Mind: Reclaiming Human Thought in the Age of AI</em></a>. Thought Leader Press; March 16, 2026.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202602/were-measuring-ai-on-the-wrong-ruler" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202602/were-measuring-ai-on-the-wrong-ruler</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-digital-self/202602/were-measuring-ai-on-the-wrong-ruler</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[John Nosta]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AIRuler.png.jpg?itok=WDPVrhVz" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>