<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 20:53:54 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 20:53:54 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are We Thinking About Generational Differences All Wrong?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-01/Andy%20Lopata.png.jpg?itok=YJNe-aLT" alt="Andy Lopata" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Workplace Dynamics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Are We Thinking About Generational Differences All Wrong?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Giving three popular beliefs about generational differences a reality check</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The claim that six generations now share the workplace is misleading.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Gen Z is getting disproportionate attention: Millennials are the current driver in most organisations.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research finds little empirical basis for generational differences in workplace behaviour.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Generational insight is a useful starting point, but people are framed by their generation, not defined by it.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Generations.jpeg.jpg?itok=o_y1qkMw" width="320" height="214" data-insert-type="image" title="Tinashe N peopleimages.com / Adobe Stock" alt="Tinashe N peopleimages.com / Adobe Stock"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Tinashe N peopleimages.com / Adobe Stock</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Talk of generational differences in the workplace has rarely been louder. Recently, Generation Z (born between 1997 and 2012) officially outnumbered Baby Boomers (1946–1964) in the full-time U.S. workforce, a milestone that reflects both a generation coming of age and another moving steadily into retirement. Combined with the rapid pace of technological change, this demographic shift has prompted widespread concern that the unwritten rules of multigenerational working are being rewritten.</p>

<p>Businesses are being pushed, with increasing urgency, to adapt to the distinct demands of their younger employees, while workers at the other end of the age spectrum navigate an environment that can feel markedly different from the one they entered decades ago.</p>
<p>But just how important is the conversation about generational differences in the modern workforce? Is there a genuine and pressing need for understanding and change, or has the debate become overstated?</p>

<p>The evidence suggests both things can be true at once. Shifting demographics and evolving expectations are real, but so is the danger of over-stereotyping entire cohorts of people based on their birth year. A more nuanced approach is likely to serve organisations and the individuals within them considerably better.</p>

<p>A good place to start is by examining three widely held 'truths' about the modern workforce that may well actually be myths.</p>
<p><strong>Myth 1: There are 5+ generations in the workplace.</strong></p>
<p>In a 2024 article in <em>Harvard Business Review,</em> Nicholas Pearce, a Northwestern University Kellogg School of Management professor, observed that, for the first time in history, many workplaces now span six generations: from the octogenarians of the Silent Generation to the teenagers of the emerging Generation Alpha, eager to pursue their first summer jobs and high school internships. In between are Baby Boomers, Generation X, Millennials, and Gen Z.</p>

<p>However, not everyone finds this framing convincing. Alastair Greener, author of <a href="https://generationallyspeaking.co.uk/author/"><em>Generationally Speaking</em></a>, argues that Pearce's six-generation claim is misleading. Greener told me that "only four or maybe three and a half generations are actually present in the workplace in any significant numbers," adding that "You won't now find many octogenarians working, while most Boomers, who technically are part of the four who are in the workplace, have gone, because today the youngest Boomer is 62."</p>

<p>The data appears to support this more cautious view. That Gen Z is overtaking Baby Boomers in the workforce, far from signalling a crowded six-generation workplace, underlines how rapidly the generational composition is narrowing.</p>
<p>With Generation Alpha not yet represented in workforce statistics in any meaningful way, and Boomer numbers in ongoing decline, the evidence points to three or four generations as the practical reality, not six.</p>

<p><strong>Myth 2: Generation Z is the primary focus.</strong></p>
<p>With a new generation in the workplace whose members have grown up with technology at their fingertips, in a connected global society, it makes sense that companies want to understand what makes them different and how that will impact their productivity and loyalty.</p>

<p>But has their importance been over-amplified, particularly in the short-term? While Gen Z is making the most noise, Greener argues, millennials are the drivers in current organisations. “Implementation, in terms of the day-to-day running of the business, will probably predominantly be carried out by millennials."</p>

<p>By contrast, he says, "the youngest Gen Zs are 15 years old in 2026. So, they've got a long way to go. If they go to university, that's a long time before they get into the workplace. But it's not like there’s a sudden cliff where it changes dramatically. It's more of a blurred evolution. Millennials are the dominant generation now, not Gen Z."</p>



  


<p><strong>Myth 3: Generational traits can be easily identified.</strong></p>
<p>While it can be helpful to use generational traits to recognise shifts in workforce behaviour and expectations, it can also be deceptive. Generational traits lie on an underlying assumption that everyone within the same generation acts in the same way. And people aren’t like that.</p>

<p>A range of factors combine to influence behaviour, from family upbringing and cultural norms to personality style and socioeconomic status. Greener sees generation as just another factor. "I use the phrase, we're<em> framed by</em> our generation, not defined by it. And the reason I say that is because patterns are useful. And there are patterns.</p>

<p>“A generation will communicate in a certain way, it's likely to behave in a certain way. But that's not everybody. People need to look beyond the stereotype and stop putting people in pigeonholes." Greener<a href="https://generationallyspeaking.co.uk/research/"> survey</a>ed more than 4,000 people across six generations for <em>Generationally Speaking,</em> and the results indicated that we communicate according to generational stereotypes only 65% of the time.</p>

<p>His finding is supported by peer-reviewed research. A 2024 meta-analysis published in the <em>Journal of Organizational Behavior</em> found few systematic, meaningful differences among generations across a range of workplace outcomes, concluding that generational characterisations persist largely in spite of the evidence, not because of it.</p>

<p>Greener emphasises that people are "framed by" their generation, meaning it provides a general context, but they are not "defined by" it; there is significant diversity within each generation. The key is to use generational insights as a starting point but then dive deeper to understand the unique individual.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>The increase in focus on generational difference has happened for a reason. Organisations are concerned about challenges in recruitment and retention and are seeking to understand how they can adapt their practices to attract and keep the best new talent. An increase in focus need not, however, lead to an obsession on one generation at the expense of others, or to overgeneralising how we see the people who work for us.</p>

<p>The generational conversation needs more nuance. It also nees to avoid eye-catching headlines based on peripheral data and to focus on a personalised approach to working with colleagues and staff. Generational influence is just one of the factors we consider. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/connected-leadership/202602/are-we-thinking-about-generational-differences-all-wrong" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/connected-leadership/202602/are-we-thinking-about-generational-differences-all-wrong</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/connected-leadership/202602/are-we-thinking-about-generational-differences-all-wrong</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Andy Lopata]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Generations.jpeg.jpg?itok=Xfw7mf-I" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Does Therapy Keep Reinventing Itself?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/320x400-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=DoR2rV5d" alt="Mark Shelvock, RP, MACP, MA" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Does Therapy Keep Reinventing Itself?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Therapy is not just science. It’s culture.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychotherapy is partly science, but deeply cultural.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many “new” therapies reinterpret older psychological ideas.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Therapy serves a broader social function beyond symptom reduction.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Over the past century, psychotherapy has produced what looks like an endless parade of theories. The field has moved from Freud’s couch to behavior modification, cognitive therapy, humanistic psychology, mindfulness, somatic healing, egoic states/parts-based therapies, and today’s language of trauma and nervous-system regulation.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/giammarco-boscaro-zeH-ljawHtg-unsplash.jpg?itok=_4OQBhLN" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Giammarco Boscaro on Unsplash" alt="Photo by Giammarco Boscaro on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Giammarco Boscaro on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Each new wave arrives with confidence, often promising to correct the limitations of the one before it. Yet, something curious always happens: old ideas never fully disappear.</p>
<p>Mindfulness echoes ancient contemplative traditions, while somatic therapies resemble older pre-modern healing systems that never separated mind from body. Attachment theory, meanwhile, revives early psychoanalytic insights about relationships and emotional bonds, now widely recognized as central to therapeutic change regardless of the modality. </p>

<p>Psychologist Jonathan Shedler has argued that psychotherapy often suffers from a kind of collective amnesia, repeatedly “calling a rose by another name”. Cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) offers a revealing example. Rather than emerging entirely separate from earlier traditions, CBT translated many enduring psychological insights into the language of cognition, measurement, and “evidence-based” science, forms of explanation that carried cultural authority in the late twentieth century.</p>

<p>Ironically,<a href="https://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/amp-65-2-98.pdf"> Shedler’s research</a> empirically demonstrates that CBT often works best when therapists engage relationally, flexibly, and emotionally, echoing principles long emphasized in psychodynamic work. What appears, at first glance, to be a "revolution" may instead be a translation: familiar ideas returning in a vocabulary that a scientifically oriented culture could accept.</p>

<h2>Therapy as a Meaning-Making Institution</h2>
<p>Psychotherapy is partly scientific, but it also functions as a cultural institution of meaning-making. Therapy helps modern people grapple with questions that human societies have always faced:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why do I suffer?</li>
<li>Who am I?</li>
<li>What makes a life good, happy, and meaningful?</li>
<li>How should I relate to others and to myself?</li>
<li>What is happening inside me, and in the world around me?</li>
</ul>

<p>Historically, religion, philosophy, and communal traditions helped answer these questions. In many modern Western societies, however, these shared frameworks have weakened or diversified. Increasingly, psychotherapy has become one of the primary places where individuals bring existential dilemmas once addressed elsewhere.</p>

<p>Therapy, in this sense, does more than treat symptoms; it translates human suffering into the psychological language a culture finds credible at a particular moment in history.</p>
<h2>Each Generation Produces the Therapy It Needs</h2>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/gioia-m-_Hb6BGnnvUQ-unsplash.jpg?itok=DQg11Sqp" width="320" height="441" data-insert-type="image" title="Photo by Gioia M. on Unsplash" alt="Photo by Gioia M. on Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Photo by Gioia M. on Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Across recent history, shifts in psychotherapy closely track broader social transformations. Freud emerged during an era shaped by Victorian morality, rigid social roles, and strong expectations of repression and duty. His focus on unconscious desire and internal conflict reflected a culture struggling with excessive constraint and hidden psychological tensions.</p>


<p>Mid-20th-century behaviorism arose during a period fascinated by engineering, efficiency, control, and an intense cultural projection of scientific mastery. In a world shaped by industrialization, wartime mobilization, and technological optimism, psychology increasingly framed humans as systems that could be measured, conditioned, and optimized.</p>

<p>Not surprisingly, this mechanistic view of reality provoked substantial resistance. Humanistic, existential, and transpersonal psychologies emerged in the postwar decades alongside civil rights movements, countercultural experimentation, liberation psychologies, and growing interest in authenticity, freedom, and human consciousness. These approaches attempted to restore subjectivity, creativity, and spirit to psychological life.</p>



  


<p>Today’s therapeutic landscape reflects a different emotional climate. Economic instability, digital saturation, burnout, identity fragmentation, and chronic uncertainty have made overwhelm a defining psychological experience of modern life. It is therefore unsurprising that trauma, safety, attachment, and nervous-system regulation have become dominant psychological languages.</p>

<p>Contemporary therapy emphasizes grounding, connection, and embodied awareness in response to a widespread loss of stability. So, therapies in this sense often mirror the emotional problems each era struggles to name.</p>
<h2>Why Old Therapies Keep Returning</h2>
<p>Human problems do not change as quickly as therapeutic fashions do. Across generations, people continue to struggle with connection, loss, belonging, identity, power, mortality, meaning, and so forth. So, what changes is not the human psyche itself, but the metaphors through which we understand it: Freud spoke in drives and repression; cognitive therapies spoke in thoughts and beliefs; and now today, many people speak in terms of nervous systems or regulation.</p>

<p>Psychotherapy therefore develops less like a linear scientific revolution and more like a mythology adapting to new cultural symbols. Each generation reinterprets enduring human dilemmas using concepts that feel credible within its historical moment. Therapy also tends to expand during periods of social transition; times when traditional institutions lose authority, communities’ fragment, or shared meaning systems become unstable. When inherited frameworks no longer provide reliable answers, individuals turn inward.</p>

<p>Psychotherapy becomes a space for confession, identity formation, moral reflection, and ritualized meaning-making. While therapy is not intended to replace religion, it often performs overlapping psychological functions, responding to what Carl Jung described as the “religious function” of the psyche: the human need to orient toward personal orientation, meaning, growth, and development. </p>

<p>Seen this way, psychotherapy does more than heal individuals. It helps stabilize societies by providing narratives through which people can understand suffering during uncertain and wild times.</p>
<h2>What Therapy’s Evolution Reveals</h2>
<p>Perhaps the real question is not which therapy will finally solve human suffering and of all life’s problems. Instead, the therapies we co-create may tell us as much about our culture as they do about the human mind. Our current therapeutic language reveals the kind of world we are trying to survive in; not necessarily a final or objective psychological truth.</p>

<p>From a wider lens, psychotherapy looks less like a steady march toward ultimate knowledge and more like an ongoing conversation between culture and psyche, one that must be translated as society changes. It is my belief that this repetition is not a failure of psychology, but a sign of something deeply human: every generation must rediscover, in its own language, how to make meaning out of suffering.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/navigating-the-serpentine-path/202602/why-does-therapy-keep-reinventing-itself" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/navigating-the-serpentine-path/202602/why-does-therapy-keep-reinventing-itself</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/navigating-the-serpentine-path/202602/why-does-therapy-keep-reinventing-itself</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Shelvock, RP, MACP, MA]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/giammarco-boscaro-zeH-ljawHtg-unsplash.jpg?itok=Y2HWGg9-" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Hidden Guilt and Shame of Childhood Emotional Neglect]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/jonice_webb.png.jpg?itok=Ks8xqhUh" alt="Jonice Webb Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Guilt</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Hidden Guilt and Shame of Childhood Emotional Neglect</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What happens when your feelings were never truly seen.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Childhood emotional neglect can quietly create deep guilt and shame about having feelings.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Suppressing emotions often begins as a child’s solution to feeling like a burden.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Feeling that something is wrong with you may come from emotional absence, not personal failure.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Learning to accept your feelings can begin to loosen long-held guilt and shame.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/AdobeStock_1770903001.jpeg.jpg?itok=ONuCO5Ue" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="carballo / Stock Adobe" alt="carballo / Stock Adobe"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: carballo / Stock Adobe</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Childhood emotional neglect happens when your parents fail to respond enough to your emotions as they raise you.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Adults who were emotionally neglected in childhood can be quite perfectionistic and hard on themselves. But for many, it does not stop there.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Why? Because the messages of childhood emotional neglect run deep. They go to the heart of the child and stay there for a lifetime. They not only damage your ability to understand and trust your own feelings, but they also damage your ability to understand and trust yourself.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The messages of childhood emotional neglect are like invisible infusions of guilt and shame that happen every day in the life of the child.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">The First Guilt/Shame Message of Childhood Emotional Neglect</h2>
<p><strong>No one wants to see your feelings.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">When, because of emotional neglect, children receive the message from their parents that their feelings are a burden, excessive, or simply wrong, they take a highly effective, adaptive action. They naturally push their emotions down, under the surface, so that they will trouble no one. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Believe it or not, this brilliant strategy usually works quite well. As a child, you become un-sad, un-angry, un-needy, and overall unemotional so that your parents are less bothered or burdened by you. Life becomes easier in the family, but life inside you becomes deeply lonely. </p>
<h2 dir="ltr">The Second Guilt/Shame Message of Childhood Emotional Neglect: </h2>

<p><strong>Your feelings are shameful.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">As a child of emotional neglect, you are set up to feel, on some deep level, for your entire life, that you are a burden, excessive, or somehow wrong. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Because childhood emotional neglect affects your relationship with your own feelings, it sets you up to feel guilty and ashamed for the very personal, inescapable human experience of having feelings. </p>

<p dir="ltr">It feels wrong to feel your feelings and wrong to let others see your feelings. And it feels right to hide your feelings. You may even try not to have feelings at all. Yet your feelings are the most deeply personal, biological expression of your true self. They will not be denied.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Trying to deny your feelings is like the classic little Dutch boy trying to block the hole in the dike with his finger. It may feel like it works temporarily, but those feelings just keep coming, growing, and pressurizing, like the water behind the dike. Being unable to control them and stop them altogether makes you feel weak and incompetent. And ashamed.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">The Third Guilt/Shame Message of Childhood Emotional Neglect</h2>
<p><strong>There is something wrong with you.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Since many emotionally neglected adults were not actively mistreated in childhood, they may remember their childhoods as fairly happy and carefree. When they look back on their childhoods to find an explanation for their issues and struggles in their adult lives, they can’t pinpoint any incidents or factors to help them make sense of their current problems. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Between a “happy childhood” and inexplicable emotions, they are left with the assumption that some deep part of themselves is seriously amiss. “It’s my own fault. Something is wrong with me,” is a natural conclusion.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">Signs and Signals of CEN-Induced Guilt and Shame </h2>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">You sometimes feel emotionally numb</li>
<li dir="ltr">You have a deep sense that something is wrong with you</li>
<li dir="ltr">You feel that you are intrinsically different from other people</li>
<li dir="ltr">You tend to push down feelings or avoid them</li>
<li dir="ltr">You try to hide your feelings so others won’t see them</li>
<li dir="ltr">You tend to feel inferior to others</li>
<li dir="ltr">You believe you have no excuse for not being happier in your life</li>
</ul>


<h2 dir="ltr">The Antidote For Your Guilt &amp; Shame</h2>
<p dir="ltr">I hope that, as you read the guilt/shame messages above, you realized one glaring fact about them: They are all false!</p>
<p dir="ltr">Now, please read the three vital and true remedies below. If you absorb them, own them, and follow them, they will change how you feel about yourself and your life.</p>

<ol>
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Feelings are not subject to the laws of right and wrong. </strong></li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">You cannot choose your feelings because they’re literally wired into your biology. It is essential to accept what you feel because that must be done before you can manage what you feel.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li dir="ltr"><strong>Your feelings are a sign of your health and strength. </strong></li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">Your emotions are the opposite of a sign of weakness. When others see what you feel, they instantly connect with you. And when others know your feelings, they have an opportunity to respond to your true self. That is powerful.</p>



  


<ol start="3">
<li dir="ltr"><strong>There is nothing wrong with you. </strong></li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr">The only thing wrong with you is the message of CEN that your child self internalized. And you share those same messages with millions of other people. You are an intact, healthy person who can change your beliefs, learn to manage your emotions, let go of your guilt and shame, and heal.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The feelings of guilt and shame you carry did not come from who you are. They came from what was missing. And once you begin to see that, it becomes harder to keep treating yourself as the problem.</p>
<p dir="ltr">You may start to notice your feelings instead of pushing them away. You may pause before judging yourself. You may wonder, for the first time, whether nothing was ever wrong with you at all.</p>

<p dir="ltr">That wondering matters. It changes things.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This post also appears on <a href="https://drjonicewebb.com/the-emotional-legacy-of-childhood-emotional-neglect-guilt-and-shame/">emotionalneglect.com</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">© Jonice Webb, Ph.D.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/childhood-emotional-neglect/202602/the-hidden-guilt-and-shame-of-childhood-emotional-neglect" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/childhood-emotional-neglect/202602/the-hidden-guilt-and-shame-of-childhood-emotional-neglect</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/childhood-emotional-neglect/202602/the-hidden-guilt-and-shame-of-childhood-emotional-neglect</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonice Webb Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/AdobeStock_1770903001.jpeg.jpg?itok=4wjhwgET" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>