<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 18:05:15 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 18:05:15 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sorting Through a Life, One Box at a Time]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/jessica_fein.png.jpg?itok=rw6tAHf0" alt="Jessica Fein" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Grief</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Sorting Through a Life, One Box at a Time</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: How to deal with the stuff your loved ones left behind.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sorting through your person's belongings can be emotionally overwhelming, but there are ways to simplify.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The only roadmap you need to follow is the one that feels right to you.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">As with most things in grief, enlisting help makes is a bit more bearable.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">The other day, my niece asked if she could see something I have in my basement. A simple question, yet I found myself stuttering through flimsy excuses to avoid revealing what’s happening in the lowest level of my home. It’s not that there’s anything nefarious down there; it’s that over the years I’ve accumulated three unfinished-basement rooms full of other people’s belongings, rendering the cellar essentially unnavigable. </p>

<p dir="ltr">The first time I was tasked with sorting through someone’s things, I was in my 20s. Days after my 90-something grandmother died in her sleep, my mother and I boxed up the contents of her small apartment. We were more task-oriented than emotionally vulnerable, since the building management had set a deadline, and we moved almost everything to storage in my mother’s home.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The last time I had this responsibility was three years ago, after my 17-year-old daughter, Dalia, died. This time, every item, from mismatched socks to nail polish, held meaning. Where we bought this sweatshirt or that hat; how we snuggled under the pile of fluffy throw blankets, every stuffed animal’s complex backstory. I could take as much time as I wanted, and I did. At least half of Dalia’s things remain exactly where they were the morning she died.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In between my grandmother’s death and my daughter’s, I lost both of my parents and my two sisters. Each time, I was the one left to decide what to keep, donate, toss, or store. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Along the way, I learned a few things about how to approach—and just as important, how not to approach—the assignment. The good news is that, with a little forethought and understanding, the task can become a privilege and a meaningful way to honor your person rather than simply another thing to cross off the to-do list. But that doesn’t mean it will be easy, so keep the following in mind.</p>

<h2>Don’t go it alone.</h2>
<p dir="ltr">You know all the people who say, “Let me know if there’s anything I can do”? Here’s something. Ask someone you trust to help you go through the stuff. Enlist others to buy boxes, make dump runs, or research donation sites. Remember, people want to be useful. Giving them something to do helps you both.</p>

<h2>Remember that your person’s memories don’t have to be yours.</h2>
<p dir="ltr">My oldest sister had dozens of photo albums that I couldn’t bear to look through or throw out after she died. I decided to box them all up and bring them to my house to be dealt with “another time.” That time came two full years later, when a friend of mine was helping me organize my home office. “What are these?” She asked, stumbling over the boxes in the back corner of my closet. I’d forgotten about the albums altogether. What I ultimately found were pictures of teenagers I didn’t know on a road trip and college friends I couldn’t identify at football games and a whole bunch of other memories that didn’t belong to me. You’re not betraying your person by throwing out their memorabilia, just like you’re not honoring your person by keeping their items in a box in a closet.</p>

<h2>But if you want to hold onto certain items, “just because,” go for it.</h2>
<p dir="ltr">There’s no right or wrong about what you decide to keep and what you choose to toss. I’ve kept binders of medical notes about my daughter. Will I ever read them? Probably not. But they’re an important snapshot of a chapter of our lives that I’m not ready to discard.</p>


<h2>There’s no formula you have to follow. </h2>
<p dir="ltr">You can be precious about keeping everything (provided you have space for it), or you can hire someone to haul it all away. When I started going through my mother’s belongings, I spent hours trying on her shoes, her dresses, her coats. By the end of the second week, I didn’t have any more energy or physical space to devote to the cause. I went from sentimental to pragmatic, shifting my strategy to match my mood. </p>

<h2>Consider sharing meaningful items.</h2>
<p dir="ltr">No matter how much you love your mother’s scarves or your father’s ties, there are likely only so many you want to keep. But the very things that remind you of your person will be meaningful to other people, too. My father was a classical music aficionado, with dozens of recordings of <em>Verdi’s Requiem</em>. I planned to give one to several of the important people in his life. The truth is, those recordings are all in a box in my basement more than 10 years after my father’s death, but writing this is inspiring me to finally distribute them.</p>



  


<h2>Which brings me to my final caution: Beware of boxing things to be dealt with later, lest your basement begin to resemble a museum.</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Chances are you’ll reach a saturation point and start packing things up “for another day.” Remember those boxes from my grandmother’s apartment? They’re still unopened, nearly three decades after she died, nestled beside boxes of belongings from other people I’ve loved and lost, stacked on shelves that can only be reached if I climb over inherited furniture. Timing and emotional saturation may make packing things away inevitable. But do yourself a favor and put dates in the calendar to revisit what you’ve stored, perhaps as a way to mark death days or birthdays in years to come.</p>

<p dir="ltr">It’s an honor to be entrusted with what remains of someone’s life. The sweater she wore, the music he listened to, the dishes they used for special occasions can all help us feel close to them. But they can’t do that from a box in the basement. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/grace-in-grief/202602/sorting-through-a-life-one-box-at-a-time" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/grace-in-grief/202602/sorting-through-a-life-one-box-at-a-time</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/grace-in-grief/202602/sorting-through-a-life-one-box-at-a-time</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jessica Fein]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-ketut-subiyanto-4246108.jpg?h=349c2a66&amp;itok=qnS5ShUZ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Moral Energy Problem]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/erik_raschke.png.jpg?itok=wQDs-O3S" alt="Erik Raschke" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Autism</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Moral Energy Problem</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Two Dutch researchers explain why parents of disabled children stop fighting.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Professionals routinely judge parents while claiming to collaborate with them.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A moral philosopher found that seeing a disabled person as fully human requires sustained "moral energy."</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The solution is structural: ecosystems that keep families visible, not individual willpower.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>A few years ago, a professional told me I was in denial about my autistic son's abilities. She had assessed him twice. She had her own report of things he "couldn't" do. I had a decade of evidence that he could do more than her report said. </p>
<p>What I didn't understand then is that this type of communication between professionals and parents is also a structural problem, one that two Dutch researchers I interviewed for my upcoming book, <em>What Will You Do When I'm Gone</em>, have spent years trying to name.</p>

<h2>Little Space for the Parent's Voice</h2>
<p>Edith Raap, a researcher at University of Applied Sciences in Utrecht who studies what she calls <em>levend verlies</em> or living loss, studies the chronic grief that parents of disabled children carry, not because their child has died, but because the life they imagined turned out radically different. Raap's research began with a simple observation: There seems to be little space in the Dutch care system for the parent's voice. Professionals are trained to look at the child, while the parents are placed more as an observer than an integral part of the conversation.</p>

<p>The judgment, Raap argues, is in the language itself. Professionals talk about "involving parents" as if parents aren't already involved, as if they need an invitation to care about their own child. Parents should involve professionals, she says, since parents are the ones navigating the system, filling out the paperwork, proving every year that their child is still disabled. </p>

<p>In her interviews with parents, Raap found something that professionals rarely hear: a quiet hopelessness. "I sometimes don't want my child," parents told her, and while at first she found this shocking, she learned that this statement came not out of a lack of love, but because the weight of their caregiving and the sidelining by professionals is slowly crushing them. When a parent confesses their despair to another parent, the response is recognition. When a parent says it to a professional, the response is often risk assessment, a note in a file, and, often, reporting to another institution. </p>

<h2>Draining of Moral Energy</h2>
<p>Simon van der Weele, a moral philosopher at the University of Humanistic Studies in Utrecht, comes at the same problem from the institutional side. He has spent years doing ethnographic fieldwork inside Dutch group homes for people with severe intellectual disabilities.</p>
<p>When I interviewed van der Weele, he often used the term "moral energy" or the capacity to see another person as fully human. There is a gradual decay of empathy among professionals who work long hours, get little recognition, but must use a range of creative energies to constantly connect with the severely disabled. He told me he noticed it in himself during fieldwork, the everyday repetition of disregard creating what he called a "moral atmosphere." You walk in alert, ready to work and care for those with profound differences, but after a few weeks, the energy begins to drain.</p>

<p>For families, the erosion is slower. Van der Weele described parents who once told richly detailed stories about what their child's gestures meant, who searched for personality in small anecdotes, gradually going quiet. When the professionals did not see what the parents saw, when they missed out on the slight gestures, or showed outright skepticism, the friction of understanding warmed. With every conflict, with every professional's empirically backed dismissal of a parent's evaluation, the moral imagination, so imperative in keeping someone visible as a full person, began to atrophy.</p>

<p>The places where families stayed engaged, van der Weele found, shared specific qualities. For example, the staff had been there for 19 or 20 years, collaborating with parents instead of dismissing them, drawing each other into shared narratives about residents. The places where it broke down had constant turnover. "When there's a different person working with your child every two years," van der Weele said, "you start from zero every time."</p>


<p>Raap and van der Weele are describing two ends of the same failure. Raap shows how the system silences parents from the start—through judgment embedded in language, through professional authority that overrides parental knowledge. Van der Weele shows what happens decades later, when that silence has calcified into numbness, and the family has stopped imagining a future for their child.</p>

<p>My son's Dutch school predicted he was only capable of "non-wage-earning day activities." He now holds a paid job in New Jersey. But that outcome required a decade of refusing to accept the professional consensus—of maintaining moral energy when every institution around me was draining it. Not every parent has the resources or energy for that fight. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/what-will-you-do-when-im-gone/202602/the-moral-energy-problem" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/what-will-you-do-when-im-gone/202602/the-moral-energy-problem</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/what-will-you-do-when-im-gone/202602/the-moral-energy-problem</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Erik Raschke]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-kseniachernaya-4740574.jpg?itok=JCaJgPCI" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Survivors Can Cope When Epstein News Reopens Trauma]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/Adrienne%20%281%29.png.jpg?itok=qP7mIEF6" alt="Adrian Fletcher Psy.D., M.A." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sexual Abuse</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Survivors Can Cope When Epstein News Reopens Trauma</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Understanding trauma responses and choosing self-care during triggering news.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Limiting exposure to the news is a healthy boundary.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Grounding and emotional release can help calm trauma activation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Survivors do not owe anyone their story or advocacy.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Recently, a friend reached out and said, “I’ve been thinking about you. With all the awfulness coming out, I hope you’re taking care of yourself.”</p>
<p>Her check-in stayed with me. It’s what inspired me to write this for anyone quietly struggling as new information about the Epstein files continues to surface.</p>

<p>Each time these stories reappear, I feel it in my body before my mind can make sense of it. My breathing slows. My chest tightens. My stomach drops. My nervous system recognizes something long before words arrive. For survivors of childhood sexual abuse, trafficking, exploitation, or organized abuse, these headlines don’t land as “news.” They land as recognition.</p>

<p>For those living with dissociative identity disorder (DID), this activation may show up even more intensely through emotional flooding, shutdown, dissociation, body memories, or increased internal communication or conflict. Parts of the system may react differently or hold different pieces of the impact.</p>

<p>I write this not only as a psychologist who has spent decades working with trauma but as someone who lives with DID myself. I know what it’s like to watch powerful people remain protected while survivors carry the weight. I know the anger, grief, exhaustion, and familiar ache that comes from realizing again and again that justice is not guaranteed.</p>

<p>If the Epstein files have stirred something in you or within your DID system, there is nothing wrong with you. Your reaction makes sense. Below are practical ways to care for yourself when trauma is activated, whether you live with DID or identify as a survivor without a dissociative diagnosis.</p>
<h2>What You Can Do When You Feel Triggered</h2>

<p><strong>1. Name what’s happening. </strong>You are not “too sensitive.” You are not being dramatic. Your body and possibly parts of you are responding to reminders of past trauma. You might say:</p>
<blockquote><p><em>This is a trauma response.</em></p>
<p><em>A part of me is reacting, and that makes sense.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Naming what’s happening reduces shame and helps bring awareness rather than fear.</p>

<p><strong>2. Limit news exposure when needed. </strong>You do not have to read every article or watch every update. You are allowed to mute, unfollow, or step away, especially if different parts of you are becoming overwhelmed or activated. Ask yourself (or your system):</p>
<blockquote><p>Is this helping right now? Or is it increasing distress?</p>
</blockquote>


<p>Protecting your nervous system or your parts is not avoidance. It’s self/selves care.</p>
<p><strong>3. Expect different emotional responses. </strong>You may notice:</p>
<ul>
<li>Anger, sadness, or fear</li>
<li>Numbness or shutdown</li>
<li>Body sensations without clear emotion</li>
<li>Internal conflict or shifts between parts</li>
</ul>
<p>All of this would be considered a normal reaction to psychological trauma and reactivation.<br>Instead of ignoring your emotions, try:</p>

<ul>
<li>Gentle movement</li>
<li>Writing, drawing, or art</li>
<li>Letting your emotions come without judgment</li>
<li>Checking in internally with parts: <em>“What do we need right now?”</em></li>
</ul>
<p>As one of my former therapists used to say, “You have to feel it to heal it.” Feelings need space and movement, and a former mentor of mine modeled using art as a way to expressively release pain and anger, particularly the use of collage art.</p>



  


<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Art.jpeg.jpg?itok=TWqExRB7" width="320" height="427" data-insert-type="image" alt="Experiential Collage Art Inspired by Larry Rhul" title="Adrian Fletcher made at the DID Healing Together Conf. 2024"></div>
<div class="caption">Experiential Collage Art Inspired by Larry Rhul</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Adrian Fletcher made at the DID Healing Together Conf. 2024</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>4. Gently ground in the present. </strong>When trauma is activated, it can feel as if the past is happening all over again. Grounding can help orient the body and your parts to the here and now: </p>
<ul>
<li>Name five things you can see.</li>
<li>Feel your feet on the floor.</li>
<li>Hold something cold or warm.</li>
<li>Practice slow, steady breathing.</li>
<li>Remind yourself: <em>“We are safe right now”</em> (if this is true for you).</li>
</ul>

<p>You don’t need to regulate yourself instantly. Even small moments of grounding can help reduce overwhelm.</p>
<p><strong>5. Don’t turn anger against yourself or your parts. </strong>It makes sense to feel furious when people in power are not held accountable. Anger does not make you bad, broken, or dangerous. It is what we choose to do with our feelings of anger that makes all the difference. Do your best to not take them out on yourselves or others. What causes harm is when anger turns inward:</p>

<blockquote><p><em>I should be over this.</em></p>
<p><em>Why am I still affected?</em></p>
<p><em>Something must be wrong with me or my system.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nothing is wrong with you. Your nervous system and your parts developed to survive. They are doing what they learned to do.</p>
<p><strong>6. You do not owe anyone your story. </strong>You do not have to educate others, defend survivors, share your experiences, or speak publicly. This applies to every survivor and every system. Advocacy can be meaningful, but only if it’s chosen by you and feels safe for you. You are allowed to rest. As Brene Brown often reminds us, we share our stories with those who have earned the right to hear them.</p>

<p><strong>7. Reach out for support. </strong>If you can, consider:</p>
<ul>
<li>Texting a trusted person to say you’re having a hard day</li>
<li>Scheduling a therapy/coaching/preferred modality of healing session</li>
<li>Letting someone sit with you</li>
<li>Allowing support without explanation</li>
</ul>
<p>Many survivors and many DID systems are struggling quietly right now. You are not alone.</p>

<p>Stories in the news like this can reopen grief, anger, and old wounds, and they can also remind us of something important: We survived.</p>
<p>You are here. You have awareness, choice, and tools you may not have had before. Even when things feel chaotic or heavy, healing is still unfolding part by part, moment by moment.</p>

<p>Be gentle with yourself and your DID system.</p>
<p>Protect your heart, but try not to close it.</p>
<p>Take breaks when you need them; I cannot emphasize this one enough.</p>
<p>As survivors and advocates have shared in other contexts, Elizabeth Smart has said, “I see myself as a survivor, I made it out the other side,” and Simone Biles has shown that prioritizing mental health is an act of strength. Caring for yourself right now, whether individually or as a system, is not selfish; it is resilience.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/keeping-it-real-and-resilient/202602/how-survivors-can-cope-when-epstein-news-reopens-trauma" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/keeping-it-real-and-resilient/202602/how-survivors-can-cope-when-epstein-news-reopens-trauma</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/keeping-it-real-and-resilient/202602/how-survivors-can-cope-when-epstein-news-reopens-trauma</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Adrian Fletcher Psy.D., M.A.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Art.jpeg.jpg?itok=VeDzHgXD" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Dangerous Myth of “Find Your Why”]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-03/James%20M%20Kerr_0.png.jpg?itok=g6_R0Hl-" alt="James M. Kerr" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Leadership</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Dangerous Myth of “Find Your Why”</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: Instead of chasing purpose, make yourself indispensable.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The pursuit of our "why" has led many to feel unsatisfied, stressed out, and exhausted by their job.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">An entire cottage industry has been built around promoting the importance of finding one's "why".</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">In reality, the greatest meaning people derive from their jobs comes as a byproduct of doing their best work.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Purpose has become one of the most celebrated ideas in modern leadership. </p>
<p>Clearly, finding purpose in our actions is a powerful psychological concept. It can anchor resilience, guide decision-making, and inspire us to go the extra mile when we would rather take a break. But I fear that we have inadvertently taken it way too far.</p>

<p>Advocates, like Simon Sinek, David Mead, and Peter Docker<a href="#_edn1">[i]</a> suggest we must achieve spiritual self-actualization through our work, or we are complete failures.</p>
<p>In reality, the pursuit of this mystical state of being has led many to feel unsatisfied, stressed-out, and generally exhausted by unfulfilled work lives.</p>

<p>I’m a loser if I’m not working my “<em>why"?</em></p>
<p>I should risk harm to my mental health by incessantly worrying about whether I’m sufficiently enthralled by my job?</p>
<p>The idea that we should all be in the throes of scratching some mystical inner-calling itch feels a bit contrived to me.</p>
<p>Here's what my contrarian point of view is based on.</p>

<p><strong>1. I have bills to pay.</strong> Deep down inside, we all know “why” we work. It’s not the spiritual enlightenment. It’s providing for myself and my family, building financial independence, and ensuring the security of my loved ones.</p>
<p><strong>2. Philosophy doesn’t enhance my buying power.</strong> I know of no employers that reward employees for having a deeply moving “why”—especially if those same employees miss their targets. Financial rewards come from delivering results that matter to the firm, and buying power comes from financial rewards, not philosophy.</p>

<p><strong>3. It’s a huge distraction:</strong> The time people spend chasing their “why” is time <em>not</em> spent developing the skills that they need to get ahead. Let’s flip the script here and make work about work and not about transcendence.</p>
<p><strong>4. It can incite an existential crisis:</strong> Feeling like a failure is depressing. Many of the leadership professionals that I’ve coached over the years have spiraled when they came to realize that their job is really just a job and not some mythic quest.</p>

<p><strong>5. Becoming indispensable fixes most ills.</strong> One’s relevance becomes more meaningful the more they contribute. We can all contribute more at work by dedicating ourselves to becoming really good at what we do. The better we get at our job, the higher the likelihood that we become recognized as valuable. A sense of purpose tends to follow when we feel valued. </p>

<p>This is probably a good point to emphasize:</p>
<p><em>The meaning that we derive from our jobs often manifests as a byproduct of doing great work—it’s not the other way around.</em></p>
<p>If you’re pushing back on the <em>Find Your Why</em> movement, like I am, chances are great that you’re tired of fluffy leadership advice.</p>
<p>So, let me leave you with something much more concrete: Find that little thing within your job that others would profoundly miss if you were not there to do it.</p>

<p>Aim to deliver that every day, and your work will have purpose. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/indispensable-thinking/202602/the-dangerous-myth-of-find-your-why" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/indispensable-thinking/202602/the-dangerous-myth-of-find-your-why</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/indispensable-thinking/202602/the-dangerous-myth-of-find-your-why</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[James M. Kerr]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-mikhail-nilov-7584714.jpg?itok=RLdXtkOW" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Signs You're Experiencing 'Emotional Numbing']]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/photoofmarktravers.png.jpg?itok=4rcV_Py2" alt="Mark Travers Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Emotions</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Signs You're Experiencing 'Emotional Numbing'</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Three ways confusing numbness with safety leads to real psychological costs.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotional safety is a state in which you feel secure expressing your whole range of feelings.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Emotional numbness is a reduced capacity to feel emotions, often as a coping response.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Confusing emotional safety and emotional numbness can leave us stuck in patterns that feel safe but aren’t.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/a-g-_7llTamuXV8-unsplash.jpg?itok=p2jO279x" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title=" A. G. / Unsplash" alt=" A. G. / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: A. G. / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>In pop psychology, as well as everyday conversation, people often toss around phrases like “I just want to feel safe” or “Being numb helps me cope.” But as research and clinical observation show, emotional safety and emotional numbness are distinct psychological states, and confusing the two can slow your growth, isolate you from support, and leave you stuck in patterns that feel safe but aren’t.</p>

<p>Before we dive into the signs of confusion, we must define both terms so we can distinguish them ourselves:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Emotional safety</strong> is a state in which you feel secure expressing your whole range of feelings, rooted in the belief that supportive connections, trust, and acceptance are possible in your relationships and environment.</li>
<li><strong>Emotional numbness</strong> refers to a reduced capacity to feel emotions, often as a coping response to overwhelming stress, trauma, or internal conflict.</li>
</ul>

<p>Ironically, numbness can <em>feel</em> safe because it reduces emotional pain. But that feeling of “nothing matters” isn’t the same as genuine safety; it’s more of a psychological shutdown. And research backs that up.</p>
<p>A growing body of work highlights how emotional numbness shows up in clinical contexts. For example, a <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2817641">2024 study</a> published in <em>JAMA Network Open</em> found that trauma-exposed individuals, particularly those with posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), exhibit rapid swings between emotional states.</p>

<p>Emotional numbing symptoms, in particular, are known to intensify this pattern of reacting sharply to negative stimuli and then shutting down emotionally. So, while it feels as though numbing is helping them in the moment, it isn’t difficult to see how it isn’t a balanced state of safety, either. In reality, it’s a survival adaptation.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36442491/">2023 article</a> in <em>The Lancet Psychiatry</em> argues that emotional safety is foundational for overall well-being, especially in clinical environments where reducing emotional distress <em>without</em> undermining emotional expression is itself a therapeutic goal. This article clarifies to us, without a doubt, that emotional safety is supposed to enable connection and self-regulation, not emotional detachment.</p>

<p>With this backdrop, here are three key signs that what you’re experiencing isn’t emotional safety, but rather emotional numbness.</p>
<h2>1. You Prefer Feeling No Emotions Over Feeling Uncomfortable</h2>
<p>Emotional safety is a state of calm vulnerability, where you can <em>feel</em> your emotions without fear of judgment or threat. It doesn’t mean you’re never uncomfortable, but you can tolerate discomfort with support and without shutting down emotionally.</p>

<p>Emotional numbness, in contrast, is characterized by emotional blunting or flat affect. You might describe your experience as not feeling anything, good or bad. That absence might <em>feel</em> like a hard-won “immunity” from emotional hurt, but it’s really a defense mechanism. Emotional numbing (especially in trauma and stress contexts) shows that this numbness corresponds to reduced emotional reactivity, which isn’t the same as regulated, safe emotional experience.</p>

<p>If you notice this tendency in your behavior, you may need to ask yourself the following questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do I notice subtle emotional shifts (joy, irritation, sadness, etc.), or do I feel blank most of the time?</li>
<li>When something meaningful happens, do I feel it, even a little, or do I shrug it off?</li>
</ul>
<p>If you picked the latter alternative in both scenarios, you may have confused your tendency for emotional numbing with emotional safety.</p>

<h2>2. You Avoid or Suppress Emotions Instead of Integrating Them</h2>
<p>Emotional safety allows for the presence of all feelings, even difficult ones, without overwhelming panic, withdrawal, or self-attack. A person who feels emotionally safe understands, even at the nervous system level, that this safety is begotten by regulating emotion, not erasing it.</p>



  


<p>On the other hand, emotional numbness shows up as avoidance, suppression, or shutdown. You might notice the following patterns in an emotionally numb individual:</p>
<ul>
<li>Changing the subject when emotions come up</li>
<li>Feeling disconnected from loved ones</li>
<li>Using busyness or distraction to avoid feelings</li>
</ul>
<p>These patterns are not a sign of mastery; they’re methods of avoidance. And it’s almost common knowledge now that avoidance and suppression are maladaptive coping responses, ones that maintain distress over time, rather than true safety or regulation. Here’s a quick distinction for anyone confused about their own emotional state:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Emotional safety</strong> acknowledges feelings, creates discomfort, and builds relational trust.</li>
<li><strong>Emotional numbness, </strong>on the other hand, blocks out feelings, avoids discomfort, and undermines connection.</li>
</ul>
<p>If your emotional life feels “flat,” or if you’re <em>not</em> aware of what you’re feeling most of the time, that’s a classic sign of emotional numbness.</p>

<h2>3. You Only Feel Emotionally ‘Safe’ When You’re Disconnected</h2>
<p>This is an important symptom of emotional numbness, and often one that confuses most people. Individuals who might be emotionally numbed out can come to believe that they are emotionally safe because they don’t register hurt at all. In other words, they interpret, or rather misinterpret, their numbness as protection.</p>

<p>But here’s the catch: True emotional safety doesn’t isolate you from experience; it is supposed to ground you within it. And while emotional numbness may feel like safety precisely because it removes the emotional risk, that safety remains illusory.</p>
<p>In trauma psychology, emotional numbing is often seen as part of a survival response rather than an adaptive emotional state. In the above-mentioned 2024 <em>JAMA Network Open </em>study, 1,440 trauma-exposed individuals reported numbness as well as strong negative reactions. In other words, their systems oscillated between states of threat and shutdown, not a balanced state of safe emotional regulation.</p>

<p>In contrast, emotional safety is a stable platform that enables you to have access to feelings without being overwhelmed by them.</p>
<p>If you’re curious to know if your emotional stability is held up by numbness or safety, ask yourself this question: Do you feel safe <em>only</em> when you don’t feel anything? Or can you experience <em>range</em> and recovery, both the highs and lows, in a way that doesn’t ruin you?</p>

<p>If your calm comes from detachment, it may be a clear sign that you’re relying on a maladaptive coping mechanism to escape your emotions.</p>
<p><em>A version of this post also appears on Forbes.com.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-signs-youre-experiencing-emotional-numbing" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-signs-youre-experiencing-emotional-numbing</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/social-instincts/202602/3-signs-youre-experiencing-emotional-numbing</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Travers Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/a-g-_7llTamuXV8-unsplash.jpg?itok=PZrbGwc_" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>