<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 13:37:39 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 13:37:39 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why "Tell Me Lies" Is a Show Worth Sitting With]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/screen_shot_2020-06-05_at_10.38.54_am.jpg?itok=VruCyXgf" alt="Denise Fournier Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Relationships</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why "Tell Me Lies" Is a Show Worth Sitting With</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What "Tell Me Lies" can teach us about human relationships.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">"Tell Me Lies" depicts a dynamic that plays out in families, cults, and predatory industries.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sometimes, the price we pay for comfort and belonging is our authenticity, truth, self-respect, or safety.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Wanting to belong is a deep human need but it shouldn't cost you yourself.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Staying rooted and speaking truth can stop harm and violence from spreading.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-elina-araja-1743227-3317936.jpg?itok=il9Pyp28" width="320" height="433" data-insert-type="image" title="Pexels, used with permission " alt="Pexels, used with permission "></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Pexels, used with permission</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>Tell Me Lies</em> is a Hulu series that follows a group of college students whose lives are slowly overtaken by the charming, exploitative behavior of one person among them. On the surface, it's a story about young love, toxic obsession, and dysfunctional social relationships. But it’s also a painfully accurate portrayal of complex and nuanced themes like psychological manipulation, self-abandonment, and surrendering authenticity to belong. The show is slow at times, and sometimes plays like softcore porn. It's definitely not for everyone. But if you can move past that, the series offers a fascinating look at deeper human vulnerabilities that make us susceptible to harm.</p>

<p>What the show captures so well is the price we're willing to pay to stay comfortable, especially inside relationships that feel like oxygen. The college campus, where most of the show’s drama plays out, is a particular kind of pressure cooker. In a certain small world, with certain people, during a certain window of time, the need to make things work can override almost everything else. Under certain circumstances, it’s easier to let yourself be manipulated than to risk losing what feels essential.</p>

<h2>Same Darkness, Different Disguises</h2>
<p>This isn't unique to college. Dysfunctional families, exploitative industries, and high-control cults all operate in the same logical frame and prey on the same vulnerabilities. When our survival (physical or reputational) depends on belonging, and our options feel limited, we become willing to tolerate what would otherwise be intolerable. We silence our own knowing, handing over our authority, our truth, and our self-respect to hold on to what feels most stabilizing. As social creatures, most humans find the threat of defamation and expulsion from the social system to be deeply destabilizing. This is precisely the leverage that Stephen, the narcissistic, sociopathic center of the friend group, uses to perpetuate innumerable abuses that go unchecked and unchallenged.</p>

<p>This is how cult leaders are able to take everything from their followers—many of whom are seeking a substitute for the nuclear family, drawing stability and hope from belonging and belief. This is how antisocial gatekeepers lure the people who are hungriest for inclusion, access, and opportunity into their traps. People in narcissistic, sociopathic territory aren't only harmful in their direct impact on individuals; they're harmful in their capacity to charm, attract, and collect. That's what makes their violent effects ripple so far and wide.</p>

<p>As concerning and discouraging it can be to acknowledge that sociopaths live among us, the response shouldn’t be cynicism, isolation, or a refusal to trust or need other people. We are hardwired to be in relationship. Wanting to belong and connect reflects a deep need, not a weakness.</p>
<h2>How the Harm Stops Spreading</h2>

<p>But there is power and freedom in being clear about what you're depending on, and asking yourself honestly whether it's costing you your truth. Your authenticity. Your freedom.</p>
<p>Some dependencies are healthy. A relationship that supports and stretches you, a community that holds you, a belief system that grounds you—these are safe, reliable sources of stability. But when belonging requires you to abandon yourself, silence your own knowing, and compromise your self-respect or safety, the price is too high. If your throat is blocked with the truths you’re stifling, and you’re choking on secrets and lies, it’s important to pay attention. Because the harm won’t stop on its own.</p>

<p>Staying rooted in yourself doesn't guarantee you'll never be fooled. But it gives you something to recognize and return to when the pain overwhelms the pleasure and the spell wears off. It means you will recognize harm, even if it takes you a while to act on it. That recognition, that refusal to look away—when the harm is hitting you, or when it’s hitting another—is how ripples of violence stop spreading.</p>


<h2>The Logic Is Everywhere</h2>
<p>Not all of us will date a narcissist or be in a cult, but our lives will nonetheless be impacted by their logic. People who seek to control and dominate, who are absent of empathy and incapable of caring about the consequences of their actions, heavily influence all our social, cultural, and economic systems. Many of those with the most influence—the ones who are running the world as we know it—have access to that much power because their lack of scruples and moral conscience made it easy for them to succeed in systems built on competition rather than cooperation. The insidious impact of these individuals and these systems of harm runs deep and wide. </p>

<p>You don’t need to have dated a Stephen for <em>Tell Me Lies </em>to resonate with<em> </em>you. You just need to be a human being in the world, and to consider when you’ve chosen comfort over what’s right, when you’ve surrendered your agency to someone else, and when you’ve seen harm and haven’t spoken up about it. </p>
<p>It’s human and natural to need connection and want comfort. But unchecked, these drives can lead us to overlook real harm. If we listen to ourselves, trust our intuition and body, and stay honest about the price we’re paying to feel good and stay comfortable, we can do something to stop the harm. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindfully-present-fully-alive/202602/why-tell-me-lies-is-a-show-worth-sitting-with" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindfully-present-fully-alive/202602/why-tell-me-lies-is-a-show-worth-sitting-with</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/mindfully-present-fully-alive/202602/why-tell-me-lies-is-a-show-worth-sitting-with</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Denise Fournier Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-elina-araja-1743227-3317936.jpg?itok=l-lrnN29" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Ways Spring Brings Hope]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-09/Dr_Laura_Gabayan.png.jpg?itok=O4beWnwx" alt="Laura Gabayan, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Resilience</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Ways Spring Brings Hope</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Hope can promote good health, build resilience, and strengthen relationships.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 28, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p>Spring is coming on March 20. It can be a time of hope and renewal. Spring ends the winter season like light ends the darkness. The coming of spring reminds us of the peaks and valleys of life. If you are in a valley, know that there is light at the end of the tunnel and a peak will come soon. Just as the seasons change, so too will your life. While it may be hard to be positive if you are facing life challenges, there are three ways that spring can start a season of hope.</p>

<p>Moving into spring can improve your mood through increased sunlight, more regular outdoor activities, and more time spent outside. Regardless of the situation one is in, the change of season can help you move forward, survive and thrive through your present situation, and plan for a better tomorrow.</p>
<p>Without hope, I could not get through my days. As my body developed worsening symptoms over a decade ago, I took time to grieve and be devastated. I could no longer be an ER doctor, and had more limited mobility. However, this change brought with it other opportunities, and a change in my life course. My new life became focused on finding a way to work from home and stay positive as a mom and wife raising four young children. Despite the overwhelm, I had to believe that things were going to work out.</p>

<p>Hope helped me get through the day-to-day, but I knew my situation could help others. I also knew that physicians tended not to think outside the box. I then looked into those that did. I interviewed 60 wise adults displaying the 8 recognized elements of wisdom. To help others improve their lives, I published these insights in my book, <a href="https://lauragabayan.com/book/common-wisdom/"><em><strong>Common Wisdom</strong></em></a>.</p>

<p>I knew that the only way to go was forward. Many have talked about the importance of looking ahead. I know it’s hard to be positive when you are in a valley. It can be difficult to plan for the future. My suggestion is to start small. Focus first on your desire to change, and then take baby steps. Never let anyone tell you that you can’t make positive changes.</p>

<h2>3 Benefits of Hope</h2>
<p>The benefits of hope are often overlooked. Besides hope feeling good, what does it do for us?</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Hope Promotes Good Health. </strong>There is a positive relationship between having hope and your well-being. In addition to promoting emotional wellness, having hope results in the secretion of hormones that signal to the body that it can heal and rest. When the body is in stress mode, it feels that it must be in a state of fight-or-flight. </li>
<li><strong>Hope Builds Resilience. </strong>Hope can change your perspective after a setback. It’s a belief that a challenge is not there to stop you, but to teach you something. Hope builds your mental muscle so that you can overcome obstacles. While you may feel like giving up, believe that you will get through it. Give it time, and you will see it differently.</li>
<li><strong>Hope Strengthens Relationships. </strong>People want to be around friends and family who are hopeful. You are probably drawn to people who are positive about the future. You would rather be around a person who brings you up versus someone who brings you down. Having hope helps you build stronger connections with others.</li>
</ol>

<p>Hope does not emerge in a single, precise moment. You are not born with it. You have to build it inside you. It is like gratitude. Hope requires reminders, practice, and discussion. Being hopeful about a better tomorrow is what will give you a reason to get up in the morning. Like the seasons, a personal winter is temporary. You can control a situation by the way you perceive it. Hope gives you a way to look at situations with optimism instead of doom. It helps you get through the tunnel, and see the light at the end.</p>
<div class="pt-ad pt-ad--300x250 d-block d-none d-md-block d-lg-block d-xl-block block" id="block-adblock-18">
  
    
      <div class="pt-ad--container pt-ad-show-text">
      <div class="pt-ad--text">
      <span>article continues after advertisement</span>
    </div>
    <div id="div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9" class="pt-ad--content">
    <script type="text/javascript">
      if (!window.ptAdSlots || window.ptAdSlots.length === 0) {
        window.ptAdSlots = [];
      }
      window.ptAdSlots.push('div-gpt-ad-1404853927369-9')
    </script>
  <div id="google_ads_iframe_/1032688/300x250_Mobile_Content1_0__container__"></div></div>
</div>

  </div>

<p>So get ready to turn the clocks forward, get outside, and find new hope this spring.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-wisdom-insights/202602/3-ways-spring-brings-hope" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-wisdom-insights/202602/3-ways-spring-brings-hope</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-wisdom-insights/202602/3-ways-spring-brings-hope</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Gabayan, M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Goody_PR_Roses_Spring_Liz_H_Kelly_022726.jpg?itok=9KYSKuLa" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>